<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2004-01-13</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Emma Leeson Huber</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s).
 Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and
 feet of divisions (HEADS, etc.). Checked for signatures. Checked placement and
 completeness of PBs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, and UNCLEARs.
 Corrected 19 $s of 215. Converted 196 $s to GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech".
 Checked spacing of foreign GAPs. Checked for EPIGRAPHs and ARGUMENTs. Checked
 for startqs, endqs, oes, q;s, and Qs. Checked proofsheets and made corrections
 found there. Checked for CLOSERs, TRAILERs, and BYLINEs. DONE.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="A06270">
<STC T="S">16754</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99857242</BIBNO>
<VID>22934</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>ALARVM <HI>FOR</HI> LONDON, OR <HI>THE SIEDGE OF</HI> ANTWERPE.
With the ventrous actes and valo∣rous deeds of the lame Soldier. As it hath
been playde by the right Honorable the Lord Charberlaine his Seruants.</P>
<P>LONDON, Printed for William Ferbrand, and are to be sold at his
shop in Popes-head Alley, ouer against the Ta∣uerne doore, neere the
Royall-Exchange. 1602.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="prologue">
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>Prologus.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Time.</STAGE>
<L>ROund through the compasse of this e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rthly ball,</L>
<L>The massie substance hanging in the skye,</L>
<L>Hath fleeting <HI>Time</HI> pursu'd this froward age;</L>
<L>And searcht the worlds corrupt enormities.</L>
<L>Heere found I some, despite my hoary scalpe,</L>
<L>There sound I Courtiers laught my course to scorne,</L>
<L>In that place daintie mouthed Damsels scoffe,</L>
<L>Sticking my feathers with their borrowed plumes,</L>
<L>As though my beauty were not good enough.</L>
<L>And now this faire concourse heere met together,</L>
<L>That haue cal<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e
leasure to be holde their faultes,</L>
<L>VVithin my furrowed bosome deepe ingra<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'d:</L>
<L>Like a steele forg'd impression (fixed firme)</L>
<L>Are met together: you will scorne my wants,</L>
<L>Laugh at my <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>anenes,
looke basely, fume and frowne<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>But doe so, doe so, your proude eyes shall see</L>
<L>The punishment of Citty cruelty:</L>
<L>And if your hearts be not of Adamant,</L>
<L>Reforme the mischiefe of deg en<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rate mindes,</L>
<L>And make you weepe in pure relenting kinde.</L>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>A Larum for London, or the siedge of Antwerpe: with the
vertuous actes and valorous deedes of the
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ame Soldier.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Sancto Danila</HI> and two other Captaines.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dani.</SPEAKER>
<L>SO, leaue me now, and in mine absence, see</L>
<L>That not a Soldier pearch vpon the walles;</L>
<L>Least by the Citizens they be espyed,</L>
<L>And thereupon they grow suspicious,</L>
<L>Be gone, and giue the Centenels in charge,</L>
<L>They haue an eye vnto the Southerne Port:</L>
<L>And heare yee? if that any forces come,</L>
<L>Let them be straight receiu'd into the Castle,</L>
<L>But with as little tumult as you may.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>It shall be done my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dan.</SPEAKER>
<L>We must be secret, as befits the care,</L>
<L>And expedition of so great a cause;</L>
<L><HI>Antwerpe</HI> is wealthy, but withall secure,</L>
<L>Our Soldiers want the crownes they surfet with,</L>
<L>And therefore she mu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> spare from foorth her store,</L>
<L>To helpe her neighbours; nay she shall be forc't,</L>
<L>To strip her of her pouches, and on the backes</L>
<L>Of Spanish Soldiers, hang her costliest roabes.</L>
<L>The plot already is determin'd of,</L>
<L>And say <HI>Cornelius</HI> doe but keepe his word;</L>
<L>These swilling Epicures shall taste of death,</L>
<L><PB REF="3"/>Whilst we suruiue to rifle their rich Coffers.</L>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Cornelius.</STAGE>
<L>Heere comes the man, welcome <HI>Cornelius,</HI></L>
<L>I see you make religion of your word.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speake softly good my Lord least yee be heard,</L>
<L>The Cittizens are scouting heere about.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not one <HI>Gernelius</HI> dare approach so neere,</L>
<L>The Castle shot keepes them in greater awe,</L>
<L>And for discouery by the eye, feare not;</L>
<L>Within this valley we may talke at large,</L>
<L>And no man see vs: say are you resolu'd,</L>
<L>To stand firme friend vnto the Spaniard?</L>
<L>And <HI>Sancto Damla</HI> vowes you shall partake,</L>
<L>Both spoyle and honour with the best of vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L>Suppose my Lord I gaue you my consent,</L>
<L>In all the world there's not (at my commaund)</L>
<L>Aboue sixe hundred Almaignes; you your selfe,</L>
<L>Are in the Castle scarce a thousand strong,</L>
<L>And what are these to sacke so great a towne?</L>
<L>So populous and large as <HI>Antweerpe</HI> is.</L>
<L>The Citizens (were they but polliticke,</L>
<L>Carefull and studious to preserue their peace)</L>
<L>Might an houres warning, fill their streetes,</L>
<L>With fortie thousand well appointed Soldiers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dan.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, but they are remisse and negligent,</L>
<L>Their bodies vs'd to soft effeminate silkes,</L>
<L>And their nice mindes set all on dalliance;</L>
<L>Which makes them fat for slaughter, fit for spoile:</L>
<L>But say twere otherwise that in their peace</L>
<L>And daies of plenty, whilst they flourished</L>
<L>They had fore-seene the daunger might ensue,</L>
<L>And exercise themselues in feates of armes;</L>
<L>Yet wee being sole commaunder of the Castle,</L>
<L>And that commaunding them, what let is there,</L>
<L>(Were we much weaker) but we might preuaile?</L>
<L><PB REF="3"/>When once the A larum soundes (like silly mice)</L>
<L>They'll hyde them in the creuice of their walles,</L>
<L>And some for ignorance, will stand amaz'd;</L>
<L>And some will be so tender of their flesh,</L>
<L>As they will scorne to beare the weight of steele,</L>
<L>No, no braue Almaigne if men euer had</L>
<L>A fit occasion to inrich themselues,</L>
<L>And fill the vast world with their e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>hoing fame;</L>
<L>Now is that instant put into our hands;</L>
<L>And now may we be Lords of this proude towne▪</L>
<L>My minde deuines no lesse, and till my feete</L>
<L>Tread a venturous measure in their streetes,</L>
<L>I shall be sicke to thinke vpon the deed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<L>I wish my Lord as much as you detaine,</L>
<L>But such an enterprise must be well grounded,</L>
<L>Least in performance there be found defect.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dan.</SPEAKER>
<L>What patient eye can looke vpon yond Tur<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ets,</L>
<L>And see the beauty of that flower of <HI>Europe,</HI></L>
<L>And in't be rauisht with the sight of her?</L>
<L>Oh she is amorous as the wanton ayre.</L>
<L>And must be Courted: from her no
 <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> comes</L>
<L>A breath, as sweete as the Arabian spice.</L>
<L>Her garments are imbrodered with puregolde;</L>
<L>And euery part so rich and sump<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ous,</L>
<L>As Indias not to be compar'd to her,</L>
<L>She must be Courted,
 <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ary her self inuites,</L>
<L>And beckons vs vnto her sportfull bed;</L>
<L>What is he then more
 <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>umpish than rude Iron,</L>
<L>By such a load-f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>arre may not be attempted?</L>
<L>Oh braue <HI>Corneliu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</HI> if within thy vaines,</L>
<L>There be that heate of vallout? I presume;</L>
<L>Let vs for-slowe no time till wee obtaine</L>
<L>To Reuell in that bower of earthly blisse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, what lyes in me yee shall dispose,</L>
<L>My Regiment of Almaignes, and my selfe,</L>
<L>Will on the first assault reuolt to you;</L>
<L><PB REF="4"/>Meane space Ile giue you close intelligence,</L>
<L>Of any thing the Cittizens pretend:</L>
<L>But as I said, what makes this to the spoile,</L>
<L>Of such a might Citty as this is,</L>
<L>Vnlesse we be confirm'd with more supply?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beholde this scroule and be resolu'd in that,</L>
<L>From <HI>Nastricht</HI> first there comes a thousand horse,</L>
<L>Beside fiue hundred foote: vnder the guiding</L>
<L>Of <HI>Don Al<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>zo de
 Verdugo:</HI> Then</L>
<L>From <HI>L<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>yre</HI>
 doth <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> de Romero,</HI>
 bring</L>
<L>Fiue hundred foote; From <HI>A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lst</HI> two thousand more</L>
<L>Follow the conduct of <HI>Emanuell;</HI></L>
<L>The Duke of <HI>Al<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>a</HI> likewise brings his power,</L>
<L>And for a better cullour, to delude</L>
<L>These credulous inhabitants of <HI>Antwerpe,</HI></L>
<L>He causeth it be publisht he is dead,</L>
<L>And that his Soldiers guard his body hyther,</L>
<L>To haue it shipt for Spaine to be interd:</L>
<L>Which well may serue to shaddow his approach,</L>
<L>The rest by night shall haue their entraunce;</L>
<L>So that within two daies I make account,</L>
<L>We shall be gathered to a perfect head,</L>
<L>Of (at the least) sixe thousand Spaniards.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<L>I mary my Lord, this soundeth somewhat like,</L>
<L>Now dares <HI>Cornelius</HI> promise victorie.</L>
<L>But how intendes your Lordship to begin,</L>
<L>And giue an entraunce to this busines?</L>
<L>You know th' Antwerpians neuer yet tooke part,</L>
<L>In any action gainst his Maiesty,</L>
<L>But haue remain'd as neutrall, neyther ayding</L>
<L>The Prince of <HI>Orenge</HI> nor offending you:</L>
<L>How will you then inkindle flambes of warre,</L>
<L>And take occasion to commence your quarrell?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why any way; it shall be thus <HI>Cornelius,</HI></L>
<L>Ile charge the Master Gunner of the Castle,</L>
<L>To make a shot or two vpon the towne;</L>
<L><PB REF="4"/>And when they come to know the cause of it,</L>
<L>Ile say it was, because they doe not sincke,</L>
<L>The Prince of <HI>Orenge</HI> ships: but suffer them</L>
<L>To lye so neere within the Lyuer
 <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>,</L>
<L>Which not withstanding, we precisely know,</L>
<L>Doe houer there about, to no end else,</L>
<L>But to safe conduct victuals to the towne.</L>
<L>Yet this excuse will serue to cloake our ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e,</L>
<L>And shew some reason for what after follows.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<L>It cannot be but good my noble Lord,</L>
<L>And shortly (as their dayly custome is)</L>
<L>Changing the Gouernor and other Burgers,</L>
<L>Intend a solemne banquet at the State-house.</L>
<L>Euen then, and at that place, giue you direction,</L>
<L>The Gunner take his Leuill, twill affright,</L>
<L>And strike the greater terror to their soules.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Enough, Ile play them Musicke to their meate,</L>
<L>And send such Reuellers into the roome,</L>
<L>As some of them shall haue caroust their last,</L>
<L>The most I craue, is that <HI>Cornelius</HI></L>
<L>Will be as constant as he hath profest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Once more my Lord I gage my hand with yours,</L>
<L>And as he is a Soldier and a Knight,</L>
<L><HI>Cornelius</HI> vowes to be a friend to Spaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dan.</SPEAKER>
<L>I take thy word faire Knight, and backe againe</L>
<L>Returne the like to thee; both I and mine,</L>
<L>For euer vow to loue and honour thee:</L>
<L>Now breake we off our secret conference,</L>
<L>And closely as we came vnto this place,</L>
<L>So let vs circumspectly make retreate.</L>
<L>Walke thou into the towne as if thou hadst</L>
<L>But only come abroad to take the ayre.</L>
<L>I to the Castle will with-draw my selfe</L>
<L>Downe some backe way, and euer as we need,</L>
<L>Be this our meeting place, till <HI>Antwerpe</HI> bleed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Farewell my Lord, <HI>Cornelius</HI> is agreed.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt</STAGE>
<STAGE><PB REF="5"/>Enter <HI>Danila</HI> and the
<HI>Gunner.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dan.</SPEAKER>
<L>What Ordinance haue you laden on that part:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gun.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Faulcon and two Harguebuz of Crocke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dan.</SPEAKER>
<L>What telst thou me of Harguebuz of Crocke?</L>
<L>A poxe vpon your rascall squibs and crackers,</L>
<L>Haue you been loading all this day till now,</L>
<L>And come you with your Harguebuz of Crocke?</L>
<L>A plague vpon't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gun.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, blame your direction: neuerthelesse,</L>
<L>Not full assured of your Lordships pleasure,</L>
<L>We haue rais'd the Cannons that came last from
 <HI>Harlam,</HI></L>
<L>And planted them this morning for the purpose.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Twas well aduis'd; but Gunner for what part?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gun.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's as it please your Honour to direct,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dan.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's for the State-house Gunner, where the Duch</L>
<L>Sit swilling in the pride of their excesse;</L>
<L>Commend vs to them, tell them we haue sent</L>
<L>Musicke to make them merry at theyr Feast:</L>
<L>Goe bid thy full-mouth'd Cannon▪ much good doo't them.</L>
<L>Should we discharge some scuruie Culuering,</L>
<L>They'll thinke we are about some fire-worke,</L>
<L>To make them sport with.</L>
<L>For sure they fall a sleepe vpon full stomackes,</L>
<L>Shoote me their State-house through both the sides,</L>
<L>And tell them thou didst it for their health,</L>
<L>To k<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>epe them
 waking.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gun.</SPEAKER>
<L>I warrant you my Lord, Ile peirce her sides,</L>
<L>Or neuer thinke me worke-man whilst I liue.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dan.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will not stirre till I haue heard the shot.</L>
<L>Goe light thy Linckstocke at some hellish brand,</L>
<L>To send blacke vengeance to that hated towne;</L>
<L>Let euery corne of powder be a spirit,</L>
<L>Thy mortall ayme as ominous as death,</L>
<L>And neuer a splinter that the Bullet strikes,</L>
<L><PB REF="5"/>But let it prooue a very murdering piece,</L>
<L>Amongst the Burgers at their Banqueting,</L>
<L>To vomit horred plagues vpon them all.</L>
<STAGE>The peice discharges.</STAGE>
<L>There be thou like the Club of <HI>Hercules,</HI></L>
<L>Amongst the Bouzing Bacchanalian centures,</L>
<L>To beate their Renish Cannes about their eares.</L>
<STAGE>A great screeke heard within.</STAGE>
<L>Good lucke I hope hark how the sodaine noyse</L>
<L>In countring with the Cannons loude report,</L>
<L>Stops his full mouth, with the reuerberate sound,</L>
<L>And fils the circle of the emptie ayre.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter two Burgers running.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Bur.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Shot what from the Castle questionlesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 Bur.</SPEAKER>
<L>The smoke and the report may tell you so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Bur.</SPEAKER>
<L>And certainly intended at our liues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 Bur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Call to the Gouernour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Bur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee's walking heere without the Castle<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>stay,</L>
<L>The Cittizens haue sent me to demaund,</L>
<L>On what occasion, or by whose commaundement,</L>
<L>You haue discharg'd this shot vpon the towne?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dan.</SPEAKER>
<L>At my commaund Sir, what is that to you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 Bur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then thy command (I tell thee <HI>Sancto Danila)</HI></L>
<L>Is deuilish and vnchristian;</L>
<L>Which passing through the State-house of the Cittie,</L>
<L>Hath slaine three persons.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Three froathy Renish fats that haue drunk dead,</L>
<L>Or in their cuppes haue falne to cutting throates,</L>
<L>And fearing that it would be nois'd abroad,</L>
<L>To couer your foule Bestiall Gurmandize,</L>
<L>Giue it out to be a shot sent from the Castle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Bur.</SPEAKER>
<L>That men are slaine wee'll not expostulate,</L>
<L>But Gouernor, was it by your commaundement?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tell me you men of <HI>Antwerpe,</HI></L>
<L>If you doe startle at a Cannons burst,</L>
<L><PB REF="6"/>Why suffer you the Prince of <HI>Orenge</HI>
 Ships,</L>
<L>To ride vpon the riuer at their pleasure?</L>
<L>And with their f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eering tops to mocke our Fames,</L>
<L>The whilst the Sconses which doe
 <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lancke the Riuer,</L>
<L>Serue but for Fishers to vnload their nets;</L>
<L>Whilst Cankering rust, deuoures your emptie Cannons:</L>
<L>And they lye hulling vp and downe the streame?</L>
<L>Burgers of <HI>Antwerpe</HI> answere me to this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 Bur.</SPEAKER>
<L>They be of <HI>Zealand,</HI> and the Prince of
 <HI>Orenge</HI></L>
<L>Hath euer been a friend vnto the State.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dan.</SPEAKER>
<L>But enemy vnto the King my Master;</L>
<L>Therefore they shall not ride vpon the ryuer;</L>
<L>Which if your owne security doe suffer,</L>
<L>Wee'll make our Ban-dogs to awake your towne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Bur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is that the cause and reason of your shot?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Burger it is.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Bur.</SPEAKER>
<L>You should haue sent vs word of your dislike:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why so we did, did we not send our poast</L>
<L>Euen now vnto you?</L>
<L>And wrapt our Packet in a ball of lead?</L>
<L>I thinke we sent a bolde Embassador.</L>
<L>That spoke our minde in thunder: did he not?</L>
<L>You might before haue knowne of our dislike,</L>
<L>But that we did perceiue you would not see,</L>
<L>Twas well you heard of vs.</L>
<STAGE>A signet sounded, enter two with mourning penons: a Drum<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> sounding a dead march: <HI>Dalua</HI>
 carried vpon a horse couered with blacke: Soldiers after, tray∣ling their
 Pykes.</STAGE>
<L>No Cittizens of <HI>Antwerpe,</HI> this the cause</L>
<L>That makes you carelesse and neglect our power,</L>
<L>The death of Princelie <HI>Dalua,</HI> had he liu'd,</L>
<L>The Fleete of <HI>Orenge</HI> had not traded thus,</L>
<L>Nor brau'd our Castle.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="6"/>Enter two or three Cittizens running.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Cit.</SPEAKER>
<L>I pray God they meane not to assault the towne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 Cit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis <HI>Daluas</HI> Body brought vnto the Castle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3 Cit.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would he had come thus, when he came first</L>
<L>Into these Countries.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Cit.</SPEAKER>
<L>So would I, what's become of this damned fiend?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 Cit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let the deuill looke to that, for he has most right to him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3 Cit.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would the cowe hyde were off, wee might see the foure
 quarters.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Cit.</SPEAKER>
<L>A plague goe with him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 Cit.</SPEAKER>
<L>There will be olde tryumphing in hell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3 Cit.</SPEAKER>
<L>There will be olde supping of boyling leade.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Cit.</SPEAKER>
<L>That <HI>Dalua</HI> was a bloudy villaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 Cit.</SPEAKER>
<L>He was worse then the Spanish inquisition.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3 Cit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, if euer man would haue eaten vp the Ca∣niballes, twas
 he.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Cit.</SPEAKER>
<L>I feare nothing but one.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 Cit.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Cit.</SPEAKER>
<L>That the people will curse him out of's graue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 Cit.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am glad they haue curst him into it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3 Cit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, it was neuer heard that <HI>Dalua</HI> was dead,</L>
<L>But there was some notable villanie followed it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Cit.</SPEAKER>
<L>What dost thou thinke he will reuiue againe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 Cit.</SPEAKER>
<L>If doe, the deuil's on't, Ile neuer trust death on's word for a
 halfe pennie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3 Cit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, wee'll mourne in sacke for him.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, let's retyre our selues into the State-house,</L>
<L>Tis <HI>Daluas</HI> body brought into the Castle.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dan.</SPEAKER>
<L>March neerer to the Castle with your hearse,</L>
<L>Before you set it downe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alu. in the hearse.</SPEAKER>
<L>What are those villaines gone that rayl'd vpon me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sould.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Set downe and let me light,</L>
<STAGE>He comes from vnder the hearse.</STAGE>
<L><PB REF="7"/>I would not heare my selfe againe so rayl'd on,</L>
<L>Not for halfe <HI>Belgia.</HI></L>
<L>Zwounds the dogs barke at me, a plague vpon them all,</L>
<L>I thinke they doe <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ot hate the Deuill so;</L>
<L><HI>Dalua</HI> is neuer nam'd but with a curse,</L>
<L>Thinke but these ro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ges, this is a tyme to dye,</L>
<L>And heare these damned dogs reuile me thus:</L>
<L>Well I am dead, but <HI>Aluas</HI> spirit (ere long)</L>
<L>Shall haunt your ghostes, and with a fatall troope,</L>
<L>Come in the dreadfull night about your walles,</L>
<L>Grimme death did nere affright the fearfull martiall,</L>
<L>As I will fright these Bouzing Begians:</L>
<L>Whose that aboue? Lord
 <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <HI>Danila?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dan.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord of <HI>Alua;</HI> enter the Castle.</L>
<STAGE><HI>Alua</HI> enters and his troope.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Alonzo Verdugo,</HI> and his Soldiers with a still
 march.</STAGE>
<L>O the Lord <HI>Verdugo,</HI> and his Regiment,</L>
<L>From <HI>Mascricht?</HI> tis well.</L>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Iulian Romero,</HI> and his power with a still
 march.</STAGE>
<L>Iulian Romero <HI>and his Regiment from</HI> Leyre?</L>
<L>My Lord <HI>Romero</HI> where is <HI>Don Emanuell?</HI></L>
<L>To bring the power that we expect from <HI>Alst.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who's that? Lord <HI>Sancto Danila?</HI></L>
<L>Hee's entred on the other side the Castle,</L>
<L>Withall his power.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not yet full ten, my minde presageth good,</L>
<L><HI>Antwerpe</HI> ere night, shall bath her selfe in bloud.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Marques d'Hauurye, Egmount, Champaigne, Van End</HI>
and his Page: English Gouernor and one Burger.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Monsieur Champaigne,</HI> great <HI>Antwerpes</HI>
 Gouer∣nour,</L>
<L>Will you refuse these faire and fresh supplyes?</L>
<L><PB REF="7"/>Sent from the Prince of <HI>Orenge</HI> and the
 States,</L>
<L>Vnder our Conduct for your Citties guard?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cham.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lord <HI>Marques Hauurye,</HI> we reiect them not,</L>
<L>Nor yet neglect the loue of that great Prince,</L>
<L>And our kinde friend the Co-vnited States:</L>
<L>But <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ince we haue no
 neede of such a power,</L>
<L>Why should we pester <HI>Antwerpe</HI> with such troupes,</L>
<L>To spend the victuals of the Cittizens,</L>
<L>Which we can scarcely compasse now for gilt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Egm.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Prince &amp; States will furnish yee with sto<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e,</L>
<L>To feede the Army and relieue the Towne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cham.</SPEAKER>
<L>It may be so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bur.</SPEAKER>
<L>And it may not be so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Outwords and honours be engag'd for it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eng. Gou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vnder correction my Lord Gouernour,</L>
<L>The <HI>Marques</HI> and Count <HI>Egmonts</HI> noble words,</L>
<L>(Although the Prince of <HI>Orenge</HI> and the States</L>
<L>Should be forgetfull) were a pawne of worth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>What sayes the Collonell of the Almaines to it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Van.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is <HI>Van Ends</HI> opinion my good Lord,</L>
<L>That the rich promise of such noble Peeres,</L>
<L>As <HI>Marques Hanurie</HI> and Count <HI>Egmont</HI> are,</L>
<L>Is pawne <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nough for
 all the Citties wealth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bur.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Almaine lyes, wealth is worth more than wordes.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Standing aside.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cham.</SPEAKER>
<L>I way their promise with my sound beliefe,</L>
<L>And tye my thoughts to their assured trust,</L>
<L>Yet are there many reasons of import,</L>
<L>To bar<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e your Armies
 entrance to this towne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Egm.</SPEAKER>
<L>The graund obiection is decyded.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cham.</SPEAKER>
<L>True.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Egm.</SPEAKER>
<L>The lesser then are easily refeld.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cham.</SPEAKER>
<L>Suppose the Prince &amp; States do Victuall them,</L>
<L>Yet their <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>isorder
 in our Ciuell streetes,</L>
<L>May be perni<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ious,
 and breede mutinie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>By this supposall you enfeeble vs,</L>
<L><PB REF="8"/>And taxe our worth with indiscretion,</L>
<L>As though our skill and our Authority,</L>
<L>Stood vpon bases of weake discipline.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bur.</SPEAKER>
<L>We said not so, and yet their ryotings,</L>
<L>May taynt our wiues and ieoperdize our wealth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Van.</SPEAKER>
<L>In silence be it my Lord, you need thē not.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>To cham aside.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Egm.</SPEAKER>
<L>All ryots shall be death by martiall law,</L>
<L>And all commaunders, shall be vigilent</L>
<L>Ouer their troopes, that order may he kept.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cham.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lords of <HI>Egmount</HI> and of <HI>Hau<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rye,</HI></L>
<L>What are your numbers?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Iust 3000, foote,</L>
<L>One thousand horse, 800. at the least.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eng Gou.</SPEAKER>
<L>An honourable tender of true friends,</L>
<L>To send such ayde for safeguard of your Citty.</L>
<STAGE>(Aside.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bur.</SPEAKER>
<L>T will shake our bags too much to pay so many.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cham.</SPEAKER>
<L>At whose expence shall all this army rest?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Egm.</SPEAKER>
<L>Some part your selues, some part the Prince will pay.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cham.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sixe hundred Almaignes are our garison,</L>
<L>A guard sufficient to defende our walles,</L>
<L>And men enough, because we need no more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bur.</SPEAKER>
<L>And they too many to be paide by vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Van.</SPEAKER>
<L>O may these slaues refuse this succour sent,</L>
<L>Their myserie shall bring their miserie.</L>
<STAGE>Aside.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Count <HI>Egmont,</HI> surelie <HI>Ant werpe</HI> is
 bewitcht,</L>
<L>Securitie hath slaine their prouidence,</L>
<STAGE>Take Egm. aside</STAGE>
<L>And riches makes them retchles of their friends;</L>
<L>We must assume the charge vpon ourselues,</L>
<L>And pray the Prince and States to beare the pay;</L>
<L>Or else their priuate auarice, will pull</L>
<L>Publicke destruction on this flower of townes,</L>
<L>To the disgrace of all the Netherlands.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Egm.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will make tender of so much to them,</L>
<L>Two monthes the Prince of <HI>Orenge</HI> and the States,</L>
<L>And we our selues, will pay foure thousand men:</L>
<L>If afterward, our powers be not of vse,</L>
<L><PB REF="8"/>We shall withdraw them to their Prouinces,</L>
<L>May this content you curious Cittizens?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cham.</SPEAKER>
<L>The offer is so Honorable now,</L>
<L>As modestly, we cannot challenge it:</L>
<L>Captaine <HI>Cornelius</HI> what's your counsell?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Van.</SPEAKER>
<L>This:</L>
<L>Say, that you feare the Spaniards will conceiue</L>
<STAGE>Aside to Champ.</STAGE>
<L>Some high displeasure, if you take them in,</L>
<L>My Lords these fat purs'd peasants are so proude,</L>
<L>Friends and defence, are lesse esteem'd then pelfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gouernor of <HI>Antwerpe,</HI> how are you resolu'd?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cham</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lords, the Prince of <HI>Orenge</HI> and your selues,</L>
<L>And all the States deserue our dutious loue</L>
<L>And humble seruice: first, for sending power,</L>
<L>Then promising pay and victuals for that power:</L>
<L>But with your pardon, yet there is a let,</L>
<L>That makes vs loath to take your armie in.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Egm.</SPEAKER>
<L>What let <HI>Champaigne?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Champ.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Spanish Gouernor,</L>
<L><HI>Danila,</HI> commaunder of the Castle heere,</L>
<L>If we receiue your troopes into our Towne,</L>
<L>Will iudge we haue some purpose of reuolt,</L>
<L>And raising armes against the King of Spaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>What if he doe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cham.</SPEAKER>
<L>His fierie spirit enflam'd,</L>
<L>Will send our bullets from the Cittadell,</L>
<L>And teare the sumptuous buildings of ou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> towne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bur.</SPEAKER>
<L>As late he did when we were banqueting,</L>
<L>And thought no harme, but drinking health to health,</L>
<L>He shot, and slew some innocent poore soules,</L>
<L>And rent our State-house and some buildings else.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Van.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee'll rend you better if our purpose holde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Egm.</SPEAKER>
<L>What was the cause?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cham.</SPEAKER>
<L>Because we did not sincke,</L>
<L>The Prince of <HI>Orenge</HI> Ships, that lay to waft</L>
<L>Prouision to our Citty vp the Riuer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="9"/>
<SPEAKER>Eng. Gouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Obserue by that you discreete Gouernors,</L>
<L>What loue or faith the Spaniard holdes with you,</L>
<L>That for his pride would haue your Citty pine;</L>
<L>Hauing destroy'd the corne on Flaunders side,</L>
<L>And cross'd a bridge of Conuoy to your towne;</L>
<L>Then that the Riuer should not victuall you,</L>
<L>He wish'd you sinke that shipping in the <HI>Skelt.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Egm.</SPEAKER>
<L>Collect by this the Spaniards crueltie,</L>
<L>Who though occasion should not come from you,</L>
<L>Would picke a quarrell for occasion,</L>
<L>To sacke your Cittie, and to sucke your bloud,</L>
<L>To satisfie his pride and luxurie:</L>
<L>Let <HI>Harlem▪ Marstricht, Alst</HI> example you,</L>
<L>And many Citties models of his wrath,</L>
<L>Thinke on my Father and the Countie <HI>Horne,</HI></L>
<L>Whose tragedie, if I recount with ruth,</L>
<L>May mooue the stones of <HI>Antwerpe</HI> to relent▪</L>
<L>They seru'd the Spaniard as his Liedge-men sworne,</L>
<L>Yet, for they did but wish their countrie good,</L>
<L>He pickt a quarrell, and cut off their heades.</L>
<L>Burgers the Spaniard waites to take your liues,</L>
<L>That he may spoyle your towne, your wealth, your wiue<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eng. Gou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Receiue your friends, preuent his treachery,</L>
<L>Least vnawares you taste his tirranye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>What benefit (good Country-men) gaine we,</L>
<L>That prostitute our fortunes and our bloud,</L>
<L>In your defence?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cham.</SPEAKER>
<L>Say, shall we let them in?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Van.</SPEAKER>
<L>In troth I thinke the Spaniard meanes no harme.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cham.</SPEAKER>
<L>Meane what he may, wee'll not offend such friends,</L>
<L>As these, the Prince of <HI>Orenge</HI> and the State,</L>
<L>Your Armie is at <HI>Kibdorpe</HI> Port you say?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>There stay our forces.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cham.</SPEAKER>
<L>We will let them in,</L>
<L>And quarter them with all conuenient speede,</L>
<L><HI>Van End</HI> draw vp your Almaignes to one place,</L>
<L><PB REF="9"/>And keep good rule for feare of ciuill braules,</L>
<L>And now my Lords I will attend on you.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Exeunt</HI> Champ. Marq. Eg<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bur.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will attend to looke and guard my doores,</L>
<L>And keepe my wealth, my wife, and daughter safe,</L>
<L>For feare these hungry soldiers get a snatch.</L>
<STAGE>Exit</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Manet Van and his boy.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Van.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yonker come heere, haste to the Castle wall,</L>
<L>And call to speake with <HI>Sancto Danila,</HI></L>
<L>Tell him from me, the Flies begin to swarme▪</L>
<L>The Sunne growes hot, the heards do shake their hornes,</L>
<L>The Shepheards bring great flockes home to the folde;</L>
<L>Say, if the Butcher slaughter not in t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ne,</L>
<L>The beastes will surfet, and the Soldiers pyne,</L>
<L>Therefore begin before one glasse be runne,</L>
<L>And we shall win ere setting of the Sunne:</L>
<L>Remember this, be secret and away.</L>
<STAGE>Exit boy.</STAGE>
<L>Now <HI>(Antwerpe)</HI> comes the Spaniards holly-day,</L>
<L>With them ioyne I, my share is in the gold,</L>
<L>I runne with the Hare, and with the hound I holde;</L>
<L>This Sunday shall be dismall to the towne,</L>
<L>The Burgers dye, their gallant wiues go<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> downe.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>As he is going out Stumpe encounters him.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Burger, Champaigne,</HI> and their Wiues.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Afore good wife, I feare that all's not well,</L>
<L><HI>Monsieur Champaigne</HI> what's your opinion?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cham.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doubtles, the Spaniards do intend some hurt,</L>
<L>Harke how the tumult still increaseth?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>For shame,</L>
<L>Be not so fearefull, say that for some offence,</L>
<L>Eyther commenced, or but in conceipt;</L>
<L>The Spaniards were maliciouslie inclin'd:</L>
<L>Haue yee not Soldiers to withstand their force?</L>
<L>What should you need to be solicitous,</L>
<L><PB REF="10"/>Keepe yee
 <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay wife thou dost mistake,</L>
<L>If thou immagine we inten<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> to fight;</L>
<L>Tis not <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> at
 the charge</L>
<L>To pay <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> should
 not they</L>
<L>Be at the care to see the Cittie safe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 Wif.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Citty's safe enough without their care,</L>
<L>Will you to dinner?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cham.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wherefore shoote they thus,</L>
<L>Vnlesse there were some villanie abroach?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 Wif.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wherefore shoote they but to trye their peeces,</L>
<L>I warrant you husband tis no otherwise.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Marques</HI> with his swoord drawne.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heere comes the <HI>Marques</HI> he can tell the newes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cham.</SPEAKER>
<L>The cause my Lord of this intestine vp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ore?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>The cause is murder, miserie and death:</L>
<L>You men of <HI>Antwerpe,</HI> if with all the speede</L>
<L>And expedition, that in men remaines,</L>
<L>You take not weapons to repulse the foe,</L>
<L>That like a swarme of deadlie stinging Hornets,</L>
<L>Haue all this while lay hid within their nest;</L>
<L>But now doe flye abroad with dreadfull noise,</L>
<L>As if so many Furies were awakt.</L>
<L>To armes then all that loue your Countries peace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bur.</SPEAKER>
<L>How doe ye meane my Lord? or who are those</L>
<L>Your Lordship shaddows, vnder-neath the name</L>
<L>Of swarming Hornets?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you so dull of<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ence?</L>
<L>And still so lull'd in your securitie?</L>
<L>Whom should I meane, but bloudie <HI>Danila,</HI></L>
<L>And furious <HI>Alua</HI> his compeere in armes,</L>
<L>That fill the Castle yard with their Battilions,</L>
<L>And striue to take possession of your streetes:</L>
<L>To armes then straight, if you will keep them backe.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ist like that <HI>Alua</HI> is reuiu'd againe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="10"/>
<SPEAKER>1 Wif.</SPEAKER>
<L>As like as he intendes to take the towne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cham.</SPEAKER>
<L>But I suspect there is some treacherie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 Wif.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you beleeue his words, he doth but iest,</L>
<L>To try how we will take it if twere so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Champ.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay by his lookes and by his sodaine haste,</L>
<L>It should appeare the Marques doth not iest.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Egmont <HI>and</HI> Stump.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Egm.</SPEAKER>
<L>To armes to armes, oh where's the Gouernor?</L>
<L>Giue order that your Cittizens prepare,</L>
<L>To stand vpon their guard, defend themselues,</L>
<L>For whom you trusted, turnes his weapons point</L>
<L>Vpon your bosomes: all the Almaigne force,</L>
<L>Is quite reuolted, and the enemie</L>
<L>Entring your streetes: <HI>Van End</HI> that damned slaue,</L>
<L>Giues ayde to Spaine, and with his trayterous hand</L>
<L>Drawes in destruction, if you looke not to it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cham.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where are the Switzers should supply the Trenches?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Egm.</SPEAKER>
<L>Drunke in their lodgings, and in reeling foorth,</L>
<L>The Spaniards (vnresisted) murder them.</L>
<L>For honors s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ke, for
 wretched <HI>Antwerpes</HI> sake,</L>
<L>Stand not amazed, but with couragious hearts,</L>
<L>And forward hands, fight for your libertie.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stum.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are yet your eye-lids open, are you yet</L>
<L>Awakt out of the slumber you were in?</L>
<L>Or will you still lye snorting in your sloath?</L>
<L>Be still perswaded you are safe enough?</L>
<L>Vntill the verie instant, you doe feele</L>
<L>Their naked swoords glide through your weasond-pipes?</L>
<L>Or doe you thinke with belching P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ffes that flye</L>
<L>From your full paunches, you can blow them backe?</L>
<L>Or is the bottom<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> of
 a deepe carouse,</L>
<L>Able to drowne them? will their furie melt</L>
<L>At the beholding of your daintie wiues?</L>
<L>Or can submission be a stickler</L>
<L>In these hot braules? I tell ye burgers no,</L>
<L><PB REF="11"/>Faire words will be as oyle to burning pitch;</L>
<L>And golde as Sulpher to inkindled; flames,</L>
<L>Your daughters chastitie must quench their lust;</L>
<L>And your deare wiues,
 <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> their lawlesse armes:</L>
<L>I said as much but would not be beleeu'd,</L>
<L>Now tell me if I prophesied aright?</L>
<L>Or that my zealous words deseru'd rebuke?</L>
<L>Did I not say, the Crocadile did weepe,</L>
<L>But to obtaine his pray? the Sea looke smooth,</L>
<L>But for a storme: would any thing be thought,</L>
<L>By the close confluence of the Spanish troopes</L>
<L>Into the Castle, but some massacre?</L>
<L>Yet was I rated to obiect as much,</L>
<L>Reuil'd and bafled for my loyaltie:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cham.</SPEAKER>
<L>I <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Soldier,
 leane thy bitter words,</L>
<L>And helpe to fight for <HI>A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>twerpes</HI> libertie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stump.</SPEAKER>
<L>You haue another groate to giue me then,</L>
<L>I know your liberall mindes will scorne t'impose,</L>
<L>The sweat of bloudie daunger on the brow</L>
<L>Of any man, but you'l reward him for it:</L>
<L>He shall atleast (when he hath lost his limmes)</L>
<L>Be sent for harbour to a spittle-house.</L>
<L>How say yee, shall he not? Good reason then,</L>
<L>But we should venture; yes, to laugh at you,</L>
<L>Whilst we beholde the Spaniard cut your throates:</L>
<L>An obiect base <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> set aworke;</L>
<L>A swettie Cobler, whose best industrie,</L>
<L>Is but to cloute a Shoe, shall haue his fee;</L>
<L>But let a Soldier, that hath spent his bloud,</L>
<L>Is lame'd, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>,
 or any way distrest,</L>
<L>Appeale for suc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>our,
 then you looke a sconce</L>
<L>As if you knew him not; respecting more</L>
<L>An Ostler, or some drudge that rakes your kennels,</L>
<L>Than one that fighteth for the common wealth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bur.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is thy countrie that doth binde thee to it,</L>
<L>Not any imposition we exacte.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="11"/>
<SPEAKER>Stum.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bindes me my country with no greater bondes,</L>
<L>Than for a groate to fight<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> then for a groate,</L>
<L>To be infeebled, or to loose a limme?</L>
<L>Poore groates-worth of effection; Well, Ile learne</L>
<L>To pay my debt and to measure my desert</L>
<L>According to the rate: a groate I had,</L>
<L>And so much as a groate amounts vnto you,</L>
<L>My swoord shall pay ye in exchange of blowes.</L>
<STAGE>Ex<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter two <HI>Cittizens.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cham.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cittizens how now?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Cit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh <HI>Monsieur Champaigne,</HI></L>
<L>We are vndone for want of discipline,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 Cit.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Spaniards hurrie into euerie streete,</L>
<L>What shall we doe for safeguard of our liues?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bur.</SPEAKER>
<L>What shall yee doe? stand euery man at's doore,</L>
<L>And take in's hand a Holbert or browne bill,</L>
<L>And studie to defend him as he may.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cha.</SPEAKER>
<L>I heare them comming, let vs shift away.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ex<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>unt</STAGE>
<STAGE>In the Alarum, <HI>Alua</HI> and <HI>Danila</HI> pursue
<HI>Marques Hauurie,</HI> and <HI>Count Egmont</HI> furisus<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>e.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alu.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Marques d' Hauurie</HI> stay, thou canst not scape.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dan.</SPEAKER>
<L>And stay Count <HI>Egmont: Danilaes</HI> conquering sword,</L>
<L>Pursues thy life, therfore abide and yeeld it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L>Insatiate <HI>Alua,</HI> that like Sun-ri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e ground,</L>
<L>Neuer suffis'd with sweetest shewers that fall,</L>
<L>But with a thousand mouthes gapes still for more.</L>
<L>So thy desire of bloud nere satisfied,</L>
<L>With the rich tribute of so many liues,</L>
<L>Whose guiltles bloud hath dyed poore <HI>Belgius</HI>
 checkes,</L>
<L>And chang'd her like a drunken Bacchanall,</L>
<L>Still with a thousand quenchles appe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>es,</L>
<L>Dost thirst for more, as if that epithite</L>
<L>Were the sole obiect of thy hearts best hope<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></L>
<L><PB REF="12"/>Know Tyrant, <HI>Marques Hauurie</HI> flyes thee
 not,</L>
<L>As fearing all the vttermost thou canst,</L>
<L>But the oppression of vnequall power,</L>
<L>False treason, that betrayed our liues to thee,</L>
<L>And the sharpe scourge, that fond securitie,</L>
<L>Hath iustlie throwne on <HI>A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>twerpes</HI> wilfulnes</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Egm.</SPEAKER>
<L>These are the sluices that haue brought on vs,</L>
<L>The swelling pride and tyranie of Spaine,</L>
<L>Which <HI>Antwerpe</HI> careles off, although fore-warnde</L>
<L>By many bleeding instances about her,</L>
<L>Could not; nay, would not be aduis'd at all.</L>
<L>Tell me but this, <HI>Alua</HI> and <HI>Danila</HI> both,</L>
<L>What state is there, be it nere so populare,</L>
<L>Abounding in the height of fortunes giftes;</L>
<L>And all felicities of worldlie Pompe,</L>
<L>That sees sad desolation sit in teares,</L>
<L>Vpon her neighbour Citties? warres keene edge,</L>
<L>Hath surrowed through their entrailes, let them blood,</L>
<L>In euerie art<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re
 that maintaineth life,</L>
<L>Yet will not dread her daunger to be neere?</L>
<L>But warme her at their fiers, sing at their sighes,</L>
<L>Reuelling in her countlesse vanities,</L>
<L>As a perpetuall date were set thereon.</L>
<L>Tell me I say, you that haue seene all this,</L>
<L>And as deuils, Saints in the blacke Kallender</L>
<L>Of wretchedst woe may truelie be set downe,</L>
<L>As Authors of these sad confusions?</L>
<L>Doe not you deeme that state well worth the illes,</L>
<L>That this remissenes brought vpon the rest?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>They cannot but confesse so much Count <HI>Eg∣mont.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eg,</SPEAKER>
<L>If this be graunted what's your glorie then?</L>
<L>An armed man to kill an naked soule:</L>
<L>A thousand Sickles thrust into a field,</L>
<L>Of Summer ripened and resistles corne:</L>
<L>A mightie tide to ouer-run a land;</L>
<L>Where no defence or bancke to keepe it backe▪</L>
<L><PB REF="12"/>This is your honor, this their miserie,</L>
<L>That are not conquer'd, but dye wilfullie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Warre taketh ho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>le
 on all aduantages.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>What neede aduantage, where is no resist?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dan.</SPEAKER>
<L>So much the better, this is our discipline,</L>
<L>Therefore submit or dye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not while I haue a hand to lift my swoord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor you Count <HI>Egmont?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Egm.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Alua,</HI> nor I.</L>
<L><HI>Egmont</HI> will with honour both liue and dye.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>The Alarum againe, and <HI>Champaigne</HI> is pursued in by
<HI>Ro∣mero, Verdugo</HI> and <HI>Van End,</HI> where he is slaine: so is the
<HI>Marques Hauurie,</HI> and all engirting Count <HI>Egmont, Alua</HI> steps
to defend him, &amp; they strike at him.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Holde when I bid ye; strike yee all at mee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why stands thou then to guard an enemie?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Because I will, honor encites me to it,</L>
<L>The honor of this worthie Noble-man,</L>
<L>And his high spirit euen in the face of death.</L>
<L>Yeeld thee braue <HI>Egmont, Alua</HI> doth intreate thee,</L>
<L>In pittie of thy bolde aduenturous youth,</L>
<L>And hopefull Fortunes shining in thine eyes,</L>
<L>Thou seest these slaine, yet will<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> saue thy life:</L>
<L>Thou seest me wounded to preserue thy life.</L>
<L>I that was neuer pittifull before,</L>
<L>Am forc't to pitty thee, what wouldst thou more?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Egm.</SPEAKER>
<L>Such pitty <HI>Alua,</HI> as thou shewedst my Father,</L>
<L>And Noble <HI>Horne,</HI> such thou intendst tome,</L>
<L>Therfore proceede &amp; neuer pitty me. <HI>They offer at him
 agen</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Strike not I chargeue: come <HI>Egmont</HI> come,</L>
<L>Is weare that thou shalt yeeld; strike, spare me not,</L>
<L>Alas thou art too faint; come, yeeld thee now,</L>
<STAGE>Striuing to g<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t
 againe his weapons</STAGE>
<L>I faith I will not hurt thee: So, haue done,</L>
<L>Nay, no more weapons, thou art my prisoner.</L>
<L><PB REF="13"/>And I will vse thee verie honorablie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Egm.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Alua,</HI> let foorth my life, &amp; then thou honorst m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not for the world, prisoner thou shalt to Spaine,</L>
<L>And there be entertain'd to thy desertes.</L>
<L>Now pittie, packe from <HI>Aluaes</HI> hart againe,</L>
<L>Against my nature once I lookt on thee,</L>
<L>For this C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>unts
 sake: now to the desarts flye,</L>
<L>For hauocke, spoile and murder now I crye.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Champaignes</HI> wife hurried by two rascall
Solders.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lad.</SPEAKER>
<L>Haue mercie on a woman I beseech you,</L>
<L>As you are men and Soldiers:</L>
<L>If you be christians doe not doe me shame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 So<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d.</SPEAKER>
<L>Search her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Sold.</SPEAKER>
<L>Zwonds turne her inside outward.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Sold.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ransacke her, euerie part of her.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Stump.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<L>For manhood spare me.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>They stand to search her.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>St<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m.</SPEAKER>
<L>How nimblie death be-stirs him euery where,</L>
<L>And I that am a wearie of my life,</L>
<L>And would faine dye I cannot,</L>
<L>Death is so proude he will not looke on me,</L>
<L>These muddie roagues that hoorded vp their coyne,</L>
<L>Now haue their throates cut for the coyne they haue:</L>
<L>They that for two pence would haue seene me starue,</L>
<L>And still my olde rotten stump and I,</L>
<L>Trot vp and downe as long as we can wag.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>They begin to strip her.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<L>As you are men▪ be mercifull to me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Sol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cast lots who shall haue her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 Sol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile giue thee my share for thy part.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Sol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile haue my share in her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 Sol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Off with her Iewels</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stum.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now, two Soldiers ransacking a woman?</L>
<L><PB REF="13"/>O tis <HI>Champaignes</HI> wife that was the
 Gouernor,</L>
<L>Heere is she, that would not haue been seene</L>
<L>with a moath vpon her, for a thousand pound;</L>
<L>That spent as much on Munkeys, Dogs and Par<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ets,</L>
<L>As would haue kept ten Soldiers all the yeere.</L>
<L>Zblood I haue seene her, where I haue past by her</L>
<L>In the streetes, to stop her nose with her sweete gloues,</L>
<L>For feare my smell should haue infected her;</L>
<L>And now I liue to see her l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>g'd, and torne</L>
<L>By lowzie totter'd roagues: O <HI>Antwerpe, Antwerpe,</HI></L>
<L>Now Madame <HI>Marchpaigne,</HI> minx, your Blowes</L>
<L>And you are one.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Sol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lets haue her in the next corner.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 Sold.</SPEAKER>
<L>Draw her along,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stum.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take that she has it is sufficient,</L>
<L>But goe no further, it is inhumaine to abuse a woman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Sol.</SPEAKER>
<L>What roague art thou, darst speake vnto a Spa∣niard?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stumpe.</SPEAKER>
<L>No roague Sir, but a Soldier as you are,</L>
<L>And haue had one leg more then I haue now.</L>
<STAGE>Pointing to his leg.</STAGE>
<L>Sir, heer's my Pasport, I haue knowne the warres,</L>
<L>And haue had the vantage of as faire a spoile as you haue
 heere.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 Sol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away you whorson cripple rascall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stu.</SPEAKER>
<L>You totter'd shake-rag'd roagues, what domi∣neere you?</L>
<L>If <HI>Daluas</HI> self were heere, he should not doe it.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>He drawes his swoord, killes one, and the other flyes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good Soldier, heer's one Iewell that they haue not</L>
<L>That I doe vallue at a thousand crownes,</L>
<L>I pray thee take it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stum.</SPEAKER>
<L>What should I doe with it, can you tell?</L>
<L>To haue my throate cut for it, ha:</L>
<L>No, no your Sister Mince-pies groate</L>
<L>Will doe me no pleasure now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<L>For Gods loue, as you euer did respect a woman,</L>
<L>Helpe to conuay me to some place of safetie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="14"/>
<SPEAKER>Stum.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where is it? not in <HI>Antwerpe.</HI></L>
<L>Your closet will not serue your turne,</L>
<L>You cannot walke to your garden-house.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<L>For Gods sake helpe me as you are a man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stump.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, follow me, Ile doe the best I can.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>A company of rascall Soldiers came heere pursuing the Ladie,
he fightes and beares her away from them all.</STAGE>
<STAGE>After a triumphant shout within, enter <HI>Alua, Dauila,
Rome∣ro, Verdugo, Van End,</HI> with their Rapiers drawne, crying.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<L>Victorie, victorie, <HI>Antwerpe</HI> and victorie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alu.</SPEAKER>
<L>So valliant Lords, this Musicke likes me well,</L>
<L>Now may we boldely say the towne is ours:</L>
<L>Yet sheath not your victorious swoords awhile,</L>
<L>Till you haue reapt the Haruest of your paine,</L>
<L>In which pursuite, torture, exacte and kill,</L>
<L>No lesse then in your fury you haue done.</L>
<L>If the proude <HI>Antwerpers</HI> (that doe suruiue)</L>
<L>Lay not their treasure at your conquering feete.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Though no resistance any where appeare,</L>
<L>Yet let not anger so decline with you</L>
<L>Be proude of victorie, as well yee may,</L>
<L>Knowing the worth of your attained prize.</L>
<L>Tis wealthie <HI>Antwerpe</HI> you haue won, and how?</L>
<L>Not by a lingering siedge, of monthes or yeares,</L>
<L>But in a moment; entring at a leauen,</L>
<L>By two a clocke her haughtie pride is shrunke,</L>
<L>And she in duetie stoopeth to your will.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can any heere report the certaine number,</L>
<L>Of those that haue been slaine during the conflict?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>I had a note my Lord, as I remember,</L>
<L>The number of the dead, by vs cut off,</L>
<L><PB REF="14"/>Is seauenteene thousand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dan.</SPEAKER>
<L>But of our men,</L>
<L>How many fell there in this short assault?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Three hundred, or not manie more my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alua.</SPEAKER>
<L>For those three hundred, let ten thousand more,</L>
<L>Of this subiected Cittie loose their liues,</L>
<L>Chaine them together in the Market place,</L>
<L>By hundreds and two hundreds▪ and with shot,</L>
<L>Ring them about vntill they all be slaine,</L>
<L>Spare neither widdow, matron, not young maide,</L>
<L>Gray-bearded Fathers, nor the babe that suckes.</L>
<L>One Spaniards bloud, I value better worth,</L>
<L>Then many hundreds of these drunken Dutch.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ver.</SPEAKER>
<L>First, if it please yee, quarter we the towne,</L>
<L>That euerie one may know his priuiledge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well thought vpon <HI>Verdugo:</HI> thus it shall be.</L>
<L>The Burse, the State-house, and the Market place,</L>
<L>Belongs to me: the Castle and that side,</L>
<L>To <HI>Sancto Danila:</HI> on the other hand</L>
<L>The key, and water-port <HI>(Verdugo)</HI> is yours.</L>
<L>Saint Georges port, and Kibdop, we assigne</L>
<L>To Lord <HI>Romeso:</HI> and for you <HI>Van End,</HI></L>
<L>The North part of the Cittie, Venus streete,</L>
<L>Remaines the subiect of desired spoile:</L>
<L>So Lords, if I haue well deuided, speake;</L>
<L>If not, you shall be pleas'd before we part?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Lordship hath discreetelie cast our lots,</L>
<L>And for my part, I doe accept of mine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>So doth <HI>Romero.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ver.</SPEAKER>
<L>And <HI>Verdugo</HI> too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Van.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I no lesse, than who is best content.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alu.</SPEAKER>
<L>About it then, be euerie one as quicke,</L>
<L>In rifling of these rich Burgers, as he was</L>
<L>In the assault: the world may talke of vs,</L>
<L>As well for vallor as our quicke dispatch.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Da.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Soldiers and my self will straight begin.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="15"/>
<SPEAKER>Rom.</SPEAKER>
<L>And mine shall follow.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile not be behinde.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alua.</SPEAKER>
<L>What will <HI>Verdugo?</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter English Gouernor and <HI>Godfry.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ver.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not be Idle long,</L>
<L>But who are these so saw cily intrude?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alua.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who are ye? speake, that like vnbidden guests,</L>
<L>Dare tempt the patience of incensed <HI>Alua?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gou.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are of England (<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>astiles Generall)</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Of England are ye<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
 what although you be,</L>
<L>Backe slaues vnto the doore from whence ye came,</L>
<L>And on your knees sollicite <HI>Aluaes</HI> greatnes:</L>
<L>If you doe looke for mercie at his hands.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ver.</SPEAKER>
<L>Backe when he bids you; now downe vpon your knees,</L>
<L>And craule vnto his presence to beg life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alu.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Verdugo,</HI> drag him by the long tail'd beard,</L>
<L><HI>Alua</HI> doth scorne to waite vpon their leasure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ve.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come forward with a pox; now speake your mind,</L>
<L>And speake discreetlie, least you speake your last.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gou.</SPEAKER>
<L>This crueltie is more then we deserue,</L>
<L>And more than we expected would be showne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Taxe ye me then with crueltie so soone?</L>
<L>You shall haue cause.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Offer to strike▪</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ver.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay heare them speake my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>What can they say to shield thēselues from death?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Goue.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nothing my Lord if in your angrie spleane</L>
<L>You haue alreadie past your sentence on vs:</L>
<L>But would the Duke of <HI>Alua</HI> coole his rage,</L>
<L>And mildelie heare vs: we would say my Lord,</L>
<L>That Englands league with Spaine, King <HI>Phillips</HI>
 word,</L>
<L>Past to our gratious Mistris, were enough</L>
<L>To warrant all the liues of any such,</L>
<L>As are her subiects in this wretched towne:</L>
<L>And not their liues alone, but safe protection</L>
<L>Both for their goods and money: but if now</L>
<L><PB REF="15"/>Your Highnes hath commission to breake</L>
<L>The holie contract which your King hath made,</L>
<L>We must be patient and abide the worst.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why what art thou that standst vpon the league?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Go.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gouernor (my Lord) of the English house.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sirra, you challenge the vertue of the league,</L>
<L>Yet vnderstand not how the league is made.</L>
<L>So long as you conuerse not with the foes</L>
<L>Of royall <HI>Phillip,</HI> nor withstand his right,</L>
<L>You are exempt the rigour of his scourge;</L>
<L>But being heere, in this rebellious towne,</L>
<L>You must partake the punishment they feele.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Go.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are not heere great Lord, to ioyne with them</L>
<L>In any bolde confederacie of warre,</L>
<L>But for the trafficke, which all nations else,</L>
<L>(As well as England) haue within this place.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why left ye not the Cittie then, perceiuing</L>
<L>We meant to call their duetie to account?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Go.</SPEAKER>
<L>We had no signe of any such intent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>You cannot so be quit nor so excus'd,</L>
<L>Therefore prouide before to morrow night,</L>
<L>To bring vnto vs fortie thousand Crownes,</L>
<L>For ransome of your house; or if you faile,</L>
<L>Both goods and liues shall all be forfeited:</L>
<L>So much we are content to yeeld vnto,</L>
<L>Because we will not seeme to breake the league.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Go.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas my Lord, tis more then (at this time)</L>
<L>Our goods and money will amount vnto,</L>
<L>Considering that our credit (by this trouble)</L>
<L>Is quite cut off, with any of the Citty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shift as you can, I vow to haue no lesse,</L>
<L>And at the appointed time.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ver.</SPEAKER>
<L>Consider of it,</L>
<L>His fauour's great in giuing you such scope.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Go.</SPEAKER>
<L>So is the Cat that dallieth with the mouse,</L>
<L>But in the end, her pastime is his death;</L>
<L><PB REF="16"/>We must prouide, the Spaniards thirst is great,</L>
<L>And better that we quench it with our golde,</L>
<L>Than let them swallow and carouse our bloudes:</L>
<L>I prethee <HI>Godfrie</HI> trie thy friendes abroad,</L>
<L>And any money that thou hast bring foorth,</L>
<L>That we may make the summe which he desires.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>God.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile doe the best I can, though hard it be,</L>
<L>To finde a friend in this extreamitie.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Sancto Danila,</HI> an olde Cittizen and
Soldiers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let not your rough intreatie so molest,</L>
<L>The soule of him whose spirit alreadie stoopes,</L>
<L>Vnder the heauy burthen of weake age;</L>
<L>You haue my treasure, what more can you craue?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> so we
 please: there yet remaines</L>
<L>A <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ewell of more
 worth than all thy wealth,</L>
<L>Which (like a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>) thou didst hide from vs.</L>
<L>Thou hast a daughter, whome till we enioy,</L>
<L>All <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> proceedes
 from vs, sits heere,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> point of my
 Semiter;</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> speake?</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> in this
 tumult.</L>
<L>What <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> than her
 graue my Lord,</L>
<L>Can be <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> she
 hath?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Torture the slaue,</L>
<L>His guilefull heart, that studies to conceale,</L>
<L>My deare hearts treasure, shall be forc't in sighes</L>
<L>To publish, what his stubborne tongue denies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou hearst olde fellow, trifle than no longer,</L>
<L>But shew him where thy daughter doth abide.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why pawse ye on my bidding let him dye,</L>
<L>That doubles with a Spaniard in his will.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heare ye my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not any whispering noise,</L>
<L>Not any tittle, doth not beare the sound,</L>
<L><PB REF="16"/>Of beauties sweet fruition to mine eares.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cit.</SPEAKER>
<L>My daughter li<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es,
 but not within the reach</L>
<L>Of my commaund: a Nunnerie in the armes</L>
<L>Of her religious peacefull priuiledge,</L>
<L>Doth clip her silly frighted Virgins life,</L>
<L>From whence my Lord she cannot be recall'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beare Arte vpon thy tongue, that may vnlocke</L>
<L>The gates of that in closed Sanctuarie,</L>
<L>And first intreate; but if intreatie faile,</L>
<L>Then vse commaund; if neither will preuaile,</L>
<L>Yet so thou shalt not cease, but in the cordes</L>
<L>Of violent furie drag the Damsell thence:</L>
<L>My soldiers shall attend to see it done,</L>
<L>That if, thou shrinke, their weapons naked points,</L>
<L>May gordge thy sides, till thou bleed out thy life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cit.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would that Sacrifice might end this strife.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Da.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away with him loue faints through colde delay,</L>
<L>Tis <HI>Danila</HI> speakes, and what he will he may.</L>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Factor.</STAGE>
<L>Of whence are you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fac.</SPEAKER>
<L>Of England Noble Lord,</L>
<L>A Factor to a London Marchant heere,</L>
<L>Who hauing tryed my friends, and strain'd my purse,</L>
<L>To make my ransome: am now carrying it</L>
<L>To mightie <HI>Alua,</HI> to redeeme my life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dan.</SPEAKER>
<L>What value is it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fac.</SPEAKER>
<L>Full fiue hundred Dollors.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is this the vtmost penny thou canst make?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fac.</SPEAKER>
<L>The length and depth of my abilitie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dan.</SPEAKER>
<L>It will not seruetor search thy chest for more</L>
<L>Or bide the torture we impose on such,</L>
<L>As cunningly, withholde what we demaund.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fac.</SPEAKER>
<L>There is not in the world (that I may call</L>
<L>Rightly mine owne) one Stiuer or one Do<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>te,</L>
<L>More then is there compriz'd within th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> bag.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Giue him the strippado;
 <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></L>
<L><PB REF="17"/>Out of your disioynted limmes other summes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fac.</SPEAKER>
<L>The world doth know, my conscience and iust heauen,</L>
<L>That there is all (at this time) I possesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Saue what is throwne into some hollow vault,</L>
<L>Or sunke into some Well; or buried deepe</L>
<STAGE>Hois<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> him vp and
 let him downe againe.</STAGE>
<L>Within the earth: so hoise the peasant vp,</L>
<L>Now let him downe; will ye confesse as yet,</L>
<L>Where we may finde the treasure you haue hid?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fac.</SPEAKER>
<L>That which (my Lord) is not, cannot be hid,</L>
<L>And to say that I know not, will but wrong</L>
<L>Your expectation, and deceiue my selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let him rest my Lord, it seemes the wretch</L>
<L>Argues the troth, and this is all he hath.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hence greedy begger, harke (peeld sheepe)</L>
<L>Goe hide thee in some bush, till waxing houres</L>
<L>Giue thee another fleece to cloath thee with.</L>
<L>Yonder ariseth the bright morning Starre.</L>
<STAGE>Enter an old cittizen with his daughter.</STAGE>
<L>Whose rich resplendour gildes my happy thoughts,</L>
<L>And opens mynes of treasure to my soule;</L>
<L>Welcome faire sweet, mine armes shall be thy throane,</L>
<L>Where seated once, mocke death, and laugh to scorne,</L>
<L>The boysterous threates, of bloud be-sprinckled warre,</L>
<L>Who whilst he shewes wilde Friscoes in the streetes,</L>
<L>And with his Gamballes, ouerthrowes huge buildings,</L>
<L>Mingle their totter'd ruynes, with the limmes</L>
<L>And Clotted bloud of many thousand soules:</L>
<L>Shall as an Anticke in thy sight appeare,</L>
<L>Yeelding no more occasion to be fear'd,</L>
<L>Than painted shapes of Lyons on a wall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Daug.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beholde a Virgin, whose distilling teares</L>
<L>Turne the drye dust to paste, where she doth kneele,</L>
<L>Beholde the Siluer cognisance of age,</L>
<L><PB REF="17"/>Soyl'd with dissoluing drops of sorrows rage:</L>
<L>If me you touch with a lasciuious hand,</L>
<L>As from his eyes descendes a floud of teares;</L>
<L>So will you draw a riuer from his heart,</L>
<L>Of his lifes bloud; both waies you shall obscure,</L>
<L>The honor of your name: if Virgin I,</L>
<L>Or aged he, misdoe by tyranie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let conquest satisfie, since in the strength</L>
<L>Of your succes-full power, our Cittie vailes,</L>
<L>And lyes in prostrate duetie at your feete:</L>
<L>Or if not conquest, be appeas'd with golde,</L>
<L>Which in aboundance pleades for our release,</L>
<L>Onely refraine, our conscience to wound,</L>
<L>With that, for which there is no phisicke found.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dan.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am impatient, she shall be my loue,</L>
<L>Of all the spoiles are reapt by painefull warre,</L>
<L>Blot beautie out, and what's our victorie?</L>
<L>But as a banquet without companie.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Alarum.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter a Soldier.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Arme you my Lord, and to the fight againe,</L>
<L>A crew of stragling Soldiers (lately vanquisht)</L>
<L>Haue gathered head, and in the heate of rage,</L>
<L>Giue fresh assault: the leader to the rest,</L>
<L>Is a lame fellow that doth want a legge,</L>
<L>Who layes about him like a deuill of hell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dan.</SPEAKER>
<L>A troope of Muskets guarde this damsell hence,</L>
<L>And to my lodging see her safely brought,</L>
<STAGE>alarum againe</STAGE>
<L>Why stirre yee not? inuiron her with shot,</L>
<L>Whilst we extinguish (with a shewer of bloud)</L>
<L>This late inkindled fire: be gone I say.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sol.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is impossible to passe the streetes,</L>
<L>They are so pesterd with this brainsicke
 <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>:</L>
<L>And harke my Lord, except you mount be time,</L>
<L>(The clamorous tumult drawes so neere this place,)</L>
<L><PB REF="18"/>Both you and we shall be surpriz'd by them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Da.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is there no Fortresse neere, nor house of strength,</L>
<L>Where I may leaue my Loue, till this blacke cloude,</L>
<L>Of swolne Hostilitie be ouer-blowne?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sold.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not any (good my Lord) leade on your troopes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then rather than another shall inioy,</L>
<L>What <HI>Danila</HI> held esteemed in his eye,</L>
<L>Heere it began, and heere my loue shall dye.</L>
<STAGE>Shootes her with a Pistoll.</STAGE>
<L>Another Stab her Father, both combinde,</L>
<L>By natures lawes, by natures law shall end.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt</STAGE>
<STAGE>Stab the olde man.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Leiutenant <HI>Vaughan</HI> and Captaine.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vaugh.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet is not <HI>Antwerpe</HI> quite bereft of life,</L>
<L>So long as we two breath, to stand for her,</L>
<L>Nor shall her ransacke passe, without some right</L>
<L>Of iust reuenge: witnes this last assault,</L>
<L>Wherein the Scales of Iustice haue been fill'd,</L>
<L>With (at the least) a hundred Spaniards liues,</L>
<L>That thought their victorie to be secure.</L>
<L>But who are these? a Burger, and with him</L>
<L>His tender daughter, hauing both sustain'd</L>
<L>The heauy stroake of death?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>I knew them well.</L>
<L>They were my neighbors, ne<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re vnto the Bu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>se.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Had these gray hayres retain'd the reuerent worth</L>
<L>Of graue experience, as they might haue done;</L>
<L>And had you bin more rich in inward giftes,</L>
<L>And lesse magnificent in outward shew,</L>
<L>Then had you liu'd, to dye a naturall death:</L>
<L>And you to see some of his honor'd yeeres.</L>
<L>But pride and luxury, haue euer been,</L>
<L>The gate of miserie, and nurse of sinne:</L>
<L>Yet though you me contemn'd, I grieue your fall,</L>
<L>And will in pitty, giue you buriall.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE><PB REF="18"/>Enter <HI>Lenchy</HI> and <HI>Martin</HI> two
little children running.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas poore <HI>Lenchy,</HI> whether shall we goe:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Len.</SPEAKER>
<L>I cannot tell; come <HI>Martin</HI> let vs hide vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where is my Father?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Len.</SPEAKER>
<L>He is in our house.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let vs goe thether?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Len.</SPEAKER>
<L>All the streete is full of Spaniards; they haue kil'd</L>
<L>Little <HI>Maria,</HI> and <HI>Hans Vanderbrooke.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ah whether shall we goe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Len.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let's hide vs heere, no Spaniard wil come hether.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay <HI>M. Hulders</HI> Orchard is hard by.</L>
<L>Wee'll get in there, and hyd's among the trees,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Len.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come let vs run.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>A great noise as they are going.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas the Spaniard's comming, what shal we doe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Len.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas poore <HI>Martin</HI> we shall both be kil'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas poore <HI>Lenchy,</HI> kisse me prettie Sister,</L>
<L>Now we must dye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Len.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let's sit downe heere, and <HI>Mart.</HI> I wil clip thee in</L>
<L>Mine armes, they shall not see thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>But they will kill thee,</L>
<L>Alas where is my poore old Father now, and my poor mo∣ther?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter two Spaniards running, with theyr swords drawne.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Spa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Kill, kill, kill.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 Spa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tue, Tue, Tue, Tue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Spa,</SPEAKER>
<L>Fuora villiaco.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 Spa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Follow, follow, follow, follow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I pray you M. Spaniard hurt vs not,</L>
<L>We are poore children, we haue done no harme.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Len.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good Gaffer doe not kill my little brother.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Spa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fuora villiaco, sa, sa, sa, sa,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ah Master Spaniard doe not kill my Sister,</L>
<L>My father is a poore blinde man, and he will dye,</L>
<L><PB REF="19"/>If you kill her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 Spa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cut the Bastards throates.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>The children gets fast holde, and hang vpon the
Spaniards.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Len.</SPEAKER>
<L>O kill vs not, wee'll hang vpon your armes,</L>
<L>Sweet Gaffer, stay and looke me in the face,</L>
<L>Haue you the heart to kill a prettie Girle?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good Master Spaniard doe not kill vs,</L>
<L>Take any thing we haue, but saue our liues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Spa.</SPEAKER>
<L>How the young brattes cling about our swords?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 Spa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Zwounds, dash out their braines.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter olde blinde <HI>Harman</HI> and his wife.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Har.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where are my children? <HI>Martin, Lenchy</HI> speake,</L>
<L>I heard you cry speake prettie soules, where are you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Husband, <HI>Harman,</HI> whether will you goe?</L>
<L>Alas you fall into the enemies hands</L>
<L>For lacke of sight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Har.</SPEAKER>
<L>My children wife, my children, where are they?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Spa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heere you blind traytor, whether you shall go,</L>
<L>To your throate-cutting.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heere Father, heere, alas we shall be kild.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wif.</SPEAKER>
<L>O my sweet children,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 Sp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Out you Brabant bitch, thinke you with whining</L>
<L>To preserue your whelpes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wif.</SPEAKER>
<L>O spare the infants▪ and the aged blinde,</L>
<L>These haue not might, nor power to doe you hurt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Spa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cut all their throates.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Har.</SPEAKER>
<L>Kill vs, but let our little children liue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Len.</SPEAKER>
<L>Helpe mother helpe, or else we shall be kild.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Har. weeping.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hard harted Soldiers, where haue you bin bred?</L>
<L>Get honour on the proude resisting foe,</L>
<L>My selfe haue bin a Soldier as you are,</L>
<L>Now blinde with age:</L>
<L>Olde men, weake women, and poore wretched infants,</L>
<L>Should be respected in the heate of slaughter.</L>
<L><PB REF="19"/>O doe not this foule iniurie to armes;</L>
<L>Let my poore Babies leade me to my graue,</L>
<L>Where are you my poore children?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Father, heere.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Har.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where art thou <HI>Lenchy?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Len.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heere poore Father.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Har.</SPEAKER>
<L>Olde as I am, and I haue tolde this towne;</L>
<L>That you should sacke it, I did prophesie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 Spa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then Prophet, didst thou prophesie of this?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Stabs the Children.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wif.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ah bloudie Spaniard, that hast slaine my children.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Spa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bitch, art thou rayling? take thou this.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Stabs her.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 Spa.</SPEAKER>
<L>And this,</L>
<STAGE>Stabs him.</STAGE>
<L>Get you together with your damned brats.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Har.</SPEAKER>
<L>O cruel Spaniard that dost spare no age nor sexe,</L>
<L>Where art thou wife, and my poore little children?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Falles downe.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wif.</SPEAKER>
<L>Their blessed soules in <HI>Abrahams</HI> bosome restes,</L>
<L>Their bodies lye betwixt thy selfe and me,</L>
<L>By whome these prettie wretches were begot,</L>
<L>O let me ioyne my freezing lips to thine,</L>
<L>Now farewell <HI>Antwerpe,</HI> say not we did flye,</L>
<L>Where with thy fall, olde, yong, and all must dye.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Alua,</HI> English Gouernor and soldiers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alua.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thinke yee to purchase freedome at this rate?</L>
<L>Some thriftles prodigall bestowes in wine,</L>
<L>Or spends in dalliance on his Curtizan,</L>
<L>Fiue thousand crownes:
 <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> like your store affoords</L>
<L>No greater plentie▪ eyther from your chestes,</L>
<L>That swell with surfet of your auarice,</L>
<L>Raine downe a larger shewer of fruitfull golde,</L>
<L>Or tender flowring pittie, nere will spring.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gou.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe protest (my Lord) beside our Plate,</L>
<L>And housholde furniture, this is the summe,</L>
<L><PB REF="20"/>Of all the wealth, at this time may be found</L>
<L>Within the English-house.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alu.</SPEAKER>
<L>And is not plate</L>
<L>Good boote for Soldiers? haue you that</L>
<L>And dare yee yet pleade needie pouertie?</L>
<L>Goe fetch it me, or presentlie Ile send</L>
<L>A crew of such sharpe caruers to your gate,</L>
<L>As shall anotamize your panting hearts,</L>
<L>To fill their conquering hands with wished spoiles.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Go.</SPEAKER>
<L>The League with Engl. gaue vs better hope.</L>
<STAGE>Exit</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Talke nor of league nor England, nothing sound</L>
<L>In our warres musicke, that can please the sence;</L>
<L>Vnlesse it haue the chearefull sound of golde.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Factor.</STAGE>
<L>What's he? examine him: if he bring golde,</L>
<L>Free passage haue he; but if emptie be</L>
<L>The hollowes of his hands; or cannot point</L>
<L>By Demonstration, or expresse by speech,</L>
<L>Where it is fled, in this tempestious storme,</L>
<L>That we by hugging it, may bannish feare,</L>
<L>And burnish her pale cheekes with firmer red,</L>
<L>Let him haue that belongs, the torturing Corde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fac.</SPEAKER>
<L>Excuse my want, that haue alreadie paide</L>
<L>To <HI>Sancto Da<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ila,</HI> fiue hundred Dollors.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why not as much to me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fac.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue it not,</L>
<L>Alas (my Lord) consider of my state,</L>
<L>I am but Factor for another man;</L>
<L>Yet of those goods committed to my charge,</L>
<L>Haue I made bolde (so much as I haue said)</L>
<L>To free my life from further preiudice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alu.</SPEAKER>
<L>How art thou free, when <HI>Alua</HI> is not fee'd?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fac.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hope (my Lord) one ransome will suffice,</L>
<L>For one poore life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alu.</SPEAKER>
<L>That ransome let me see.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="20"/>
<SPEAKER>Fac.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis paide (my Lord) to <HI>Sancto Da<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ila.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alu.</SPEAKER>
<L>That which he hath is his, and none of mine,</L>
<L>vnlesse thou canst transforme vs, and of two</L>
<L>Make but one person: goe to, trifle no<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</L>
<L>But shew me how I may be satisfied,</L>
<L>Or bide the perrill that ensues thereon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fac.</SPEAKER>
<L>More satisfaction than I haue (my Lord)</L>
<L>I cannot giue, how ere you torture me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alu.</SPEAKER>
<L>That will we try, if roape and Gibbet holde,</L>
<L>Let him indure the punishment, he needes</L>
<L>Will wilfully impose vpon himselfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fac.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh that you would at once with ruthles steele,</L>
<L>Carue vp my brest, and let my bloud suffice,</L>
<L>To quench your thirst for that I cannot giue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alu.</SPEAKER>
<L>So, let him downe, stand off and giue him ayre,</L>
<L>Speake now, and tell vs where thy coyne is hid?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fac.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will yee beleeue me if I speake the truth?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alu.</SPEAKER>
<L>So it be truth which thou intendes to speake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fac.</SPEAKER>
<L>As I doe hope this troubled soule of mine,</L>
<L>Which now is ready to forsake this flesh,</L>
<L>Shall finde a resting place with my redeeme<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>:</L>
<L>The coyne you seeke, and all the coyne I haue,</L>
<L>Lyes in the Coffers of proude <HI>Danila.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lye there and pine then, for deluding me.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Verdugo.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fac.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heere comes another; many strokes (at last)</L>
<L>Cut downe the strongest Oake, much more, the tree</L>
<L>Hath but a few yeares growth, and that by stormes,</L>
<L>And often whirle-windes shaken and decayed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ver.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hast thou bin lately falne into the hands</L>
<L>Of such as haue had ryfling of thy purse?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fac.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue good Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ver.</SPEAKER>
<L>What art, a Cittizen?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fac.</SPEAKER>
<L>Euen what ye will, a miserable man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ver.</SPEAKER>
<L>It seemes, I come too late to profit by thee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="21"/>
<SPEAKER>Fac.</SPEAKER>
<L>You may immagine by my sicke faint speech,</L>
<L>And by my faltring limmes distract and seuer'd,</L>
<L>Whether I haue bin tortur'd, yea or no.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ve.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did they then torture thee for that thou hadst?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fac.</SPEAKER>
<L>They did and had it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ver.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nothing then remaines?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fac.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nothing but this poore miserable life,</L>
<L>Which I would gladly were surrendred too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ver.</SPEAKER>
<L>They for that thou hadst, did torture thee,</L>
<L>I see that thou hast not: heere wee'll put</L>
<L>A period to thy daies. Hang him out-right,</L>
<L>And so speed all, whose naked indigence,</L>
<L>Haue not to feede <HI>Verdugo</HI> for expence.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fac.</SPEAKER>
<L>My destiny, was to dye this shamefull death,</L>
<L>Which I accept with thankes to him that giues it,</L>
<L>And England now and London both farewell,</L>
<L>Let after times of Spanish rygor tell.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Hang him.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Van End</HI> and a Burgers wife.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Van.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thus will I feast my selfe with <HI>Antwerpes</HI> spoile,</L>
<L>And glut my pyning soule with tragicke Actes,</L>
<L>Say pamperd Froe, where is thy treasure hid?</L>
<L>Speake truth, or breath thy last vpon this steele,</L>
<L>The bloudy temper'd torment of this towne.</L>
<L>Ile batter downe your pride from whence it came,</L>
<L>And with your ornaments adorne vast hell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>wif.</SPEAKER>
<L>Spare me <HI>Van End</HI> I am a harmeles woman,</L>
<L>Astonisht vnto death with frighting wordes,</L>
<L>Refraine thy deedes, and let the stronger sort,</L>
<L>Be miserable patients of thy wrath</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Van.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pittie preuailes not, treasure is the fee,</L>
<L>That bribes the terror of my threatning brest;</L>
<L>And therefore speake, else hast thou spoke thy last.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>Within that vault lyes all my wretched wealth,</L>
<L>My golde my plate, my Iewels all are there.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="21"/>
<SPEAKER>Van.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then, there that heape of glorie lyes for me,</L>
<L>Which is the way?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>She pushes him downe.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>wif.</SPEAKER>
<L>That is the cursed way,</L>
<L>Goe thou accurst into that shade of hell,</L>
<L>The Image of that euerlasting night,</L>
<L>Where thy damn'd ghoast must dwel exempt from light.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Stumpe.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stum.</SPEAKER>
<L>What stirre is heere? what discontented rumor</L>
<L>Sendes second message to my dull strucke dayes,</L>
<L>Accustom'd to the screeching yell of death?</L>
<L>Lady, what grieuance? what is there to doe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>wif.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh gentle Soldier, heauen hath got me triumph,</L>
<L>Ouer that hell-borne furie, damn'd <HI>Van End,</HI></L>
<L>That solde the beautie of this famos towne:</L>
<L>And rauisht <HI>Antwerpe</HI> of her Maiden ioy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stum.</SPEAKER>
<L>For Gods sake let me come plague the dog,</L>
<L>Ile stone the Iew to death, and paint this Vault</L>
<L>With the vnhallowed bloud of wicked treason:</L>
<L>Heere, weare this waightie Iewell in thy hat,</L>
<L>The towne hath sent it for a token slaue;</L>
<STAGE>Throw stones.</STAGE>
<L>I bought this with the goate you gaue me sir;</L>
<STAGE>Another sto.</STAGE>
<L>Soldiers must loath despis'd dingratitude.</L>
<L>This woman for her ransome sends you this;</L>
<STAGE>another.</STAGE>
<L>Giue these two vnto <HI>Charon</HI> for your passing.</L>
<STAGE>another.</STAGE>
<L>And with this last, present grim <HI>Belzebub.</HI></L>
<STAGE>another.</STAGE>
<L>So sleepe thy soule with princely <HI>Lucifer,</HI></L>
<L>And take such fare as treason will affoord.</L>
<L>Come Lady, thus you see good friends must part,</L>
<L>Lament not for his losse his tyme was come,</L>
<L>And friendes from friends, must eyther goe or run.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter three or four soldiers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Sol.</SPEAKER>
<L>You see that all is lost, all spoilde and sackt,</L>
<L><PB REF="22"/>What thinke you the best course to get away?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 Sol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is there no place of strength, nor hope of safetie▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3 Sol.</SPEAKER>
<L>No hope but death for three daies being past</L>
<L>Since the first entred; now being in colde bloud,</L>
<L>The Spaniard is as hot in execution,</L>
<L>As the first houre he entred on the towne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Sol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Like maymed men let's passe out one by one,</L>
<L>The safest way and with the least suspect.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 Sol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Disseuering of ourselues, and knowne for</L>
<L>Wallons, ther's not a man of vs shal passe the gates.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Stumpe</HI> and hearing them.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3 Sol.</SPEAKER>
<L>And if we troope thus as we doe together,</L>
<L>We shall be put to swoord immediately.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Sol.</SPEAKER>
<L>It were best to seeke some low part of the wall,</L>
<L>On the moate side, and so escape by swimming.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 Sol.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Courts of guard, and Sentenels are kept,</L>
<L>And there's no hope of that.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stumpe.</SPEAKER>
<P>Harke you hark you, whether wil you flye? I wold know that;
 sbloud whether? whether? ha; where will you be releiu'd? there's not a towne
 dare receiue you: the Spaniard has all the country; you cannot stragle a foote
 out of the walles, but your throates are cut; what haue you to carry with you,
 but your scuruie notch'd limmes? you damn'd roagues, whether will you goe, to
 feede Wolues? A you whorson rascals; and though these villanos Bur∣gers haue
 (by their owne securitie beene the destruction of the Cittie, a pox on them:
 yet it will bee laide to our charge, because we were in it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Sol.</SPEAKER>
<P>By the mas the olde Lieuetenant sayes true, it wil be so
 indeed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stum.</SPEAKER>
<P>You are all Wallons, but in the miserablest case that euer poore
 slaues were in: for you see, that if any man hate a man, call him but Wallon,
 the Spaniards cut his throate, what country-man so ere he be▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 Sol.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay it is very true, it is most sure:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="22"/>
<SPEAKER>Stu.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Dutch on the other side, they hate you worse then Deuils,
 because the Spaniards entred where you kept the Trenches.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3 Sol.</SPEAKER>
<P>Villaines doe questionles, nay it is certaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stum.</SPEAKER>
<P>What will you doe then? here is my poore stumpe and I haue
 stumbled through a thousand shot, &amp; yet we halt together; there was neuer
 one poore peece of Timber has been so sindg'd as it has been:
 <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>bloud it has been foure times a
 fire vnder me, and yet we scramble to∣gether trotting, trotting: You'll bee
 staru'd euerie mo∣thers Sonne of yee, and worried with dogs, and yet you'll
 flye.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Sol.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why Lieuetenant <HI>Vaughan,</HI> what would yee haue vs
 doe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stum.</SPEAKER>
<P>Dye like men, what should we doe, if there were any hope of
 safety but there is not, there is not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 Sol.</SPEAKER>
<P>Leiuetenant <HI>Vaughan,</HI> leade vs, and wee'll follow you to
 the death.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3 Sol.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wee'll not forsake you to the last gaspe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stum.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, Ile halt before you, follow mee as straight as you
 can▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Sol.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, and cut some of their throates before wee dye.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stum.</SPEAKER>
<P>They say the Spaniards and their whoores are at dice vpon the
 Change: Ile lay my wodden legge afore them, cast at it who will; but who stands
 there?</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter the Captaine.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>It is Leiuetenant <HI>Vaughan</HI> as I take it, Leiuetenant
 what newes?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>um.</SPEAKER>
<P>What newes quoth our Captaine! where haue you been?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>I tooke the Friery to escape the Spaniards.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>um.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, haue seene the day Captaine, you
 <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> rather been a c<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ting throates, then at a Masse,
 <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>was not de∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>ion <PB REF="23"/> draue you to the place: so Captaine,
 Captaine, the world is turn'd: doe you remember the groate they offe∣red me,
 when you came to trayne Soldiers? ha, giue him a groate? ha, ha, I haue since
 that seene their Mistresses <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>
 by a lowzy Lackey, as naked as a new shau'd Water-dog: &amp; Lord why went you
 to the Fryery? why to the Fryerie?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>What should I doe when the poore Wallons fighting at the
 Trenches,</P>
<L>The Spaniards entring on the counterscarfe,</L>
<L>Had not a Soldier sent to second them.</L>
<L>The great swolne bellyed Burgers get browne Billes,</L>
<L>As to driue rascall beggers from their doores;</L>
<L>The madding people so amaz'd with feare,</L>
<L>That turning head with euery little noise,</L>
<L>Stopt vp the entrance of the streetes with throngs,</L>
<L>That when Count <HI>Egmont, Hauury</HI> and the rest,</L>
<L>Call'd to the Burgers for supplyes of men,</L>
<L>The vncertaine murmure of the multitude,</L>
<L>Increast but the confusion of the towne:</L>
<L>The villanous and dastard recreant Almaines,</L>
<L>Kneele to the Spaniards, casting downe their armes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stum.</SPEAKER>
<P>A those Almaines, those Almaines, they cryed liue Spaniards: a
 vengeance take them, they were cal'd hygh Almaines, but they are low enough
 now; for a num∣ber of them are cut off by the waste: you may call them blanch'd
 Almaines and you wil, for their guts are blanch'd about their heeles.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>By these disorders of witlesse Townes-men,</L>
<L>Perceiuing that the Spaniards would preuaile;</L>
<L>What should I doe but shift to saue my life?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Capt. your life's in as great danger now as ere it was,</L>
<L>The Spaniard is as cruell in colde bloud as ere he was;</L>
<L>O Captaine, Captaine, where is <HI>Antwerpe</HI> now?</L>
<L>It <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> my natiue
 place, where should I then be free,</L>
<L>If made a sl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ue,
 where I was freelie borne?</L>
<L><PB REF="23"/>Ther's not a towne almost in Brabant now,</L>
<L>That giues a man the safet<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> of a night:</L>
<L>What should we then doe liuing:</L>
<L>Haue you and I seene that, that we haue seene,</L>
<L>And come to this?</L>
<L>If you reserue the courage you were wont,</L>
<L>Of a braue Soldier and a Gentleman,</L>
<L>Let's doe something yet worthy the talking of,</L>
<L>I haue wonne a companie of poore hurt Soldiers,</L>
<L>Yet able to welde weapons and to fight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Sol.</SPEAKER>
<L>And we will follow you, liue or dye:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 Sol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Loue life and loue death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3 Sol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Through <HI>Aluas</HI> quarter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stum.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why brauely spoke,</L>
<L>If you will take such part then as we doe,</L>
<L>Helpe me to leade these stragling companies,</L>
<L>And wee'll amongst their quarters ere we dye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>My hand and heart, and doe engage my soule.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why then come lads; why this is resolu'd like men,</L>
<L>If we must goe, wee'll goe together then.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter two soldiers leading in the fat Burger in a Cord<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Sol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Confesse ye slaue where thou hast hid thy money,</L>
<L>Or we will hang thee on a Gibbet straight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bur.</SPEAKER>
<L>That euer I was borne; Gentlemen beleeue me,</L>
<L>I haue no more than what I tolde you of,</L>
<L>Some thousand Gilders in my counting house.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 Sol.</SPEAKER>
<L>You haue no more than?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Burg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not as I haue faith</L>
<L>To God, and to the safetie of my Country.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 Sol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then hang him presentlie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay curteous Gentlemen,</L>
<L>As you are Spaniards famous for your actes,</L>
<L>Let me not dye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Sol.</SPEAKER>
<L>The roague would flatter vs,</L>
<L><PB REF="24"/>S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ra,
 immagine tis too weake a key,</L>
<L>To tune our hearts to; when the cryes of Babes,</L>
<L>Screekes of distressed women and olde men,</L>
<L>Haue not preuail'd to quallifie our rage:</L>
<L>Let vs dispatch him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gentlemen, but heare me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 Sol.</SPEAKER>
<L>If thou canst tell vs where thy treasure's hid,</L>
<L>Or else for euer let thy lips be dumbe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas would yee haue me lye?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Sol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay fellow Soldier,</L>
<L>I ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e bethought me
 of a prettie tricke,</L>
<L>To sift this butter-box a better way:</L>
<L>Wee 'll tye him by the thumbes vnto this poast,</L>
<L>And tickle him vntill he doe confesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 Sol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Contentyfaith, so at the least, suppose</L>
<L>We get no money yet we shall haue sport.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay Gentlemen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Sol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sirra, apply your wits,</L>
<L>Or with my swoord Ile hacke your Filchers off.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bur.</SPEAKER>
<L>O that I were in'th bottom of my Seller.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 Sol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is thy money hid there? speake?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bur.</SPEAKER>
<L>No truelie sir,</L>
<L>But then I hope I should not hang byth thumbes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Sol.</SPEAKER>
<L>He dallyes with vs, tickle him a good.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh God, God, what shall I do, sweet gentlemen.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>They tickle him.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 Sol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Confesse then, sirra.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bur.</SPEAKER>
<L>O Lord I shall sound,</L>
<L>By these ten endes, I haue nor plate nor coyne,</L>
<L>Your Generall and Countrimen haue all.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Alarum, enter <HI>Stumpe</HI> and <HI>Captaine,</HI> the
Spaniards fly.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>What <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> we heer,
 a Burger tyed <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>yth thumbs?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stum.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is the Tallow-cake, the Rammish Fat,</L>
<L>That would not giue a penny to a Soldier,</L>
<L><PB REF="24"/>I know him well; now Sir how feele your
 selfe▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh Gentlemen neuer so much distrest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stum.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your greazie panch will not defend you then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not from these Spaniards, they
 <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> think,</L>
<L>Nay farre more couetous than deuils of hell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stum.</SPEAKER>
<L>You cannot satisfie them with a groate,</L>
<L>But if I should requite thy vilde contempt,</L>
<L>Heere should I leaue thee, that as thy treasure</L>
<L>Has bin a pray to their deuouring lust,</L>
<L>So in this dung-hill of thy carryon flesh,</L>
<L>Their rauenous swoords might finde a du<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tie feast,</L>
<L>For naught but draffe art thou composed of.</L>
<L>Nor fit for any thing but to feede wormes,</L>
<L>Yet thou shalt finde a difference twixt my thoughts</L>
<L>And the base temper of thy muddy minde:</L>
<L>Goe liue, if thou canst scape their bloudie hands,</L>
<L>Till want and beggerie cut short thy daies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bur.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thanke you sir; I haue (for all their threates)</L>
<L>One bag of Dollors cast into a well,</L>
<L>And that Ile giue yee for this friendlie succour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hence tumbrell from my sight, when boūty might</L>
<L>Haue calm'd my sharpe affliction then thy hand</L>
<L>Was fast clos<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d vp;
 but now it is too late,</L>
<L>Thou wouldst seeme prodigall, away base churle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me intreate you sir, to take that summe,</L>
<L>My heart repents me much, for what is past.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stum.</SPEAKER>
<L>Guts, trouble me no more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bur.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Lord preserue you sir,</L>
<L>Surely you seeme an honest Gentleman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wilt thou leaue off thy prating and be gone?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bur.</SPEAKER>
<L>With all my heart sir, and I thanke you too.</L>
<STAGE>Exit</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>How like <HI>Leuiathan,</HI> his clumsie limbes</L>
<L>Walke not but tumble, that sad common wealth,</L>
<L>Nourceth such Droanes to sucke her honny vp,</L>
<L>In time of need shall finde as small supply,</L>
<L>As he hath been to <HI>Antwerpes</HI> wretchednes:</L>
<L><PB REF="25"/>But valliant Soldier, what is now to doe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stum.</SPEAKER>
<L>What, but to hunt the foote-steps of pale death,</L>
<L>Vntill we rouze him in his sooty caue,</L>
<L>There, will no prospect of our Countries fall,</L>
<L>Offend our eye-sight; there no treacherie</L>
<L>Of haughty Spaniards treade a bloudy March;</L>
<L>Nor any base obiection of ingrate,</L>
<L>And thankelesse Cittizens sit in our doores:</L>
<L>But we shall quietly inioy the peace,</L>
<L>For which we breath; there shall we be secure,</L>
<L>There free from thought of this worlds miserie,</L>
<L>And there indeede finde true felicitie:</L>
<L>For there our trauell shall be recompenc'd,</L>
<L>Our loue requited, and our wounds repayde</L>
<L>With double merrit. Haste then vnto the place,</L>
<L>Vpon the earth is nothing but disgrace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>I flye with thee true honourable minde,</L>
<L>And we together will that Mancion finde.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Alarum and excursions, enter <HI>Stumpe</HI> and
<HI>Captaine,</HI> bloudy and wounded.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stum.</SPEAKER>
<L>See Captaine, now I haue it on my brest,</L>
<L>The Honourable cognisance of death,</L>
<L>This purple riuer, from this weeping fount,</L>
<L>More glads and quickens my decayed spirit,</L>
<L>Than euer christ all spring in heate of Summer:</L>
<L>The weary traueller, his strength reuiues,</L>
<L>To draw out tedious houres still on earth,</L>
<L>But mine doth florish to possesse, anon</L>
<L>The blessed hauen of eternity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>I trust I shall be there with as much speed,</L>
<L>My pasport (I doe thinke) the Spaniards</L>
<L>Has seal'd as deeply, and my iourney layde</L>
<L>With no lesse easie trauell to be there.</L>
<L>See, if thy bleeding woundes can speake to me,</L>
<L><PB REF="25" MS="y"/>Mine can as fast make answere vnto
 thine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stum.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me imbrace this sweet affinity,</L>
<L>Like in our liues agreeing in our deathes:</L>
<L>But what doe I behold? thine eye-lids faint,</L>
<L>And the warme touch of thy desired cheeke,</L>
<L>Begins to freeze; wilt thou anticipate</L>
<L>Those ioyes before me? gentle Captaine slay,</L>
<L>There's but a minute that deuides our hopes:</L>
<L>Oh he is dead, may his departing soule,</L>
<L>Vsher my spirit aboue those fleeting clowdes:</L>
<L>Death, why delayst thou? set thy lazy hand</L>
<L>To the deuorcement of my loathed flesh.</L>
<L>I am prepar'd, my penitent sad thoughts,</L>
<L>Haue long agoe washt my contagious sinne:</L>
<L>The bloud that I haue spilt (the Massacres</L>
<L>Procur'd and practis'd by this hand of mine)</L>
<L>Heauen lay not to my charge; for though my sword</L>
<L>Was neuer drawne but in a rightfull cause,</L>
<L>Yet much misprision hath attended it;</L>
<L>That, and all else, this sigh craues pardon for,</L>
<L>Mine eyes were nere accustomed to teares,</L>
<L>Let it suffice, these woundes doe weepe for them:</L>
<L><HI>Antwerpe</HI> farewell, if thou haue done me wrong,</L>
<L>This latest gaspe, sends pardon from my tung.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Astorish.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter in triumph, with Drum, Colours and Soldiers, <HI>Sancto
Danila.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now warre hath wrapt his bloudy colours vp,</L>
<L>And sheath'd his fatall swoord with his, we ours,</L>
<L>Prefixing truce to our laborious armes;</L>
<L>This Cittie late of christening the fame,</L>
<L>For wealth and glorie: now remaines the Map,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> destruction
 and perpetu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ll
 <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>yne;</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> with
 slaughtered carkasses,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> before were
 stuft with pride,</L>
<L>An left as <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>:</L>
<L><PB REF="26" MS="y"/>Oh in remorse of humaine clemency,</L>
<L>My heart (not thinkes) could sigh, my eyes shed teares,</L>
<L>To call to minde and see their misery:</L>
<L>But they were wanton and lasciuious,</L>
<L>Too much addicted to their priuate lust:</L>
<L>And that concludes their Martirdoome was iust.</L>
<L>Holde, one of you, conuay this serious letter</L>
<L>To warlicke <HI>Alua,</HI> tell him as he wil'd,</L>
<L>After my forces lodg'd in Garison,</L>
<L>Ile meete his Grace at <HI>Bridges,</HI> and from thence</L>
<L>Acquaint the Court of <HI>Spaine</HI> with our successe;</L>
<L>Pray God the tyrany exprest in <HI>Antwerpe,</HI></L>
<L>Like to the ecchoing clamour of a Trumpet,</L>
<L>Speake not our deedes before our owne approach.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Sol.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, behold where lye the mangled bodies</L>
<L>Of those two fierce assailing Brabanters,</L>
<L>That all this while kept vs at such a bay,</L>
<L>And when we thought the towne was wonne, procur'd</L>
<L>So great a deluge of <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>berian</HI> bloud.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 Sol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let's drag them at our horses tayles my Lord,</L>
<L>And as we passe through euery towne and village,</L>
<L>Make them example to the world for pride?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who toucheth them but in disgrace, my swoord</L>
<L>Shall lop his arme off▪ were they proude sayst thou?</L>
<L>Their pride was honourable, deseruing loue</L>
<L>Rather then hate; nay should we doe them right,</L>
<L>Had they been strengthned with conuenient ayde</L>
<L>We had been bea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>
 from the towne againe</L>
<L>And made exchange of conquest: which subdu'd</L>
<L>There neuer liued two
 <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Heroieth spirits</L>
<L>That for their Country haue deser<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d as much</L>
<L>To be renouned; as euer
 <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> was</L>
<L>Or Romaine <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> or
 the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></L>
<L>They for their <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> could but loose their Liv<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>These haue inequall ser<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ice done as much</L>
<L>Take vp their bodyes; of ten thousand others</L>
<L><PB REF="26" MS="y"/>Rest by our swords, and left un<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>vied</L>
<L>These two will we in person see interr'd,</L>
<L>And doe them right, the law of Armes require<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>;</L>
<L>So march we hence, striking a mournfull sound</L>
<L>Till we haue sayde our honourd foes in ground</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt</STAGE>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="epilogue">
<HEAD>Epilogus</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Time</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Time</SPEAKER>
<L>Thus worldlings, Time in his unwonted loue</L>
<L>Hath staid his course, to rubb the memorie</L>
<L>Of actions long since cast behind his back</L>
<L>His care is fruitefull, and doth wish to see</L>
<L>No heauie or disastrous chance befall</L>
<L>The sonnes of men if they will warned be</L>
<L>But when they <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
 against my discipline</L>
<L>Wasting the treasure of my precious houre</L>
<L>No maruayle then, like misery catch holde</L>
<L>On them, did fasten oh this wofull toune</L>
<L>Whose bleeding fortune, whose lamenting
 <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></L>
<L>Whose streetes besmear'd with bloud, whose blubred eyes</L>
<L>Whose totter'd walls, whose buildings ouerthrowne</L>
<L>Whose riches lost, and pouertie made knowne:</L>
<L>May be a meane all Citties to affright</L>
<L>How they in sinne and pleasure take delight</L>
</SP>
<TRAILER>FINIS</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

