<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2006-07-17</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Elspeth Healey</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Proofed text and corrected markup.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A06589">
<STC T="S">17050</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99845365</BIBNO>
<VID>10262</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>ENDIMION,
The Man in the
<HI>Moone.</HI></P>
<P>Playd before the Queenes Ma∣iestie
at Greenewich on Candlemas day
at night, by the Chyldren of
Paules.</P>
<P><FIGURE>
<P>NOSCE TE IPSUM NE QUID NIMIS</P>
<P>LOVE AND LIVE</P>
</FIGURE></P>
<P>AT LONDON,
Printed by I. Charlewood, for
the widdowe Broome.
1591.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="printer to the reader">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>❧The Printer to the
Reader.</HEAD>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">S</SEG>Ince the Plaies in Paules were
dissolued, there are certaine
Commedies come to my
handes by chaunce, vvhich
were presented before her Maiestie at se∣uerall
times by the children of Paules. This
is the first, and if in any place it shall dys∣please,
I will take more paines to perfect the
next. I referre it to thy indifferent iudge∣ment
to peruse, whom I woulde willinglie
please. And if this may passe with thy good
lyking, I will then goe forwarde to publish
the rest. In the meane time, let this haue
thy good worde for my beuere, courage∣ment.</P>
<CLOSER>Farewell</CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="prologue">
<PB REF="3"/>
<HEAD>The Prologue.</HEAD>
<P>MOst high and happy Princesse, we must
tell you a tale of the Man in the Moone,
which if it seeme ridiculous for the me∣thod,
or superfluous for the matter, or for the
meanes incredible, for three faultes wee can
make but one excuse. It is a tale of the Man in
the Moone.</P>
<P>It was forbidden in olde time to dispute of
<HI>Chymera,</HI> because it was a fiction, we hope in
our times none will apply pastimes, because
they are fancies; for there liueth none vnder
the Sunne, that knowes what to make of the
Man in the Moonee. VVee present neither Co∣medie,
nor Tragedie, nor storie, nor anie thing,
<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="broken" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> whosoeuer heareth may say this, VVhy
heere is a tale of the Man in the Moone.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 N="1" TYPE="act">
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<PB REF="3"/>
<HEAD>Actus primus. Scaena prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Endimion. Eumenides.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>End.</SPEAKER>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">I</SEG> Finde <HI>Eumenides</HI> in all thinges
both varietie to content, &amp; sa∣tietie
to glut, sauing onelie in
my affections, which are so
stayed, and withall so statelie,
that I can neither satis-fie my
hart with loue, nor mine eyes
with wonder. My thoughts <HI>Eumenides</HI> are stitched to
the starres, which beeing as high as I can see; thou maist
imagin how much higher they are then I can reach.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eume.</SPEAKER>
<P>If you be enamored of any thing aboue the
Moone, your thoughts are ridiculous, for that thinges
immortall are not subiect to affections, if allured or en∣chaunted
with these transitory things vnder the Moone,
you shew your selfe sencelesse, to attribute such lofty ty∣tles,
to such loue trifles.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>End.</SPEAKER>
<P>My loue is placed neither vnder the Moone
nor aboue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum.</SPEAKER>
<P>I hope you be not sotted vpon the man in the
Moone.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>End.</SPEAKER>
<P>No but setled, eyther to die, or possesse the
Moone herselfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is <HI>Endimion</HI> mad, or doe I mistake? doe you
loue the Moone <HI>Endimion?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>End.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Eumenides</HI> the Moone.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum.</SPEAKER>
<P>There was neuer any so peeuish to imagin the
Moone eyther capable of affection, or shape of a Mi∣stris:
for as impossible it is to make loue fit to her humor
which no man knoweth, as a coate to her forme, which
continueth not in one bignesse whilst she is measuring.
Cease of <HI>Endimion</HI> to feede so much vpon fancies. That
melancholy blood must be purged, which draweth you
<PB REF="4"/>
to a dotage no lesse miserable then monstrous.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>End.</SPEAKER>
<P>My thoughts haue no vaines, and yet vnlesse
they be let blood, I shall perrish.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum.</SPEAKER>
<P>But they haue vanities, which beeing refor∣med,
you may be restored.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>End.</SPEAKER>
<P>O fayre <HI>Cynthia,</HI> why doe others terme thee vn∣constant,
whom I haue euer founde vnmoueable? Iniu∣rious
tyme, corrupt manners, vnkind men, who finding
a constancy not to be matched, in my sweete Mistris,
haue christned her with the name of wauering, waxing,
and waning. Is shee inconstant that keepeth a setled
course, which since her first creation altereth not one
minute in her mouing? There is nothing thought more
admirable, or commendable in the sea, then the ebbing
and flowing, and shall the Moone, from whom the Sea
taketh this vertue, be accounted fickle for encreasing, &amp;
decreasing? Flowers in theyr buds, are nothing worth
till they be blowne, nor blossomes accounted till they be
ripe fruite, and shal we then say they be changeable, for
that they growe from seedes to leaues, from leaues to
buds, from buds to theyr perfection? then, why be not
twigs that become trees, children that become men, and
Mornings that grow to Euenings, termed wauering, for
that they continue not at one stay? I but <HI>Cynthia,</HI> being
in her fulnes, decayeth, as not delighting in her greatest
beautie, or withering when she should be most honou∣red.
When mallice cannot obiect any thing, folly will,
making that a vice, which is the greatest vertue. What
thing (my Mistris excepted) being in the pride of her
beauty, &amp; latter minute of her age, that waxeth young
againe? Tell mee <HI>Eumenides,</HI> what is hee that hauing a
Mistris of ripe yeeres, &amp; infinite vertues, great honors,
and vnspeakeable beauty, but woulde wish that shee
might grow tender againe? getting youth by yeeres, and
neuer decaying beauty, by time, whose fayre face, ney∣ther
<PB REF="4"/>
the Summers blase can scorch, nor VVinters blast
chappe, nor the numbring of yeeres breede altering of
colours. Such is my sweete <HI>Cynthia,</HI> whom tyme cannot
touch, because she is diuine, nor will offend because she
is delicate. O <HI>Cynthia,</HI> if thou shouldest alwaies conti∣nue
at thy fulnes, both Gods and men woulde conspire
to rauish thee. But thou to abate the pride of our affec∣tions,
dost detract from thy perfections, thinking it suf∣ficient,
if once in a month we enioy a glymse of thy ma∣iestie,
and then, to encrease our greefes, thou doost de∣crease
thy glemes, comming out of thy royall robes,
wherewith thou dazelist our eyes, downe into thy swath
clowtes, beguiling our eyes. And then</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum.</SPEAKER>
<P>Stay there <HI>Endimion,</HI> thou that committest I∣dolatry,
wilt straight blaspheme, if thou be suffered.
Sleepe woulde doe thee more good then speech: the
Moone heareth thee not, or if shee doe, regardeth thee
not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>End.</SPEAKER>
<P>Vaine <HI>Eumenides,</HI> whose thoughts neuer grow
higher thē the crowne of thy head. Why troublest thou
me, hauing neither heade to conceiue the cause of my
loue, or a hart to receiue the impressions? followe thou
thine owne fortunes, which creepe on the earth, &amp; suf∣fer
me to flye to mine, whose fall though it be desperate,
yet shall it come by daring. Farewell</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum.</SPEAKER>
<P>Without doubt <HI>Endimion</HI> is bewitched, other∣wise
in a man of such rare vertues, there could not har∣bor
a minde of such extreame madnes. I wil follow him,
least in this fancie of the Moone, he depriue himselfe of
the sight of the Sunne.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Actus primus. Scaena secunda.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Tellus. Floscula.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tellus.</SPEAKER>
<P>Trecherous and most periurde <HI>Endimion,</HI> is
<HI>Cynthia</HI> the sweetnes of thy life, and the bitternes of my
<PB REF="5"/>
death? What reuenge may be deuised so full of shame,
as my thoughts are replenished with mallice? Tell me
<HI>Floscula</HI> if falsenes in loue can possibly be punished with
extremitie of hate. As long as sworde, fire, or poison
may be hyred, no traytor to my loue shall liue vnreuen∣ged.
Were thy oathes without number, thy kisses with∣out
measure, thy sighes without end, forged to deceiue
a poore credulous virgin, whose simplicity had beene
worth thy fauour and better fortune? If the Gods sitte
vnequall beholders of iniuries, or laughers at Louers de∣ceipts,
then let mischiefe be as well forgiuen in women,
as periurie winked at in men.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flosc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Madame, if you woulde compare the state of
<HI>Cynthia</HI> with your owne, and the height of <HI>Endimion</HI>
his thoughts, with the meanenesse of your fortune, you
would rather yeeld then contende, being betweene you
and her no comparison, and rather wonder then rage at
the greatnes of his minde, beeing affected with a thing
more then mortall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tellus</SPEAKER>
<P>No comparison <HI>Floscula?</HI> and why so? is not
my beauty diuine, whose body is decked with faire flow∣ers,
and vaines are Vines, yeelding sweet liquor to the
dullest sprits, whose eares are Corne, to bring strength,
and whose heares are grasse, to bring abundance? Doth
not Frankinsence, &amp; Myrthe breath out of my nostrils,
and all the sacrifice of the Gods, breede in my bowels?
Infinite are my creatures, without which, neyther thou
nor <HI>Endimion,</HI> nor any could loue, or liue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flosc.</SPEAKER>
<P>But knowe you not fayre Ladie, that <HI>Cynthia</HI>
gouerneth all things? Your grapes woulde be but drie
huskes, your Corne but chaffe, and all your vertues
vaine, were it not <HI>Cynthia</HI> that preserueth the one in the
bud, and nourisheth the other in the blade, and by her
influence both comforteth all things, and by her autho∣ritie
commaundeth all creatures; Suffer then <HI>Endimion</HI>
<PB REF="5"/>
to followe his affections, though to obtaine her be im∣possible,
and let him flatter himselfe in his owne ima∣ginations,
because they are immortall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tellus</SPEAKER>
<P>Loth I am <HI>Endimion</HI> thou shouldest die, be∣cause
I loue thee well, and that thou shouldest liue it
greeueth mee, because thou louest <HI>Cynthia</HI> too well. In
these extremities what shall I doe? <HI>Floscula</HI> no more
words, I am resolued. He shall neyther liue, nor die.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flosc.</SPEAKER>
<P>A strange practise, if it be possible.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tellus</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, I will entangle him in such a sweet nette,
that he shall neither find the meanes to come out, nor
desire it. All allurements of pleasure will I cast before
his eyes, insomuch that he shall slake that loue which he
now voweth to <HI>Cynthia,</HI> and burne in mine, of which he
seemeth carelesse. In thys languishing, betweene my a∣morous
deuises, and his owne loose desires, there shall
such dissolute thoughts take roote in his head, and ouer
his hart grow so thicke a skinne, that neither hope of
preferment, nor feare of punishment, nor counsel of the
wisest, nor company of the worthiest, shall alter his hu∣mor,
nor make him once to thinke of his honor.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flosc.</SPEAKER>
<P>A reuenge incredible, and if it may be, vnna∣turall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tellus.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hee shall knowe the mallice of a woman, to
haue neither meane, nor ende, and of a woman deluded
in loue, to haue neither rule, nor reason. I can doe it, I
must, I will. All his vertues will I shadow with vices, his
person (ah sweet person) shall he decke with such rich
Roabes, as he shall forget it is his owne person, his sharp
wit (ah wit too sharpe, that hath cut off all my ioyes)
shall hee vse, inflattering of my face, and deuising Son∣nets
in my fauour. The prime of his youth and pride
of his time, shall be spent in melancholy passions, care∣lesse
behauiour, vntamed thoughts, and vnbridled af∣fections.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="6"/>
<SPEAKER>Flosc.</SPEAKER>
<P>When thys is done what then, shall it conti∣nue
tyll hys death, or shall he doate for euer in this de∣light?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tellus.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ah <HI>Floscula,</HI> thou rendest my hart in sunder,
in putting me in remembrance of the end.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flosc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why if this be not the end, all the rest is to no
ende.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tellus</SPEAKER>
<P>Yet suffer mee to imitate Iuno, who woulde
turne Iupiters louers to beastes on the earth, though she
knew afterwards they should be starres in heauen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flosc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Affection that is bred by enchauntment, is like
a flower that is wrought in silke, in colour and forme
most like, but nothing at all in substance or sauour.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tellus</SPEAKER>
<P>It shall suffice me if the world talke that I am
fauoured of <HI>Endimion.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flosc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, vse your owne wyll, but you shal finde
that loue gotten with witch-craft, is as vnpleasant, as
fish, taken with medicines vnwholsome.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tellus Floscula,</SPEAKER>
<P>they that be so poore that they haue
neyther nette nor hooke, will rather poyson dowe then
pyne with hunger: and she that is so opprest with loue,
that shee is neyther able with beauty, nor wit to obtaine
her freende, wyll rather vse vnlawfull meanes, then try
vntollerable paines. I will doe it.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flosc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then about it. Poore <HI>Endimion,</HI> what traps
are layde for thee, because thou honourest one that all
the world wondreth at. And what plots are cast to make
thee vnfortunate, that studiest of all men to be the faith∣fullest.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Actus primus. Scaena tertia.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Dares, Samias, Sir Tophas, Epiton.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dares</SPEAKER>
<P>Now our Maisters are in loue vp to the eares,
vvhat haue wee to doe, but to be in knauery, vp to the
crownes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="6"/>
<SPEAKER>Samias</SPEAKER>
<P>O that we had Sir <HI>Tophas</HI> that braue Squire,
in the midst of our myrth, <HI>&amp; ecce autem,</HI> vvyl you see the
deuill?</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Sir Tophas.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>Epi.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heere syr.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>I brooke not thys idle humor of loue, it tick∣leth
not my lyuer, from whence the Loue-mongers in
former age seemed to inferre they should proceede.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Loue sir may lye in your lunges, and I thinke it
doth, and that is the cause you blow, and are so pursie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Top.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tush boy, I thinke it but some deuise of the
Poet to get money.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>A Poet? whats that?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>Doost thou not know what a Poet is?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>No.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Top.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why foole, a Poet is as much as one shoulde
say, a Poet. But soft, yonder be two Wrennes, shall I
shoote at them?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>They are two lads.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>Larkes or wrennes, I will kill them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Larkes? are you blinde? they are two lyttle
Boyes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Top.</SPEAKER>
<P>Byrdes, or boyes, they are both but a pittance
for my breakefast, therefore haue at them, for theyr
braines must as it were imbroder my bolts.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Stay your courage valiant Knight, for your
wisdome is so wearie that it stayeth it selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dares</SPEAKER>
<P>Why Syr <HI>Tophas</HI> haue you forgotten your
olde freendes?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Top.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Freendes?</HI> Nego argumentum.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sam.</SPEAKER>
<P>And why not freends?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Top.</SPEAKER>
<P>Because <HI>Amicitia</HI> (as in old Annuals we find)
is <HI>inter pares,</HI> now my pretty companions, you shall see
how vnequall you be to mee, but I will not cut you quite
<PB REF="7"/>
off, you shall be my halfe friendes, for reaching to my
middle, so farre as from the ground to the wast I wil be
your freend.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dares</SPEAKER>
<P>Learnedly. But what shall become of the rest
of your bodie, from the wast to the crowne?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Top.</SPEAKER>
<P>My children <HI>quod supra vos nihil ad vos,</HI> you must
thinke the rest immortall, because you cannot reach it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay I tell ye my Maister is more then a man.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dar.</SPEAKER>
<P>And thou lesse then a mouse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Top.</SPEAKER>
<P>But what be you two?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sam.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am <HI>Samias,</HI> page to <HI>Endimion.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dar.</SPEAKER>
<P>And I <HI>Dares,</HI> page to <HI>Eumenides.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>Of what occupation are your Masters.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dares</SPEAKER>
<P>Occupation, you clowne, why they are ho∣nourable,
and warriers.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Top.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then are they my prentises.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dares</SPEAKER>
<P>Thine, and why so?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>I was the first that euer deuised warre, and
therefore by <HI>Mars</HI> himselfe giuen me for my Armes a
whole Armorie, and thus I goe as you see, clothed with
Artillary, it is not Silkes (milksops) nor Tyssues, nor the
fine wooll of <HI>Cares,</HI> but yron, steele, swords, flame, shot,
terror, clamor, blood, and ruine, that rocks a sleepe my
thoughts, which neuer had any other cradle, but cruel∣tie.
Let me see, doe you not bleede?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dares</SPEAKER>
<P>Why so?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>Commonly my words wound.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Samias</SPEAKER>
<P>What then doe your blowes?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>Not onely confound, but also confound.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Samias</SPEAKER>
<P>Howe darst thou come so neere thy Maister
<HI>Epi?</HI> Syr Tophas spare vs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>You shall liue. You <HI>Samias</HI> because you are
little. You <HI>Dares,</HI> because you are no bigger, and both
of you, because you are but two; for commonly I kil by
the dosen, and haue for euerie particular aduersarie, a
<PB REF="7"/>
peculiar weapon.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Samias</SPEAKER>
<P>May we know the vse for our better skyll in
warre?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>You shall. Heere is a burbolt for the vglie
beast the Black-bird.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dares</SPEAKER>
<P>A cruell sight.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>Heere is the Muskit, for the vntamed, (or as
the vulgar sort terme it) the wilde Mallard.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Samias</SPEAKER>
<P>O desperate attempt.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay my Maister will match them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dares</SPEAKER>
<P>I if he catch them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>Heere is a speare and shielde, and both neces∣sarie,
the one to conquer, the other to subdue, or ouer∣come
the terrible Trowte, which although he be vnder
the water, yet tying a string to the top of my speare, and
an engine of yron to the ende of my lyne, I ouerthrowe
him, and then heerein I put him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Samias</SPEAKER>
<P>O wonderfull warre. <HI>Dares,</HI> didst thou euer
heare such a dolt?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dares</SPEAKER>
<P>All the better, we shall haue good sport here∣after,
if we can get leysure.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Samias</SPEAKER>
<P>Leysure, I will rather loose my Maisters ser∣uice
then his companie, looke howe hee stroutes; But
what is this, call you it your sword?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>No, it is my Simiter, which I by constructi∣on
often studying to be compendious, call my Smyter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dares</SPEAKER>
<P>What, are you also learned sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>Learned? I am all Mars and Ars.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Samias</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay you are all Masse and Asse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>Mock you mee? You shall both suffer, yet
with such weapons, as you shall make choise of the wea∣pon
wherewith you shall perrish. Am I all a masse or
lumpe, is there no proportion in me? Am I all Asse? is
there no wit in mee. <HI>Epi,</HI> prepare thē to the slaughter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Samias</SPEAKER>
<P>I pray sir heare vs speake, we call you Masse,
<PB REF="8"/>
which your learning doth well vnderstande, is all Man,
for <HI>Mas maris</HI> is a man. Then <HI>As</HI> (as you knowe) is a
weight, and we for your vertues account you a weight.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>The Latine hath saued your lyues, the which
a world of siluer could not haue ransomde. I vnderstand
you, and pardon you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dares</SPEAKER>
<P>Well Sir <HI>Tophas</HI> we bid you farewell, &amp; at our
next meeting, we will be readie to doe you seruice.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas Samias</SPEAKER>
<P>I thanke you. <HI>Dares</HI> I thanke you, but
especiallie I thanke you both.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Samias</SPEAKER>
<P>Wiselie. Come, next time weele haue some
prettie Gentle-women with vs to walke, for without
doubt with them he will be verie daintie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dares</SPEAKER>
<P>Come let vs see what our Maisters doe, it is
high time.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>Now will I march into the fielde, where if I
cannot encounter with my foule enemies, I will with∣draw
my selfe to the Riuer, &amp; there fortifie for fish: for
there resteth no minute free from fight.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Actus primus. Saena quarta.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Tellus, Floscula, Dipsas.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tellus</SPEAKER>
<P>Behold <HI>Floscula,</HI> we haue met with the Wo∣man
by chaunce that wee sought for by trauell; I will
breake my minde to her without ceremonie or circum∣stance,
least we loose that time in aduise, that should be
spent in execution.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flosc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Vse your discretion, I will in this case, neither
giue counsell nor consent, for there cannot bee a thing
more monstrous, then to force affection by sorcery, nei∣ther
doe I imagin anie thing more impossible.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tellus</SPEAKER>
<P>Tush <HI>Floscula,</HI> in obtaining of loue, what im∣possibilities
will I not try? and for the winning of <HI>Endi∣mion,</HI>
what impieties will I not practise? <HI>Dipsas,</HI> whom
<PB REF="8"/>
as many honour for age, as wonder at for cunning, listen
in fewe words to my tale, &amp; answere in one word to the
purpose, for that neither my burning desire can afforde
long speech, nor the short time I haue to stay manie de∣layes.
Is it possible by hearbes, stones, spels, incantan∣tation,
enchauntment, exorcismes, fire, mettals, plan∣nets,
or any practise to plant affection where it is not,
and to supplant it where it is?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dipsas</SPEAKER>
<P>Faire Ladie, you may imagin that these horie
heares are not void of experience, nor the great name
that goeth of my c<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nning to bee without cause. I can
darken the Sunne by my skil, and remooue the Moone
out of her course; I can restore youth to the aged, and
make hils without bottoms; there is nothing that I can
not doe, but that onely which you would haue me doe,
and therin I differ from the Gods, that I am not able to
rule harts, for were it in my power to place affection by
appointment, I would make such euill appetites, such
inordinate lusts, such cursed desires, as all the worlde
should be filled both with supersticious heates, and ex∣treame
loue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tellus</SPEAKER>
<P>Vnhappie Tellus, whose desires are so des∣perate,
that they are neither to be conceiued of any cre∣ature,
nor to be cured by any arte.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dipsas</SPEAKER>
<P>This I can, breede slacknes in loue, though
neuer roote it out. What is he whom you loue, &amp; what
she that he honoureth?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tellus</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Endimion,</HI> sweet <HI>Endimion</HI> is he that hath my
hart, and <HI>Cynthia,</HI> too too faire <HI>Cynthia,</HI> the myracle of
Nature, of tyme, of Fortune, is the Ladie that hee de∣lights
in, and dotes on euery day, and dies for ten thou∣sand
times a day.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dipsas</SPEAKER>
<P>Would you haue his loue, eyther by absence
of sicknes aslaked. Would you that <HI>Cynthia</HI> should mi∣strust
him, or be iealous of him without colour?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="9"/>
<SPEAKER>Tellus</SPEAKER>
<P>It is the onelie thing I craue, that seeing my
loue to <HI>Endimion</HI> vnspotted, cannot be accepted, hys
trueth to <HI>Cynthia</HI> (though it be vnspeakeable) may bee
suspected.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dipsas</SPEAKER>
<P>I will vndertake it, and ouertake him, that all
his loue shal be doubted of, and therefore become des∣perate:
but this will weare out with time, that treadeth
all things downe but trueth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tellus</SPEAKER>
<P>Let vs goe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dipsas</SPEAKER>
<P>I follow.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="2" TYPE="act">
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Actus secundus. Scaena prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Endimion, Tellus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>End.</SPEAKER>
<P>O Fayre <HI>Cynthia,</HI> ô vnfortunate <HI>Endimion.</HI> Why
was not thy byrth as high as thy thoughts, or
her beautie lesse then heauenlie? or why are not thyne
honors as rare as her beautie? or thy fortunes as great as
thy deserts? Sweet <HI>Cynthia,</HI> how wouldst thou be plea∣sed,
how possessed? wil labours (patient of all extremi∣ties)
obtaine thy loue? There is no Mountain so steepe
that I will not climbe, no monster so cruell that I will
not tame, no action so desperate that I will not attempt.
Desirest thou the passions of loue, the sad and melan∣cholie
moodes of perplexed mindes, the not to be ex∣pressed
torments of racked thoughts? Beholde my sad
teares, my deepe sighes, my hollowe eyes, my broken
sleepes, my heauie countenaunce. Wouldst thou haue
mee vowde onelie to thy beautie and consume euerie
minute of time in thy seruice, remember my solitarie
life, almost these seauen yeeres, whom haue I entertai∣ned
but mine owne thoughts, and thy vertues? What
companie haue I vsed but contemplation? Whom haue
I wondred at but thee? Nay whom haue I not contem∣ned,
<PB REF="9"/>
for thee? Haue I not crept to those on whom I
might haue troden, onelie because thou didst shine vp∣on
them? Haue not iniuries beene sweet to mee, if thou
vouchsafest I should beare them? Haue I not spent my
golden yeeres in hopes, waxing old with wishing, yet
wishing nothing but thy loue. With <HI>Tellus,</HI> faire <HI>Tellus,</HI>
haue I dissembled, vsing her but as a cloake for mine
affections, that others seeing my mangled and disorde∣red
minde, might thinke it were for one that loueth me,
not for <HI>Cynthia,</HI> whose perfection alloweth no compa∣nion,
nor comparison.</P>
<P>In the midst of these distempred thoughts of myne,
thou art not onelie iealous of my truth, but careles, su∣spicious,
and secure: which strange humor maketh my
minde as desperate as thy conceits are doubtfull. I am
none of those Wolues that barke most, when thou shy∣nest
brightest. But that fish, (thy fish <HI>Cynthia</HI> in the
floode <HI>Aranis)</HI> which at thy waxing is as white as the
driuen snowe, and at thy wayning, as blacke as deepest
darknes. I am that <HI>Endimion</HI> (sweet <HI>Cynthia)</HI> that haue
carryed my thoughts in equall ballance with my actions,
being alwaies as free from imagining ill, as enterpry∣sing;
That <HI>Endimion,</HI> whose eyes neuer esteemed anie
thing faire, but thy face, whose tongue termed nothing
rare but thy vertues, and whose hart imagined nothing
miraculous, but thy gouernment. Yea that <HI>Endimion,</HI>
who diuorsing himselfe from the amiablenes of all La∣dies,
the brauerie of all Courts, the companie of al men,
hath chosen in a solitarie Cell to liue, onely by feeding
on thy fauour, accounting in the worlde (but thy selfe)
nothing excellent, nothing immortall; thus maist thou
see euerie vaine sinew, muscle, and artery of my loue, in
which there is no flatterie, nor deceipt; error, nor arte.
But soft, here commeth <HI>Tellus,</HI> I must turne my other
face to her like <HI>Ianus,</HI> least she be as suspicious as <HI>Juno.</HI></P>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="10"/>
Enter Tellus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tellus</SPEAKER>
<P>Yonder I espie <HI>Endimion,</HI> I will seeme to su∣spect
nothing but sooth him, that seeing I cannot ob∣taine
the depth of his loue, I may learne the height of
his dissembling; <HI>Floscula</HI> and <HI>Dipsas,</HI> with-drawe your
selues out of our sight, yet be within the hearing of our
saluting; How now <HI>Endimion,</HI> alwaies solitary? no com∣panie
but your owne thoughts? no freende but melan∣cholie
fancies?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Endimion</SPEAKER>
<P>You know (fayre <HI>Tellus)</HI> that the sweet re∣membrance
of your loue, is the onely companion of my
life, and thy presence, my paradise, so that I am not a∣lone
when no bodie is with mee, and in heauen it selfe
when thou art with me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tellus</SPEAKER>
<P>Then you loue me <HI>Endimion.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>End.</SPEAKER>
<P>Or els I liue not <HI>Tellus.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tellus</SPEAKER>
<P>Is it not possible for you <HI>Endimion,</HI> to dissem∣ble?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>End.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not <HI>Tellus,</HI> vnlesse I could make me a woman.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tellus</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, is dissembling ioyned to theyr sex inse∣parable?
as heate to fire, heauines to earth, moysture to
water, thinnesse to ayre?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>End.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, but founde in their sex, as common, as
spots vpon Doues, moles vpon faces, Caterpillers vpon
sweet apples, cobwebs vpon faire windowes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tellus</SPEAKER>
<P>Doe they all dissemble?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Endimion</SPEAKER>
<P>All but one.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tellus</SPEAKER>
<P>Who is that?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>End.</SPEAKER>
<P>I dare not tell. For if I shoulde say you, then
would you imagin my flattery to be extreame, if ano∣ther,
then woulde you thinke my loue to be but indiffe∣rent.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tellus</SPEAKER>
<P>You will be sure I shall take no vantage of
your words. But in sooth <HI>Endimion,</HI> without more cere∣monies,
is it not <HI>Cynthia?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="10"/>
<SPEAKER>Endimion</SPEAKER>
<P>You know <HI>Tellus,</HI> that of the Gods we are
forbidden to dispute, because theyr dieties come not
within the compasse of our reasons, and of <HI>Cynthia</HI> we
are allowed not to talke but to wonder, because her ver∣tues
are not within the reach of our capacities.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tellus</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, she is but a woman.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>End.</SPEAKER>
<P>No more was <HI>Venus.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tellus</SPEAKER>
<P>Shee is but a virgin.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Endimion</SPEAKER>
<P>No more was <HI>Vesta.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tellus</SPEAKER>
<P>She shall haue an ende.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Endim.</SPEAKER>
<P>So shall the world.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tellus</SPEAKER>
<P>Is not her beautie subiect to time?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>End.</SPEAKER>
<P>No more then time is to standing still.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tellus</SPEAKER>
<P>Wilt thou make her immortall?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>End.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, but incomparable.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tellus</SPEAKER>
<P>Take heede <HI>Endimion,</HI> lest like the Wrastler
in <HI>Olimpia,</HI> that striuing to lifte an impossible weight,
catcht an incurable straine, thou by fixing thy thoughts
aboue thy reach, fal into a disease without al recure? But
I see thou art now in loue with <HI>Cynthia.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Endim.</SPEAKER>
<P>No <HI>Tellus,</HI> thou knowest that the statelie
Cedar, whose toppe reacheth vnto the clowdes, neuer
boweth his head to the shrubs that growe in the valley,
nor Iuie that climeth vp by the Elme, can euer get hold
of the beames of the Sunne; <HI>Cynthia</HI> I honour in all hu∣militie,
whom none ought, or dare aduenture to loue,
whose affections are immortall, &amp; vertues infinite. Suf∣fer
me therefore to gaze on the Moone, at whom, were
it not for thy selfe, I would die with wondering.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Actus secundus. Scaena secunda.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Dares, Samias, Scintilla, Fauilla.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dares</SPEAKER>
<P>Come <HI>Samias,</HI> diddest thou euer heare such a
sighing, the one for <HI>Cynthia,</HI> the other for <HI>Semele,</HI> &amp; both
<PB REF="11"/>
for moone shine in the water?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let them sigh, and let vs sing, how say you gen∣tlewomen,
are not our Masters too farre in loue?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Their tongues happily are dipt to the roote in
amorous words and sweete discourses, but I thinke their
hearts are scarce tipt on the side, with constant desires.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dares</SPEAKER>
<P>How say you <HI>Fauilla,</HI> is not loue a lurcher, that
taketh mens stomacks away that they cannot eate, their
spleene that they cannot laugh, their harts that they can∣not
fight, theyr eyes that they cannot sleepe, and leaueth
nothing but lyuers to make nothing but Louers?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fauil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Away peeuish boy, a rodde were better vnder
thy girdle, than loue in thy mouth: it will be a forward
Cocke that croweth in the shell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dares</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas good olde gentlewoman, how it becom∣meth
you to be graue,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scint.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Fauilla</HI> though she be but a sparke, yet is shee
fyre.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fauil.</SPEAKER>
<P>And you <HI>Scintilla</HI> bee not much more then a
sparke, though you would be esteemed a flame.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sam.</SPEAKER>
<P>It were good sport to see the fight betweene
two sparkes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dares</SPEAKER>
<P>Let them to it, and wee will warme vs by theyr
wordes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scint.</SPEAKER>
<P>You are not angry <HI>Fauilla?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Faui.</SPEAKER>
<P>That is <HI>Scintilla,</HI> as you list to take it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sam.</SPEAKER>
<P>That, that.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scnit.</SPEAKER>
<P>This it is to be matched with girles, who com∣ming
but yesterday from making of babies, would before
to morrowe be accounted Matrons.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fauil.</SPEAKER>
<P>I crye your Matronship mercy; because your
Pantables bee higher with corke, therefore your feete
must needs be higher in the insteppes: you will be mine
elder, because you stande vppon a stoole, and I on the
flowre.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="11"/>
<SPEAKER>Sam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good, good.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let them alone, and see with what countenance
they will become friendes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, you thinke to bee the wyser, because you
meane to haue the last worde.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Step betweene them least they scratch. In faith
gentlewomen, seeing wee came out to bee merry, let not
your iarring marre our iestes: be friendes, how say you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scint.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am not angry, but it spited mee to see howe
short she was.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fauil.</SPEAKER>
<P>I ment nothing, till she would needs crosse me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dares</SPEAKER>
<P>Then so let it rest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scint.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am agreede.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fauil.</SPEAKER>
<P>And I, yet I neuer tooke any thing so vnkindly
in my life.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tys I haue the cause, that neuer offered the
occasion.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dares</SPEAKER>
<P>Excellent and right like a woman.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sam.</SPEAKER>
<P>A strange sight to see water come out of fire.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dares</SPEAKER>
<P>It is their propertie, to carrie in their eyes, fire,
and water, teares and torches, and in their mouthes, ho∣nie
and gall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scint.</SPEAKER>
<P>You will be a good one if you liue, but what
is yonder formall fellowe?</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Sir Tophas.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dares</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir <HI>Tophas,</HI> syr <HI>Tophas,</HI> of whom we tolde you:
if you bee good wenches make as though you loue him,
and wonder at him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fauil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wee will doo our parts.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dares</SPEAKER>
<P>But first let vs stand aside, and let him vse his
garbe, for all consisteth in his gracing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>Epi.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>At hand syr.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas.</SPEAKER>
<P>How likest thou this Martiall life, where no∣thing
but bloud besprinkleth our bosomes? Let me see
<PB REF="12"/>
be our enemies fatte?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Passing fat: and I would not chaunge this life to
be a Lord, and your selfe passeth all comparison, for o∣ther
Captaines kill and beate, and there is nothing you
kill, but you also eate.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>I will drawe out their guttes out of their bel∣lies,
and teare the flesh with my teeth, so mortall is my
hate, and so eger my vnstaunched stomacke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>My master thinkes himselfe the valiantest man
in the world if hee kill a wren: so warlike a thing he ac∣compteth
to take away life, though it be from a Larke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Epi,</HI> I finde my thoughtes to swell, and my spi∣rite
to take winges, in so much that I cannot continue
within the compas of so slender combates.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fauil.</SPEAKER>
<P>This passeth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why is he not madde?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sam.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, but a little vaine glorious.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas.</SPEAKER>
<P>Epi.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Syr.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>I will encounter that blacke and cruell ene∣mie,
that beareth rough and vntewed lockes vpon his
bodie, whose Syre throweth downe the strongest walles,
whose legs are as many as both ours, on whose head are
placed most horrible hornes, by nature, as a defence from
all harmes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>What meane you Master to be so desperate?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>Honour inciteth mee, and very hunger com∣pelleth
mee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>What is that monster?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>The Monster <HI>Ouis.</HI> I haue saide, let thy wits
worke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>I cannot imagin it; yet let me see, a black enemie
with rough lockes it may be a sheep, and <HI>Ouis</HI> is a sheep:
his Syre so strong, a Ram is a sheepes Sire: that beeing
also an engine of war, hornes he hath, and foure legs, so
<PB REF="12"/>
hath a sheepe: without doubt this monster is a blacke
sheepe; Is it not a sheepe that you meane?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou hast hit it, that Monster will I kill and
sup with.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come let vs take him off Syr <HI>Tophas</HI> all haile.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>Welcome children, I seldome cast mine eyes
so low as to the crownes of your heads, and therfore par∣don
me that I spake not all this while.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dares</SPEAKER>
<P>No harme done, here be faire Ladies come to
wonder at your person, your valour, your witte, the re∣port
whereof, hath made them careles of their owne ho∣nours,
to glut their eyes and harts vpon yours.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>Report cannot but iniure mee, for that not
knowing fully what I am, I feare shee hath beene a nig∣gard
in her praises.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scint.</SPEAKER>
<P>No gentle knight, Report hath beene prodigal,
for shee hath left you no equall, nor her selfe credite, so
much hath she tolde, yet no more than we now see.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dares</SPEAKER>
<P>A good wench.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fauil.</SPEAKER>
<P>If there remaine as much pittie toward wo∣men,
as there is in you courage against your enemies, thē
shall we be happie, who hearing of your person, came to
see it, and seeing it, are now in loue with it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>Loue me Ladies? I easily beleeue it, but my
tough heart receiueth no impression with sweet words.
<HI>Mars</HI> may pearce it, <HI>Venus</HI> shall not paint on it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fauil.</SPEAKER>
<P>A cruell saying.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ther's a girle.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dares</SPEAKER>
<P>Will you cast these Ladyes away, and all for a
little loue? doo but speake kindly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>There cōmeth no soft syllable within my lips,
custome hath made my wordes bloudy, and my hart bar∣barous:
that pelting word loue, how watrish it is in my
mouth, it carrieth no sound, hate, horror, death, are spea∣ches
that nourish my spirits. I like hony but I care not
<PB REF="13"/>
for the bees, I delight in musicke but I loue not to play
on the bagpipes, I can vouchsafe to heare the voice of
women, but to touch their bodies I disdaine it, as a thing
childish, and fit for such men as can digest nothing but
milke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scint.</SPEAKER>
<P>A hard heart, shall wee dye for your loue, and
finde no remedy.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue already taken a surfet.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good master pittie them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>Pittie them <HI>Epi?</HI> no I do not thinke that this
breast shalbe pestred with such a foolish passion. What
is that the gentlewoman carrieth in a chaine?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why it is a Squirrill.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>A Squirril? O Gods what things are made for
money.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dares.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is not this gentleman ouerwise?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fauil.</SPEAKER>
<P>I could stay all day with him, if I feared not to
be shent.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is it not possible to meete againe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dares</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes at any time.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fauil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then let vs hasten home.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir Tophas, the God of warre deale better with
you, than you doo with the God of loue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fauil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Our loue we may dissemble, disgest we cannot,
but I doubt not but time will hamper you, and helpe vs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>I defie time, who hath no interest in my heart:
come <HI>Epi.</HI> let me to the battaile with that hideous beast,
loue is pappe and hath no relish in my taste, because it
is not terrible.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dares</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeede a blacke sheepe is a perrilous beast,
but let vs in till another time.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fauil.</SPEAKER>
<P>I shall long for that time.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Actus secundus. Scaena tertia.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Endimion, Dipsas, Bagoa.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>End.</SPEAKER>
<P>No rest <HI>Endimion?</HI> still vncertaine how to settle
thy steps by day, or thy thoughts by night? thy trueth
is measured by thy fortune, and thou art iudged vnfaith∣full
because thou art vnhappy. I will see if I can beguile
<PB REF="13"/>
my selfe with sleep, &amp; if no slumber will take hold in my
eyes, yet will I imbrace the golden thoughts in my head,
and wish to melt by musing: that as <HI>Ebone,</HI> which no
fire can scorch, is yet cōsumed with sweet sauours, so my
heart which cannot bee bent by the hardnes of fortune,
may be brused by amorous desires, On yonder banke
neuer grewe any thing but Lunary, and hereafter I will
neuer haue any bed but that banke. O <HI>Endimion, Tellus</HI>
was faire, but what auaileth Beautie without wisedome?
Nay <HI>Endimion</HI> she was wise, but what auaileth wisdome
without honour? Shee was honourable <HI>Endimion,</HI> belie
her not, I but howe obscure is honor without fortune?
Was she not fortunate whome so many followed? Yes,
yes, but base is fortune without Maiestie: thy Maiestie
<HI>Cynthia</HI> al the world knoweth and wondereth at, but not
one in the world that can immitate it or comprehend it.
No more <HI>Endimion,</HI> sleepe or dye; Nay die for to sleepe
it is impossible, and yet I knowe not how it commeth to
passe, I feele such a heauines both in mine eyes and hart,
y<SUP>t</SUP> I am sodainly benummed, yea in euery iont: it may be
wearinesse, for when did I rest? it may bee deepe melan∣choly,
for when did I not sigh? <HI>Cynthia,</HI> I so, I say <HI>Cynthia.</HI></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>He falles a sleepe.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dipsas</SPEAKER>
<P>Little doost thon knowe <HI>Endimion</HI> when thou
shalt wake, for hadst thou placed thy heart as lowe in
loue, as thy head lieth now in sleepe, thou mightest haue
commanded <HI>Tellus,</HI> whome nowe in stead of a Mistris,
thou shalt finde a tombe. These eyes must I seale vp by
Art, not Nature, which are to be opened neither by Art
nor Nature. Thou that laist downe with golden lockes,
shalt not awake vntill they bee turned to siluer haires:
and that chin, on which scarcely appeareth soft downe,
shalbe filled with brissles as hard as broome: thou shalt
sleep out thy youth and flowring time, and become dry
hay before thou knewest thy selfe greene grasse, &amp; ready
<PB REF="14"/>
by age to step into the graue whē thou wakest, that was
youthfull in the Courte when thou laidst thee downe to
sleepe. The malice of <HI>Tellus</HI> hath brought this to passe,
which if shee could not haue intreated of mee by fayre
meanes, she would haue commaunded by menacing, for
from her gather wee all our simples to maintaine our
sorceries. Fanne with this hemlocke ouer his face, and
sing the inchantment for sleepe, whilst I goe in and fi∣nish
those cerimonies that are required in our Art: take
heede yee touch not his face, for the Fanne is so seasoned
that who so it toucheth with a leafe shall presently dye,
and ouer whom the vvind of it breatheth, he shall sleepe
for euer.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bagoa</SPEAKER>
<P>Let me alone, I will bee carefull. What happe
hadst thou <HI>Endimion</HI> to come vnder the hands of <HI>Dipsas.</HI>
O faire <HI>Endimion,</HI> how it grieueth me that that faire face
must be turned to a withered skinne, &amp; taste the paines
of death before it feele the reward of loue. I feare <HI>Tellus</HI>
will repent that which the heauens themselues seemed
to rewe, but I heare <HI>Dipsas</HI> comming, I dare not repine,
least she make me pine, and rocke me into such a deepe
sleepe, that I shall not awakd to my marriage.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Dipsas.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dipsas</SPEAKER>
<P>How now, haue you finished?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bagoa</SPEAKER>
<P>Yea.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dipsas</SPEAKER>
<P>Well then let vs in, and see that you doo not so
much as whisper that I did this, for if you do, I will turne
thy haires to Adders, and all thy teeth in thy heade to
tongues, come away, come away.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="3" TYPE="act">
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<PB REF="14"/>
<HEAD>Actus tertius. Scaena prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Cynthia, three Lordes, Tellus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cynth.</SPEAKER>
<P>IS the report true, that <HI>Endimion</HI> is striken into
such a dead sleep, that nothing can either wake
him or mooue him?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum.</SPEAKER>
<P>Too true Madame, and as much to be pittied
as wondered at.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tellus</SPEAKER>
<P>As good sleepe and doe no harme, as wake and
doe no good.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cynth.</SPEAKER>
<P>What maketh you <HI>Tellus</HI> to bee so short? the
time was <HI>Endimion</HI> onely was.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum.</SPEAKER>
<P>It is an olde saying Madame, that a waking dog
doth a farre off barke at a sleeping Lyon.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sem.</SPEAKER>
<P>It were good <HI>Eumenides</HI> that you tooke a nappe
with your friend for your speech beginneth to be heauy</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum.</SPEAKER>
<P>Contrarie to your nature <HI>Semele,</HI> which hath
beene alwaies accounted light.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cynth.</SPEAKER>
<P>What haue we heare before my face, these vn∣seemely
and malepart ouerthwarts? I will tame your
tongues, and your thoughts, and make your speeches an∣swerable
to your dueties, and your conceits fitte for my
dignitie, els will I banish you both my person and the
worlde.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pardon I humbly aske; but such is my vnspot∣ted
faith to <HI>Endimion,</HI> that whatsoeuer seemeth a needle
to pricke his finger, is a dagger to wound my heart.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cynth.</SPEAKER>
<P>If you bee so deere to him, howe happeneth it
you neither go to see him, nor search for remedy for him?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue seene him to my griefe, and sought re∣cure
with despaire, for that I cannot imagine who should
restore, him that is the wounder to all men: your high∣nes,
on whose handes the compasse of the earth is at cōmaund,
(though not in possession) may shewe your selfe
<PB REF="15"/>
both worthy your sex, your nature, and your fauour, if
you redeeme that honorable <HI>Endimion,</HI> whose ripe yeres
foretell rare vertues, and whose vnmellowed conceits
promise rype counsell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyn.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue had tryal of <HI>Endimion,</HI> &amp; conceiue greater
assurance of his age, then I coulde hope of hys youth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tel.</SPEAKER>
<P>But timely Madam crookes that tree that wil be
a camock, and young it pricks that will be a thorne, and
therefore he that began without care to settle his life, it
is a signe without amendment he will end it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cynth.</SPEAKER>
<P>Presumptuous gyrle, I will make thy tongue
an example of vnrecouerable displeasure, <HI>Corsites</HI> carry
her to the Castle in the Deserte, there to remaine and
weaue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cors.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shall she worke stories or poetries?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cynthia</SPEAKER>
<P>It skylleth not which, goe to, in both, for she
shall find examples infinite in eyther, what punishment
long tongues haue. <HI>Eumenides,</HI> if eyther the Sooth∣sayers
in Egipt, or the Enchaunters in Thessaly, or the
Philosophers in Greece, or all the Sages of the worlde,
can find remedie, I will procure it, therefore dispatch
with al speede: you <HI>Eumenides</HI> into Thessalie. You <HI>Zon∣tes</HI>
into Greece, (because you are acquainted in Athens.)
You <HI>Panthon</HI> to Egypt, saying that <HI>Cynthia</HI> sendeth, and
if you will, commaundeth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum.</SPEAKER>
<P>On bowed knee I giue thanks, and with wings
on my legs, I flye for remedie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Zon.</SPEAKER>
<P>We are readie at your highnes commaund, &amp;
hope to returne to your full content.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyn.</SPEAKER>
<P>It shall neuer be said that <HI>Cynthia,</HI> whose mercy
and goodnes filleth the heauens with ioyes, &amp; the world
with meruailes, will suffer eyther <HI>Endimion</HI> or any to
perrish, if he may be protected.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your Maiesties wordes haue beene alwaies
deedes, and your deedes vertues.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<PB REF="15"/>
<HEAD>Actus tertius. Scaena secunda.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Corsites, Tellus,</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cors.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heere is the Castle (fayre Tellus) in which you
must weaue, till eyther time end your dayes, or <HI>Cinthia</HI>
her displeasure. I am sorrie so fayre a face shoulde bee
subiect to so hard a fortune, and that the flower of beau∣tie,
which is honoured in Courts, shoulde heere wither
in pryson.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tellus</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Corsites, Cynthia</HI> may restraine the libertie of
my bodie, of my thoughts she cannot, and therefore doe
I esteeme my selfe most free, though I am in greatest
bondage.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cors.</SPEAKER>
<P>Can you then feede on fancie, and subdue the
mallice of enuie by the sweetnes of imagination.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tellus</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Corsites,</HI> there is no sweeter musicke to the
miserable then dispayre, and therefore the more bitter∣nesse
I feele, the more sweetnes I find, for so vaine were
liberty, and so vnwelcome the following of higher for∣tune,
that I chuse rather to pine in this Castle, then to
be a Prince in any other Court.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cors.</SPEAKER>
<P>A humor contrary to your yeeres, and nothing
agreeable to your sex: the one commonly allured with
delights, the other alwaies with soueraigntie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tellus</SPEAKER>
<P>I meruaile <HI>Corsites</HI> that you being a Captain,
who should sound nothing but terror, and suck nothing
but blood, can finde in your hart to talke such smooth
wordes, for that it agreeth not with your calling to vse
words so soft, as that of loue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cors.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ladie, it were vnfit of warres to discourse with
womē, into whose minds nothing can sinck but smooth∣nes;
besides, you must not thinke that Souldiours bee
so rough hewne, or of such knottie mettle, that beautie
cannot allure, and you beeing beyonde perfection en∣chaunt.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tellus</SPEAKER>
<P>Good <HI>Corsites</HI> talke not of loue, but let me to
<PB REF="16"/>
my labor: the little beautie I haue, shall be bestowed on
my Loome, which I now meane to make my Louer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cors.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let vs in, and what fauour <HI>Corsites</HI> can shewe,
<HI>Tellus</HI> shall commaund.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tellus</SPEAKER>
<P>The onely fauour I desire, is now and then to
walke.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Actus tertius. Scaena tertia.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Syr Tophas, <HI>and</HI> Epi.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>Epi.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heere sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>Vnrigge mee. Hey ho.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whats that?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>An interiection, whereof some are of mour∣ning:
as <HI>eho, vah.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>I vnderstand you not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou seest me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>I.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou hearst me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>I.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou feelest me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>I.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>And not vnderstand'st me?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>No.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>Then am I but three quarters of a Nowne
substantiue. But alas Epi, to tell thee the troth I am a
Nowne Adiectiue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>Because I cannot stand without another.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who is that?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>Dipsas.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Are you in loue?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Top.</SPEAKER>
<P>No: but loue hath as it were milkt my thoughts,
and drained from my hart the very substance of my ac∣customed
courage; it worketh in my heade like newe
<PB REF="16"/>
Wine, so as I must hoope my skonce with yron, least
my head breake, and so I bewray my braines: but I pray
thee first discouer me in all parts, that I may be like a
Louer, and then will I sigh and die. Take my gunne,
and giue me a gowne: <HI>Caedant arma togae.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heere.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>Take my sworde and shielde, and giue mee
beard, brush, and Cyssers: <HI>bella gerant alii tu pari semper
ama.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Will you be trimd sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>Not yet: for I feele a contention within me,
whether I shall frame the bodkin beard or the bush. But
take my pike and giue mee pen: <HI>dicere que puduit, scri∣bere
iussit amor.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>I wyll furnish you sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>Nowe for my bowe and bolts, giue me ynke
and paper, for my Smiter a pen-knife: for <HI>Scalpellum
calami, atramentum, charta libelli, sint semper studiis arma
parata meis.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir will you giue ouer warres, &amp; play with that
bable called loue?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Giue ouer warres? no Epi,</HI> Militat omnis
amans, et habet sua castea Cupido.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Loue hath made you very eloquent, but your
face is nothing fayre.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>Non formosus erat, sed erat facundus Vlisses.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay I must seeke a newe Maister if you can
speake nothing but verses.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Quicquid conabar dicere versus erat.</HI> Epi, I
feele all <HI>Ouid de arte amandi</HI> lie as heauie at my heart as
a loade of logges. O what a fine thin hayre hath <HI>Dip∣sas,</HI>
what a prettie low forehead? VVhat a tale &amp; state∣lie
nose? What little hollowe eyes? What great and
goodly lyppes? Howe harmelesse shee is beeing tooth∣lesse,
her fingers fatte and short, adorned with long
<PB REF="17"/>
nayles like a Bytter. In howe sweete a proportion her
cheekes hang downe to her brests like dugges, and her
pappes to her waste like bagges. VVhat a lowe sta∣ture
shee is, and yet what a great foote shee carryeth?
Howe thrifty must she be in whom there is no waste?
Hovve vertuous is shee like to be, ouer whom no man
can be ielous?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Stay Maister, you forget your selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>O <HI>Epi.</HI> euen as a dish melteth by the fire, so
doth my wit increase by loue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pithily, and to the purpose, but what? beginne
you to nodde.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>Good <HI>Epi</HI> let me take a nappe: for as some
man may better steale a horse, then another looke ouer
the hedge: so diuers shall be sleepie when they woulde
fainest take rest.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>He sleepes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who euer saw such a woodcock, loue <HI>Dipsas?</HI>
without doubt all the world will novve account him va∣liant,
that ventureth on her, whom none durst vnder∣take.
But heere commeth two wagges.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Dares and Samias.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thy Maister hath slept his share.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dares</SPEAKER>
<P>I thinke he doth it because he would not paie
me my boord wages.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Samias</SPEAKER>
<P>It is a thing most strange, and I thinke mine
will neuer returne, so that wee must both seeke nevve
Maisters, for we shall neuer liue by our manners.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>If you want Maisters, ioyne with me and serue
Sir <HI>Tophas,</HI> who must needes keepe more men, because
he is toward marriage.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Samias</SPEAKER>
<P>What <HI>Epi,</HI> wher's thy Maister?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yonder sleeping in loue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dares</SPEAKER>
<P>Is it possible?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="17"/>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hee hath taken his thoughts a hole lower, and
sayth, seeing it is the fashion of the world, hee will vaile
bonet to beautie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Samias</SPEAKER>
<P>how is he attyred?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Louelie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dares</SPEAKER>
<P>Whom loueth this amorous knight?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Dipsas.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Samias</SPEAKER>
<P>That vglie creature? Why shee is a foole, a
scold, fat, without fashion, and quite without fauour.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tush you be simple, my Ma. hath a good mar∣riage.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dares</SPEAKER>
<P>Good? as how?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why in marrying <HI>Dipsas,</HI> hee shall haue euerie
day twelue dishes of meate to his dinner, though there
be none but <HI>Dipsas</HI> with him. Foure of flesh, four of fish,
foure of fruite.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sam.</SPEAKER>
<P>As how Epi?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>For flesh these, woodcock, goose, bitter, &amp; rayle.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Da.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeed he shal not misse, if <HI>Dipsas</HI> be there.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>For fish these, crab, carpe, lumpe, and powting.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Excellent, for of my word, she is both crabbish,
lumpish, and carping.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>For fruite these, fretters, medlers, hartichockes,
and Lady longings. Thus you see hee shall fare like a
King, though he be but a begger.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dares</SPEAKER>
<P>Well Epi, dine thou with him, for I had ra∣ther
fast then see her face. But see thy Ma. is a sleepe, let
vs haue a song to wake this Amorous knight.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Agreed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Content.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Song.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Top.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sleepe is a bynding of the sences, loue a loosing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let vs heare him awhile.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>There appeared in my sleepe a goodly Owle,
who sitting vpon my shoulder, cryed twyt, twyt, &amp; be∣fore
myne eyes presented her selfe the expresse image
<PB REF="18"/>
of <HI>Dipsas.</HI> I meruailed what the Owle said, til at the last,
I perceiued twyt twyt, to it, to it: onely by contraction
admonished by thys vision, to make account of my
sweet <HI>Venus.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir Tophas, you haue ouer-slept your selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Top.</SPEAKER>
<P>No youth, I haue but slept ouer my loue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dares</SPEAKER>
<P>Loue? Why it is impossible, that into so no∣ble
and vnconquered a courage, loue should creepe, ha∣uing
first a head as hard to pearce as steele, then to passe
to a hart arm'd with a shirt of male.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>I but my Maister yawning one day in the Sun,
loue crept into his mouth before he could close it, and
there kept such a tumbling in his bodie, that he was glad
to vntrusse the poynts of his hart, and entertaine Loue
as a stranger.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>If there remaine any pittie in you, pleade for
me to <HI>Dipsas.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dares</SPEAKER>
<P>Pleade? Nay wee will presse her to it. Let vs
goe with him to <HI>Dipsas,</HI> and there shall wee haue good
sport. But sir <HI>Tophas</HI> when shall we goe? for I finde my
tongue voluble, and my hart venturous, and all my selfe
like my selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Samias</SPEAKER>
<P>Come <HI>Dares,</HI> let vs not loose him till we find
our Maisters, for as long as he liueth, we shall lack nei∣ther
mirth nor meate.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>We will trauice. Will you goe sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>I praesequar.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Actus tertius, Scaena quarta.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Eumenides, Geron.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eumenides</SPEAKER>
<P>Father, your sad musique beeing tuned
on the same key that my harde fortune is, hath so mel∣ted
my minde, that I wish to hang at your mouthes
ende, tell my life end.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="18"/>
<SPEAKER>Geron</SPEAKER>
<P>These tunes Gentleman haue I beene accu∣stomed
with these fiftie Winters, hauing no other house
to shrowde my selfe, but the broade heauens, and so fa∣miliar
with mee hath vse made miserie, that I esteeme
sorrowe my cheefest solace. And welcommest is that
guest to mee, that can rehearse the saddest tale, or the
bloodiest tragedie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eumenides</SPEAKER>
<P>A strange humour, might I enquire the
cause?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geron</SPEAKER>
<P>You must pardon me if I denie to tell it, for
knowing that the reuealing of griefes, is as it were a re∣newing
of sorrow, I haue vowed therefore to conceale
them, that I might not onely feele the depth of euerla∣sting
discontentment, but dispaire of remedie? But
whence are you? What fortune hath thrust you to thys
distresse?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eumenides</SPEAKER>
<P>I am going to Thessalie, to seeke reme∣die
for <HI>Endimion</HI> my deerest freende, who hath beene
cast into a dead sleepe, almost these twentie yeeres, wax∣ing
olde, and readie for the graue, beeing almost but
newlie come forth of the cradle.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geron</SPEAKER>
<P>You neede not for recure trauell farre, for who
so can cleerely see the bottome of thys Fountaine, shall
haue remedie for any thing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum.</SPEAKER>
<P>That mee thinketh is vnpossible, why vvhat
vertue can there be in water?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geron</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, who soeuer can shedde the teares of a
faythfull Louer, shall obtaine any thing he would, reade
these words engrauen about the brimme.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum.</SPEAKER>
<P>Haue you knowne this by experience, or is it
placed heere of purpose to delude men?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geron</SPEAKER>
<P>I onely would haue experience of it, and then
shoulde there bee an ende of my miserie. And then
woulde I tell the strangest discourse that euer yet was
heard.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="19"/>
<SPEAKER>Eum</SPEAKER>
<P>Ah Eumenides.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geron</SPEAKER>
<P>What lacke you Gentleman, are you not wel?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eumenides</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes Father, but a qualme that often com∣meth
ouer my hart doth nowe take hold of me, but did
neuer any Louers come hether?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geron</SPEAKER>
<P>Lusters, but not Louers; for often haue I seene
them weepe, but neuer could I heare they saw the bot∣tome.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum.</SPEAKER>
<P>Came there women also?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geron</SPEAKER>
<P>Some.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum</SPEAKER>
<P>What did they see?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geron</SPEAKER>
<P>They all wept that the Fountaine ouerflowed
with teares, but so thicke became the water with theyr
teares, that I could scarce discerne the brimme, much
lesse beholde the bottome.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum</SPEAKER>
<P>Be faithfull Louers so skant?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geron</SPEAKER>
<P>It seemeth so, for yet heard I neuer of any.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eumenides</SPEAKER>
<P>Ah Eumenides, howe art thou perplex∣ed?
call to minde the beautie of thy sweet Mistris, and
the depth of thy neuer dying affections, howe oft hast
thou honoured her, not onelie without spotte, but su∣spition
of falsehoode? And howe hardly hath shee re∣warded
thee, without cause or colour of despight?</P>
<P>Howe secrete hast thou beene these seauen yeeres,
that hast not, nor once darest not, to name her for dis∣contenting
her? Hovve faythfull? that hast offered
to dye for her, to please her. Vnhappie Eumeni∣des.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geron</SPEAKER>
<P>Why Gentleman did you once loue?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eumenides</SPEAKER>
<P>Once? I Father and euer shall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geron</SPEAKER>
<P>Was she vnkind, and you faithfull?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shee of all women the most froward, and I of
all creatures the most fond.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geron</SPEAKER>
<P>You doted then, not loued: for affection is
<PB REF="19"/>
grounded on vertue, and vertue is neuer peeuish: or on
Beautie, and Beautie loueth to be praised.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum.</SPEAKER>
<P>I but if all vertuous Ladies should yeelde to all
that be louing, or all amiable gentlewomen entertaine all
that be amorous, theyr vertues would bee accounted vi∣ces,
and their beauties deformities, for that loue can bee
but betweene two, and that not proceeding of him that
is most faithfull, but most fortunate.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geron</SPEAKER>
<P>I would you were so faithfull, that your teares
might make you fortunate.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yea father, if that my teares cleare not this foun∣taine,
then may you sweare it is but a meere mockerie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geron</SPEAKER>
<P>So saith euery one yet, that wept.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ah, I fainte, I dye. Ah sweete <HI>Semele</HI> let me a∣lone,
and dissolue by weeping into water.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geron</SPEAKER>
<P>This affection seemeth straunge, if hee see no∣thing
without doubt this dissembling passeth, for no∣thing
shall drawe mee from the beleefe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum.</SPEAKER>
<P>Father, I plainelie see the bottome, and there in
white marble engrauen these wordes, <HI>Aske one for all,
and but one thing at all.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geron</SPEAKER>
<P>O fortunate <HI>Eumenides,</HI> (for so haue I hearde
thee call thy selfe) let me see, I cannot discerne any such
thing. I thinke thou dreamest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ah Father thou art not a faithfull louer, and
therefore canst not beholde it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geron</SPEAKER>
<P>Then aske that I may be satisfied by the euent,
and thy selfe blessed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum.</SPEAKER>
<P>Aske? so I will: and what shall I doo but aske,
and whome should I aske but <HI>Semele,</HI> the possessing of
whose person, is a pleasure that cannot come within the
compasse of comparison, whose golden lockes seeme
most curious, when they seeme most carelesse, whose
sweete lookes seeme most alluring, when they are most
chaste: and whose wordes the more vertuous they are,
<PB REF="20"/>
the more amorous they bee accounted. I pray thee for∣tune
when I shall first meete with fayre <HI>Semele,</HI> dash my
delight with some light disgrace, least imbracing sweet∣nesse
beyond measure, I take a surfit without recure: let
her practise her accustomed coynesse, that I may dyet
my seife vpon my desires: otherwise the fulnesse of my
ioyes will diminish the sweetnesse, and I shall perrish by
them before I possesse them.</P>
<P>Why doe I trifle the time in words? The least minute
beeing spent in the getting of <HI>Semele,</HI> is more worth
then the whole worlde: therefore let mee aske. What
nowe <HI>Eumenides?</HI> Whether art thou drawn? Hast thou
forgotten both friendship and duetie? Care of <HI>Endimi∣on,</HI>
and the commaundement of <HI>Cynthia?</HI> Shall hee dye
in a leaden sleepe, because thou sleepest in a golden
dreame? I, let him sleepe euer, so I slumber but one mi∣nute
with <HI>Semele.</HI> Loue knoweth neither friendshippe
nor kindred.</P>
<P>Shall I not hazard the losse of a friend, for the obtay∣ning
of her for whome I woulde often loose my selfe?
Fonde <HI>Eumenides,</HI> shall the intycing beautie of a most
disdainfull Ladie, bee of more force then the rare fide∣litie
of a tryed friend? The loue of men to women is
a thing common, and of course: the friendshippe of
man to man infinite, and immortall. Tush, <HI>Semele</HI>
dooth possesse my loue. I but <HI>Endimion</HI> hath deser∣ued
it. I will helpe <HI>Endimion.</HI> I founde <HI>Endimion</HI> vn∣spotted
in his trueth. I but I shall finde <HI>Semele</HI> constant
in her loue. I will haue <HI>Semele.</HI> What shall I doe? Father
thy gray haires are Embassadours of experience. Which
shall I aske?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geron</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Eumenides,</HI> release <HI>Endimion,</HI> for all thinges
(friendship excepted) are subiect to fortune: Loue is
but an eye worme, which onely tickleth the heade with
hopes, and wishes: friendshippe the image of eterni∣tie,
<PB REF="20"/>
in which there is nothing moueable, nothing mis∣cheeuous.
As much difference as there is betweene
Beautie and Vertue, bodies and shadowes, colours and
life: so great oddes is there betweene loue and friend∣shippe.</P>
<P>Loue is a <HI>Camelion,</HI> which draweth nothing into the
mouth but ayre, and nourisheth nothing in the bodie
but lunges: beleeue mee <HI>Eumenides,</HI> Desire dyes in the
same moment that Beautie sickens, and Beautie fadeth
in the same instant that it flourisheth. When aduersities
flowe, then loue ebbes: but friendship standeth stifflie
in stormes. Time draweth wrinckles in a fayre face, but
addeth fresh colours to a fast friende, which neither
heate, nor cold, nor miserie, nor place, nor destiny, can al∣ter
or diminish. O friendship of all things the most rare,
and therefore most rare because most excellent, whose
comforts in misery is alwaies sweet, and whose counsels
in prosperitie are euer fortunate. Vaine loue, that onely
comming neere to friendship in name, woulde seeme to
be the same, or better, in nature.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum.</SPEAKER>
<P>Father I allowe your reasons, and will therefore
conquer mine own. Vertue shall subdue affections, wis∣dome
lust, friendship beautie. Mistresses are in euery
place, and as common as Hares in <HI>Atho,</HI> Bees in <HI>Hybla,</HI>
foules in the ayre: but friends to be founde, are like the
Phaenix in <HI>Arabia,</HI> but one, or the Philadelphi in
<HI>Arays,</HI> neuer aboue two. I will haue <HI>Endimion,</HI> sacred
Fountaine, in whose bowels are hidden diuine secrets, I
haue encreased your waters with the teares of vnspotted
thoughts and therefore let mee receiue the reward you
promise: <HI>Endimion,</HI> the truest friende to mee, and faith∣fullest
louer to <HI>Cynthia,</HI> is in such a dead sleepe, that no∣thing
can wake or mooue him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geron</SPEAKER>
<P>Doost thou see any thing?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eumenides</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>I see in the same Piller, these wordes:</HI>
<PB REF="21"/>
When shee whose figure of all is the perfectest, and neuer to
bee measured: alwaies one, yet neuer the same: still incon∣stant,
yet neuer wauering, shall come and kisse <HI>Endimion</HI> in
his sleepe, hee shall then rise, els neuer. <HI>This is straunge.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geron</SPEAKER>
<P>What see you els?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum.</SPEAKER>
<P>There commeth ouer mine eyes either a
darke mist, or vppon the fountaine a deepe thicknesse:
for I can perceiue nothing. But howe am I deluded?
or what difficult (nay impossible) thing is this?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geron</SPEAKER>
<P>Me thinketh it easie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good father and howe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geron</SPEAKER>
<P>Is not a circle of all Figures the perfectest?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geron</SPEAKER>
<P>And is not <HI>Cynthia</HI> of all cyrcles the most abso∣lute?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geron</SPEAKER>
<P>Is it not impossible to measure her, who still
worketh by her influence, neuer standing at one
stay?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geron</SPEAKER>
<P>Is shee not alwaies <HI>Cynthia,</HI> yet seldome in the
same bignesse, alwaies wauering in her waxing or way∣ning,
that our bodies might the better bee gouerned,
our seasons the daylier giue their increase, yet neuer to
bee remooued from her course, as long as the heauens
continue theirs?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geron</SPEAKER>
<P>Then who can it bee but <HI>Cynthia,</HI> whose
vertues beeing all diuine, must needes bring things
to passe that bee myraculous. Goe, humble thy selfe to
<HI>Cynthia,</HI> tell her the successe, of which my selfe shall bee
a witnesse. And this assure thy selfe, that shee that sent
to finde meanes for his safetie, will now worke her cun∣ning.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum.</SPEAKER>
<P>How fortunate am I, if <HI>Cynthia</HI> be she that may
<PB REF="21"/>
doo it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geron</SPEAKER>
<P>Howe fonde art thou, if thou doo not beleeue
it?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will hasten thither, that I may intreat on
my knees for succour, and imbrace in mine armes my
friend.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geron</SPEAKER>
<P>I will goe with thee, for vnto <HI>Cynthia</HI> must I
discouer all my sorrowes, who also must worke in mee a
contentment.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum.</SPEAKER>
<P>May I nowe knowe the cause?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geron</SPEAKER>
<P>That shall bee as wee walke, and I doubt not
but the straungnesse of my tale will take away the tedi∣ousnesse
of our iourney.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let vs goe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geron</SPEAKER>
<P>I followe.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="4" TYPE="act">
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Actus quartus. Scaena prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Tellus, Corsites.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tellus</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>I</HI> Maruell <HI>Corsites</HI> giueth me so much libertie:
all the worlde knowing his charge to bee so
high, and his nature to bee most straunge, who hath so
ill intreated Ladies of great honour, that he hath not suf∣fered
them to looke out of windowes, much lesse to
walke abroade: it may bee hee is in loue with mee, for
<HI>(Endimion,</HI> hard harted <HI>Endimion,</HI> excepted) what is he
that is not enamourd of my beautie? But what respectest
thou the loue of all the world, <HI>Endimion</HI> hates thee. A∣las
poore <HI>Endimion,</HI> my maylce hath exceeded my loue:
and thy faith to <HI>Cynthia,</HI> quenched my affections. Quen∣ched
<HI>Tellus?</HI> nay kindled them a fresh; in so much that
I finde scorching flames, for dead embers, and cruell en∣counters
of warre in my thoughtes, in steede of sweete
parlees. Ah that I might once againe see <HI>Endimion,</HI> ac∣cursed
<PB REF="22"/>
girle, what hope hast thou to see <HI>Endimion?</HI> on
whose head already are growne gray haires, and whose
life must yeelde to Nature, before <HI>Cynthia</HI> ende her dis∣pleasure.
Wicked <HI>Dipsas,</HI> and most deuilish <HI>Tellus,</HI> the
one for cunning too exquisit, the other for hate too in∣tollerable.
Thou wast commanded to weaue the stories
&amp; Poetries, wherin were shewed both examples &amp; pu∣nishments
of tatling tongues, and thou hast only imbro∣dered
the sweet face of <HI>Endimion,</HI> deuises of loue, melan∣choly
imaginations, and what not, out of thy worke, that
thou shouldst studie to picke out of thy mind. But here
cometh <HI>Corsites,</HI> I must seeme yeelding and stoute, ful of
mildnesse, yet tempered with a Maiestie: for if I be too
flexible, I shall giue him more hope then I meane, if too
froward, enioy lesse liberty then I would, loue him I can∣not,
&amp; therfore will practise that which is most contra∣rie
to our sex, to dissemble.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Corsites.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faire <HI>Tellus,</HI> I perceiue you rise with the Larke,
and to your selfe sing with the Nightingale.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tellus</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord I haue no play-fellow but fancy, be∣ing
barred of all companie I must question with my
selfe, and make my thoughts my frindes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>I would you would account my thoughtes also
your friends, for they be such as are only busied in won∣dering
at your beautie, &amp; wisdome: &amp; some such as haue
esteemed your fortune too hard, and diuers of that kind
that offer to set you free, if you will set them free</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tellus</SPEAKER>
<P>There are no colours so contrarie as white and
blacke, nor Elements so disagreeing as fire and water, nor
any thing so opposite as mens thoughts &amp; their words.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>He that gaue <HI>Cassandra</HI> the gift of prophecying
with the curse, that spake shee neuer so true, shee should
neuer be beleeued, hath I think poysoned the fortune of
men, that vttering the extremities of their inward passi∣ons,
<PB REF="22"/>
are alwayes suspected of outward periuries.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tellus</SPEAKER>
<P>Well <HI>Corsites</HI> I will flatter my selfe, and beleeue
you. What would you doe to enioy my loue?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sette all the Ladies of the Castle free, and make
you the pleasure of my life: more I cannot doe, lesse
I will not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tellus</SPEAKER>
<P>These be great wordes, and fit your calling: for
Captaines must promise things impossible. But wil you
doe one thing for all.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Any thing sweet <HI>Tellus,</HI> that am ready for all.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tellus</SPEAKER>
<P>You knowe that on the Lunary bancke slee∣peth
<HI>Endimion.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corsites</SPEAKER>
<P>I knowe it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tel.</SPEAKER>
<P>If you will remoue him from that place by force,
and conuey him into some obscure caue by pollicie, I
giue you here the faith of an vnspotted virgine, that you
onelie shall possesse me as a louer, and in spight of ma∣lice,
haue mee for a wife.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Remooue him <HI>Tellus?</HI> Yes <HI>Tellus,</HI> hee shall bee
remooued, and that so soone, as thou shalt as much com∣mend
my dilligence as my force. I goe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tellus</SPEAKER>
<P>Stay, will your selfe attempt it?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corsites</SPEAKER>
<P>I <HI>Tellus:</HI> as I would haue none partaker of
my sweete loue, so shall none be partners of my labours:
but I pray thee goe at your best leysure, for <HI>Cynthia</HI> be∣ginneth
to rise, and if she discouer our loue we both pe∣rish,
for nothing pleaseth her but the fairenesse of virgi∣nitie.
All thinges must bee not onely without lust, but
without suspicion of lightnes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tellus</SPEAKER>
<P>I will depart, and goe you to <HI>Endimion.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corsites</SPEAKER>
<P>I flye <HI>Tellus,</HI> beeing of all men the most for∣tunate.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Simple <HI>Corsites,</HI> I haue set thee about a taske being
but a man, y<SUP>t</SUP> the gods thēselues cannot performe: for little
<PB REF="23"/>
doost thou knowe howe heauie his head lies, howe hard
his fortune: but such shiftes must women haue to de∣ceiue
men, and vnder colour of things easie, intreat that
which is imposible: otherwise we should be cūbred with
importunities, oathes, sighes, letters, and all implements
of loue, which to one resolued to the contrary, are most
lothsome. I will in and laugh with the other Ladies at
<HI>Corsites</HI> sweating.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Actus quartus. Scaena secunda.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Samtas, Dares and Epiton.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Will thy master neuer awake?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dares</SPEAKER>
<P>No, I thinke hee sleepes for a wager: but how
shall wee spende the time? Sir <HI>Tophas</HI> is so farre in loue
that he pineth in his bedde, and commeth not abroade?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sam.</SPEAKER>
<P>But here commeth <HI>Epi,</HI> in a pelting chafe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>A poxe of all false Prouerbes, and were a Pro∣uerbe
a Page, I would haue him by the eares.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why art thou angry?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why? you knowe it is sayd, the tyde tarieth no
man.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sam.</SPEAKER>
<P>True.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>A monstrous lye; for I was tide two houres, and
tarried for one to vnlose mee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dares</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas poore <HI>Epi.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Poore? No, no, you base conceited slaues, I am a
most complyt Gentleman, although I bee in disgrace
with sir <HI>Tophas.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dares</SPEAKER>
<P>Art thou out with him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, because I cannot gette him a lodging with
<HI>Endimion,</HI> hee would faine take a nappe for fortie or fifty
yeeres.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dares</SPEAKER>
<P>A short sleepe, considering our long life.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is he still in loue?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="23"/>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>In loue? why he doth nothing but make Sonets.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Canst thou remember any one of his Poems?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, this is one. The beggar Loue that knows not
where to lodge: At last within my hart when I slept, he
crept, I wakt, and so my fancies began to fodge.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sam.</SPEAKER>
<P>That's a verie long verse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why the other was shorte, the first is called
from the thombe to the little finger, the second from the
little finger to the elbowe, and some hee hath made to
reach to the crowne of his head, and downe again to the
soule of his foote: it is sette to the tune of the blacke
Saunce, <HI>ratio est,</HI> because Dipsas is a black Saint.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dares</SPEAKER>
<P>Very wisely, but pray thee <HI>Epi</HI> how art thou
complet, and beeing from thy Maister what occupati∣on
wilt thou take?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>No my harts, I am an absolute Microcosmus, a
pettie worlde of my selfe, my library is my heade, for I
haue no other bookes but my braines: my wardrope on
my backe, for I haue no more apparrell then is on my
body; my armorie at my fingers ends, for I vse no other
Artillarie then my nailes; my treasure in my purse. <HI>Sie
omnia mea mecum porto.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dares</SPEAKER>
<P>Good.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now syrs, my Pallace is pau'd with grasse, and
tyled with starres: for <HI>celo tegitur qui non habet vrnam,</HI>
he that hath no house, must he in the yard.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Samias</SPEAKER>
<P>A braue resolution, But how wilt thou spend
thy time?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not in any Melancholie sort, for mine exercise
I will walke horses.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dares</SPEAKER>
<P>Too bad.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why is it not saide: It is good walking when
one hath his horse in his hand?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Worse, and worse, but how wilt thou liue?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>By angling; O tis a stately occupation to stande
<PB REF="24"/>
foure houres in a colde Morning, and to haue his nose
bytten with frost, before hys baite be mumbled with a
Fish.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dares</SPEAKER>
<P>A rare attempt, but wilt thou neuer trauell?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes in a Westerne barge, when with a good
winde and lustie pugges, one may goe ten miles in two
daies.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Samias</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou art excellent at thy choyse, but what
pastime wilt thou vse, none?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes the quickest of all.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Samias</SPEAKER>
<P>What dyce?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, when I am in hast, xxj. games at Chesse,
to passe a fewe minutes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dares</SPEAKER>
<P>A life for a little Lord, and full of quicknesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tush let mee alone, but I must needes see if I
can finde where <HI>Endimion</HI> lieth, and then goe to a cer∣taine
fountaine hard by, where they say faithfull Louers
shall haue althings they will aske. If I can finde out any
of these, <HI>ego et Magister meus erimus in tuto,</HI> I and my
Maister shall be freendes. He is resolued to weep some
three or foure payle-fuls, to auoyde the rume of loue
that wambleth in his stomacke.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter the Watch.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Samias</SPEAKER>
<P>Shall we neuer see thy Maister <HI>Dares?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dares</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, let vs goe nowe, for to morrowe <HI>Cynthia</HI>
will be there.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will goe with you. But hovve shall wee see
for the Watch?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Samias</SPEAKER>
<P>Tush let me alone, Ile begin to them. Mai∣sters
God speede you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Watch</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir boy, we are all sped alreadie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>So me thinks, for they smell all of drinke, like a
beggers beard.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dares</SPEAKER>
<P>But I pray sirs, may we see <HI>Endimion?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Watch.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, we are commanded in <HI>Cynthias</HI> name
<PB REF="24"/>
that no man shall see him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sam.</SPEAKER>
<P>No man? Why we are but boyes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Watch.</SPEAKER>
<P>Masse neighbours hee sayes true, for if I
sweare I will neuer drinke my liquor by the quart, and
yet call for two pints, I thinke with a safe conscience I
may carouse both.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dares</SPEAKER>
<P>Pithily, and to the purpose.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Watch.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tush tush neighbors, take me with you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Samias</SPEAKER>
<P>This will grow hote.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dares</SPEAKER>
<P>Let them alone.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Watch.</SPEAKER>
<P>If I saie to my wife, wife I will haue no
Reysons in my pudding, she puts in Corance, smal Rey∣sons
are Reysons, and boyes are men. Euen as my wife
shoulde haue put no Reysons in my pudding, so shall
there no boyes see <HI>Endimion.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dares</SPEAKER>
<P>Learnedly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let Maister Constable speake: I thinke hee is
the wisest among you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma. Const.</SPEAKER>
<P>You know neighbors tis an an old said
saw, children and fooles speake true.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All say.</SPEAKER>
<P>True.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma. Const.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, there you see the men bee the
fooles, because it is prouided from the children.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dares</SPEAKER>
<P>Good.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma. Const.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then say I neighbors, that children must
not see <HI>Endimion,</HI> because children &amp; fooles speak true.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>O wicked application.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Samias</SPEAKER>
<P>Scuruily brought about.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Watch.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay he sais true, &amp; therefore till <HI>Cynthia</HI> haue
beene heere he shall not be vncouered. Therefore away.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dar.</SPEAKER>
<P>A watch quoth you? a man may watch 7. yeres
for a wise worde, &amp; yet goe without it. Their wits are all
as rustie as their bils. But come on Ma. Const. shall we
haue a song before we goe? <HI>Const.</HI> With all my hart.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Song.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<PB REF="25"/>
<HEAD>Actus quartus. Scaena tertia.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Corsites solus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corsites</SPEAKER>
<P>I am come in sight of the Lunary bank, with∣out
doubt <HI>Tellus</HI> doteth vpon me, and cunningly that I
might not perceiue her loue, shee hath sette mee to a
taske that is done before it is begunne. <HI>Endimion,</HI> you
must change your pillowe, and if you be not wearie of
sleepe, I vvill carrie you where at ease you shall sleepe
your fill. It were good that without more ceremonies
I tooke him, least beeing espyed, I be intrapt, and so in∣curre
the displeasure of <HI>Cynthia,</HI> who commonly setteth
watch that <HI>Endimion</HI> haue no wrong.</P>
<STAGE>He lifts.</STAGE>
<P>What nowe, is your Maistership so heuie? or are
you nayld to the ground? Not styrre one whit? then
vse all thy force though he feele it and wake. VVhat
stone still? turnd I thinke to earth, with lying so long
on the earth. Didst not thou <HI>Corsites</HI> before <HI>Cynthia</HI> pul
vp a tree, that fortie yeeres was fastned with rootes and
wrethed in knots to the grounde? Didst not thou with
maine force pull open the yron Gates, which no Ram
or Engine could moue? Haue my weak thoughts made
braunfallen my strong armes? or is it the nature of loue
or the Quintessence of the mind to breede numnesse, or
lythernesse, or I knowe not what, languishing in my
ioynts and sinewes, beeing but the base strings of my
bodie? Or dooth the remembraunce of <HI>Tellus</HI> so refine
my spirits into a matter so subtill and diuine, that the
other fleshie parts cannot worke whilst they muse?
Rest thy selfe, rest thy selfe: nay rent thy selfe in peeces
<HI>Corsites,</HI> and striue in spight of loue, fortune and nature,
to lift vppe this dulled bodie, heauier then deade, and
more sencelesse then death.</P>
<STAGE><PB REF="25"/>
Enter Fayries</STAGE>
<P>But what are these so fayre fiendes that cause my
hayres to stand vpright, and spirits to fall downe? hags,
out alas, Nymphes I craue pardon. Aye me, out what
doe I heere.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>The Fayries daunce, and with a song pinch
him, and hee falleth a sleepe, thy kisse <HI>Endi∣mion,</HI>
and depart.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Cynthia, Floscula, Semele, Panelion, Zontes, Py∣thagoras,
Gyptes, Corsites.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cynthia</SPEAKER>
<P>You see <HI>Pythagoras</HI> what ridiculous opini∣ons
you hold, and I doubt not but you are nowe of ano∣ther
minde.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pytha.</SPEAKER>
<P>Madam, I plainlie perceiue that the perfec∣tion
of your brightnesse, hath pearced through the
thicknesse that couered my minde; in so much that I
am no lesse gladde to be reformed, then ashamed to re∣member
my grosenes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gyptes</SPEAKER>
<P>They are thrise fortunate that liue in your
Pallace, where Trueth is not in colours but life, vertues
not in imagination, but execution.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cynthia</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue alwaies studied to haue rather liuing
vertues then painted Gods, the bodie of Trueth, then
the tombe. But let vs walke to <HI>Endimion,</HI> it may bee it
lyeth in your Artes to deliuer him, as for <HI>Eumenides,</HI> I
feare he is dead.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pytha.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue alledged all the naturall reasons I can
for such a long sleepe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gyptes</SPEAKER>
<P>I can doe nothing till I see him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cynthia</SPEAKER>
<P>Coine <HI>Floscula,</HI> I am sure you are glad that
you shall behold <HI>Endimion.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flosc.</SPEAKER>
<P>I were blessed if I might haue him recouered.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cynthia</SPEAKER>
<P>Are you in loue with his person.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="26"/>
<SPEAKER>Flos.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, but with his vertue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cynthia</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhat say you <HI>Semele?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Semele</SPEAKER>
<P>Madame, I dare say nothing for feare I of∣fende.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cynthia</SPEAKER>
<P>Belike you cannot speake except you bee
spightfull. But as good be silent as saucie. <HI>Panelion,</HI>
what punishment were fitte for <HI>Semele,</HI> in whose speech
and thoughts, is onely contempt and sowrenesse?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pane.</SPEAKER>
<P>I loue not Madam to giue any iudgement. Yet
sith your highnesse commaundeth, I thinke, to commit
her tongue close prisoner to her mouth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cynthia</SPEAKER>
<P>Agreed; <HI>Semele,</HI> if thou speake thys twelue-month,
thou shalt forfet thy tongue. Behold <HI>Endimion,</HI>
alas poore Gentleman, hast thou spent thy youth in
sleepe, that once vowed all to my seruice. Hollow eyes?
gray haires? wrinckled cheekes? and decayed limmes?
Is it destinie, or deceite that hath brought this to passe?
If the first, who could preuent thy wretched starres. If
the latter, I would I might knowe thy cruell enemie. I
fauoured thee <HI>Endimion</HI> for thy honor, thy vertues, thy
affections: but to bring thy thoughts within the com∣passe
of thy fortunes, I haue seemed strange, that I
might haue thee staied, and nowe are thy dayes ended
before my fauour beginne. But whom haue we heere,
is it not <HI>Corsites?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Zon.</SPEAKER>
<P>It is, but more like a Leopard then a man.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Awake him. Howe nowe <HI>Corsites,</HI> what make
you heere? How came you deformed? Looke on thy
hands, and then thou seest the picture of thy face.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corsites</SPEAKER>
<P>Myserable wretch, and accursed. How am I
deluded? Madame, I aske pardon for my offence, and
you see my fortune deserueth pittie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cynthia</SPEAKER>
<P>Speake on, thy offence cannot deserue grea∣ter
punishment: but see thou rehearse the trueth, else
shalt thou not find me as thou wishest me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="26"/>
<SPEAKER>Corsites</SPEAKER>
<P>Madam, as it is no offence to be in loue bee∣ing
a man mortall, so I hope can it be no shame to tell
with whom, my Ladie beeing heauenlie. Your Maie∣stie
committed to my charge fayre <HI>Tellus,</HI> whose beau∣tie
in the same moment tooke my hart captiue, that I
vndertooke to carry her bodie prisoner. Since that time
haue I found such combats in my thoughts betweene
loue and dutie, reuerence and affection, that I coulde
neyther endure the conflict, nor hope for the conquest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cynthia</SPEAKER>
<P>In loue? A thing farre vnsitting the name of
a Captaine, and (as I thought) the tough and vnsmoo∣thed
nature of <HI>Corsites.</HI> But forth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corsites</SPEAKER>
<P>Feeling this continuall warre, I thought ra∣ther
by parlee to yeeld, then by certaine danger to per∣rish,
I vnfolded to <HI>Tellus</HI> the depth of my affections,
and framed my tongue to vtter a sweet tale of loue, that
was wont to found nothing but threats of warre. Shee
too fayre to be true, and too false for one so fayre, after
a nice deniall, practised a notable deceyt, commaunding
me to remooue <HI>Endimion</HI> from this Caban, and carrie
him to some darke Caue, which I seeking to accom∣plish,
founde impossible. And so by Fayries or fiendes
haue beene thus handled.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cynthia</SPEAKER>
<P>Hovve say you my Lordes, is not <HI>Tellus</HI>
alwaies practising of some deceites? In sooth <HI>Corsites</HI>
thy face is novve too foule for a Louer, and thine hart
too fonde for a Souldiour. You may see when VVarri∣ors
become wantons, howe theyr manners alter with
theyr faces. Is it not a shame <HI>Corsites,</HI> that hauing
liued so long in <HI>Mars</HI> his Campe, thou shouldest now
bee rockt in <HI>Venus</HI> Cradle. Doost thou we are <HI>Cupids</HI>
Quiuer at thy gyrdle, and make Launces of lookes?
Well <HI>Corsites</HI> rouse thy selfe, and be as thou hast beene,
and let <HI>Tellus</HI> who is made all of loue, melt herselfe in her
owne loosenes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="27"/>
<SPEAKER>Corsites</SPEAKER>
<P>Madam I doubt not but to recouer my for∣mer
state, for <HI>Tellus</HI> beautie neuer wrought such loue in
my minde, as now her deceite hath dispight, and yet to
be reuenged of a woman, were a thing then loue it selfe
more womanish.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gyptes</SPEAKER>
<P>These spots Gentleman are to be worne out,
if you rubbe them ouer with this Lunarie, so that in
place where you receiued this maine, you shall finde a
medicine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corsi.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thanke you for that. The Gods blesse mee
frō loue &amp; these prettie Ladies that haunt this greene.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flos.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Corsites,</HI> I would <HI>Tellus</HI> saw your amiable face.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Zontes</SPEAKER>
<P>How spightfully <HI>Semele</HI> laugheth, that dare
not speake.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cynthia</SPEAKER>
<P>Coulde you not stirre <HI>Endimion</HI> with that
doubled strength of yours?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cors.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not so much as his finger with all my force.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyn.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Pythagoras</HI> and <HI>Gyptes,</HI> what thinke you of <HI>Endi∣mion?</HI>
what reason is to be giuen, what remedie?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyth.</SPEAKER>
<P>Madame it is impossible to yeelde reason for
things that happen not in compasse of nature. It is most
certaine, that some strange enchauntment hath bound
all his sences.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cynthia</SPEAKER>
<P>What say you <HI>Gyptes.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gyptes</SPEAKER>
<P>VVith <HI>Pythagoras,</HI> that it is enchauntment,
and that so strange that no Arte can vndoe it, for that
heauines argueth a mallice vnremooueable in the En∣chauntresse,
and that no power can ende it, till shee die
that did it, or the heauens shew some meanes more then
miraculous.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flos.</SPEAKER>
<P>O <HI>Endimion,</HI> could spight it self deuise a mischiefe
so monstrous as to make thee dead with life, and lyuing
beeing altogether dead? Where others number their
yeeres, their houres, their minutes, and steppe to age by
staires, thou onely hast thy yeeres and times in a cluster,
<PB REF="27"/>
being olde before thou remembrest thou wast younge.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cynth.</SPEAKER>
<P>No more <HI>Floscula,</HI> pittie dooth him no good, I
would any thing els might, and I vowe by the vnspot∣ted
honour of a Ladie he should not misse it: but is this
all <HI>Giptes,</HI> that is to be done?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Giptes,</SPEAKER>
<P>All as yet. It may be that either the Enchaun∣tresse
shall dye, or els be discouered, if either happen I
will then practise the vtmost of my arte. In the meane
season, about this Groue would I haue a watch, and the
first liuing thing that toucheth <HI>Endimion,</HI> to be taken.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cynth.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Corsites</HI> what say you, will you vndertake this?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corsites</SPEAKER>
<P>Good Madame pardon mee, I was ouertaken
too late, I should rather breake into the middest of a
maine battaile, then againe fall into the handes of those
fayre babies.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cynth.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, I will prouide others. <HI>Pithagoras</HI> and
<HI>Giptes,</HI> you shall yet remaine in my Courte, till I heare
what may be done in this matter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyth</SPEAKER>
<P>Wee attende.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cynth.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let vs goe in.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="5" TYPE="act">
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Actus quintus. Scaena prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Samias, Dares.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Samias</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>EVmenides</HI> hath tolde such strange tales, as I
may well wonder at them, but neuer beleeue
them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dares</SPEAKER>
<P>The other old man, what a sad speech vsed he,
that caused vs almost all to weepe. <HI>Cynthia</HI> is so desirous
to knowe the experiment of her owne vertue, and so
willing to ease <HI>Endimions</HI> harde fortune, that she no soo∣ner
heard the discourse, but shee made her selfe in a rea∣dines
to trye the euent.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wee willl also see the euent, but whist heere
<PB REF="28"/>
commeth <HI>Cynthia,</HI> with all her traine: Let vs sneake in
amongst them.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Cynthia, Floscula, Semele, Panelion, &amp;c.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cynth.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Eumenides,</HI> it cannot sinke into my heade, that
I should bee signified by that sacred Fountaine, for
many thinges are there in the worlde, to which those
words may bee applyed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good Madame vouchsafe but to trye, els shall
I thinke my selfe most vnhappie, that I asked not my
sweete Mistris.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cynth.</SPEAKER>
<P>Will you not yet tell me her name?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pardon mee good Madame, for if <HI>Endimion</HI>
awake hee shall: my selfe haue sworne, neuer to re∣ueale
it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cynth.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, let vs to <HI>Endimion.</HI> I will not be so state∣lie
(good <HI>Endimion</HI>) not to stoope to doe thee good: and
if thy libertie consist in a kisse from mee, thou shalt haue
it. And although my mouth hath beene heere tofore as
vntouched as my thoughts, yet now to recouer thy life,
(though to restore thy youth it be impossible) I will do
that to <HI>Endimion,</HI> which yet neuer mortall man coulde
bost of heretofore, nor shall euer hope for heereafter.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Shee kisseth him.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum.</SPEAKER>
<P>Madame hee beginneth to stirre.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cynth.</SPEAKER>
<P>Soft <HI>Eumenides,</HI> stand still.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ah, I see his eyes almost open.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cynth.</SPEAKER>
<P>I commaund thee once againe stirre not: I wil
stand behinde him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan</SPEAKER>
<P>What doe I see, <HI>Endimion</HI> almost awake?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Endimion, Endimion,</HI> art thou deafe or dumbe?
or hath this long sleepe taken away thy memorie? Ah
my sweet <HI>Eudimion,</HI> seest thou not <HI>Eumenides?</HI> thy faith∣ful
friende, thy faythfull <HI>Eumenides,</HI> who for thy saftie
hath beene carelesse of his owne content. Speake <HI>Endi∣mion,
Endimion, Endimion.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="28"/>
<SPEAKER>End,</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Endimion?</HI> I call to minde such a name.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hast thou forgotten thy selfe <HI>Endimion?</HI> then do
I not maruell thou remembrest not thy friend. I tell thee
thou art <HI>Endimion,</HI> and I <HI>Eumenides:</HI> beholde also <HI>Cyn∣thia,</HI>
by whose fauour thou art awaked, and by whose
vertue thou shalt continue thy naturall course.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cynth.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Endimion,</HI> speake sweete <HI>Endimion,</HI> knowest
thou not <HI>Cynthia?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>End.</SPEAKER>
<P>O heauens, whom doe I beholde, faire <HI>Cynthia,</HI>
diuine <HI>Cynthia?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cynth.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am <HI>Cynthia,</HI> and thou <HI>Endimion.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>End.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Endimion,</HI> What do I heere? What, a gray beard?
hollow eyes? withered bodie: decayed lymbes? and all
in one night?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum.</SPEAKER>
<P>One night? thou hast heere slept fortie yeeres,
by what Enchauntresse as yet it is not knowne: and be∣hold
the twig to which thou laiedst thy head, is now be∣come
a tree, callest thou not <HI>Eumenides</HI> to remembrance?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>End.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thy name I doo remember by the sounde, but
thy fauour I doe not yet call to minde, onely diuine <HI>Cyn∣thia,</HI>
to whom time, fortune, destinie, &amp; death, are subiect,
I see and remember, and in all humilitie, I regard and re∣uerence.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cynth.</SPEAKER>
<P>You haue good cause to remember <HI>Eumeni∣des,</HI>
who hath for thy safetie forsaken his owne solace.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>End.</SPEAKER>
<P>Am I that <HI>Endimion,</HI> who was wont in Court to
leade my life, and in Iustes, turneys, and armes to exer∣cise
my youth? am I that <HI>Endimion?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou art that <HI>Endimion</HI> and I <HI>Eumenides,</HI> wilt
thou not yet call me to remembrance?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>End.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ah sweete <HI>Eumenides,</HI> I now perceiue thou art
hee, and that my selfe haue the name of <HI>Endimion,</HI> but
that this should bee my bodie I doubt: for howe coulde
my curled lockes bee turned to gray haires, and my
stronge bodie to a dying weaknesse, hauing waxed olde,
<PB REF="29"/>
and not kowing it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cynthia</SPEAKER>
<P>Well <HI>Endimion</HI> arise, a while sit downe, for
that thy limmes are stiffe, and not able to stay thee, and
tell what hast thou seene in thy sleepe all this while?
What dreames, visions, thoughts, and fortunes? For it is
impossible, but in so long time, thou shouldest see
things straunge.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>End.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fayre <HI>Cynthia</HI> I will rehearse what I haue
seene, humblie desiring, that when I exceede in length,
you giue me warning, that I may ende: for to vtter all
I haue to speake would bee troublesome, although
happilie the straungenesse may somewhat abate the te∣diousnesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cynth.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well <HI>Endimion</HI> begin.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>End.</SPEAKER>
<P>Me thought I sawe a Ladie passing faire, but
verie mischeeuous, who in the one hande carryed a
knife, with which shee offered to cut my throte: and in
the other a looking-glasse, wherein seeing how ill anger
became Ladies, shee refrained from intended violence.
She was accompanied with other Damsels, one of which
with a sterne countenance, &amp; as it were with a setled ma∣lice
engrauen in her eyes, prouoked her to execute mis∣cheefe:
an other with visage sad and constant onelie in
sorrow, with her armes crossed, and watery eyes, seemed
to lament my fortune, but durst not offer to preuent the
force. I started in my sleepe, feeling my verie veines to
swell, and my sinewes to stretch with feare, and such a
colde sweate bedewed all my bodie, that death it selfe
could not be so terrible, as the vision.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cynth.</SPEAKER>
<P>A straunge sight. <HI>Giptes</HI> at our better leysure
shall expound it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum.</SPEAKER>
<P>After long debating with her selfe, mercie o∣uercame
anger, and there appeared in her heauenly face
such a diuine Maiestie, mingled with a sweete mildenes,
that I was rauished with the sight aboue measure, and
<PB REF="29"/>
wished that I might haue enioied the sight without end,
and so she departed with the other Ladyes, of which the
one retained still an vnmoueable crueltie, the other a
constant pittie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cynth.</SPEAKER>
<P>Poore <HI>Endimion,</HI> how wast thou affrighted?
What els?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>End.</SPEAKER>
<P>After her immediatly appeared an aged man,
with a beard as white as snow, crying in his hand a book
with three leaues, &amp; speaking as I remēber these words.
<HI>Endimion,</HI> receiue this booke with three leaues, in which
are contained counsels, policies, and pictures, and with
that he offered mee the booke, which I reiected: wher∣with
moued with a disdainefull pittie, hee rent the first
leafe in a thousand shiuers, the second time hee offered
it, which I refused also: at which bending his browes,
and pitching his eyes fast to the ground, as though they
were fixed to the earth, and not againe to be remoued:
then sodainlie casting them vp to the heauens, he tore in
a rage the second leafe, and offered the booke only with
one leafe. I know not whether feare to offende, or desire
to knowe some strange thing, moued mee: I tooke the
booke, and so the olde man vanished.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cynthia</SPEAKER>
<P>What diddest thou imagine was in the last
leafe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>End.</SPEAKER>
<P>There I portraid to life, with a colde quaking
in euery ioynt. I behelde many wolues barking at thee
<HI>Cynthia,</HI> who hauing ground their teeth to bite, did
with striuing bleede themselues to death. There might
I see ingratitude with an hundred eyes, gazing for be∣nefites,
and with a thousand teeth, gnawing on the
bowelles wherein shee was bred. Trecherie stoode all
cloathed in white, with a smyling countenance, but
both her handes bathed in blood. Enuye with a pale
and megar face, (whose bodie was so leane, that one
might tell all her bones, and whose garment was so
<PB REF="30"/>
totterd, that it was easie to number euery thred) stood
shooting at starres, whose dartes fell downe againe
on her owne face. There might I beholde Drones,
or Beetles, I knowe not howe to terme them creeping
vnder the winges of a princely Eagle, who being carried
into her neast, sought there to sucke that veine,
that woulde haue killed the Eagle. I mused that
thinges so base, shoulde attempt a facte so barba∣rous,
or durst imagine a thing so bloody. And ma∣nie
other thinges Madame, the repeticion whereof, may
at your better leysure seeme more pleasing: for. Bees
surfette sometimes with honnie, and the Gods are
glutted with harmony, and your highnesse may be dul∣led
with delight.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cynth.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am content to bee dieted, therefore lette
vs in. <HI>Eumenides,</HI> see that <HI>Endimion</HI> bee well tended,
least eyther eating immoderatlie, or sleeping againe
too long, hee fall into a deadly surfette, or into his
former sleepe.</P>
<P>See this also bee proclaimed, that whosoeuer will
discouer this practise, shall haue of <HI>Cynthia</HI> infinite
thankes, and no small rewardes.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flosc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ah <HI>Endimion,</HI> none so ioyfull as <HI>Floscula,</HI> of thy
restoring.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes <HI>Floscula,</HI> let <HI>Eumenides</HI> be somewhat glad∣der,
and doe not that wrong to the setled friendship of
a man, as to compare it with the light affection of a wo∣man.
Ah my deere friend <HI>Endimion</HI> suffer mee to dye,
with gazing at thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>End.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Eumenides,</HI> thy friendshippe is immortall, and
not to be conceiued, and thy good will <HI>Floscula,</HI> bet∣ter
then I haue deserued. But let vs all wayte on
<HI>Cynthia:</HI> I maruell <HI>Semele</HI> speaketh not a word.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum.</SPEAKER>
<P>Because if shee doe, shee loseth her tongue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>End.</SPEAKER>
<P>But how prospereth your loue?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="30"/>
<SPEAKER>Eum.</SPEAKER>
<P>I neuer yet spake worde since your sleepe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>End.</SPEAKER>
<P>I doubt not but your affection is olde, and your
appetite colde.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum.</SPEAKER>
<P>No <HI>Endimion,</HI> thine hath made it stronger, and
nowe are my sparkes growne to flames, and my fancies
almost to frenzies: but let vs followe, and within wee
will debate all this matter at large.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Actus quintus. Scaena secunda.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Sir Tophas, Epiton.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Epi,</HI> loue hath iustled my libertie from the
wall, and taken the vpper hand of my reason.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let me then trippe vp the heeles of your affec∣tion,
and thrust your goodwill into the gutter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>No <HI>Epi,</HI> Loue is a Lorde of misrule, and kee∣peth
Christmas in my corps.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>No doubt there is good cheere: what dishes of
delight doth his Lordshippe feast you withal?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>First, with a great platter of plum-porrige
of pleasure, wherein is stued the mutton of mis∣trust.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Excellent loue lappe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>Then commeth a Pye of patience, a Henne
of honnie, a Goose of gall, a Capon of care, and
many other Viandes, some sweete, and some sowre,
which proueth loue to bee as it was saide of, in olde
yeeres. <HI>Dulce venenum.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>A braue banquet.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>But <HI>Epi.</HI> I praye theee feele on my chinne,
some thinge prycketh mee. VVhat doost thou feele
or see.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>There are three or foure little haires.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>I pray thee call it my bearde, howe shall I
bee troubled, when this younge springe shall growe
<PB REF="31"/>
to a great wood?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>O sir your chinne is but a quyller yet, you will be
most maiesticall when it is full fledge. But I maruell that
you loue <HI>Dipsas</HI> that olde Crone.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Agnosco veteris vestigia flammae,</HI> I loue the
smoke of an olde fyre.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why shee is so colde, that no fyre can thawe her
thoughts.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>It is an olde goose <HI>Epi,</HI> that will eate no oates,
olde Kine will kicke, olde Rats gnawe cheese, and olde
sackes will haue much patching. I preferre an old Cony
before a Rabbet sucker, and an ancient henne before a
younge chicken peeper.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Argumentum ab antiquitate,</HI> My master loueth
anticke worke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>Giue mee a pippin that is withered like an
olde wife.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>Then, <HI>a contrario sequitur argumentum.</HI> Giue
me a wife that lookes like an olde pippin.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nothing hath made my master a foole, but flat
Schollership.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>Knowest thou not that olde wine is best?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>And thou knowest that like will to like?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>I.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>And thou knowest that <HI>Venus</HI> loued the best
Wine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>So.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>Then I conclude, that <HI>Venus</HI> was an olde wo∣man
in an olde cuppe of wine. For, <HI>est Venus in vinis, ig∣nis
in igne fuit.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>O lepidum caput,</HI> O mad cap master. You were
worthy to winne <HI>Dipsas,</HI> were shee as olde againe, for
in your loue, you haue worne the nappe of your witte
<PB REF="31"/>
quite off, and made it thredbare. But soft who comes
heere?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>My solicitors.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sam.</SPEAKER>
<P>All haile sir <HI>Tophas,</HI> how feele you your selfe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>Statelie in euery ioynt, which the common
people terme stifnes. Doth <HI>Dipsas</HI> stoope? vvyll shee
yeeld? will she bende?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dares</SPEAKER>
<P>O sir as much as you would wish, for her chin
almost toucheth her knees.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Maister, she is bent I warrant you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhat conditions doth she aske?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Samias</SPEAKER>
<P>Shee hath vowed shee will neuer loue anie
that hath not a tooth in his head lesse then she.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>How manie hath shee?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dares</SPEAKER>
<P>One.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>That goeth harde Maister, for then you must
haue none.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>A small request, and agreeable to the gra∣uitie
of her yeeres. What shoulde a wise man doe with
his mouth full of bones like a channel house. The Tur∣tle
true hath nere a tooth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Samias</SPEAKER>
<P>Thy Maister is in a notable vaine, that will
loose his teeth to be like a Turtle.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let him loose his tongue to, I care not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dares</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay you must also haue no nayles, for shee
long since hath cast hers.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>That I yeelde to, what a quiet life shal <HI>Dip∣sas</HI>
and I leade, when wee can neither byte nor scratch?
You may see youthes, how age prouides for peace.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Samias</SPEAKER>
<P>How shal we doe to make him leaue his loue,
for we neuer spake to her?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dares</SPEAKER>
<P>Let me alone. Shee is a notable Witch, and
hath turnde her maide <HI>Bagoa</HI> to an Aspen tree, for be∣wraying
her secretes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Top.</SPEAKER>
<P>I honor her for her cunning, for now when I am
<PB REF="32"/>
wearie of walking on two legges, what a pleasure may
she doe mee to turne me to some goodly Asse, and help
mee to foure.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dares</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay then I must tell you the troth, her hus∣band
<HI>Geron</HI> is come home, who this fifty yeeres hath had
her to wife.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>What doe I heare? Hath she an husbande?
Goe to the Sexteene, and tell him desire is deade, and
will him to digge his graue. O heauens, an husbande?
What death is agreeable to my fortune?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Samias</SPEAKER>
<P>Be not desperate, and we will helpe you to
find a young Ladie,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>I loue no grissels they are so brittle, they will
cracke like glasse, or so dainty, that if they bee touched,
they are straight of the fashion of waxe: <HI>Animus maio∣ribus
instat.</HI> I desire olde Matrons. What a sight would
it be to embrace one whose hayre were as orient as the
pearle? whose teeth shal be so pure a watchet, that they
shall staine the truest Turkis? whose nose shall throwe
more beames from it then the fierie Carbuncle? whose
eyes shall be enuirond about with rednesse, exceeding
the deepest Corall? And whose lippes might compare
with siluer for the palenesse? Such a one if you can help
me to, I will by peece-meale curtoll my affections to∣wardes
<HI>Dipsas,</HI> and vvalke my swelling thoughts till
they be cold.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVisely prouided. How say you my freendes,
will you angle for my Maisters cause?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Samias</SPEAKER>
<P>Most willingly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dares</SPEAKER>
<P>If wee speede him not shortly, I will burne
my cappe, we will serue him of the spades, and digge an
old wife out of the graue, that shall be answerable to his
grauitie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>Youthes adiew; hee that bringeth mee first
newes, shall possesse mine inheritance.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="32"/>
<SPEAKER>Dares</SPEAKER>
<P>What, is thy Maister landed?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Know you not that my Maister is <HI>Liber tenens?
Samias</HI> What's that?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<P>A Free-holder. But I will after him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Samias</SPEAKER>
<P>And wee to heare what newes of <HI>Endimion</HI> for
the conclusion.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Actus quintus. Scaena tertia.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Panelion, Zontes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pane.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who would haue thought that <HI>Tellus</HI> beeing
so fayre by nature, so honourable by byrth, so wise by
education, woulde haue entred into a mischiefe to the
Gods so odious, to men so detestable, and to her freend
so malicious.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Zontes</SPEAKER>
<P>If <HI>Bagoa</HI> had not bewraied it, howe then
shoulde it haue come to light? But wee see that Golde
and fayre words, are of force to corrupt the strongest
men; And therefore able to worke sillie women like
waxe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Panelion.</SPEAKER>
<P>I maruell what <HI>Cynthia</HI> will determine in
this cause.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Zontes</SPEAKER>
<P>I feare as in all causes, heare of it in iustice,
and then iudge of it in mercy; for howe can it be that
shee that is vnwilling to punish her deadliest foes with
dysgrace, will reuenge iniuries of her trayne vvith
death.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Panelion</SPEAKER>
<P>That olde witch <HI>Dipsas</HI> in a rage, hauing
vnderstoode her practise to bee discouered, turned
poore <HI>Bagoa</HI> to an Aspen tree, but let vs make hast
and bring <HI>Tellus</HI> before <HI>Cynthia,</HI> for she was comming
out after vs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Zontes</SPEAKER>
<P>Let vs goe.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE><PB REF="33"/>
Cynthia, Semele, Floscula, Dipsas, Endimion,
Eumenides.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cynthia</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Dipsas,</HI> thy yeeres are not so manie as thy
vices, yet more in number then commonly nature dooth
affoorde, or iustice shoulde permit. Hast thou almost
these fiftie yeeres practised that detested wickednes of
witchcraft? Wast thou so simple, as for to know the na∣ture
of Simples, of all creatures to be most sinfull?</P>
<P>Thou hast threatned to turne my course awry, and
alter by thy damnable Arte, the gouernment that I now
possesse by the eternall Gods. But knowe thou <HI>Dipsas,</HI>
and let all the Enchaunters knowe, that <HI>Cynthia</HI> beeing
placed for light on earth, is also protected by the pow∣ers
of heauen. Breath out thou mayst wordes, gather
thou mayst hearbes, finde out thou maist stones agree∣able
to thine Arte, yet of no force to appall my heart,
in which courage is so rooted, and constant perswasion
of the mercie of the Gods so grounded, that all thy
witch-craft I esteeme as weake, as the world dooth thy
case wretched.</P>
<P>Thys noble Gentleman <HI>Geron,</HI> once thy husband,
but nowe thy mortall hate, didst thou procure to lyue
in a Deserte, almost desperate. <HI>Endimion</HI> the flovvre
of my Courte, and the hope of succeeding time, hast
thou bewitched by Arte, before thou wouldest suffer
him to florish by nature.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dipsas</SPEAKER>
<P>Madam, thinges past may be repented, not
recalled: there is nothing so wicked that I haue not
doone, nor any thing so wished for as death. Yet among
al the things that I committed, there is nothing so much
tormenteth my rented and ransackt thoughts, as that in
the prime of my husbands youth, I diuorced him by my
deuillish Arte, for which, if to die might be amendes,
I would not liue till to morrowe. If to liue and still be
<PB REF="33"/>
more miserable would better content him, I would wish
of all creatures to be oldest and vgliest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geron</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Dipsas,</HI> Thou hast made this difference be∣tweene
me and <HI>Endimion,</HI> that being both young, thou
hast caused mee to wake in melancholie, loosing the
ioyes of my youth, and hym to sleepe, not remembring
youth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cynthia</SPEAKER>
<P>Stay, heere commeth <HI>Tellus,</HI> we shall nowe
knowe all.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Corsites, Tellus, Panelion. &amp;c.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corsites</SPEAKER>
<P>I woulde to <HI>Cynthia</HI> thou couldest make as
good an excuse in truth, as to me thou hast done by wit.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tellus</SPEAKER>
<P>Truth shall be mine answere, and therefore I
will not studie for an excuse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cynthia</SPEAKER>
<P>Is it possible <HI>Tellus,</HI> that so few yeres should
harbor so many mischiefes? Thy swelling pride haue I
borne, because it is a thing that beautie maketh blame∣lesse,
which the more it exceedeth fairenes in measure,
the more it stretcheth it selfe in disdaine. Thy deuises
against <HI>Corsites</HI> I smyle at, for that wits the sharper they
are, the shrewder they are. But this vnacquainted and
most vnnaturall practise with a vile Enchauntresse, a∣gainst
so noble a Gentleman as <HI>Endimion,</HI> I abhorre, as a
thing most malicious, and will reuenge, as a deede most
monstrous.</P>
<P>And as for you <HI>Dipsas,</HI> I will send you into the De∣serte
amongst wilde beastes, and try whether you can
cast Lyons, Tygars, Bores, and Beares, into as deade a
sleepe as you did <HI>Endimion,</HI> or turne them to trees, as
you haue doone <HI>Bagoa.</HI> But tell me <HI>Tellus,</HI> what was the
cause of this cruel part, farre vnfitting thy sexe, in which
nothing should be but simplenes: and much disagree∣ing
from thy face, in which nothing seemed to bee but
softnes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tellus</SPEAKER>
<P>Diuine <HI>Cynthia,</HI> by whom I receiue my life, and
<PB REF="34"/>
am content to ende it. I can neyther excuse my faulte
without lying, nor confesse it without shame; Yet
were it possible that in so heauenlie thoughts as yours,
there coulde fall such earthly motions as mine, I would
then hope, if not to bee pardoned without extreame
punishment, yet to be heard without great maruell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cynthia</SPEAKER>
<P>Say on <HI>Tellus,</HI> I cannot imagine anie thing
that can colour such a crueltie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tellus</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Endimion,</HI> that <HI>Endimion</HI> in the prime of his
youth, so rauisht my hart with loue, that to obtaine my
desires, I coulde not finde meanes, nor to resite them
reason.</P>
<P>What was shee that fauoured not <HI>Endimion,</HI> being
young, wise, honorable, and vertuous; besides, vvhat
mettall was shee made of (be shee mortall) that is not
affected with the spice, nay infected with the poyson of
that (not to be expressed, yet alwaies to be felt) Loue?
which breaketh the braines, and neuer brooseth the
browe: consumeth the hart, and neuer toucheth the
skinne: and maketh a deepe skarre to be seene, be∣fore
any wounde at all be felt. My hart too tender to
vvithstande such a diuine furie, yeelded to Loue.
Madame I not without blushing confesse, yeelded to
Loue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cynthia</SPEAKER>
<P>A strange effect of loue, to worke such an
extreame hate. How say you <HI>Endimion,</HI> all this was for
loue?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>End.</SPEAKER>
<P>I say Madam then the Gods sende mee a wo∣mans
hate.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cynthia</SPEAKER>
<P>That were as bad, for then by contrarie you
shoulde neuer sleepe. But on <HI>Tellus,</HI> let vs heare the
ende.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tellus</SPEAKER>
<P>Feeling a continuall burning in all my bowels,
and a bursting almost in euerie vaine, I could not smoo∣ther
the inwarde fyre, but it must needes bee per∣ceiued
<PB REF="34"/>
by the outwarde smoke, and by the flying a∣broade
of diuers sparkes, diuers iudged of my scalding
flames.</P>
<P><HI>Endimion</HI> as full of arte as witte, marking mine eyes,
(in which hee might see almost his owne,) my sighes,
by which he might euer heare his name sounded, aymed
at my hart, in which he was assured his person was im∣printed,
and by questions wrunge out that, which was
readie to burst out. VVhen he sawe the depth of my
affections, he sware, that mine in respect of his, were as
fumes to Aetna, vallies to Alpes, Ants to Eagles, and
nothing could be compared to my beautie but his loue,
and eternitie. Thus drawing a smooth shoe vppon a
crooked foote, hee made me beleeue, that (which all of
our sexe willinglie acknowledge) I was beautifull. And
to wonder, (which indeede is a thing miraculous) that
any of his sexe should be faithfull.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cynthia</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Endimion,</HI> how will you cleere your selfe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>End.</SPEAKER>
<P>Madam, by mine owne accuser.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cynthia</SPEAKER>
<P>Well <HI>Tellus</HI> proceede, but breefelie, least ta∣king
delight in vttering thy loue, thou offende vs with
the length of it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tellus</SPEAKER>
<P>I will Madame quickly make an ende of my
loue &amp; my tale. Finding continuall increase of my tor∣menting
thoughts, and that the enioying of my loue,
made deeper woundes then the entering into it. I could
finde no meanes to ease my griefe, but to followe <HI>Endi∣mion,</HI>
and continually to haue him in the obiect of mine
eyes, who had me slaue and subiect to his loue.</P>
<P>But in the moment that I feared his falsehoode,
and fryed my selfe most in myne affections, I founde,
(ah griefe, euen then I lost my selfe.) I founde him in
most melancholie and desperate termes, cursing hys
starres, his state, the earth, the heauens, the world, and
all for the loue of</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="35"/>
<SPEAKER>Cynthia</SPEAKER>
<P>Of whom? <HI>Tellus</HI> speake boldly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tellus</SPEAKER>
<P>Madame, I dare not vtter for feare to of∣fende.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cynthia</SPEAKER>
<P>Speake I say; who dare take offence, if thou
be commaunded by <HI>Cynthia?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tellus</SPEAKER>
<P>For the loue of <HI>Cynthia.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cynthia</SPEAKER>
<P>For my loue <HI>Tellus,</HI> that were strange. <HI>Endi∣mion</HI>
is it true?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>End.</SPEAKER>
<P>In all things Madame. <HI>Tellus</HI> doth not speak
false.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cynthia</SPEAKER>
<P>What will this breede to in the ende? Well
<HI>Endimion,</HI> wee shall heare all.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tellus</SPEAKER>
<P>I seeing my hopes turnde to mishaps, and a
setled dissembling towards me, and an vnmooueable de∣sire
to <HI>Cynthia,</HI> forgetting both my selfe and my sexe;
fell vnto this vnnaturall hate; for knowing your ver∣tues
<HI>Cynthia</HI> to be immortall, I coulde not haue an ima∣gination
to withdraw him. And finding mine owne af∣fections
vnquenchable, I coulde not carrie the minde
that any els should possesse what I had pursued. For
though in maiestie, beautie, vertue, and dignitie, I al∣waies
humbled and yeelded my selfe to <HI>Cynthia,</HI> yet in
affections, I esteemed my selfe equall with the Goddes∣ses,
&amp; all other creatures according to theyr states with
my selfe. For stars to theyr bignes haue theyr lights, and
the sunne hath no more. And little pytchers when they
can holde no more, are as full as great vessels that runne
ouer. Thus Madam in all trueth, haue I vttered the vn∣happinesse
of my loue, and the cause of my hate, yeel∣ding
wholy to that diuine iudgement which neuer erred
for want of wisedom, or enuied for too much partiality.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cynthia</SPEAKER>
<P>How say you my Lords to this matter? But
what say you <HI>Endimion,</HI> hath <HI>Tellus</HI> tolde troth?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>End.</SPEAKER>
<P>Madame in all things, but in that shee saide I
loued her, and swore to honour her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="35"/>
<SPEAKER>Cynthia</SPEAKER>
<P>Was there such a time when as for my loue
thou didst vowe thy selfe to death, and in respect of it
loth'd thy life? speake <HI>Endimion,</HI> I will not reuenge it
with hate.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>End.</SPEAKER>
<P>The time was Madam and is, and euer shall be
that I honoured your highnesse aboue all the world, but
to stretch it so far as to call it loue, I neuer durst. There
hath none pleased mine eye but <HI>Cynthia,</HI> none deligh∣ted
mine eares but <HI>Cynthia,</HI> none possessed my hart but
<HI>Cynthia.</HI> I haue forsaken all other fortunes to followe
<HI>Cynthia,</HI> and heere I stande ready to die if it please <HI>Cyn∣thia.</HI>
Such a difference hath the Gods sette between our
states, that all must be dutie, loyaltie, and reuerence,
nothing (without it vouchsafe your highnes) be termed
loue. My vnspotted thoughts, my languishing bodie,
my discontented life, let them obtaine by princelie fa∣uour
that, which to challenge they must not presume,
onelie wishing of impossibilities: with imagination of
which, I will spende my spirits, and to my selfe that no
creature may heare, softlie call it loue. And if any vrge
to vtter what I whisper, then will I name it honor. From
this sweet contēplation if I be not drinen, I shall liue of al
men the most content, taking more pleasure in mine a∣ged
thoughts, then euer I did in my youthful actions.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyn.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Endimion,</HI> this honorable respect of thine, shalbe
christned loue in thee, &amp; my reward for it fauor. Perse∣uer
<HI>Endimion</HI> in louing me, &amp; I account more strength
in a true hart, then in a walled Cittie. I haue laboured to
win all, and studie to keepe such as I haue wonne, but
those that neither my fauour can mooue to continue
constant, nor my offered benefits gette to bee faith∣full,
the Gods shal eyther reduce to trueth, or reuenge
their trecheries with iustice. <HI>Endimion</HI> continue as thou
hast begun, and thou shalt finde that <HI>Cynthia</HI> shyneth
not on thee in vaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="36"/>
<SPEAKER>End.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your Highnesse hath blessed mee, and your
wordes haue againe restored my youth: mee thinkes I
feele my ioyntes stronge, and these mouldy haires to
molt, &amp; all by your vertue <HI>Cynthia,</HI> into whose hands the
Ballance that weigheth time &amp; fortune, are committed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cynth.</SPEAKER>
<P>What younge againe? then it is pittie to pu∣nish
<HI>Tellus.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tellus</SPEAKER>
<P>Ah <HI>Endimion,</HI> now I know thee and aske par∣don
of thee: suffer mee still to wish thee well.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>End.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Tellus, Cynthia</HI> must commaund what she will.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flosc.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Endimion,</HI> I reioyce to see thee in thy former
estate.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>End.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good <HI>Floscula,</HI> to thee also am I in my former
affections.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Endimion,</HI> the comfort of my life, howe am I
rauished with a ioy matchlesse, sauing onelie the enioy∣ing
of my mistrisse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cynth.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Endimion,</HI> you must nowe tell who <HI>Eumenides</HI>
shrineth for his Saint.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>End.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Semele</HI> Madame.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cynth.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Semele Eumenides?</HI> is it <HI>Semele?</HI> the very waspe
of all women, whose tongue stingeth as much as an Ad∣ders
tooth?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum.</SPEAKER>
<P>It is <HI>Semele, Cynthia:</HI> the possessing of whose
loue, must onelie prolong my life.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cynth.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay sith <HI>Endimion</HI> is restored, wee will haue
all parties pleased. <HI>Semele,</HI> are you content after so long
triall of his faith, such rare secresie, such vnspotted loue,
to take <HI>Eumenides?</HI> Why speake you not? Not a word?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>End.</SPEAKER>
<P>Silence Madame consents: that is most true.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cynth.</SPEAKER>
<P>It is true <HI>Endimion. Eumenides,</HI> take <HI>Semele.</HI>
Take her I say.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum.</SPEAKER>
<P>Humble thanks Madame, now onely doe I be∣gin
to liue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Semele</SPEAKER>
<P>A harde choyce Madame, either to be married
<PB REF="36"/>
if I say nothing, or to lose my tongue if I speake a word.
Yet doe I rather choose to haue my tongue cut out, then
my heart distempered: I will not haue him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cynth.</SPEAKER>
<P>Speakes the Parrat? shee shall nod heereafter
with signes: cut off her tongue, nay her heade, that ha∣uing
a seruant of honourable birth, honest manners, <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="missing" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
true loue, will not be perswaded.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Semele</SPEAKER>
<P>He is no faithfull I <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="missing" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>or then
would he haue asked his Mistris.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geron</SPEAKER>
<P>Had he not beene faithfull, he had neuer seene
into the fountaine, and so lost his friend and Mistrisse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thine own thoughts sweet <HI>Semele,</HI> witnesse a∣gainst
thy wordes, for what hast thou founde in my life
but loue? and as yet, what haue I founde in my loue but
bitternesse? Madame pardon <HI>Semele,</HI> and let my tongue
ransome hers.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thy tongue <HI>Eumenides?</HI> what shouldst thou liue
wanting a tongue to blaze the beautie of <HI>Semele.</HI> Well
<HI>Semele,</HI> I will not commaund loue, for it cannot bee en∣forced:
let me entreat it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Semele</SPEAKER>
<P>I am content your Highnesse shall command,
for now only do I thinke <HI>Eumenides</HI> faithfull, that is wil∣ling
to lose his tongue for my sake: yet loth, because it
should doe me better seruice. Madame, I accept of <HI>Eu∣menides.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cynth.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thanke you <HI>Semele.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ah happie <HI>Eumenides,</HI> that hast a friend so faith∣full,
and a mistris so faire: with what sodaine mischiefe
will the Gods daunt this excesse of ioye? Sweet <HI>Semele,</HI>
I liue or dye as thou wilt.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cynth.</SPEAKER>
<P>What shall become of <HI>Tellus? Tellus</HI> you know
<HI>Endimion</HI> is vowed to a seruice, from which death cannot
remooue him. <HI>Corsites</HI> casteth still a louely lookes to∣wards
you, how say you will haue your <HI>Corsites,</HI> and so re∣ceiue
pardon for all that is past?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tellus</SPEAKER>
<P>Madame most willingly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="37"/>
<SPEAKER>Cynthia</SPEAKER>
<P>But I cannot tel whether <HI>Corsites,</HI> be agreed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corsites</SPEAKER>
<P>I Madame more happie to enioy <HI>Tellus</HI> then
the Monarchie of the world.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why she caused you to be pincht with Fairies.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>I but her fairenesse hath pinched my hart more
deepelie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cynthia</SPEAKER>
<P>Well enioy thy loue. But what haue you
wrought in the Castle <HI>Tellus?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tellus</SPEAKER>
<P>Onely the picture of <HI>Endimion.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cynthia</SPEAKER>
<P>Then so much of <HI>Endimion</HI> as his picture
commeth to, possesse and play withall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corsites</SPEAKER>
<P>Ah my sweete <HI>Tellus,</HI> my loue shal be as thy
beautie is, matchlesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cynthia</SPEAKER>
<P>Now it resteth <HI>Dipsas,</HI> that if thou wilt for∣sweare
that vile Arte of Enchaunting, <HI>Geron</HI> hath pro∣mised
againe to receiue thee, otherwise if thou be wed∣ded
to that wickednes, I must and will see it punished to
the vttermost.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dipsas</SPEAKER>
<P>Madam, I renounce both substance and sha∣dow
of that most horrible and hatefull trade, vowing to
the Gods continuall penaunce, and to your highnes o∣bedience.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cynthia</SPEAKER>
<P>Howe say you <HI>Geron,</HI> will you admit her to
your Wife?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geron</SPEAKER>
<P>I with more ioy then I did the first day: for
nothing could happen to make me happy, but onely her
forsaking that leude and detestable course. <HI>Dipsas</HI> I im∣brace
thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dipsas</SPEAKER>
<P>And I thee <HI>Geron,</HI> to whom I will heereafter
recite the cause of these my first follies.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cynthia</SPEAKER>
<P>Well <HI>Endimion,</HI> nothing resteth nowe but
that we depart. Thou hast my fauour, <HI>Tellus</HI> her friend,
<HI>Eumenides</HI> in Paradice with his <HI>Semele, Geron</HI> contented
with <HI>Dipsas.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay soft, I cannot handsomly goe to bed
<PB REF="37"/>
without <HI>Bagoa.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cynthia</SPEAKER>
<P>Well <HI>Syr. Tophas,</HI> it may bee there are more
vertues in mee then my selfe knoweth of, for <HI>Endimion</HI>
I awaked, and at my words he waxed young, I will trie
whether I can turne this tree againe to thy true loue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P>Turne her to a true loue or false, so shee be a
wench I care not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cynthia</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Bagoa, Cynthia</HI> putteth an end to thy harde
fortunes, for being turnd to a tree for reuealing a truth,
I will recouer thee againe, if in my power be the effect
of truth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tophas</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Bagoa?</HI> a bots vpon thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cynthia</SPEAKER>
<P>Come my Lordes let vs in, you <HI>Gyptes</HI> and
<HI>Pythagoras,</HI> if you cannot content your selues in our
Court, to fall from vaine follies of Phylosophers, to such
vertues as are here practised, you shall be entertained
according to your deserts, for <HI>Cynthia</HI> is no stepmother
to strangers.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pytha.</SPEAKER>
<P>I had rather in <HI>Cynthias</HI> Court spende tenne
yeeres, then in Greece one houre.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gyptes</SPEAKER>
<P>And I chuse rather to liue by the sight of
<HI>Cynthia,</HI> then by the possessing of all Egipt.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cynthia</SPEAKER>
<P>Then follow.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eumenides</SPEAKER>
<P>We all attend.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
<BACK>
<DIV1 TYPE="epilogue">
<PB REF="38"/>
<HEAD>❧The Epilogue.</HEAD>
<P>A Man walking abroade, the wind and
Sunne stroue for soueraignty, the one
with his blast, the other with his beames.
The wind blew hard, the man wrapped his
garmēt about him harder: it blustred more
strongly, he then girt it fast to him: I cannot
preuaile sayd the wind. The Sunne casting
her Christall beames, began to warme the
man: he vnlosed his gowne. yet it shined
brighter: he then put it off. I yeelde sayd
the winde, for if thou continue shining, he
will also put off his cote.</P>
<P>Dread Soueraigne, the malicious that
seeke to ouerthrowe vs with threats, do but
stiffen our thoughts, and make them stur∣dier
in stormes: but if your Highnes vouch
safe with your fauorable beames to glaunce
vpon vs, we shall not onlie stoope, but with
all humilitie, lay both our handes and
hearts, at your Maiesties feete.</P>
<PB REF="38"/>
</DIV1>
</BACK>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

