<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2002-08-19</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Mona Logarbo</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TEMPHEAD, checked ID, and added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate.
Checked for N=""s.
Checked for GROUP tags.
Proofed title page.
Checked <SUP>s</SUP>.
Checked I / J.
Reviewed structure. Changed P to SIGNED on PB REF="2". Placed TRAILER on PB REF="37" after DIV2 since "FINIS" applies to the entire play and not just to the DIV2 of the last act.
Checked placement and completeness of PBs.
Checked for duplicate pages.
Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, —, q;s, and UNCLEARs.
Corrected $s and $Word$s by inserting vendor-responsible GAP DESC and in a few instances by inserting the appropriate letter(s). Use a single $ to represent a single incomprehensible letter and not to represent a series of two or more incomprehensible letters.
Checked for &amp;cs with incorrect spacing.
Checked for LBs.
Checked for startqs, endqs and Qs.
Checked proofsheets and made corrections.
Sample: 08 minutes. Proofing: 15 minutes. Tag review and corrections: ** minutes. DONE 08-19-02.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A06975">
<STC T="S">17398</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99847375</BIBNO>
<VID>12408</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>The dumbe Knight.</P>
<P><HI>A historicall Comedy, acted sundry times</HI> by the children of his Maie∣sties Reuels.</P>
<P><FIGURE>
</FIGURE></P>
<P><HI>LONDON,</HI> Printed by <HI>Nicholas Okes,</HI> for <HI>Iohn Bache,</HI> and are to be sold at his shop in Popes-head Palace, neere to the Royall Exchange. 1608.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>To the vnderstanding Reader.</HEAD>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">R</SEG>VMOR that <HI>Hydra</HI> headed Monster, with more tongues then eyes, by help of his intelli∣gencer enuy hath made strange miscon∣structions on this dumbe Knight, which then could not answere for himselfe: but now this publication doth vnty his tongue, to answer the obiections of all sharp critticall censures which heretofore haue vndeseruedly past vp∣on him. And for my part (Iprotest) the wrongs I haue receiued by some (whose worths I will not traduce) with a milde neglect I haue laught at their follies; for I thinke my selfe happy, because I haue beene enuyde, since the best now in grace haue beene sub∣iect to some slanderous tongues that want worth themselues, and thinke it great praise to them to detract praise from other that deserue it; yet hauing a partner in the wrong, whose worth hath beene of∣ten approued, I count the wrong but halfe a wrong, because hee knowes best how to answer for himselfe: But I now in his absence, make this Apologie, both for him and me. Thus leauing you and the booke together, I euer rest yours.</P>
<SIGNED>Lewes Machin.</SIGNED>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 N="1" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="3"/>
<PB REF="3"/>
<HEAD>Act. 1.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Sce. 1. Musicke,</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter the King of Cypres, Phylocles, Florio, and attend<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nts in armes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cypr.</SPEAKER>
<L><SEG REND="decorInit">I</SEG>Nnough, these loud sounds deafes my passions</L>
<L>How long shall loue make me a slaue to hope,</L>
<L>And mixe my calme desires with <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></L>
<L>O <HI>Phylocles</HI> t'is heresie I hold,</L>
<L>Thought and affection cannot be controld.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet mai't be bent and suppled wi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h extreames,</L>
<L>Sith few dare see the end of violence</L>
<L>What makes the skilfull Leech to vse the fire,</L>
<L>Or warre her engines, or st<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tes policie,</L>
<L>But to recouer things most desperate?</L>
<L>Renolt is recreant when pursuit is braue,</L>
<L>Neuer to faint doth purchase what we craue</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyp.</SPEAKER>
<L>True my <HI>Phylocles,</HI> yet my recreant soule,</L>
<L>Slaued to her beauty, would renounce all warre,</L>
<L>And yeeld her right to loue, did not thy spirit</L>
<L>Mixt with my longing, fortifie these armes.</L>
<L>But I am now resolud and this sad houre,</L>
<L>Shall giue an end to my disemprature.</L>
<L>Summon a parley.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter a loft, the Queene of Sicille, the Duke of Epire, Alphouso and attendants.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queene.</SPEAKER>
<L>What saies our tyrant sutor, our disease in loue,</L>
<L>That makes our thoughts a slaue vnto his sword:</L>
<L>What saies my Lord?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="4"/>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madame attend me, this is my latest summons,</L>
<L>The many sunnes my sorrowes haue beheld,</L>
<L>And my sad nights of longings, all through hope,</L>
<L>T'enioy the ioy of earth, (your owne deare selfe)</L>
<L>Are growne so infinite in length and waight,</L>
<L>That like to wearied <HI>Atl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>,</HI> I inforce</L>
<L>These warres as <HI>Hercules,</HI> to beare my loade:</L>
<L>Briefly I must enioy you, or else loose</L>
<L>The breath of life, which to preuent, behold,</L>
<L>My sword must be my <HI>Cupid,</HI> and with feathered steele,</L>
<L>Force pity from your breast, your Cities walles,</L>
<L>Chidden with my Canons, haue set ope a path</L>
<L>And boldly bids me enter, all your men of warre,</L>
<L>Feebled with famine, and a weary siege,</L>
<L>Take danger from mine actions, onely your selfe,</L>
<L>Strong in your will, oppose euen destiny:</L>
<L>And like the giants warre offend the heauens,</L>
<L>Which to preuent, do but discend and giue</L>
<L>Peace to my loue-suit, and as orecome thereby,</L>
<L>I'le yeeld my selfe your prisoner, and be drawne,</L>
<L>A thrall in your triumphant victory.</L>
<L>If otherwise, behold these fatall swords,</L>
<L>Shall neuer be sheath'd, till we be conquerours:</L>
<L>And not respecting innocence nor sexe,</L>
<L>The cries of infants, nor the prayers of age,</L>
<L>All things shall perish, till within my armes</L>
<L>I fould your selfe my thrall and conquerour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou maiest be maister of my bodies Tombe</L>
<L>But for my soule and minde, they are as free</L>
<L>As their creation: and with Angels wings</L>
<L>Can soare beyond thy reach; trust me king of <HI>Cypres</HI></L>
<L>Those coales the Roman Portia did deuour,</L>
<L>Are not burnt out, nor haue th'Egiptian wormes,</L>
<L>Yet lost their stings, steele holds his temper still,</L>
<L>And these are ransomes from captiuity.</L>
<L>But art thou noble, hast thou one royall thought?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="4"/>
<SPEAKER>Cyp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Approue me by your question.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then briefly thus:</L>
<L>To shun the great effusion of their bloods,</L>
<L>Who feele no touch in mine affections,</L>
<L>Dare you to single combate, two to two,</L>
<L>Referre your right in loue?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who are your combatants? we loue equality.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is the first, the Epyre duke, a man,</L>
<L>Sprung from the line, of famous <HI>Scanderbag:</HI></L>
<L>The next <HI>Alphonso,</HI> sprung from noble bloud:</L>
<L>Who laden with rich lusitanian prize,</L>
<L>Hath rod through <HI>Syrac<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></HI> twice in pompe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Their likings to the motion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ep.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are like wrath,</L>
<L>Neuer vnannd to beat weake iniury.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay more, we are the sonnes of destiny:</L>
<L>Ve<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>'s our guide, our ayme is dignity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<L>S'foot king, shalt not forsake them: this I see,</L>
<L>Loue, fight, and death, are rul'd by destiny.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyp.</SPEAKER>
<L>My spirit speakes thy motion.</L>
<L>Madame, although aduantage might euade,</L>
<L>And giue my loue more hope, yet my bent will,</L>
<L>Bowd to your pleasure, doth imbrace your lawe,</L>
<L>We do accept the combate, and our selfe</L>
<L>Will with that Duke try fortunes, this my friend,</L>
<L>The more part of my selfe, me deerest <HI>Philocles,</HI></L>
<L>One of an Angels temper, shall with that that Lord</L>
<L>Trie best and worst the place, the time, the sword.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epy.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are your rights, we claime as challengers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyp.</SPEAKER>
<L>And we would lose that vantage, but since fame</L>
<L>Makes vertue dulat, we embrace our rights:</L>
<L>The place before these walles, the houre next sunne,</L>
<L>The pollax and the hand axe for the fight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is enough,</L>
<L>My hostage is my person and my loue:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyp.</SPEAKER>
<L>And mine my hope, my f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ith and royalty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="5"/>
<SPEAKER>Epy.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are of poysse sufficient, and one light</L>
<L>Shall at one instant, giue vs day and night.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt. Queene, Mariano, Alphonso.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee's gone my <HI>Philocles:</HI> and as she goes euen so,</L>
<L>The sunne forsakes the heauens to kisse the sea,</L>
<L>Day in her beauty leaues vs, and methinkes,</L>
<L>Her absence doth exile all happines.</L>
<L>Tell me my <HI>Philocles,</HI> nay pray thee tell me true,</L>
<L>Euen from that loue</L>
<L>Which to vs both should bend one sympathy:</L>
<L>Discharge an open breast, dost thou not thinke,</L>
<L>She is the mirror of her beauteous sexe?</L>
<L>Vnparalleld, and vncompanioned.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Enuy will say shee's rare, then truth must vow,</L>
<L>She is beyond compare, sith in her lookes,</L>
<L>Each motion hath a speaking maiesty,</L>
<L>She is herselfe, compared with her selfe:</L>
<L>For but her selfe, she hath no companion.</L>
<L>But when I thinke of beauty, wit and grace,</L>
<L>The elements of actiue delicacy,</L>
<L>Those all eie-pleasing harmonies of sight</L>
<L>Which do inchant mens fancies, and stir vp</L>
<L>The life bloud of dull earth, O then methinkes,</L>
<L>Faire <HI>Mariana</HI> hath an equall place</L>
<L>And if not outshine, it shewes more beautifull.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyp.</SPEAKER>
<L>More then my Queene?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>More in the glosse of beauty, lesse in worth,</L>
<L>Of wisedome and great thoughts, the one I finde</L>
<L>was made for wonder, th'other for admire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thine equall praises makes my facnies rich:</L>
<L>And I am pleas'd with thy comparisons,</L>
<L>Things of like nature liue in best consent,</L>
<L>Beauty with subiects, maiesty with Kings,</L>
<L>Then let those two Ideaes liuely moue,</L>
<L>Spirit beyond all spirit, in our breasts,</L>
<L><PB REF="5"/>
That in the end of our great victory,</L>
<L>we may attaine both loue and maiesty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Although my first creation and my birth,</L>
<L>My thoughts and other tempers of my soules,</L>
<L>Tooke all their noble beings from the sword,</L>
<L>And made me onely for the vse of warres:</L>
<L>Yet in this combate, something methinkes apeares,</L>
<L>Greater then greatest glory, and doth raise</L>
<L>My minde beyond her selfe,</L>
<L>S'foot methinkes <HI>Casars</HI> Pharsalia,</L>
<L>Nor <HI>Sc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>os</HI> Carthage, nor <HI>Emilias</HI> acts,</L>
<L>Were worthy chaires of triumph, they ore mens</L>
<L>Poore mangled bodies, and fire-wasted climes,</L>
<L>Made their triumphant passage, but we two</L>
<L>Must conquer thoughts and loue, more then the gods can doe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyp.</SPEAKER>
<L>True, and therein</L>
<L>Consists the glorious garland of our praise,</L>
<L>But we neglect th'aff<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ires of preparation. <HI>Florio</HI> be it your charge</L>
<L>To see th'erection of the squared lists,</L>
<L>Fit ground for either army, and what else,</L>
<L>Belongs vnto such royall eminence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo.</SPEAKER>
<L>How neere will your maiesties hand the lists extend</L>
<L>Vnto the Cities walles?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyp.</SPEAKER>
<L>So as the dullest eie,</L>
<L>May see the heedfulst passage in the fight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo.</SPEAKER>
<L>What square or circuite?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Threescore pace each way.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your maiesty shal haue your will perform'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do, and you do vs grace; and now thou sunne,</L>
<L>That art the eye of heauen, whose pure sight,</L>
<L>Shall be our guide, and Ioues great Chronicler,</L>
<L>Looke from thy spheare,</L>
<L>No guilt of pride, of mallice or of blood,</L>
<L>Puts on our armour, onely pure naked loue</L>
<L>Tutors our hopes, and doth our actions moue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Enough my <HI>Philocles,</HI> thine orizons are heard.</L>
<L><PB REF="6"/>
Come lets away.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Lollia, the wife of Prat the Orator.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lol.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now fy vpon't, who would be an Orators wife, and not a Gen∣tlewoman if she could chuse? a Lady is the most sweet lasciuious life, conieyes and kisses, the tire, O the tire, made castell vpon castell, iew∣ell vpon iewell, knot vpon knot, crownes, garlands, gardins, and what not? the hood, the rebato, the french fall, the loose bodyed gowne, the pinne in the haire, now clawing the pate, then picking the teeth, and euery day change, when we poore soules must come and goe for euery mans pleasure, and what's a Lady more then another body? we haue legges and hands, and rouling e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>es, hanging lips, sleeke browes, cher∣rie cheekes, and other things as Ladies haue, but the fashion carries it away.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Mistresse Collaquintida.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why how now Mistresse <HI>Prat?</HI> i'the old disease still, will it ne∣uer be better, cannot a woman finde one kind man amongst twentie? O the daies that I haue seene, when the lawe of a womans wit, could haue pu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> her husbandspurse to execution.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lol.</SPEAKER>
<P>O Mistresse <HI>Collaquintida,</HI> mine is euen the vnnaturallest man to his wife.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith for the most part, all schollers are so: for they take so vpon thē to know al things, that indeed they know nothing: &amp; besides, they are with study and ease, growne so vnweldy, that a woman shall neare want a sore stomacke that's troubled with them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lol.</SPEAKER>
<L>And yet they must haue the gouernment of all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<P>True, and great reason they haue for it, but a wise man will put it in a womans hand, what? shee'le saue what he spends.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lol.</SPEAKER>
<L>You haue a pretty ruffe, how deep is it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay this is but shallow, marry I haue a ruffe is a quarter deep, measured by the yeard.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeed, by the yeard?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<P>By the standard I assure you: you haue a pretty set too, how big is the steele you set with?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lol.</SPEAKER>
<P>As big as a reasonable sufficient; pitty of my life, I haue forgot my selfe, if my husband should rise from his study, and misse me, wee should haue such a coile.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="6"/>
<SPEAKER>Co.</SPEAKER>
<P>A coyle, why what coyle? if he were my husband and did but thwart mee, I would ring him so many alarums, sound him so many brasse trumpets, beate him so many drums to his confusion, and thunder him such a peale of great shot, that I would turne his brain in the panne, and make him madde with an eternall silence.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lo.</SPEAKER>
<P>O mistresse <HI>Coloquintida,</HI> but my husbands anger is the worst fauouredst without all conscience of any mans in all Sicilie, he is euen as peeuish as a sick munkie, and as waspish as an ill pleasd bride the second morning.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Co.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let your wrath be reciprocall, and pay him at his owne wea∣pon: but to the purpose for which I came, the party you wote of, commends him to you in this diamond, hee that met the party you know, and said the parties partie was a party of a partly pretty vnder∣standing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lo.</SPEAKER>
<L>O the Lord, <HI>Alphonso.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Co.</SPEAKER>
<P>The very same belceue it, he loues you, and sweares he so loues you, that if you doe not credit him you are worse then an infidell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeede mistresse <HI>Coloquintida,</HI> he hath the right garbe for ap∣parell, the true touch with the tongue in the kisse, and he dances well but falles heauily: but my husband woman, my husband, if we could put out his cattes cics, there were something to be said but they are e∣uer peeping &amp; prying that they are able to pierce through a milstone: besides: I may say to you, he is a little iealous too, and see where hee comes, wee shall haue a coyle now.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Prate the Orator.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Co.</SPEAKER>
<L>Begin you to pout first, for thats a womans preuention.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pra.</SPEAKER>
<P>What <HI>Lollia</HI> I say, where are you my house lookes you, my men lack you, I seeke you, and a whole quest of inquiry cannot finde you, fy, fy, fy, fy, Idlenes is the whip of thrift, a good huswife should euer be occupied?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeede I haue much ioy to bee occupied in any bodies com∣pany.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prate.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, whats the matter?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why Orators wiues shortly will bee knowne like images on water staires, euer in one wetherbeaten suite, as if none wore hoodes but Monkes and Ladies, nor feathers but fore-horses and waiting gen∣tlewomen,
<PB REF="7"/>
nor chaines but prisoners and Lords officers, nor perri∣wigs but players and hotte braines, but the weakest must to the walles still.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prate.</SPEAKER>
<L>Go to, you shall haue what you will.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay nay, 'twas my hard fortune to be your wife, time was I might haue done otherwise, but it matters not, you esteeme me as you doe your selfe, and thinke all things costly enough that couers shame, and that a paire of silken foresleeues to a satten brestplate, is a garment good enough for a capitoll: but is master <HI>Wrangle,</HI> master <HI>Tangle,</HI> or master <HI>Trobleare</HI> of that opinion? in faith sir no.</P>
<L>Ther's neuer a gallant in our state</L>
<L>That goes more rich in gaudy brauery:</L>
<L>And yet I hope for quality of speech,</L>
<L>Audacious words or quirkes or quidities,</L>
<L>You are not held their much inferiour.</L>
<L>Fy, fy, I am asham'd to see your basenesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Co.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeede master <HI>Prate</HI> she telles you truly; I wonder that you being a proper man and an Orator will not go braue, according to the custome of the country.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prate.</SPEAKER>
<P>Go to neighbour, he that wil rise to the top of a high ladder must goe vp, not leape vp: but be patient wench, and thou shalt short∣ly see me gallant it with the best, and for thy selfe my <HI>Lollia,</HI></P>
<L>Not <HI>Lollia Paulina,</HI> nor those blasing starres,</L>
<L>Which makes the world the Apes of Italy:</L>
<L>Shall match thy selfe in sun-bright splendency.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, verily for my selfe I care not, tis you that are my pride, if you would goe like your selfe I were appeasd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prate.</SPEAKER>
<P>Beleeue it wench so I will, but to the purpose for which I came, the end of this great warre is now brought to a combate, two to two, the Duke of <HI>Epyre</HI> and <HI>Alphonso</HI> for our Queene against the King and Prince <HI>Philocles:</HI> now wench if thou wilt goe see the fight, I will send and prouide thee of a good standing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeede, for you haue nere a good one of your owne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prate.</SPEAKER>
<L>What, <HI>President</HI> I say?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pre.</SPEAKER>
<L>Anon, anon sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="7"/>
<SPEAKER>Prate.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why when I say, the villains bellie is like a bottomlesse pit, euer filling and yet emptie, at your leasure sir.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter President Prates man eating.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pre.</SPEAKER>
<P>I can make no more haste then my teeth will giue mee leaue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prate.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well sir, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> you without the towne, to the place for the combate, and prouide me for my wife some good standing, to see the conflict.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pre.</SPEAKER>
<P>How master how, must I prouide a good standing for you for my mistresse? truly Master I thinke a mary bone pye, candi'd er∣ringoes, preseru'd dattes, or marmaladd of cantharides were much better harbingers, cock sparrowes stew'd, doues brai<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>es or swannes pizels are very prouocatiue, roasted potatoes or boild skerrets are your onely lofty dishes, me thinks these should fit you better then I can doe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prate.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whats this, whats this I say? prouide mee a standing for my wife vpon a scaffold.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pre.</SPEAKER>
<L>And truely Master, I thinke a priuat chamber were better.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prate.</SPEAKER>
<L>I graunt you, if there were a chamber conuenient.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pre.</SPEAKER>
<P>Willing minds will make shift in a simple hole, close win∣dowes, strong locks, hard bed and sure posts, are your onely orna∣ments.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prate.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thinke the knaue he madde, sirra you chop logicke, blockhead, you that haue your braine panne made of dry leather, &amp; your wit euer wetshod: pack about your businesse, or Ile pack your pen and inckhorne about your cares.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pre.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well sir, I may go or so, but would my mistresse take a standing of my preferment, I would so mount her, shee should loue strange things the better all her life after.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prate.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why when sir.</L>
<STAGE>Exit President.</STAGE>
<L>And come sweete wife, nay neighbour let vs haue your company too.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE><PB REF="8"/>
Enter at one dore a Herald, and Floria marshall for the King, with officers bearing the lists, at the other dore a he∣rald and Coelio marshall for the Queene.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cae.</SPEAKER>
<L>Holla, what are you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo.</SPEAKER>
<L>High marshall for the King, your Character.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cae.</SPEAKER>
<L>I likewise for the Queene, where lies your equall gr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>und?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here vnderneath these walles, and the<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> and there ground for the battailes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cae.</SPEAKER>
<L>Place there the Queenes seate,</L>
<L>And there and there chaiers for the combatants.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Place here the lists, fixe euery ioint as strong</L>
<L>As 'twe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e a wall, for on this foote of earth</L>
<L>This day shall stand two famous monuments,</L>
<L>The one a throne of glory bright as gold,</L>
<L>Burnisht with angels luster, and with starres,</L>
<L>Pluckt from the crowne of conquest, in which shall sit</L>
<L>Men made halfe Gods through famous victory:</L>
<L>The other a rich tombe of memorable fame,</L>
<L>Built by the curious thoughts of noble mindes,</L>
<L>In which shall sleepe these valiant soules in peace,</L>
<L>Whom Fortunes hand shall only ouerthrow.</L>
<L>Heauen in thy Palme, this day the ballance hings.</L>
<L>Which makes Kings Gods, or men more great then Kings.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cae.</SPEAKER>
<L>So now let the heralds giue the champions signe</L>
<L>Of ready preparations.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Herralds.</STAGE>
<STAGE>The cornets sound, and enter at one end of the stage a H<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ld, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="3 words" DISP="〈◊◊◊〉"/> with <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ther with hand <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, the Duke of Epyra, and Alphon<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ke <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, the Queene and Mari∣ana and Prate, Lo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ia, Coloqui<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> and President aloft.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo.</SPEAKER>
<L>What are you that appeare, and what deuoyre</L>
<L>Drawes you within these lists?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epy.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am the Duke of Epyne, and the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 words" DISP="〈◊◊〉"/></L>
<L>Which doth attract my spirit to run this marshall course,</L>
<L><PB REF="8"/>
Is the faire guard of a distressed Queene,</L>
<L>Would wedde to hate and in equality and brutish force,</L>
<L>Which to withstand I boldly enter thus,</L>
<L>And will defaile, or else proue recreant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo.</SPEAKER>
<L>And what are you or your intendiments?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am <HI>Alphonso</HI> marshall of this realme,</L>
<L>Who of like tempered thoughts and like desires,</L>
<L>Haue grounded this my sanctimonious zeale,</L>
<L>And will approue the Dukes assertions,</L>
<L>Or in this field lie slaine and recreant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Enter and prosper as your cause deserues.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>The cornets sound, and enter at the other end of the stage a Herald, two Pages with axes and pollaxes, then the king of Cypres and Philocles, like combatants and their Army.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cae.</SPEAKER>
<L>What are you that appeare, and what deuoyre</L>
<L>Drawes you within these lists?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cy.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am the King of <HI>Cypres,</HI> who led on</L>
<L>By the diuine instinct of heauenly loue,</L>
<L>Come with my sword to beg that royall maid,</L>
<L>And to approue by gift of heauen and fate</L>
<L>She is a one to me appropriate:</L>
<L>Which to maintaine I challenge entrance here,</L>
<L>Where I will liue a King or recreant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cae.</SPEAKER>
<L>And what are you or your intendiments?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am lesse then my thoughts, more then my selfe,</L>
<L>Yet nothing but the creature of my fate,</L>
<L>By name my nature onely is obscur'd,</L>
<L>And yet the world baptis'd me <HI>Philocles.</HI></L>
<L>My entrance here is proofe of holy zeale,</L>
<L>And to maintaine that no seuere disdaine,</L>
<L>False shape of chastitie, nor womans will,</L>
<L>Neglectiue petulāce, or vncertaine hope,</L>
<L>Foule vizard coynes, nor seducing fame</L>
<L>Should rob the royall temper of true loue</L>
<L><PB REF="9"/>
From the desired aime of his desires,</L>
<L>Which my best bloud shall witnesse, or this field</L>
<L>Intombe my body made a recreant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cae.</SPEAKER>
<L>Enter and pro sper as your cause deserues.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Drawes 2 swords.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Princes, lay your hands on these swords points</L>
<L>Here you shall sweare by hope, by heauen, by loue;</L>
<L>And by the right you challenge in true fame,</L>
<L>That here you stand not arm'd with any guile,</L>
<L>Malignant h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>te, or vsurpation</L>
<L>Of philters charmes, of nightspels characters,</L>
<L>Or other blacke infer<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ll vantages,</L>
<L>But euen with thoughts as pure</L>
<L>As your pure vallures, or the sunnes pure beames,</L>
<L>T'approue the right of pure affection;</L>
<L>And howsoe're your fortunes rise or fall,</L>
<L>To breake no faith in your conditions,</L>
<L>So help you Ioue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>We sweare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>How often doth my maiden thoughts correct</L>
<L>And chide my froward will, for this extreame</L>
<L>Pursuit of bloud! beleeue me, faine I would</L>
<L>Recall mine oathes vow, did not my shame</L>
<L>Hold fast my cruelty, by which is taught</L>
<L>Those gems are prized best, are deerest bought,</L>
<L>S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>eep my loues softnes then, waken my flame,</L>
<L>Which guards a vestall sanctity; Princes behold,</L>
<L>Vpon those weapons sits my God of loue,</L>
<L>And in their powers my loues seuerity.</L>
<L>If them you conquere, we are all your slaues,</L>
<L>If they triumph, weele mourne vpon your graues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now by my maiden modesty I wish</L>
<L>Good fortune to that <HI>Philocles,</HI> my minde</L>
<L>Presages vertue, in his eaglets eies.</L>
<L>S'foot he lookes like a sparrow hauke, or a wanton fire</L>
<L>A flash of lightning, or a glimpse of day,</L>
<L>His eie steales to my heart, and lets it see</L>
<L><PB REF="9"/>
More then it would, peace, blab no secresie,</L>
<L>He must haue blowes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sound co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ets, Princes respect your guards.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Heere they fight, and Philocles ouerthrow<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> Alphonso, and Epyre ouerthrowes Cypres.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I craue the Queenes conditions, or this blow</L>
<L>Sends this afflicted soule to heauen or hell.</L>
<L>Speake madame, will you yeeld or shall he die?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Neither bould Prince, if thou but touch a haire,</L>
<L>The kings breath shall redeeme it: madame your loue</L>
<L>Is safe in angels guarding, let no feare</L>
<L>Shake hands with doubtfulnesse, you are as safe</L>
<L>As in a tower of Diamonds.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>O t'is but glasse,</L>
<L>And cannot beare this axes massinesse.</L>
<L>Duke, thy braue words that second thy braue deedes,</L>
<L>Fils me with emulation, onely we two</L>
<L>Stand equall victors; then if thou hast that tie</L>
<L>And bond of well knit valure, which vnites</L>
<L>Vertue and same together, let vs restore</L>
<L>Our captiues vnto freedome, and we two,</L>
<L>In single combate trie out the mastery.</L>
<L>Where whoso falles each other, shall subscribe</L>
<L>To euery clause in each condition.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art the index of mine ample thought,</L>
<L>And I am pleas'd with thine election.</L>
<L>Speake madame, if euer I deserued grace,</L>
<L>Grace me with your consent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>T'is all my will.</L>
<L>Thy noble hand erect and perfit me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>What saies his maiesty?</L>
<L>My starres are writ in heauen, nor death nor fate</L>
<L>Are slaues to feare, to hope or human state.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyp.</SPEAKER>
<L>I neither feare thy fortune nor my ruine;</L>
<L>But hold them all beyond all prophesie.</L>
<L><PB REF="10"/>
Thou hast my free consent, and on thy power</L>
<L>Lies my liues date o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> my deaths hower.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then rise and liue with safety.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Alphonso,</HI> here my hand,</L>
<L>Thy fortune lends thy peace no infamy.</L>
<L>And now thou glorious issue of Ioues braine,</L>
<L>That burnt the <HI>Telamonian</HI> Rauisher,</L>
<L>Looke from thy spheare, and if my heart containe</L>
<L>An impure thought of lust, send thy monsters forth</L>
<L>And make me more then earthly miserable.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Here the cornets sound, they fight, and Philocles ouer∣comes the Duke, the Queene defends.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yeld, recant or dye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thine axe hath not the power to wound my thought,</L>
<L>And yeelds a word my tongue could neuer sound,</L>
<L>I say th'art worthy valiant, for my death,</L>
<L>Let the Queene speake it, tis an easie breath.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not for the worlds large circuite, hold gentle Prince,</L>
<L>Thus I doe pay his ransome, lowe as the ground,</L>
<L>I tender mine vnspotted virgin loue,</L>
<L>To thy great willes commandement, let not my care</L>
<L>My woman tyrannie, or too strict guard,</L>
<L>In bloudy purchase take away those sweetes</L>
<L>Till now haue gouernd your amazd desires:</L>
<L>For trust me king, I will redeeme my blame,</L>
<L>With as much loue, as <HI>Philocles</HI> hath fame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thus comes a calme vnto a Sea-wract soule,</L>
<L>Ease to the pained, foode vnto the staru'd,</L>
<L>As you to me my best creation.</L>
<L>Trust me my Queene, my loues large chronicle</L>
<L>Thou neuer shalt ore read, because each day</L>
<L>It shall beget new matter of amaze:</L>
<L>And liue to doe thee grace eternally,</L>
<L>Next whom my <HI>Philocles</HI> my bounteous friend,</L>
<L><PB REF="10"/>
Author of life, and soueraigne of my loue,</L>
<L>My heart shall be thy throne, thy breast the shrine,</L>
<L>Where I will sit to study gratefulnes</L>
<L>To you and you my Lords, my best of thoughts,</L>
<L>Whose loues haue shewd a dutious carefulnes,</L>
<L>To all free thankes and graces, this vnity</L>
<L>Of loue and kingdomes, is a glorious sight.</L>
<L>Mount vp the royal Champion, musicke &amp; cornets sound.</L>
<L>Let shouts and cries make heauen and earth rebound.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epy.</SPEAKER>
<L>How like the sunnes great bastard ore the world,</L>
<L>Rides this man mounted engine, this proud prince</L>
<L>And with his breath sindges our continents</L>
<L>Sit fast proud <HI>Phaeton,</HI> for by heauen ile kicke</L>
<L>And plunge thee in the sea: if thou'lt needes ride,</L>
<L>Thou shouldst haue made thy seat vpon a slaue,</L>
<L>And not vpon mine honours firmament.</L>
<L>Thou hast not heard the God of wisedomes tale,</L>
<L>Nor can thine youth curbe greatnes, till my hate,</L>
<L>Confound thy life with villaine policy.</L>
<L>I am resolu'd since vertue hath disdaind</L>
<L>To cloath me in her riches, henceforth to proue</L>
<L>A villaine fatall, blacke and o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>nous:</L>
<L>Thy vertue is the ground of my dislike:</L>
<L>And my disgrace, the edge of enuies sword,</L>
<L>Which like a rasor shall vnplumbe thy crest;</L>
<L>And rob thee of thy natiue excellence,</L>
<L>When great thoughts giue their homage to disgrace</L>
<L>Thers's no respect of deedes, time, thoughts or place.</L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="2" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Act. 2.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Sce. 1. Musicke.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Prat, Lollia, Colloquintida, and President.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prat.</SPEAKER>
<L>COme wife, me thought our partie stood stifly to it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pres.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeed they were stiffe whilest they stood, but when they
<PB REF="11"/>
were downe, they were like men of a low world, a man might haue wound their worst a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ger about his finger.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lol.</SPEAKER>
<P>Goe to sirra, you must haue your fooles bolt in euery bodies quiuer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pre.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeed mistresse, if my master should breake his arrow with foule shooting or so, I would bee glad if mine might supply the whole.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>t.</SPEAKER>
<L>I find you kinde sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pre.</SPEAKER>
<P>True sir, according to my kinde, and to pleasure my kinde Mistresse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prat.</SPEAKER>
<P>Go to sirra, I will not haue your kindnes to intermeddle with her kinde, she is meate for your master.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pre.</SPEAKER>
<L>And your man sir, may licke your foule trencher.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<L>I but not eate of his mutton.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pre.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet I may deep my bread in the woole, Mistresse <HI>Colloquintida.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prat.</SPEAKER>
<P>Goe to sirra, you will bee obscene, and then I shall knocke you; but to the combate, me thought our side were the more proper men.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lol.</SPEAKER>
<P>True, and therefore thoy had the worse fortune: but see heere is the Lord <HI>Florio.</HI></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Florio.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Master Orator, it is the King and Queenes maiesties plea∣sure, that you presently repaire vnto the Court, touching the draw∣ing out of certaine Articles for the benefite of both the king∣domes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prat.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, I will instantly attend their maiesties.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe, for they expect you seriously.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Florio.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prat.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wise you can haue my seruice no longer. Sirra, President, attend you vpon your mistresse home: and wife, I would haue you to hold your iourney directly homeward, and not to imitate prin∣ces in their progresse, step not out of your way to visit a new gossip, to see a new garden-house, to smell the perfumes of Court ierkins, or to handle other tooles then may fit for your modestie: I would not haue you to step into the Suburbs, and acquaint your selfe either with monsters or motions, but holding your way directly hom<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ward, shew your selfe still to bee a rare hous∣wife.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="11"/>
<SPEAKER>Lol.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'faith, I'faith, your blacke out-side will haue a yellowe li∣ning.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prat.</SPEAKER>
<P>Content thee wife, it is but my loue that giues thee good coun∣saile. But here comes one of my clients.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Drap, a country Gentleman.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Drap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, master Orator, I am bold to trouble you about my suit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Si, M<SUP>r</SUP>. country gentleman, I am now for present busines of the kings.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dra.</SPEAKER>
<L>You may the better remember me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pra.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hey day, I shall mixe your businesse with the kings.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dra.</SPEAKER>
<L>No but you may let his maiestie know my necessity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pra.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, sir, you must not confine me to your seasons, I tell you I will collect mine owne leasures.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Veloups a Citizen.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ve.</SPEAKER>
<P>Master Orator, is it your pleasure I attend you about my dispatches?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pra.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, it is my pleasure you dispatch your selfe from mine incum∣brance, I tell you I am for instant businesse of the Kings,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ve.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, I haue borne mine attendance long.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pra.</SPEAKER>
<P>Beare it till your bones ake, I tell you I cannot beare it now, I am for new busines.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dra. Ve.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet the old would be dispatcht, it was first paid for.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prat.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you be gentlemen do not make me mad.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dra. Ve.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, our suits are of great waight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prat.</SPEAKER>
<P>If you be Christians do not make me an Atheist, I shall pro∣phane if you vex me thus.</P>
<STAGE>Enter the Lord Mechant.</STAGE>
<P>What more vexation? my Lord, my Lord, saue your breath for your broth, I am not now at leasure to attend you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<L>A word good Mr. Orator.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prat.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not a word I beseech your Lordship, I am for the Kings bu∣sinesse, you must attend me at my chamber.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Prat.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me. Dra. Ve.</SPEAKER>
<L>And euery where else, wee will not leaue you.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pre.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now methinkes my master is like a horse-leech, and these su∣tors so many sicke of the gout, that come to haue him suck their bloud: O t'is a mad world.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lol.</SPEAKER>
<P>Goe to sirra, you will neuer leaue your crabtree similies;
<PB REF="12"/>
but pity of me who haue we heare?</P>
<STAGE>Enter Alphonse.</STAGE>
<L>O t'is the Lord <HI>Alphonso.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alph.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mistresse God saue: nay your lip I am a stranger; &amp; how doth Mistresse <HI>Colloquintida,</HI> O you are an excellent seasoner of city sto∣mackes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith my Lord I haue done my best to make somebody relish your sweet meates; but harke you my Lord, I haue strucke the stroak, I haue done the deed, there wants nothing but time, place and her consent.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Call you that nothing?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<P>A <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ste, a trifle, vpon her, vpon her my Lord, she may seeme a little rough at the first; but if you stand stifly to her, shee'le fall; a word with you M<SUP>r</SUP>. <HI>President.</HI></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>They whisper.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mistresse <HI>Prat,</HI> I am a souldier, and can better act my loue then speake it, my suit you know by your neighbour, my loue you shall proue by my merit, to both which my tokens haue bin petty witnesses and my body shal seale &amp; deliuer vpon thee such a braue confirmatiō, that not all the Orators in Sicill shall bee able to cancell the deede.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lol.</SPEAKER>
<P>Truely my Lord, methinkes you being witty should bee honest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alph.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay wench, if I were a foole, ther's no question but I would be honest; But to the purpose, say wench, shall I enioy, shall I possesse?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lol.</SPEAKER>
<L>To enioy my loue, is not to possesse my body.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tut wench, they be words of one signification, and cannot be separated.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay then I should wrong my husband.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sfoot, thou shouldest but do for him as he does for the whole world; why an Orator were a needle name, if it were not to defend wrong: then wench, do as he doth, write by a president.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lol.</SPEAKER>
<L>O my Lord, I haue a husband,</L>
<L>A man whose waking ielousie suruiues,</L>
<L>And like a Lion, sleepes with open eies;</L>
<L>That not a minute of mine houres are free</L>
<L>From the intelligence of his secret spies.</L>
<L>I am a very toward <HI>Danae</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="12"/>
Thorow whose roofe, suspition will not let,</L>
<L>Gold showers haue passage, nor can I deceiue,</L>
<L>His <HI>Argus</HI> eies, with any policy:</L>
<L>And yet I sweare I loue you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Death of affection, if thou lou'st me, as thou saiest thou dost,</L>
<L>Thou canst inuent some meanes for our delight.</L>
<L>The rather <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>th it euer hath beene said,</L>
<L>That walles of brasse withstand not willing mindes:</L>
<L>And women whenth'are prone make loue admir'd:</L>
<L>For quaint indeuours, come instruct thy wit:</L>
<L>And finde some scale to our hie hight of blisse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then breefly thus my Lord.</L>
<L>To morrow doth the Senate sit to iudge,</L>
<L>Causes both criminall and of the stave;</L>
<L>Where of necessity my husbands place,</L>
<L>Must be fild by himselfe, because his tongue,</L>
<L>Must guild his clients causes, Now if you please,</L>
<L>All that selfe houre, when he is turmoil'd,</L>
<L>About those serious trifles, to vouchsafe</L>
<L>To visit me, his absence and my care</L>
<L>Shall giue vs libertie of more delight.</L>
<L>You know my meaning, and I am asham'd</L>
<L>My loue should thus betray my modesty;</L>
<L>But make the vse according to your fancy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<L>What houre assures his absence?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Eight is the latest time.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<L>This kisse leaue my faith with thee, farewell.</L>
<L>Th'ast giuen me double glory from thy breath,</L>
<L>Nothing shall lose me time but certaine death.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Alp.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pre.</SPEAKER>
<P>Truely Mistresse <HI>Collaquint<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>àa,</HI> you are an excellent peece of sweet gall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well sir, will you lead the way homeward?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pre.</SPEAKER>
<L>To your bed chamber <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, or your priuie lodging.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> alone.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Night clad in blacke mournes for the losse of day,</L>
<L><PB REF="13"/>
And hides the siluer spangles of the aire,</L>
<L>That not a sparke is left to light the world,</L>
<L>Whil'st quiet sleep the nourisher of life</L>
<L>Takes full possession on mortality.</L>
<L>All creatures take their rest in soft repose</L>
<L>Saue malecontents, and we accursed louers,</L>
<L>Whose thoughts perturbed, makes vs passions slaue:</L>
<L>And robs vs of the iuice of happinesse.</L>
<L>Deere <HI>Mariana,</HI> shapt in an Angels mould,</L>
<L>Thou thral'st my senses, and inflam'st my blood,</L>
<L>Loue, power, by wisedome cannot bee withstood.</L>
<L>But see the morning starre breakes from the East,</L>
<L>To tell the world her great eie is awak't</L>
<L>To take his iourney to the westerne vales:</L>
<L>And now the court begins to rise with him.</L>
<STAGE>Here passes ouer the stage a Physi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ian, a Gentleman Vsher, and a waiting maide.</STAGE>
<L>There goes the Physitian, the waiting maid,</L>
<L>And a fine straight leg'd Gentleman Vsher,</L>
<L>The preface to a kirtill all puffe past.</L>
<L>One that writes sonnets in his Ladies praise,</L>
<L>And hides her crimes with flattering poesie.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Marian.</STAGE>
<L>But peace amazement, see the day of life,</L>
<L>Natures best worke, the worlds chiefe paragon.</L>
<L>Madame one word.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>I; so now farewell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>You do mistake me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>That your selfe can tell,</L>
<L>You ask't me one word, which I gaue, said I,</L>
<L>A word of least vse in a virgins breath,</L>
<L>Vrge not my patience then with fond reply.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Deere Lady lend an eare vnto my voice</L>
<L>Sith each were made for others happines:</L>
<L>My tong's not oild with courtly flatterings,</L>
<L><PB REF="13"/>
Nor can I paint my passions to the life;</L>
<L>But by that power which shapt this heauenly forme,</L>
<L>I am your bond-slaue, forc'd by loues command,</L>
<L>Then let soft pitty with such beauty dwell.</L>
<L>Madame I loue you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>As I am a virgin so do I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>But Madame whom?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>My selfe, no Lady better.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>But will you loue me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>No by my chastity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hope you do but iest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay ile keep mine oath,</L>
<L>Men shall abandon pride and iealousie</L>
<L>Ere ile be bound to their captiuity,</L>
<L>They shall liue continent, and leaue to range,</L>
<L>But men like to the moone, each month must change.</L>
<L>Yet we must seeke that naught their sight displeases,</L>
<L>And mixe our wedlock sweetes with loathd diseases:</L>
<L>When we consume our selues and our best beauty,</L>
<L>All our reward is why, t'was but our duty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Iudge not so hard of all for some offendors;</L>
<L>For you are subiect to the selfe same crimes,</L>
<L>Of men and women alwaies haue bene had</L>
<L>Some good of each.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>But for the most part bad:</L>
<L>Therefore ile haue none at all but die a perfit maide.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>That humour like a flower soone will fade,</L>
<L>Once did mine owne thoughts sing to that delight,</L>
<L>Till loue and you reformd my barbarousnesse:</L>
<L>Therefore deere Lady, pitty my wounded heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Surgeon here for this loue-wounded man.</L>
<L>How deep's your vlcerd orifice, I pray you tell?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Quite thorow my heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>T'is strange and looke so well;</L>
<L>Yet Ladies eies haue power to murder men,</L>
<L>And with one smile to make them whole agen.</L>
<L><PB REF="14"/>
Achilles launce to a haire, but doe you loue me prince?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Deerer then my soule.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would I could loue you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madame so you may.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>As yet I cannot, therefore let me goe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>O do not leaue me, grant me but one request,</L>
<L>And here I vow by that diuinest power,</L>
<L>The salt-seas glorious issue, whose bright spheare</L>
<L>Rules my sick heart, and knowes my chast intent,</L>
<L>That if you please t'impose on me that taske</L>
<L>Which neither men nor monster can atchieue,</L>
<L>Which euen Angels haue a dread to touch,</L>
<L>Deedes which outstretch all possibility,</L>
<L>S'foot more then can be thought, and i'le effect,</L>
<L>Or else i'le perish in th'accomplishment.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let your request fit virgin modesty,</L>
<L>And you obey your vow, I am content</L>
<L>To giue your thoughts contented happinesse,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>T'is but a kisse I aske, a minutes ioy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now <HI>Cupid</HI> help thee, is thy griefe for this,</L>
<L>Keep thy strong vow, &amp; freely take a kisse.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>He kisses her.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue obtaind my heauen, and in this touch,</L>
<L>I feele the breath of all delitiousnesse:</L>
<L>Then freely giue the sentence of my worke,</L>
<L>Muster vp all the engins of your wit,</L>
<L>Teach <HI>Iuno</HI> rules beyond malitiousnesse,</L>
<L>What eare it be, i'le die bu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>le performe it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou shalt not kil thy selfe, nor fight with monsters,</L>
<L>Nor bring the great Turkes berd to shew thy zeale:</L>
<L>Thy life thou shalt not hazard for my loue,</L>
<L>Nor will I tie thee to an endlesse taske,</L>
<L>But euen with ease, and gentle rangled knots,</L>
<L>Thou shalt vntwind thy clew of miseries,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let it haue passage, madame giue me my doome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then <HI>Philocles</HI> knit silence to my words,</L>
<L>And marke thy doome: for thus my strickter will</L>
<L><PB REF="14"/>
Loads griefe vpon thy vainer leuity.</L>
<L>Hence for the space and compasse of one yeare</L>
<L>Thou shalt abiure the liberty of speech,</L>
<L>Thou shalt not speake for fully twelue months space,</L>
<L>For friend nor foe, for danger nor for death;</L>
<L>But liue like aire, with silent emptinesse.</L>
<L>Breake thou this vow, i'le hold thee for a villaine:</L>
<L>And all the world shall know thy periu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>y.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be heauen and earth a witnesse of my vow,</L>
<L>And mine eternall silence, I am dumbe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why so, now shal I not be troubled with vaine chat</L>
<L>Oridle prate of idle wantonnesse:</L>
<L>For loue I cannot, therefore tis in vaine,</L>
<L>Would all my sutors tongues I thus could raine,</L>
<L>Then should I liue free from faind sighes and groanes,</L>
<L>With O take pitty, tis your seruant moanes,</L>
<L>And such harsh stuffe, that frets me to the heart:</L>
<L>And sonnets made of <HI>Cupids</HI> burning dart.</L>
<L>Of <HI>Venus</HI> lip, and <HI>Iunoes</HI> maiestie.</L>
<L>Then were I freed from fooles and foolerie.</L>
<L>In May the cuckoe sings, then sheel'e come hither,</L>
<L>Her voice and yours will rarely tune together.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Mari<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>na. Enter Florio.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prince <HI>Philocles,</HI> the king would speake with you:</L>
<STAGE>Speakes lou∣der &amp; louder.</STAGE>
<L>Prince <HI>Philocles,</HI> the king would speake with you,</L>
<L>Prince <HI>Philocles,</HI> the king would speake with you.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Philocles strikes Florio and fels him.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo.</SPEAKER>
<L>The pox rot off your fingers for this blow,</L>
<L>It is coronation day, thorow all my scull,</L>
<L>Theres such a fatall ringing in my braine,</L>
<L>Has woone the selt, has laid fiue fingers on;</L>
<L>But twas a knauish part of him to play so.</L>
<L>Heare me you Gods for this my open wrong,</L>
<L>Make short his fingers as you haue his tongue.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Flo.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Meschant alone:</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis not mans fortune, enuy or neglect,</L>
<L><PB REF="15"/>
Which makes him miserable, but tis meane fate,</L>
<L>Euen sole predestination, a firme gift,</L>
<L>Fixt to his birth, before the world was made,</L>
<L>For were it otherwise, then within our liues,</L>
<L>We should finde some distractions, errours change.</L>
<L>And other toies of much vncertaintie:</L>
<L>But my mishaps are fixt so to my blood,</L>
<L>They haue no sire but my creation:</L>
<L>The Queene out of suspition that my loue,</L>
<L>First set an edge vpon the Kings desires,</L>
<L>And made him wooe her with a victors sword,</L>
<L>Casts me from fauour, seazes all my lands,</L>
<L>And turnes my naked fortunes to the cold.</L>
<L>The King made proud with purchase of his wish</L>
<L>Neglects my sufferance for him, and ore lookes,</L>
<L>The low-tide of my fortunes; lest my woes</L>
<L>Should speake my wrongs to his ingratitude;</L>
<L>The whil'st those lords whose supple hams haue bow'd</L>
<L>To doe me formal reuerence, now despise</L>
<L>And sleight me in their meanest compliments:</L>
<L>O tis a torment more then hell yet knowes</L>
<L>To be an honest flatterer, or to liue</L>
<L>A saint in <HI>Limbo,</HI> which that I may preuent,</L>
<L>Ile be nor best nor worst, but all indifferent.</L>
<L>But here comes a noble man, I must turne petitioner.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Florio.</STAGE>
<L>My Lord, may I not see the king?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo.</SPEAKER>
<L>You may not.</L>
<L>His maiestie is now downe prest with seriousnesse:</L>
<L>As for your suit it is with <HI>Prat</HI> the Orator.</L>
<L>I heard his highnesse giue him a speciall charge</L>
<L>For your dispatch with fauour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<L>O but he doth neglect,</L>
<L>And sleights me like his weake orations,</L>
<L>And by your Lordships leaue, I do not thinke</L>
<L>His wisedome worthy of the conference.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay if you will correct the kings coyne you are not for my con∣ference,
<PB REF="15"/>
Fare you well.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Florio.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, and fare you well, S'foot this is more then strange,</L>
<L>That being grieu'd I may not say i'me paind.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Alphonso.</STAGE>
<L>But heere comes another: Mine honorable Lord</L>
<L>May I not haue some conference with the king?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<L>You may not, businesse of greater waight</L>
<L>Imports both him and vs: nay pray you cease;</L>
<L>As for your suit tis with the Orator.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet methinkes twere meet</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<L>That you would rather trouble him then me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<L>Its strange.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Its strange indeed, to see you wrong your ease.</L>
<L>I am not now for idle conferences, adiew.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Alph.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why this is court grace to men in misery,</L>
<L>And thus these taile-lesse Lions with their roare,</L>
<L>Affright the simple heard: O I could now</L>
<L>Turne rebell gainst their pride.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Epire.</STAGE>
<L>But heere comes the Duke:</L>
<L>My gratious Lord, vouchsafe to heare my griefes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epy.</SPEAKER>
<L>For Gods loue cease your trouble, wee are all</L>
<L>Troubled with griefes of stranger qualities.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<L>Words are no heauy burthen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epy</SPEAKER>
<L>No, had I no other waight;</L>
<L>But we are all downe prest with other poise:</L>
<L>As for your sui<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> it is refer'd to <HI>Prat:</HI></L>
<L>And he must giue you faire dispatch with fauour;</L>
<L>VVhich if he <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>leight for enuy or for bribe,</L>
<L>Repaire to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, and I will not forget</L>
<L>To giue you ease, and chide his negligence.</L>
<L>Meane space I pray you leaue me, for we all</L>
<L>Are troubled now with greatest miracles.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your grace doth do me comfort, and I will</L>
<L>Study with seruice to deserue your fauours,</L>
<L>And so I take my leaue.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>. Enter <HI>2</HI> Doctors.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your owne content<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ts follow you.</L>
<L>Now gentlemen what newes within, can this dumbe wonder speake?</L>
<L><PB REF="16"/>
Haue youcutoff <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>hose l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>s that tied his speech.</L>
<L>And made your <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ames <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> sound thorow Sicille?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>1</HI> Doct.</SPEAKER>
<L>All hopefull meanes that man or art can finde,</L>
<L>Haue we made triall of, but tis in vaine:</L>
<L>For still my Lord, the cur'es invincible.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>2</HI> Doct.</SPEAKER>
<L>Those Organs nature gaue to moue the tongue,</L>
<L>He fully doth possesse as w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ll as we;</L>
<L>Which makes vs thinke his suddaine apoplexe,</L>
<L>Is either will, vow, or a miracle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epy.</SPEAKER>
<L>I should thinke strangly, had wee strange things on earth;</L>
<L>But wonders now are most familiar:</L>
<L>But here comes his maiestie, now we shall see</L>
<L>If this dumbe beast can speake before the king.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Cornets, and enter Cypres, Queene Philoclas, Mariana and attendants.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyp.</SPEAKER>
<L>My best of friends, my deerest <HI>Philocles,</HI></L>
<L>Thy griefes run in my spirit, make me sad,</L>
<L>And duls my sense with thine affliction.</L>
<L>My soule with thine doth sympathize in woe,</L>
<L>And passion gouerns him that should rule all.</L>
<L>What say our Doctors is there no hope of help?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>1</HI> Doct.</SPEAKER>
<L>No hope my Lord, the cure is desperate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then I am king of greife, for in his words</L>
<L>Found I more musicke then in quires of Angels,</L>
<L>It was as siluer as the chime of spheares.</L>
<L>The breath of Lutes, or ioues deliciousnesse:</L>
<L>Next to my Queene, he is my ioy on earth:</L>
<L>Nor shall the world containe that happy good</L>
<L>Which with my t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>res I will not wooe for him.</L>
<L>My Lord of Epyre, let it be straigh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> proclaim'd</L>
<L>Thorow all the cicies in our kingdomes verdge,</L>
<L>That who so will avow to cure this prince,</L>
<L>And bring his wo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ke to wisht effectualnesse</L>
<L>Shall haue ten thousand crownes and our best loue;</L>
<L><PB REF="16"/>
But if he faile in his great enterprise,</L>
<L>His daring is the losse of present life,</L>
<L>Since no man hitherto could doe him good,</L>
<L>The next shall help him or else loose his bloud.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Maiesty shall haue your will performd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not all so soone deare brother, what if a womā now</L>
<L>Should turne <HI>Aesculapius</HI> and restore</L>
<L>This dumbe <HI>Hypolitus?</HI> nay do not looke strange,</L>
<L>I dare auow and vndertake the cure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epy.</SPEAKER>
<L>You sister, are you in your wits?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith of the out side of them brother, yet a womās tongue</L>
<L>Whose burthen still is superfluity,</L>
<L>May lend a man an ages complement.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam I would not haue you with the barke</L>
<L>Play your selfe into day net, this great cure,</L>
<L>I feare is farre beyond your Physicks helpe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, you know not how <HI>Apollo</HI> loues me,</L>
<L>I haue beene thought as faire as <HI>Oenon</HI> was,</L>
<L>And dare be bold to claime this miracle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cy.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Mariana</HI> attend, glory &amp; ruine compasse thee a∣bout</L>
<L>This hand shall raise thee to a golden throne,</L>
<L>And grace thee with all stiles of dignity;</L>
<L>This cast thee downe.</L>
<L>Lower then liues misfortune and orewhelme</L>
<L>Thy beauties with thy graue, performe be great,</L>
<L>Faile and be worse then worst calamitie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay gentle friend, my loue doth bid thee stay,</L>
<L>Attempt not, and be safe from misery.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sister you shall not graspe with mischiefe thus,</L>
<L>My bloud doth challenge interest in your ill,</L>
<L>And I coniure you from this desperatnes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Brother content your selfe, words but augment our strife,</L>
<L>I will performe or else my pawn's my life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Proceed faire virgin.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vouchsafe me priuacy: now <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HI> be my speed,</L>
<L>Speake gentle <HI>philocl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>s,</HI> thine oaths bond I vntie</L>
<L><PB REF="17"/>
And giue thy vowes a free infranchisment,</L>
<L>Thy well kept league hath show'd thy strength of truth,</L>
<L>And doth confirme me in my vertuousnesse:</L>
<L>Thy martyrdome and sufferance is too long,</L>
<L>And I restore it to new liberty.</L>
<L>Then speake my <HI>Philocles,</HI> speak gentle Prince</L>
<L>To her whose loue respects and honors thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cy.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now, what vertue from thy charmes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>No hope is left, deare <HI>Philocles</HI> regard my miseries.</L>
<L>Vntie that wilfull let which holds in speech,</L>
<L>And make me happy through thy noble pity.</L>
<L>I see the face of mine ill shapt contempt,</L>
<L>Where like with like hath quit most iniury:</L>
<L>Then speake my Lord, vtter one Angell breath</L>
<L>To giue me ioy, and saue me from strange death.</L>
<L>What not a word, hath this small silence brought</L>
<L>An vtter detestation to thy speech?</L>
<L>Wilt thou nor heare, nor speak, nor pity me,</L>
<L>The gentle Gods moue thee to more remorse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cy.</SPEAKER>
<L>What, wilt not be?</L>
<L>Fond maid thou hast drawne affliction on thy head,</L>
<L>And thrald thy selfe to worst calamity:</L>
<L>Till morrow sunne thy incantations vse,</L>
<L>But then effectlesse, all hopes desperate,</L>
<L>Wert thou my bosome loue thou diest the death,</L>
<L>Best ease for madnesse is the losse of breath.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt all but Phi. and Ma.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>O <HI>Philocles</HI> I am no courts disgrace,</L>
<L>No cities Prostitution, countries shame,</L>
<L>Nor one shall bring Troys fire vnto thy house,</L>
<L>Turne not away hard harted <HI>Mir<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>idon,</HI></L>
<L>See, on my knees Ile follow thee in court,</L>
<L>And make the world condemne thy cruelty:</L>
<L>Yet if my teares may mollifie thy heart,</L>
<L>Receiue them as the floods of strangest rides,</L>
<L>Turne not thy face from her that doates on thee,</L>
<L><PB REF="17"/>
Loue now hath made me subiect to thy will,</L>
<L>And pale disdaine hath tane reuenge on <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e.</L>
<L>Behold my nerues Ile weare vpon this earth,</L>
<L>And fill this roofe with lamentations.</L>
<L>What dost thou smile, hath fury so much sway</L>
<L>As euen to banish poore ciuilitie?</L>
<L>Then be thy selfe, and breake thine itching spleene:</L>
<L>For I disdaine thy ransomes victorie,</L>
<L>Life thou art weary brought, welcome my death,</L>
<L>Sweet because wisht for, good because my choice:</L>
<L>Yet when I am dead, this of me shall be said,</L>
<L>A cruell Prince murdered a louing maid.</L>
<L>And after ages to th'unborne shall tell,</L>
<L>Thy hate, my loue, thy enuie and my hell.</L>
<L>Nay do not speak I charge thee, go let nothing moue thee,</L>
<L>Death is my glory, since thou wilt not loue me.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="3" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Act. <HI>3.</HI></HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scena. <HI>1.</HI> Musiq<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter the Duke of Epyr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> and Alphonso.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epy.</SPEAKER>
<L>GRiefe which controles the motions of our thoughts,</L>
<L>Raines in my bloud and makes me passions slaue,</L>
<L>My sisters miserie torments my soule,</L>
<L>And breaks my gall when I but thinke of her:</L>
<L>She was bewicht with spelles to her misfortune,</L>
<L>Or else borne haplesse vnder a lowring starre,</L>
<L>And tis her fate to be thus miserable:</L>
<L>O <HI>Philocles</HI> hadst thou no other scale</L>
<L>To mount thy heauen but by our miseries,</L>
<L>Must all the noble fame of our great house</L>
<L>Waste downe her royall pillars to make steps</L>
<L>For thee to climbe to glory? well I see</L>
<L>Thou plots our shames in thy great dignity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Patience great Lord, me thinkes these ill raisd stormes</L>
<L>Haue not more violence then may be borne,</L>
<L>Come we will both go sue vnto the King.</L>
<L><PB REF="18"/>
We there will kneele and pray eternally,</L>
<L>And neuer rise till he remit his dome:</L>
<L>It shall be so, I will vnto the King,</L>
<L>To beg great fauour for a small offence:</L>
<L>But if she dy for this, then King take heede,</L>
<L>Thee and thy fortunes by this hand shall bleed.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Chyp, Shauenig and others with a Scaffold.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chy.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come my harts, lets make all things ready for the execution, heer's a maiden head must be cut off without a featherbed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Its a signe she deales with sharp tooles &amp; a cruell heads man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chy.</SPEAKER>
<P>If I had beene her iudge, she should haue beene tost to death in a blanket.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sha.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, I would haue had her smothered in a featherbed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chy.</SPEAKER>
<L>They say she would not pleade at her triall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sha.</SPEAKER>
<L>No thats true, for she had a great desire to be prest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chy.</SPEAKER>
<P>And I haue knowne some of her sex, haue got that fauor to be prest for speaking.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then she was vnwise to hold her tongue being a woman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chy.</SPEAKER>
<L>What is her crime that she must loose her head?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Because she liued honest, contrary to the statute.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chy.</SPEAKER>
<P>There is a great number of my neighbors wll neuer suffer for that fault.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sha.</SPEAKER>
<P>No nor thou neither if the truth were knowne, for my part I shunne that danger.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chy.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thinke we are all out of danger of the lawe for that crime.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sha.</SPEAKER>
<P>I know I am free, for I am a knaue if I haue not forgot what wench had my maiden head.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Florio.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Make roome there, his Maiesty is comming to the execution.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, now all things a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e ready: lets away.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Epyre and Alphonso.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mercy is banisht courts, the King like flint,</L>
<L>Hardens his royall temper gainst our plaints,</L>
<L>And makes our woes most vnauoidable.</L>
<L>What inauspicious starue raignd at her birth,</L>
<L><PB REF="18"/>
That heauen thus frownes vpon her misery;</L>
<L>And my good Lord, now innocence must die.</L>
<L>As white as vntroade snow, or culuer downe,</L>
<L>Kings words are lawes, and cannot be withstood;</L>
<L>Yet t'is false greatnesse, which delights in blood.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Patience my Lord, I do not thinke this ill</L>
<L>Is yet so big as vnrecouerable.</L>
<L>The king doth hold you in most choice respect,</L>
<L>And whom kings loue, they study to oblige.</L>
<L>Then call your reason home, make not this ciuill ware,</L>
<L>To suffer makes woes lesser then they are.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epy.</SPEAKER>
<L>How wel the sound can salue the sicke-mans griefe!</L>
<L>But O how ill he can disgest his pils!</L>
<L>O my good Lord, you shall not lose a sister,</L>
<L>That is the ioy and comfort of your breath,</L>
<L>T'is not your bloud shall issue from her wound<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></L>
<L>But mine that runs in riuers from her teares:</L>
<L>And rounds my face in her calamitie.</L>
<L>Well, let her pe rish, since her soule is cleare,</L>
<L>And for her death, ile make a massacrie.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Cypres, Queene, Philocles, Mariana bound, a guard of halberts and an Executioner.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your suits are bootlesse: for my vowes haue glewd</L>
<L>And closd mine eares that they retaine no sound</L>
<L>Of your intreaties, and euen now the time</L>
<L>Doth run vpon his latest minutes, and</L>
<L>Saue but by speech, theres no rec<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>uery.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Haue mercy good my Lord, O let my teares intrude</L>
<L>Betwixt your vowes and her calamitie.</L>
<L>In her you take from me my best of life,</L>
<L>My ioy, my comfort and my play-fellow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Content you madame, for my vow is past,</L>
<L>And is like fate still vnreuocable:</L>
<L>Ascend poore modell of calamity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="19"/>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>As lightly burdened with the waight of crimes,</L>
<L>As spotesse infants, or poore harmlesse lambes,</L>
<L>Thus I ascend my heauen, this first step lower,</L>
<L>Mounts to this next, this, thus and thus hath brought</L>
<L>My bodies frame vnto its highest throne;</L>
<L>Heere doth her office end, and hence my soule</L>
<L>With golden wings of thought shall mount the skie,</L>
<L>And reap a palace of pure sanctitie.</L>
<L>Farewell my soueragine, madame within your thoughts</L>
<L>Make me a tombe, and loue my memory.</L>
<L>Brother farewell, nay do not mourne my death,</L>
<L>It is not I that die to spot our house,</L>
<L>Or make you liue in after obloquy.</L>
<L>Then weep no more, but take my last adiew,</L>
<L>My vertues not my faults preserue with you.</L>
<L>Lastly, to you that are my last of hope,</L>
<L>Nay do not hide your eies, I loue them still:</L>
<L>To part friends now is greatest charitie.</L>
<L>O be thy dayes as fruitfull in delights,</L>
<L>As <HI>Eden</HI> in choice flowers, thine honours such</L>
<L>As all the world may striue to imitate.</L>
<L>Be master of thy wishes: onely this,</L>
<L>When the sad nurse to still the wrangling babe,</L>
<L>Shall sing the carefull story of my death,</L>
<L>Giue me a sigh, from thy hearts purest breath:</L>
<L>And so farewell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Exec.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madame kneelehere, forgiue me for your death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>With all my heart, thou art but lawes poore hand,</L>
<L>Thus to my death I bowe, and yet arise,</L>
<L>Angels protect my spirits in the skies.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>He offers to strike.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold, or thine owne hand shal be thine owne destruction.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Neuer did musicke soun dwith better voice.</L>
<L>Vnbind the Lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo.</SPEAKER>
<L>The feare of death hath brought her to a swound.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeuour her recouery.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sister, deere sister call thy spirits backe;</L>
<L><PB REF="19"/>
Sister, O sister, hearken to my woes,</L>
<L>Recouer breath and liue with happinesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>She stirs, giue way to ayre that she may breath.</L>
<L>Speake <HI>Mariana,</HI> thy woes are cancelled:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are not charitable vnto my moanes,</L>
<L>Thus to afflict me with a double punishment:</L>
<L>One death for one poore fault might well suffice,</L>
<L>They are most wretched who twice liues and dies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madame to saue your life I kill my soule:</L>
<L>And speckle that which was immaculate.</L>
<L>Blacke periury that open eied disease,</L>
<L>Which is the plague sore of society,</L>
<L>Brands me with mischiefe, and protests I hold</L>
<L>Nothing within me but vnworthinesse:</L>
<L>And all these ils are your creation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Which to wash off; loe heere I yeeld my selfe</L>
<L>An humble sacrifice to loue and thee:</L>
<L>All my best hopes, my fortunes and my loue,</L>
<L>My faith, my seruice, and my loialtie,</L>
<L>Shall as thy slaues attend on thy commands,</L>
<L>And make me famous in my suffrages.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Receiue her <HI>Philocles,</HI> for it pleaseth vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>But not me my thrice royall soueraigne.</L>
<L>I'le rather wed a sooty blackamoore,</L>
<L>A Leaper, monster, Incubus or hagge,</L>
<L>A wretch deformd in nature, loath'd of men</L>
<L>Then her that hath bemonster'd my pure soule,</L>
<L>Her scorne and pride had almost lost her life,</L>
<L>A maid so faulted, seldome proues' good wife.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>What is the reason you not loue her now,</L>
<L>And were so passionate in loue before?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not that I loue her lesse, but rather more,</L>
<L>Run I this backward course; onely my vow,</L>
<L>Sith vnperform'd craues satisfaction;</L>
<L>Which thus I reconcile, when this faire maide,</L>
<L>Shall with as strong a loue, as firme a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>eale,</L>
<L><PB REF="20"/>
A Faith as constant, and a shame as strong,</L>
<L>Requit my care, and shew as ample proofe</L>
<L>In mine extreames, as I haue in her death,</L>
<L>Then will I loue, enioy and honour her.</L>
<L>Till when, I will not think a louing thought;</L>
<L>Or giue the easie temper of my minde</L>
<L>To loue-sicke passion, or delitiousnesse.</L>
<L>Onely with those which do adore the sunne,</L>
<L>I'le giue her all respect and reuerence,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am well pleas'd, and with a doubtfull foe,</L>
<L>You haue good reason thus to capitulate,</L>
<L>Then hang your colours forth, ex<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ed your thought</L>
<L>Muster your strongest powers, of stricktest wit,</L>
<L>And when your reasons best artilleries bent</L>
<L>Loue not my loue, if it be not excellent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyp.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue not seene a warre breed better wit,</L>
<L>Or passion draw on more delightfulnesse:</L>
<L>Proceed in your contention, for we boast,</L>
<L>That loue is best, which is approued most.</L>
<L>But now to reuels, since our tragicke sceane</L>
<L>Is turnd to comicke mirthfull constancie;</L>
<L>In stead ofmourning we will daunce and banquet</L>
<L>And fill our emptie veines with all delights:</L>
<L>For oft we find that stormes and sorrowes proue</L>
<L>The best forerunners of a happy loue.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt all but Epyre.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epy.</SPEAKER>
<L>He will, but he will not, loues but cannot like,</L>
<L>Will and affection in this Prince are like</L>
<L>Two buckets which do neuer both ascend:</L>
<L>Or those star twins which shine not in one spheare.</L>
<L>O <HI>Phil<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>eles,</HI> I see thy soule growes fat,</L>
<L>And feeds vpon the glories of my same;</L>
<L>But I'le forestall thine Epileptique fits;</L>
<L>And by my plots breed thy destruction.</L>
<L>Reuenge now rules as soueragine of my bloud,</L>
<L>And others ruines shall aduance my good.</L>
<L><PB REF="20"/>
VVhich once attaind to, I will proue ambitious,</L>
<L>Great men like Gods, are nere thought-vitious.</L>
<L>Now <HI>Philocles</HI> stand fast, King guard thy crowne,</L>
<L>For by this braine, you both shall tumble downe.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Veloups and Drap. President sitting at his deske.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ve.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is his chamber, lets enter, heeres his clarke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pre.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fondling, said he, since I haue hem'd thee heere,</L>
<L>VVithin the circuit of this Iuory pale.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dra.</SPEAKER>
<L>I pray you sir help vs to the speech of your master.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pre.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile be a parke, and thou shalt be my Deere:</L>
<L>He is very busie in his study.</L>
<L>Feed where thou wilt, in mountaine or on dale.</L>
<L>Stay a while he will come out anon.</L>
<L>Graze on my lips, and when those mounts are drie,</L>
<L>Stray lower where the pleasant fountaines lie.</L>
<L>Go thy way thou best booke in the world.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ve.</SPEAKER>
<L>I pray you sir, what booke doe you read?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pre.</SPEAKER>
<P>A book that neuer an Orators clarke in this kingdome but is be∣holden vnto; it is called maides philosophie, or <HI>Venus</HI> and <HI>Adonis:</HI> Looke you gentlemen, I haue diuers other pretty bookes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Drap.</SPEAKER>
<P>You are very well storde sir, but I hope your master wil not stay long.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pre.</SPEAKER>
<L>No he will come presently.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Meshant.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ve.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVho haue we heere? another Client sure, crowes flock to car∣kasses; O tis the Lord <HI>Meshant.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<L>Saue you Gentlemen; sir is your master at any leasure?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pre.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heere sit thee downe where neuer serpent hisses,</L>
<L>And being set ile smother thee with kisses.</L>
<L>His businesses yet are many, you must needes attend a while.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVe must attend, vm, euen snailes keep state</L>
<L>VVhen with slow thrust their hornes peep forth the gate.</L>
<L>VVe must attend, tis customs fault not mine</L>
<L>Tomake men proud, on whom great fauours shine,</L>
<L>Its somewhat gainst my nature to attend.</L>
<L><PB REF="21"/>
But when we must, we must be patient,</L>
<L>A man may haue admittance to the king</L>
<L>As soone as to these long roabes, and as cheap.</L>
<L>Come gentlemen shall we walke?</L>
<L>Thus are the pa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ement stones before the doores</L>
<L>Of these great tongue guilt Orators, worne smoth</L>
<L>With clients dauncing for them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ve.</SPEAKER>
<P>It's strange to see how the world waits vpon them, therein they are the onely men now.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<L>O onely; they of all men in request.</L>
<L>Your physitian is the lawier for your health:</L>
<L>And moderate vnruly humours best.</L>
<L>Others are no body compard with him:</L>
<L>For all men neglect their health in regard of their profit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dra.</SPEAKER>
<L>True, and thats it makes these men grow so fat,</L>
<L>Swell with rich purchases.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yea with golden fees,</L>
<L>And golden titles too, they can worke miracles,</L>
<L>And like creators, euen of emptie nothing</L>
<L>Erect a world of goodly liuings, faire demeanes,</L>
<L>And gallant mannors, heapt one on another.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ve.</SPEAKER>
<L>They gaine indeed excessiuely, &amp; are not like vs citizens</L>
<L>Expos'd to hazard of the seas and trafficke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why heres a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ellow now, this Orator</L>
<L>Euen <HI>Prat,</HI> you would little thinke it, his father was</L>
<L>An honest proiner of our cuntry vines;</L>
<L>Yet hee's shot to his foot-cloath.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Drap.</SPEAKER>
<L>O hee is; hee proind him well and brought him vp to lear∣ning.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith reasonable learning, a s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>attring in the Latine tongue,</L>
<L>A little Rhetoricke, with wrangling sophistrie,</L>
<L>Were his preparatiues vnto his art.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ve.</SPEAKER>
<L>After these preparatiues (if you call them so)</L>
<L>The physicke wrought well for a few yeares practise,</L>
<L>Brought him in wondrous credit, and preferments</L>
<L>Came tumbling in: O such a suddaine rise,</L>
<L><PB REF="21"/>
Hath fortune for her minions, blame him not then,</L>
<L>Though he looke high on't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay for his pride, of weaker soules tearmd state,</L>
<L>It hurts none but himselfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dra.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet to my seeming it is very strange,</L>
<L>That from so base beginning, men can breath</L>
<L>Such soaring fames.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<L>Srange; it's not strange a whit,</L>
<L>Dunghils and marrish bogs, dart store of vapours,</L>
<L>And viscous exhalations, against heauen,</L>
<L>Which borrowing luster there (though basly bred)</L>
<L>Seeme yet like glorious planets fairest starres:</L>
<L>To the weake e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>es of wondring ignorance,</L>
<L>When wise men know they are but <HI>Meteors.</HI></L>
<L>But here comes the Orator.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Prate.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prat.</SPEAKER>
<L>What President I say, come and attend me to the senate house.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pre.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am ready s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>r, if you haue <HI>Copiaverborum,</HI> I haue <HI>Copia reru<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></HI> in a buckram bagge here.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Lordships pleasure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<L>Master Orator, tis not vnknowne my suit</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay your Lordship must be briefe, I not attend</L>
<L>The shallow sleight of words, your suit, your suit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<L>The restoration of my lands and honours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prat.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are confiscat.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<L>My lands confiscat, and my body free?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prat.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, my Lord, the Queen's more mercifull.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, you forget my place.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pra.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir you forget your faith,</L>
<L>T'was knowne vnto the Queene, the state and vs,</L>
<L>Your malecontented spirit, your disease in duty:</L>
<L>Your diligent purturbance of the peace:</L>
<L>Your passages, occurrences and—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir me no sirs.</L>
<L>Do not I know you were the chiefe of those</L>
<L>Which raisd the warres in Sicill? and long since</L>
<L><PB REF="22"/>
Wrought in the kings loues bloody businesse.</L>
<L>Did not you hold faire quarter and commerce</L>
<L>VVith all the spies of <HI>Cypres?</HI> fie I am asham'd,</L>
<L>Blinde impudence should make you be so bold,</L>
<L>To beare your face before authority.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<L>But heare me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pra.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will heare no reply, go home, repent, pray &amp; die.</L>
<L>Come Gentlemen, what's your businesses?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ve.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your confirmation to his highnesse grant, touching our trade with Spaine, in which if it please you to assist vs, wee haue a thousand crownes which shall attend you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pra.</SPEAKER>
<L>O I haue you in my memory, the suit is great:</L>
<L>And I must squeisse forth more then a thousand crownes.</L>
<L>We lattend me to the senate, you shal haue faire dispatches</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt all but <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<L>I not attend the shallow sleight of words,</L>
<L>Go home repent, pray and die.</L>
<L>Excellent precepts for an Orators chamber.</L>
<L>VVhere speech must bath a handful deep in gold,</L>
<L>Till the poore giuers conduit being drie,</L>
<L>The wretch goes home, doth curse, repent and die.</L>
<L>It is thy counsaile Orator, thy tale breath</L>
<L>Good onely but to season infamie.</L>
<L>From this reproch, this incarressing humour</L>
<L>Hath taught my soule a new philosophie.</L>
<L>I will goe home and there repent all good</L>
<L>Done to thy name or thy profession.</L>
<L>I will go home and there new frame my selfe</L>
<L>More thirstily pernicious to thy state,</L>
<L>Then warre or vnabated mutiny.</L>
<L>As for my praiers Orator, they are for thee;</L>
<L>Thou hast a pretty, louely, witty wife:</L>
<L>O maist thou liue, both to be knowne and know</L>
<L>Thy selfe the greatest cuckold in our land;</L>
<L>And yet not dare to amend or greiue at it.</L>
<L>Maist thou imbrace thy shame with thankful armes,</L>
<L><PB REF="22"/>
Hugge thy disgrace, make thy black poison wine,</L>
<L>And cap and crouch to thy dishonor,</L>
<L>May thy remembrance liue, vpon my knees I pray,</L>
<L>All night in belmens mouthes, with <HI>Pasqu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></HI> in the day.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Alphonso vnbrac't.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Day be my speede, night shall not cloake my sin,</L>
<L>If I haue naught to doe, its by the Sunne,</L>
<L>The light giues leaue to all mine Idlenes.</L>
<L>Quick businesse and ope eies cease on mine orator,</L>
<L>Whilst I create him horny presidents.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Coloquintida.</STAGE>
<P>But heeres my bed broker. Now my great armefull of good intelli∣gence, where is my Mistresse?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Co.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fast lockt in her bed with a close ward to deuoure thee my braue <HI>Paraquito;</HI> but husht no words, there is a calme before the tempest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tut, tell me of no stormes, but direct me to her bed chamber, my noble firelock of a flesh pistoll.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Co.</SPEAKER>
<P>Follow thy colours my braue worthy, mount vp thy standard, so enter and prosper.</P>
<STAGE>She puts Alph. into the Orators house.</STAGE>
<P>Thou hast a rich roome, safe locks, sweete sheetes, a choice armefull, with ô the rare, rare thought of imagination.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whats this, whats this, doth this Lord <HI>Alphonso</HI> turne the</L>
<L>Orator to an <HI>Antilop?</HI> tis more then excellent,</L>
<L>And from the iuice of this despight I suck</L>
<L>Delight more great then all my miseries,</L>
<L>Obserue, deare eies obserue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Co.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay go thy way for a Camell or a Camelion, thou maist com∣pare with all Europe, Africke and Asia, and one that will change tricks, though thou wert worthy to be schoolmaster either to <HI>Proteus</HI> or <HI>Aritine:</HI> what an excellent gift did God giue vnto man when he gaue him woman, but how much more when that woman was made faire? but ô the most of all when she had wit to vse euery member of her cre∣ation. Well Ile stand to it, theirs nothing but beautie, vse and old age that puts weomen of my ranck out of request, and yet like old buck∣lers though fewe of your gallant cauileres will weare vs, yet many of your stale Ruffins will imploy vs, and thats our comfort still.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<L>Was euer heard a baude more damnable?</L>
<L><PB REF="23"/>
A very mountebanke of wench flesh, an Emperick,</L>
<L>A dog-leech for the puttefied sores,</L>
<L>Of these Iust-cankerd great ones, O I could</L>
<L>Euen mad my selfe with railing at their vices.</L>
<STAGE>Prate knocks at the dore.</STAGE>
<L>But hearke one knocks, O for the orator,</L>
<L>Heauens I beseech thee, O for the orator.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Co.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now, who knocks so rudely at the dore?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pra.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis I I say, open the dore, I am in hast.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis he, iust heauens tis he, fore God the orator.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Co.</SPEAKER>
<L>Soule of my bawdie office, how are wee betraid,</L>
<L>Anon, anon sir, what Mistres <HI>Prate</HI> I say?</L>
<L>Arise for shame, your husbands at the dore,</L>
<L>I come, I come, Lord God how dull you are</L>
<L>When danger's at your heeles, rise quickly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pra.</SPEAKER>
<L>Open the dore, or I wil breake it ope.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Co.</SPEAKER>
<L>I come, I come, I thinke hee's mad with hast,</L>
<L>What Iohn, what Thomas, Robert, wher's these knaues,</L>
<L>What Iulian, Mary, Sislie, neere a maid within.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lo.</SPEAKER>
<L>For Gods loue stay, ile find the key straight way.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Lollia and Alphonso<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> in his shirt.</STAGE>
<L>O mistres <HI>Coloquintida,</HI> what shall become of vs?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Co.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay I am at my wits end, and am made</L>
<L>Duller then any spurgald, tired Iade.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sfoote ifhe enter, I will breake his neck.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not for a world deare loue, step into my closet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did euer slaue come thus vnluckily?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay now's no time for passion, good Lord in.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Alph. and enter Prate.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Co.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fy I haue almost broke my hart with running.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lo.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now deare husbād, what hath moued this hast?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pra.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thinke I was not blest this morning when I rose: for through my forgetfulnes I haue left behind me in my study the breuiates of all my causes, and now the Se<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>at is faine to daunce attendance on my lea∣sure, fy, fy, fy.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Prate.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay if he smell nothing but papers, I care not for his dry foote
<PB REF="23"/>
hunting, nor shall I neede to puffe pepper in his nostrils, but see hee comes againe.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Prate, and stumbling at his wiues bed, sees Alphonsos rich apparell lying thereon.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pra.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thinke the Diuell haue laid his ho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>nes in my way.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, and if you had wit you might coniure him out of your wiues closet.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prate.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Sancte benedicite,</HI> what haue we heere, hath the golden snake cast his skinne vpon my bed, go toe wife, I smell I smell, mee thinkes your plaine rug should not agree with this rich counterpoint.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Husband, either I haue fitted you now, or else I shall neuer fit you whilst I breath.</P>
<L>You oft haue told me, that like those of your ranke,</L>
<L>Who both adorne their credits and them selues,</L>
<L>Yea euen their causes with their costly cloaths,</L>
<L>Your selfe in like sort would striue to imitate,</L>
<L>And now my neighbour heere hath brought this suite,</L>
<L>Which if you please to buy, tis better cheape</L>
<L>Then ere t'was made by full fiue thousand crownes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prate.</SPEAKER>
<L>Saist thou me so wench, a kisse for that ifaith,</L>
<P>Fore God it is a delicate fine suite, rich stuffe, rare worke, and of the newest fashion; nay if the Senats businesse were neuer so hasty, I will stay to try it on, come, help good wenches helpe, so there, there there.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>The Orator puts on Alphonsos apparell.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sfoote will the oxe put on the Lions hyde,</L>
<L>He will, he will, tis more then excellent,</L>
<L>So guild the tombe which holds but rottennes,</L>
<L>Laughter I feare will burst me, looke how hee struts,</L>
<L>O God that euer any man should looke</L>
<L>Vpon this maumet and not laugh at him,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prate.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fit fit: excellent fit as though,</L>
<L>The body it was made for wore my mould,</L>
<L>Wife I will haue it, weele dispute no price.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Velo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>s.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ve.</SPEAKER>
<P>Master Orator, the Senat are set, and can dispatch no causes through your absence, therfore they earnestly intreat your presence.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="24"/>
<SPEAKER>Pra.</SPEAKER>
<L>I come, I come, good friend go say I come,</L>
<L>And wife see that you pay for this suite, what so ere it cost.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ex. Pra.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not aboue making you cuckold, thats the most.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lo.</SPEAKER>
<L>What is he gone?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Co.</SPEAKER>
<L>He is.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Alphonso in his shirt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why then come forth poore naked Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<P>What is he gone, may the Diuell and his hornes both follow him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lo.</SPEAKER>
<L>He is gone: but yet he hath discouered your treason.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<L>How?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Co.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, and in reuenge thereofhath vow'd, that in this naked sort as you are, you shall doe penance through the Citie for your <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>nne of vnchastitie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<P>I pray thee leaue thy womans phrase, and speake like a man, plainly, plainly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then plainly thus, he is gone and hath taken away your ap∣parell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vpon what accident?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lo.</SPEAKER>
<P>This, when your negligence had left your cloathes vpon my bed, he espied them, taskt me for the owner, I in excuse told him it was a suite brought by my gossip to be sold, hee straight like a childe proud of a new coate, presently puts it on, presently is sent for to the Senat, and at this present hath left you that the world may behold your naked doings.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<P>I would it were washt in the bloud of a Centaure, that when he puts it off, his skinne might follow it, but how shall I get to my cham∣ber?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Truly I know not, except you wil weare a smocks vpper-coate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<L>What a petticote, you mad me with your mirth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then seriously thus, as he hath tane your cloathes, you must take his, and let the world know you haue had more then fidlers fare, for you haue meat, money and cloth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sfoote how shall I looke in this Diuels suite, sure I shall grow sick to see my shape.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well extremity must then be your physick, but come, you shall attire your selfe in my chamber.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Alp. Co. and Colo.</STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="24"/>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are these the winding turnes of female shames,</L>
<L>Loose womans gamboles, and the tricks of sinne?</L>
<L>And are we borne to beare these suffrages?</L>
<L>O hee thats tide vnto a brothell bed,</L>
<L>Feeles his worst hell on earth, and may presume</L>
<L>There is no sicknes like his pestilence:</L>
<L>Well, what the issue of this iest will proue,</L>
<L>My wit but yet conceiues and after time</L>
<L>Shall perfit it and giue it liberty,</L>
<L>In such sort, that if it true fire strike,</L>
<L>A world of Apes shall study for the like.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ex.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter the Duke of Epire alone.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epy.</SPEAKER>
<L>My thoughts are troubled, Ioy forsakes me quite,</L>
<L>And all my meditations are reuenge:</L>
<L>Ambition and fell murder ioyne in me,</L>
<L>And aid each other to vntwine a state,</L>
<L>And make whole millions proue vnfortunate.</L>
<L>Now must I practise court art flattery,</L>
<L>And wisely temporise with blackest deedes:</L>
<L>Ile smile and stab now weepe, then laugh, then frowne,</L>
<L>And with sly tricks of state kill all suspition.</L>
<L>Diuels must seeme like Angels, saith ambition,</L>
<L>The blackest thoughts Ile study to excell,</L>
<L>Crownes and reuenge haue made men diue to hell.</L>
<L>My plot is cu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>rant and it cannot misse,</L>
<L>Whilst wisedome windes me on the clew of blisse.</L>
<L>The King shall kill the Queene, that acted right,</L>
<L>I soone will turne his brightest day to night.</L>
<L>Hees simple, honest, and loues downy rest,</L>
<L>Then he must fall, tis policie in state</L>
<L>To hurle them downe a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e blest with happy fate.</L>
<L>Thus each shall scourge himselfe with his owne rod,</L>
<L>Who is all policie, auowes no God.</L>
<L>Who is within there hoe?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Flori<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did your grace call?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epy.</SPEAKER>
<L>I did, where is the King?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="25"/>
<SPEAKER>Flo.</SPEAKER>
<L>He is in his priuie chamber playing at chesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Go straight and tell him I must speake with him,</L>
<L>And say my businesse doth import great haste.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I goe my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be a blest Mercury, now mount thee vp my spirit,</L>
<L>And shew thy selfe a Polititian,</L>
<L>Let slaunder rule thy tongue, enuy thy hart,</L>
<L>And let destruction be thy period</L>
<L>Of what thou speakst; for this my maxim is,</L>
<L>But rule no heauen, and but reuenge no blisse.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Cypres, Florio and attendants.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here comes the King, my Lord we must be priuat,</L>
<L>Remoue your hearings from our conference,</L>
<L>Now speake my Lord, speake freely as to heauen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epy.</SPEAKER>
<L>First with my knee I kisse this prostrate earth,</L>
<L>And humbly beg, that which my tongue shall speake,</L>
<L>So it proceede from loue and vassallage,</L>
<L>May beare a pardon or forgetfulnes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cy.</SPEAKER>
<L>You haue it, arise, discharge an open breast.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epy.</SPEAKER>
<L>O my dread Liege, my speech will make you sad,</L>
<L>(And Kings doe seldome rellish their distastes)</L>
<L>And from that sadnes such a storme will rise</L>
<L>As will euen droune vp all credulity.</L>
<L>O that my loyall hart could couer sinne,</L>
<L>Or that my tongue inured vnto griefe,</L>
<L>Might lose his spleene ere it distemper you,</L>
<L>But loue and mine alleagance bid me speake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then speake, and doe not rack me with delay.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Women, why were you made for mans affliction,</L>
<L>The first that euer made vs taste of griefe,</L>
<L>And last of whom in torments we complaine,</L>
<L>You diuels shapt like Angels, through whose deedes,</L>
<L>Our forked shames are made most visible,</L>
<L>No soule of sense would wrong bright Maiesty,</L>
<L>Nor staine their bloud with such impurity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay good Lord leaue this <HI>Allegorick</HI> speech,</L>
<L><PB REF="25"/>
And giue me knowledge from a plainer phrase.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then plainly thus, your bed is prest with lust.</L>
<L>I know you doe not credit, nay whats more,</L>
<L>I know you hate me for my vertuousnes,</L>
<L>Your Queene behaues her like a curtezan,</L>
<L>I know you hold me for a vild imposter,</L>
<L>O foolish zeale that makes me be so fond</L>
<L>To leaue my faith vnto black censuring,</L>
<L>O she hath sinn'd and done a double wrong</L>
<L>To you, to her and sacred chastity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Duke thou art valiant, and with a valiant mind,</L>
<L>Slander is worse then theft or sacrilidge,</L>
<L>Nay more then murder, or the height of treason,</L>
<L>A step beyond the vtmost plagues in hell.</L>
<L>Then thou which in that nature wrongst a Queene,</L>
<L>Deseru'st a scourge beyond their punishments,</L>
<L>Vertue should kill thee now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay doe, my brest is bare vnto thy steele,</L>
<L>Kill me because I loue thee and speake true,</L>
<L>Is this the merit of a Romane faith,</L>
<L>For this haue I obseru'd, pried in vnto,</L>
<L>And searcht each secret shift of vanity?</L>
<L>Nay pray you kill me, faith Ile patient stand,</L>
<L>Liue still a monster, hold shame in your hand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speake a word more, a King shalbe thy death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Death is a slaue to him that is resolud,</L>
<L>And my soule loathes this seruile flattery:</L>
<L>Nor will I couer such intemperate sinne,</L>
<L>But to the world make them and that transparent,</L>
<L>Vnlesse your selfe will seeke to right your selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou hast awakt me, and thy piercing words</L>
<L>Haue split my sense in sunder: yet what ground ha?</L>
<L>Remaines wheron to ground suspition? a cuckold, cuckold</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your absence is the baud to her desires,</L>
<L>For their maskes, dauncings, gaming, banquetting,</L>
<L>Strange priuate meetings and all to<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ses in loue.</L>
<L><PB REF="26"/>
As want<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> speeches to st<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>re Appetite,</L>
<L>And all inchantments that inflame desire.</L>
<L>When you returne, then all is husht and still,</L>
<L>And she demurely walkes like vertues Ghost:</L>
<L>Before your f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ce shees like a Puritane,</L>
<L>Behind your back a blushes curtezan.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cy.</SPEAKER>
<L>O I haue drunck in poison at mine eares,</L>
<L>which makes my bloud boile with vnquēched flames,</L>
<L>But speake who is it that dishonors me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epy.</SPEAKER>
<L>He that you prize a line before your life,</L>
<L>I know you will not credit faith you will not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay if thou cease to speake, thou hat<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>st my life,</L>
<L>Tak'st thou delight to kill me, then forbeare,</L>
<L>Sfoote I am mortall man kill me, doe doe doe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your best of friends, your dearest <HI>Philocles</HI></L>
<L>Vsurps your bed and makes you a cornu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e,</L>
<L>A creature vncreate in paradise.</L>
<L>And one thats onely of a womans making.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cy.</SPEAKER>
<L>I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>t possible? can I giue faith to this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay be but patient, smooth your brow a little,</L>
<L>And you shall take them as they clip each other.</L>
<L>Euen in their height of sin then dam them both,</L>
<L>And let them stinck before they aske God pardon,</L>
<L>That your reuenge may stretch vnto their soules.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cy.</SPEAKER>
<L>To be a cuckold doth exceede all griefe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epy.</SPEAKER>
<L>To haue a pleasant scoffe at Maiesty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cy.</SPEAKER>
<L>To taste the fruit forbidden from my tree.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epy.</SPEAKER>
<L>But he shall loose his paradise for that.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cy.</SPEAKER>
<L>The slaue will make base songs in my disgrace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epy.</SPEAKER>
<L>And wound your reputation in strange Lands.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cy.</SPEAKER>
<L>This iniury sads all my ioies on earth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hornes are not shund by wisdom, wealth or birth</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Watch their close meetings, &amp; thē giue vs notice,</L>
<L>Meane space my loue shall in thy bosome rest,</L>
<L>My griefe is like my birth great, great and hie:</L>
<L>Giue close intelligence, till then farewell,</L>
<L><PB REF="26"/>
Lust is the broadest path which leades to hell.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Cypres.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ep.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee's gone with blacke suspition in his heart:</L>
<L>And made his soule a slaue to iealousie,</L>
<L>My plots shall driue him to his owne destruction;</L>
<L>And I gaine both reuenge and dignitie.</L>
<L>He shall no sooner put his Queene to death,</L>
<L>But ile proclaime her spotlesse innocence.</L>
<L>All men will hate him for so vile an act,</L>
<L>And mad with rage depose him from his crowne.</L>
<L>Then I will be his death, his state doth giue,</L>
<L>Kings once depos d, long after must not liue;</L>
<L>For like a <HI>Phoenix</HI> rare in iealousie,,</L>
<L>He shall consume himselfe in scortching flames,</L>
<L>Whilest from his ashes I a <HI>Phoenix</HI> spring:</L>
<L>Many renounce their God to be a king,</L>
<L>And ile be one to kill men with a frowne.</L>
<L>None dare dispute the actions of a crowne.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="4" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Act. 4.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scen. 1. Musicke.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Florio and Meshant.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florio.</SPEAKER>
<L>THe Que<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ne is all for reuelles, her light heart,</L>
<L>Vnladen from the heauinesse of state,</L>
<L>Bestowes it selfe vpon delightfulnesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<L>She followes her creation and her sexe.</L>
<L>In my conceit it is as vile a thing,</L>
<L>To see the worthy modell of a woman,</L>
<L>Who had not beene at all; but to giue life,</L>
<L>And stirring spleene to man<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> allacrity,</L>
<L>To sit orewh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>lmd with thought, with darke amuze</L>
<L>And the sad sullennesse of a grieued dislike;</L>
<L>As to behold an old man in his furres,</L>
<L><PB REF="27"/>
Whose well spent youth, hath giuen his age full strength</L>
<L>To be his countries best physi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>an,</L>
<L>To caper to his graue, and with vaine gaudes</L>
<L>Trick vp his coffin, and vpon his tombe,</L>
<L>To leaue no knowledge but his leuitie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis true indeed, and nature in her selfe,</L>
<L>Doth giue vs still distaste in contraries.</L>
<L>And in my thoughts it is as base to see a woman man</L>
<L>As see a man a long roab'd feminine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, we forget our selues my Lord, What is the musicke rea∣dy? I pray you command the guard to take their halberts in their hands, the Vshers should haue seene this roome perfum'd, in faith they are too negligent: here comes the Queene.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter the Queene, Mariana, and waiting women, Philocles and other Lords, the King disguised like one of the guard at the one end of the stage, and the Duke so likewise disguised at the other end of the Stage.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Loud musicke there, and let the God of Harmony</L>
<L>Rauish our senses with delightfull aires,</L>
<L>Tun'd to the musicke of the higher spheare,</L>
<L>And with that mortall signe rarely shew,</L>
<L>The ioyes in Ioues high court, to feast the Gods,</L>
<L>Making that place abound in happinsse.</L>
<L>Come noble <HI>Philocles</HI> I ceaze you first,</L>
<L>(<HI>Mariana</HI> there are choice of other Lords)</L>
<L>In gracing you, it is the king I grace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come honest Lord, tis you must stand to me,</L>
<L>The Queene in mine doth challenge interest,</L>
<L>And I must flie for shelter to my friends.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<L>And ile be glad to be your couerture.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>O no my Lord, not till the weather change.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wel when you please, meane time you do me grace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay my Lord, ther's a L<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>dy worth the handling.</L>
<L>Sound musicke then, fill earth with heauens pleasure,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="27"/>
<SPEAKER>Cyp.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Queene is out of time, though she keep measure.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Heere they daunce the first straine.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be luckie villainie,</L>
<L>Hit now the marke that mine ambition aimes at</L>
<L>Me thinks I see that leane Italian diuell, iealousie, daunce</L>
<L>In his eies: possesse him spirit of rage,</L>
<L>Muffile his vnderstanding with black thoughts,</L>
<L>Let passion gouerne reason, falshood truth,</L>
<L>Obliuion hide his age, hate kill his youth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou dauncest on my heart lasciuious Queene,</L>
<L>Euen as vpon these rushes, which thou treadest:</L>
<L>See how her motions winde about his eies,</L>
<L>And doth present to him her passions,</L>
<L>Now doth her moistning palme glow in his hand</L>
<L>And courts him vnto dalliance: she dies, tis iust,</L>
<L>Shee's slaue to murder that is slaue to lust.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou curse of greatnesse, waking ei'd suspition,</L>
<L>Now help thy poorefriends, murder and ambition.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>The first straine ends.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>This straine contain'd a preticke change.</L>
<L>Proceed vnto the next.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>They daunce the second.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sinne follows sin, and change on change doth wait,</L>
<L>Thy change doth change my loue to cruell hate.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Here in this straine Mariana came to Philocles.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam methinks this change is better then the first.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>I if the musicke would not alter it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Methinks tis worse, come we wil haue another strain</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>They daunce againe.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I pleas'd, let vs proceed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Riuals in crownes and beds of kings must bleed,</L>
<L>Can that faire house containe so foule a guest.</L>
<L><PB REF="28"/>
As lust, or cloake in ordinate and base desires,</L>
<L>Vn<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>er so faire a couerture; O yes,</L>
<L>Women can blind our sense when we se best,</L>
<L>And set <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ire landskips on inconstancie,</L>
<L>Making vs blind with seeing the daunce ends,</L>
<L>Your sins are blackest, breach of loue and friends.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now to the king, blow rage till it flame hate,</L>
<L>A polititian thriues the best in state.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Epyre, and enters to the King againe.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come sweet Prince <HI>Philocles,</HI></L>
<L>Deuise some new delights to shorten time,</L>
<L>This dulnesse hath no relish in my sense,</L>
<L>It hath no pith, and sloth in my conceit</L>
<L>Is but a tipe of pride in best constructions.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<P>Madame ile stand, that a faire woman must bee proud or else a foole.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would faine heare that I'faith.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy reason wench, I pray the come disburse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>A woman faire is like a full blowne rose,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Which holds the faire no longer then it growes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>A woman faire is like the finest gold.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Which kept from vse is good though nere so old.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay good Lord leaue a little,</L>
<L>She that is faire is wise, and ought to know it,</L>
<L>For to that end did nature first bestow it.</L>
<L>Now of this knowledge if we be not proud,</L>
<L>We wrong the author, and we are allowd</L>
<L>To ranke with sensles beasts, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ith carelesse we<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></L>
<L>For want of pride detract our dignitie.</L>
<L>Now knowing it, we know truth in the same,</L>
<L>Not to be pr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ud of truth askes follies name.</L>
<L>This lesson still is read in beauties schoole,</L>
<L>She that is faire and humble is a foole:</L>
<L>For neither knowe she how to hold her good,</L>
<L><PB REF="28"/>
Or to keep safe the treasure of her bloud.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>a notable declamation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay madame by your leaue,</L>
<L>Pride giues a luster to a womans faire,</L>
<L>Things that are highest prizd, are euer deere.</L>
<L>VVhy is the Diamond the Saphyrs king,</L>
<L>But for esteeme and rarenesse? both which spring</L>
<L>From the stones pride, which is so chast and hard,</L>
<L>Nothing can pierce it, it selfe is it selfes guard,</L>
<L>Now what is pride? selfe loue, our owne esteeme,</L>
<L>A strength to make vs of our selues well deeme:</L>
<L>From whence this maxim I collect mongst other,</L>
<L>VVho hates her selfe can neuer loue another.</L>
<L>And to conclude, mans appetite growes dull</L>
<L>To what it may haue, emptie hope is full,</L>
<L>To all our sexe on earth, maid, widow, wife and bride,</L>
<L>They happy liue, when they liue with chast pride.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyp.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Queene will speake as much for lust as shee for pride, if the toy take her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Ladiship sowes dangerous seede abroad.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>But I hope my lord all grounds are not fruitfull.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well wench, shalt be the proud womans champion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>And ile defend them against all men, as at single tongue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<L>I had rather fight with a gyant, then you at that weapon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyp.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord go forth, returne in your owne shape, say I am com∣ming.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epy.</SPEAKER>
<L>I goe my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Fpyre.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile note their countenance when they heare of me.</L>
<L>Kings often see that which they would not see.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dauncing hath made me weary, what sport is next?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>What your highnesse will command.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyp.</SPEAKER>
<L>she will command you sir to play with her.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Epyre.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madame his maiestie is returnd to court.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay then away with reuels and with sports,</L>
<L>Lie husht, and still this vainer idlenesse,</L>
<L><PB REF="29"/>
It now hath lost his spleene, come Lords away.</L>
<L>My sunne is risen, brings a brighter day.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt all but Cypres and Epyre.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Darknesse is thy delight <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>asciuious Queene,</L>
<L>And thou wouldst haue thy sun p ent vp in cloude:</L>
<L>If I be he, O falsnesse did I for this,</L>
<L>In single opposition hand to hand,</L>
<L>Hazard my royall bloud for thee to be</L>
<L>My greatest shame, the scandall of my blood,</L>
<L>Whil'st rumour crownes me king of infamy<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></L>
<L>But I will be reueng'd: watch gentle Lord,</L>
<L>When next I see them, they shall tast of death,</L>
<L>Such power hath basenesse ouer great defame</L>
<L>That monarches cannot couer their own shame.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Cypres.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epy.</SPEAKER>
<L>My plot yet holds a true proportion,</L>
<L>And I do see, an euen way to rule,</L>
<L>A crowne like a bould champion bids me on,</L>
<L>And fame shall chronicle mine enterprise:</L>
<L>The Queene being dead, I must oppose my selfe,</L>
<L>Against her tyrant husband, thats my claime</L>
<L>And with strong courage, stand the shocke of warre:</L>
<L>If of my selfe I can withstand the King,</L>
<L>Then all the Land will <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> vnto mine aide, if not,</L>
<L>The king is Gods <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, my head fi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>s the blocke,</L>
<L>And thats the worst, yet future times will tell:</L>
<L>I sunke not <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>eightly, for a crowne I fell.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Epy<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Meshant, and a guard of watchmen.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come on my masters, you know the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> of the kings cōmand,</L>
<L>And what in this great businesse you must do,</L>
<L>Which is to keep him safe, and not vouchsafe</L>
<L>That any creature speake or visit him,</L>
<L>Till he be brought to the presenc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> of the king,</L>
<L>You must not start for bountie nor for threats.</L>
<L><PB REF="29"/>
No though he say he is a noble man,</L>
<L>As it may be, he may proue mightie borne,</L>
<L>Yet what for that? you must performe your office</L>
<L>Or else expect to tast sharp punishment.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>1</HI> Watch.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tut, feare not my Lord, wee that haue had <HI>Cerberus</HI> office so many yeares vnder a gate, are not to learne now to play either diules or tyrants, let vs but see him, and then take no care for his safety.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>2</HI> Watch.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay hee shall bee put into safe keeping, for my wife shall take charge of him.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Alphonso in the Orators clothes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis well deui'sd, see where he comes,</L>
<L>He may not see my presence, thinke vpon't,</L>
<L>Your charge is trusty, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> of mi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>wwaight.</L>
<L>Farewell.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Meshant.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>1</HI> Watch.</SPEAKER>
<P>Feare not: come my <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>arts, compasse him about, and ceaze on him all at once, like so many Rauens on a dead horse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now an eternall sleep, an apoplex, a swound</L>
<L>Ceaze on their senses, who in this disguise</L>
<L>Shall view or note my vile deformitie.</L>
<L>I was bewitcht with spels to my misfortune:</L>
<L>Or else starre crost with some hagges hellishnesse.</L>
<L>Sure I said my prayers, ris'd on my right side,</L>
<L>Wash't hands and eies, put on my girdle last;</L>
<L>Sure I met no splea-footed baker,</L>
<L>No hare did crosse me, nor no bearded witch,</L>
<L>Nor other ominous signe, O then why</L>
<L>Should I be thus damn'nd in the diuels nets?</L>
<L>Pst possible? this habit which I weare</L>
<L>Should become any man? now of my soule,</L>
<L>I loath to see my selfe, and willingly</L>
<L>I would euen vomit at my counteneance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>1</HI> Watch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stand sir, we arrest you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Arrest me, why I iniure no man but my selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>2</HI> Watch.</SPEAKER>
<P>You are the more vnkind, he that wrongs himselfe, will not sticke to wrong the whole world also.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="30"/>
<SPEAKER><HI>1</HI> Wa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay striue not for we arrest you by vertue of the Kings com∣mission.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well my masters be carefull, you may mistake me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>2</HI> Wa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeed it is no maruaile you are so like other men.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeed at this time, I am hardly like one of Gods making.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>1</HI> Wa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith and I am sure you are no man of a good taylors making, you are but peest worke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well yet I may hap to proue a noble man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>2</HI> Wa.</SPEAKER>
<P>A whoremaster or an vnthrift, away with him, and let <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>man man catachise him vpon paine of my displaesure.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter the Duke of Epyre alone</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Roule on the chariot wheeles of my deere p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ots,</L>
<L>And beare mine ends to their desired <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>kes:</L>
<L>As yet thers not a rub of wit, a gulfe of thought,</L>
<L>No rockie misconstruction, thorny amaze,</L>
<L>Or other let of any doubtfulnesse;</L>
<L>As yet thy way is euen smoth and plaine,</L>
<L>Like the greene Ocean, in a silent calme.</L>
<L>Blessed credulity, thou great God of errour,</L>
<L>That art the strong foundation of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>uge wrongs<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></L>
<L>To thee giue I my vowes <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 words" DISP="〈◊◊〉"/>,</L>
<L>By thy great deity he doth beleeue</L>
<L>Falshoods, that falshoods selfe could not inuent,</L>
<L>And from that misbeleefe doth draw a course</L>
<L>To ouerwhelme euen vertue, truth and sanctitie.</L>
<L>Let him go on blest starres, tis meet he fall,</L>
<L>Whose blindfold iudgement hath no guid at all.</L>
<L>But O these shadowes haue bewitchted long,</L>
<L>To threat and not to do, doth malice wrong;</L>
<L>And see heere comes the Queene.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter the Queen<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>, Mariana and other Ladies.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord the Duke, your presence and my wish,</L>
<L>Iumpe in an euen line together: come we must to cardes,</L>
<L><PB REF="30"/>
I haue some crow<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>es I needs must lose to you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epy.</SPEAKER>
<L>I humbly beseech your highnesse pardon me,</L>
<L>I haue important businesse of the Kings,</L>
<L>Which doth command mine instant diligence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Brother, indeede you shall attend the Queene,</L>
<L>Another time will serue those state dispatches.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sister content you, the affaires of state</L>
<L>Must giue their best attendance on the times,</L>
<L>And great occurrents must not lose their minutes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now ile stand to it, that to be a states man or a la<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ier, is to be of the most thanklesse occupation that euer was deriu'd from humain inuention.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why I pray thee wench?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<P>Because they bestow all the laborious toile of the minde vn∣till they be forty, that they may liue imprison'd in a study chamber till they be fourescore, onely this worlds Mammon, which is great name and riches, like a string betweene a gallie slaues legs, is the on∣ly ease of their fetters.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<P>A notable construction of a noble labor: but shall we not haue your company my Lord?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epy.</SPEAKER>
<P>My seruice Madam, but my presence the King hath imploid, onely if you please, I will send Prince <HI>Philocles</HI> to your Maiestie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>No creature better for his skill in play,</L>
<L>Is equall with our knowledge, good my Lord,</L>
<L>Send him to my priuy chamber presently.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Queene and Mariane. Enter Philocles.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epy.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will, and send affliction after him,</L>
<L>And see where he comes, My Lord your presence hath</L>
<L>Saued me much labour, and a little care,</L>
<L>I was in quest for your faire company:</L>
<L>The Queene my Lord intreats you earnestly</L>
<L>You will attend her in her priuy chamber.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vnto what end?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Only to waste some time at cards with her,</L>
<L><PB REF="31"/>
The lasie howers stick heauy on her thoughts,</L>
<L>Which she would lose with some forgetfulnesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith, &amp; play nere relisht worse within my thoghts,</L>
<L>I know not how, but loaden heauinesse</L>
<L>Drawes me to be in loue with melancholy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ep<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L>The fitter for you with more light sports</L>
<L>To chace that bloud consumer from your brest,</L>
<L>Who with a honnie poison doth deuoure,</L>
<L>And kill the very life of liuelihood.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis true, &amp; therfore shall your counsaile tutor me,</L>
<L>Where is her Maiesty?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gone to her priuie chamber where she doth ex∣pect you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will attend her presently.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe, and I will attend thee to thy graue,</L>
<L>Poore shallow Lord, by much too vertuous.</L>
<L>Hoe, whose within there?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Florio.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your graces pleasure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Go tell his Maiesty that I must speake with him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I go.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter aloft to cardes the Queene and Philocles.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come my Lord take your place, here are cards, and here are my crownes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>And here are mine, at what game will your Maiesty play?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>At mount saint.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>A royall game, and worthy of the name,</L>
<L>And meetest euen for Saincts to exercise:</L>
<L>Sure it was of a womans first inuention.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is not Saint, but Cent, taken from hundreds.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>True, for mongst millions hardly is found one saint</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeede you may allow a double game,</L>
<L>But come list for the dealing, it is my chance to deale.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Anaction most, most proper to your sex.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Cypres.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cy.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now my waking dragon, thou whose eies</L>
<L><PB REF="31"/>
Doe neuer fall or close through Lethean sleepe,</L>
<L>What is there a <HI>Hercules</HI> that dare to touch,</L>
<L>Or enter the Hesperian Rosaries?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speak softly gentle Lord behold, behold</L>
<L>The sillie birds are tangled in your snare,</L>
<L>And haue no way to scape your punishment:</L>
<L>See how her eies doe court him, and his lookes pay to her</L>
<L>loue a double interest: fie fie, they are toe blame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>What are you my Lord?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your highnes seruant, but misfortunes flaue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your game I meane.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nothing in show, yet somewhat in account,</L>
<L>Madam I am blanke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<P>You are a double game, and I am no lesse, theres an hundred, &amp; all cards made but one knaue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Marke that, of my life she meanes your Maiesty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cy.</SPEAKER>
<L>True, I know she holds me as her varlet,</L>
<L>And that I am imperfit in her game,</L>
<L>But my reuenge shall giue me better place,</L>
<L>Beyond the hate of her foule impudence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay good my Lord obserue, they will confirme you better.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whats your game now?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Foure Kings as I imagine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay I haue two, yet one doth me little good.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeed mine are 2 Queenes, &amp; one Ile throw away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doth your Maiesty marke that?</L>
<L>You are the King that she is wearie of,</L>
<L>And my sister the Queene that he will castaway.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can you decard Madam?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hardly but I must doe hurt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>But spare not any to confirme your game.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would you haue more plaine proofe of their foule <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>son?</L>
<L>They doe not plot your highnes death alone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cy.</SPEAKER>
<L>But others which they thinke depend on me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epy.</SPEAKER>
<L>My selfe and those which doe you seruices,</L>
<L>They are bloudy minded, yet for my selfe,</L>
<L><PB REF="32"/>
Were it not for your saftie, I could wish</L>
<L>You would remit and blot these errors out,</L>
<L>In hope that time would bring them to more vertue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cy.</SPEAKER>
<L>O then thou didst not loueme, nor thy faith</L>
<L>Tooke hold vpon my scandals, fie I am mad,</L>
<L>Sham'd and disgrac't, all wit-stung, wisdomlesse.</L>
<L>Within there ho?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Flori<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did your maiesty call?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Go instantly, (nay doe not looke sad or pale,</L>
<L>Neither dispute with me nor with thy thoughts:</L>
<L>But as thou lou'st thy life, effect my will)</L>
<L>Call all my guard, ascend the Queenes priuie chamber,</L>
<L>And in my name arrest her and Prince <HI>Philocles</HI> of treason:</L>
<L>Make no delay but in thy diligence</L>
<L>Shew how thou dost respect me, arrested once,</L>
<L>Conuey them vnto straitest prison: away.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Florio.</STAGE>
<L>For you my Lord, go instantly prepare,</L>
<L>And summon all the Princes of our land</L>
<L>Vnto an instant Parliament, where we</L>
<L>Will haue them both condemn'd imediately,</L>
<L>Without their answeres plaints or pitiousnes.</L>
<L>Since womens teares doe blunt reuenges sword,</L>
<L>I will not see nor heare thē speake one word.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ex. Cy. Epy.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Florio and a guard aloft to the Queene and Philocles</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Madam and Prince <HI>Philocles,</HI> in the Kings name I arrest you both of high treason.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ph<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L>He lies that saith I euer knew the word.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>I pray thee doe not affright me gentle Lord,</L>
<L>Thy words doe cary death euen in their sound.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam I am most sorrie tis my fortune,</L>
<L>But what I doe is by the Kings commission.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="32"/>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whence is that warrant grounded, or whats our treason?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am his instrument but not his counsailor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>Witnesse my teares that I am innocent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam be patient, that we doe not know,</L>
<L>Wee haue no cause to grieue at, as for enuies toile,</L>
<L>Let her euen break her owne gall with desire,</L>
<L>Our innocence is our preuention.</L>
<L>Be cheerefull Madam, tis but some villains sound,</L>
<L>Made onely to amaze, not to confound.</L>
<L>And what must wee doe my Lo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>d?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo.</SPEAKER>
<L>To prison are the words of my commission.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then leade the way; he hath of griefe no sense,</L>
<L>Whose conscience doth not know of his offence.</L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="5" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Act. <HI>5.</HI></HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scene. <HI>1.</HI> Musique.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter at one dore Epyre, at another Mariana.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epyre.</SPEAKER>
<L>HOw now mad sister, your deare loue is condemn'd,</L>
<L>A sweete adulterer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>How, condemd before their tryall?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epy.</SPEAKER>
<L>No they were condemnd by Act of Parliament.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe not hold thee brother for a man,</L>
<L>For it is reasonlesse to mock cala<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ity,</L>
<L>If he die innocent, thrice happy soule;</L>
<L>If guilty, weepe, that man should so transgresse:</L>
<L>Nature of reason thus much doth importune,</L>
<L>Man should partake in griefe with mans misfortune.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epy.</SPEAKER>
<L>For him, if ere mine eies weep, may they drop out</L>
<L>And leaue my body blinder then my sense:</L>
<L>Pittie my foe the ruine of my house,</L>
<L>My valours scandall, and mine honours poison!</L>
<L>No let him fall, for bloud must still quench lust,</L>
<L>Law hath condemd him, then his death is iust.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="33"/>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Spit out that monster enuy, it corrupts you,</L>
<L>And mildly heare me answere for my loue,</L>
<L>What did he gainst you was not honourable,</L>
<L>Which you gainst him would not haue gladly done?</L>
<L>Will you hate him for acting your owne thoughts?</L>
<L>Can it be ill in him yet good in you?</L>
<L>Let reason waigh this difference then youle find</L>
<L>His honor poizes downe his infamy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Canst thou loue him that brought thee to thy death?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>No like a God he made me with his breath.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did he not win thy loue and then reiect thee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>His honor not his loue doth now neglect me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fond maid thy soolish dotage doth mistake him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hell shall haue mercie ere I will sorsake him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Farewell then sister, friend to my greatest foe,</L>
<L>Reuenge strikes home, being ended with one blow.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Epy.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Preuention thou best midwife to misfortune,</L>
<L>Vnfold this vgly monsters treachery,</L>
<L>And let his birth be ominous strooke dead,</L>
<L>Ere it haue being in this open world:</L>
<L>Loues commands nature, brother pardon me,</L>
<L>Thine enuy di<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>s by my loues liberty.</L>
<L>Inuention (hart of wit) possesse my braine,</L>
<L>For treason is to treason her owne bane.</L>
<L>And you bright heauens, now aid me in my plots,</L>
<L>That truth may shine through falshoods leporous spots.</L>
<L>My life Ile hazard to redeeme my loue,</L>
<L>Firme constancy like rocks can neuer moue.</L>
<L>Be bold then maiden hart in his defence</L>
<L>He saued thy life, thy life's his recompence.</L>
<L>My wit and hopes haue furnish<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> me with all</L>
<L>The helpes of art, to bring forth treasons fall.</L>
<L>Now to the meanes: some say that gold hath power,</L>
<L>To enter without force a gatelesse tower;</L>
<L>And Ile try that, which if it take fast hold,</L>
<L><PB REF="33"/>
Ile neuer blame them more that doate on gold.</L>
<L>Hoe, whose within there?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Gailer.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ga.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who calles, what would you haue? I thought you were a womā you were so hasty: O Madam is it you? I cry you mercie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>My griefe speakes loud sir, and my swist desire</L>
<L>Ore rules my tongue, makes it keepe time with thought,</L>
<L>I long to see a prisoner in this ill built house.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ga.</SPEAKER>
<L>What prisoner Madam?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>The worthy Prince, the famous <HI>Philocles.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ga.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madame I dare not, without especiall warrant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue my brothers strong commission, hold there is gold.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ga.</SPEAKER>
<P>This golden calfe is an excellent Idoll; and sewe of my profes∣sion but serues it this dumb god giues tongue to all men, wit to all mē, honour to any man, but honesty to no man; and therefore as for ho∣nesty I meane not to deale with so deare a commodity, but leaue it to my better: Madam those staires direct you to his lodging.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thanke you sir.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Mariana.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ga.</SPEAKER>
<P>This is a worthy Lady to giue thus much for the bare sight of a man in affliction, if he were at liberty it were nothing: but being as it is, it is most bountifull, but it may be it is for the past houres of for∣mer recreations, well let it be what it shall be, I am sure it was not that I should hold this disputation: but see here she comes againe.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Philocles in Marianaes attire, and Mariana in his.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madame my soule cannot consent to leaue</L>
<L>Your life in this great hazard, nor can death</L>
<L>Carie such vgly shape as doth the thought</L>
<L>That you are left in this extremity:</L>
<L>Indeede I will not leaue you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you grow mad? what shall your nobler spirit</L>
<L>Which is the schoole of wisdome grow so fond,</L>
<L>As to reuolt from all our happines?</L>
<L>Our plots you know, and how to manage cares,</L>
<L>Whose true euents haue true proportions.</L>
<L><PB REF="34"/>
Then deare Lord rest resolu'd, the Gailer ouer heares:</L>
<L>Liue you with safetie, most worthy maid farewell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Farewell faire Prince; thanks M Iayler and a kind commend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gai.</SPEAKER>
<L>As much vnto your Ladiship. So now Ile lock my dores.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Mar. Phi. and Gatler.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Cypres, Meshant, Florio and attendants.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is our commission, as wee gaue in charge,</L>
<L>Deliuered ore to the Corigidors?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is, and with such strictnes and aduice,</L>
<L>For speedy execution of the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ame,</L>
<L>That by this time I know they are in the way</L>
<L>Vnto their execution, for the hower</L>
<L>Of death doth runne vpon his latest minutes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis well: for till their shamelesse liu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>s haue end,</L>
<L>There can no comfort creepe into my thoughts,</L>
<L>Or ought saue mifchi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>f keepe me company.</L>
<L>Why was I borne to this malignity</L>
<L>And l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>wnesse of base fortune: yet my place</L>
<L>Aboue the leuell of the vulgars sight,</L>
<L>O it is but to let me know thus much,</L>
<L>That those which ly within the richest graues</L>
<L>Were at the best but fortunes glorious <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>aues.</L>
<L>But see, here comes my shame.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Corigidors, Queene and Philocles bound, and a guard of halberts with the executioner.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>My dearest Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Passe and respect me not lasciuious woman,</L>
<L>Thy teares are of the speares of Crocodils,</L>
<L>See how I stop mine eares against thy plaints,</L>
<L>And glue mine vnderstandings from thy charmes,</L>
<L>Nay call on him thou hast offended most,</L>
<L>Mercy from me were worse then cruelty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>My dearest dreade, my best best soueraigne,</L>
<L><PB REF="34"/>
Whom I haue nere offended but with zeale</L>
<L>And constant loue, loyall and honorable,</L>
<L>Vouchsafe me though a Queene a subiects right,</L>
<L>And let me know for what offence I perish.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyp.</SPEAKER>
<L>For thine adulterat and monstrous lust,</L>
<L>Shamefull and grosse and most vnsufferable.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who doth accuse vs<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our selfe, and our owne soule that haue beheld</L>
<L>Your vile and most lasciuious passages.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>O that my tongue would not betray my knowledge</L>
<L>Then would I amaze them all with mine assertions:</L>
<L>Madame, challenge the law.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>My gratious Lord, since no desert in me,</L>
<L>Can merit your beliefe, nor that your eie,</L>
<L>Can rightly iudge my pure complexion:</L>
<L>Yet as your handmaid, let me beg the right,</L>
<L>Due vnto wretches from our countries lawes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyp.</SPEAKER>
<L>The tenure of the law you do demand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>That in the case of slander, where the proofe</L>
<L>Proceedes as much from enuy as from truth,</L>
<L>We are allow'd our champions to defend</L>
<L>Our innocence, with a well ordered sword.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyp.</SPEAKER>
<L>I lookt for this obiection and allow it,</L>
<L>Nor am I vnprouided for your best</L>
<L>And strongest hope in any victory; Lords attend in my Champion.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Here the noble men go forth, and bring in the Duke of Epire like a co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>batant.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you my Lord approue the Kings assertion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madame, although against the nature of my spirit,</L>
<L>And my first duty, bound to your allegeance,</L>
<L>Yet now compeld by duty and by truth,</L>
<L>I must of force become your opposite.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art no true Italian, nor true gentleman,</L>
<L>Thus to confound the glory of thy iudgement.</L>
<L><PB REF="35"/>
Hath not that arme which now is arm'd against me</L>
<L>That valour, spirit, iudgement and that worth,</L>
<L>Which onely makes you worthy, stood t'approue</L>
<L>More then my selfe will challenge to my vertues?</L>
<L>And are you now basely turnd retrograde?</L>
<L>Well, I perceiue ther's nought in you but spleene,</L>
<L>And times obseruance, still to hold the best:</L>
<L>Still I demand the Law.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyp.</SPEAKER>
<L>And you shall haue it in the amplest manner. Sound cornets.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Heere the cornets sound thrice, and at the third sound, enters Philocles disguised like a combatant.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo.</SPEAKER>
<L>There is a cōbatant on the defēdāts part; your maiesties pleasure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Giue him his oath according to the lawes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are the faire ends of this your warlike posture,</L>
<L>To proue the innocence of the<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e two conde<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>nd?</L>
<L>So help you Ioue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then giue the warlicke fignall to the fight.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Heere the combate being fought, Philocles ouercomes the Duke.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art my slaue, either confesse or die.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Didst thou speake true, I would not sound a word</L>
<L>To saue the world from cinders; yet that thou maiest</L>
<L>With more resolued fury murder me,</L>
<L>This I confesse, twas I that onely stird,</L>
<L>Out of strong falshoods hate and iealousie</L>
<L>The kings eternall wrath, and made him thinke</L>
<L>Vntruths, that euen vntruth would not suggest:</L>
<L>And all my malice sprung from that Prince <HI>Philocles.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>No twas from me that still am <HI>Philocles.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyp.</SPEAKER>
<L>My <HI>Philocles,</HI> my Queene, O double pardon me,</L>
<L>My iealousie, his enuy, and your vertues:</L>
<L><PB REF="35"/>
Are sprung from such impatient contraries,</L>
<L>I cannot reconcile them; yet O pardon me:</L>
<L>My faith in life shall make you recompence:</L>
<L>For thee rare <HI>Mariana;</HI> thou hast wrought</L>
<L>A worke of noble constant magnitude.</L>
<L>As for this monster, this my tempting diuell,</L>
<L>Whose forfait life is witnesse to his shame:</L>
<L>I giue his life and fortunes to the Queene,</L>
<L>She whom his malice would haue brought to death,</L>
<L>Shall now be iudge and Iurer of his breath.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>In which commission, (madame) let it be inrold</L>
<L>He is my brother and my best of blood.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>And onely that is charter for his life:</L>
<L>Liue enuiou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> Lord, more enuious then th'art great,</L>
<L>Liue to lament thy worst of wretchednesse,</L>
<L>Liue to repent, since this I certaine know:</L>
<L>Thine owne gald conscieuce will be thy worst woe.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter a guard of watchmen with Alphonso.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>1</HI> Watch.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come bring him away, thrust him forward, though fauour and a great purse were against him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyp.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now, what tamult haue we there?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>2</HI> Watch.</SPEAKER>
<P>And it please your maiestie we haue brought you heere a slip a peece of false coine: one that is neither stampt with true coine for his excuse, nor with good clothes for his redemption.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyp.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Alphouso,</HI> in the name of madnes how comes this <HI>Metamorphosu?</HI> Nay stand forth, discourse, if thou dost lie, thou art mine enemy.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay more, if thou sticke in any bogge, and by a tricke seeke to wind out, I <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> discouer you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alph.</SPEAKER>
<P>This coniuration (beleeue it my Lord) shall make me leap out of all <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>etters, and briefly thus I haue long time loued the faire wife of the Orator; &amp; hauing no opportunity but his absence at the senate, I tooke that season: hee out of negligence, omitting his papers returnd vnseasonably, sound mee insufficiently, and forst mee to take san∣ctuary strangely, which howeuer I purchast, yet hee found mine
<PB REF="36"/>
apparrell, and mistaken in the tenure, reacht it presently, put it on im∣mediatly: and now in the senat house is pleading in it seriously.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyp.</SPEAKER>
<P>I cannot blame him, you hauing got so much within his in∣ward garment.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<P>Of all which my Lord, I being (in a strict conceit) a baudy wit∣nesse: and hauing both from the Orators scornes and delaies receiued many indignities; though by this discouery to cry quittance with my proud enemy.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyp.</SPEAKER>
<L>And you haue amply done, yet this iest,</L>
<L>So perfit doth deserue more memory.</L>
<L><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>,</HI> go bid the Orator attend vs presently.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Flo.</STAGE>
<L>And now to you <HI>Drap</HI> and <HI>Velous,</HI> I did</L>
<L>Referre you long since to the Orator.</L>
<L>Yet I note your attention: come there is</L>
<L>Some too close fisted hardnes in your hearts,</L>
<L>You gripe too hard, your bribes will not disburse,</L>
<L>Come tell me truely, as you looke for heauen,</L>
<L>What must you pay for your dispatches?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dra. Ve.</SPEAKER>
<L>A thousand crownes we offred willingly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyp.</SPEAKER>
<L>And will your suit auaile with such disbursment?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dra. Ve.</SPEAKER>
<L>It will, and we most richly satisfied.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you bestow the m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ney on our selfe,</L>
<L>We will see the businesse perfited.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dra. Ve.</SPEAKER>
<P>With all our hearts, and be full ioy'd thereat, heere are the crownes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyp.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall haue your dispatches.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Prat and Florio.</STAGE>
<L>See heere comes the Orator, <HI>Prat</HI> come hither.</L>
<L>These Gentlemen whom long since I referd</L>
<L>To Your dispatches, are yet vnsatisfied.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas my Lord the state,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyp.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know implo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>es you, yet theres many minute<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></L>
<L>May giue your best cares leasure; come there is</L>
<L>Some odde disburse, some bribe, some gratulance,</L>
<L>Which makes you lock vp leasure, come tell true,</L>
<L>What bribe must they giue, what is your v<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>most price</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="36"/>
<SPEAKER>Pra.</SPEAKER>
<L>But fiue hundred c<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>wnes of my best conscience.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tut it is nothing, hold heere is the coine,</L>
<L>And let them haue their pattens presently:</L>
<L>Or looke to loose both place and soueraignty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Legions of diuels haunt their dilligence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fie, I would not haue a man of your high place,</L>
<L>Or for respect of wealth or base obseruance</L>
<L>In smallest things thus to neglect your credit.</L>
<L>Why looke you my Lords, this Orator is not like others of his ra<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ke,</L>
<L>Who from their ganish and fantasticke humours,</L>
<L>Go thorow the streets, spotted in peacocks plumes.</L>
<L>Wearing all colours, laces, broderies,</L>
<L>Sattans and silkes, so antike garnished,</L>
<L>That when their gownes are off, you cannot finde</L>
<L>In Italy a master shapt more nice.</L>
<L>But this fellow <HI>Prate,</HI> heer's of another <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ort,</L>
<L>Cloth'd like himselfe, demure and soberly:</L>
<L>Nay you shall see him for a president.</L>
<STAGE>Vngownes the Orator.</STAGE>
<L>Passion of mine eie-sight, who haue we heere?</L>
<L>This is <HI>Alphonso,</HI> ther's th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> Orator.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pra.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heart of impatience, I am <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Cuckold,</L>
<L>A scorne, a by word and a laughing stocke.</L>
<L>What is my wife turnd <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>hore <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> must he<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> deptn</L>
<L>Be sounded by the plumes of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></L>
<L>Well, the reuenge that I will take for this my <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>,</L>
<L>Shall make all whores hereafter <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> my name.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not for thy life, not for my loue I <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> thee:</L>
<L>Thy wife is honest, chast and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>:</L>
<L>Onely this wanton Lord, with lust and come</L>
<L>Hath much attempted, but <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> in nought,</L>
<L>For proofe see heere the crownes <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> would haue giuen</L>
<L>T'haue purchas'd her beds hono<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ut she would not,</L>
<L>Which I bestow on you for recompence.</L>
<L>Therefore as thou dost hope my grace to finde,</L>
<L>So to thy wife, be louing, gentle kinde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="37"/>
<SPEAKER>Prat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your maiestie may mould me to your pleasure</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyp.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thanke you and will quittance it.</L>
<L>Now <HI>Meshant,</HI> we restore to you your lands,</L>
<L>Your honours and neere places, next our selfe,</L>
<L>To all that feele distaste in any sore,</L>
<L>We giue to cure them, all our grace and fauour,</L>
<L>Thus stormes bring gentle sun-shine, and our hands,</L>
<L>May after shipwracke bring vs to safe lands.</L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
<TRAILER TYPE="illustration"><FIGURE>
</FIGURE></TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

