<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2002-08-07</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Judith Siefring</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Checked for N=""s. Checked for GROUP tags. Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, etc.). Checked for signatures. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, and UNCLEARs. Corrected 10 $s and $$word$$s etc. of 136. Converted 126 $$s to GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex". Checked for EPIGRAPHs and ARGUMENTs. Checked for &amp;cs with incorrect spacing. Checked for LBs. Checked for startqs, endqs, oes, q;s, and Qs. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Checked for CLOSERs, TRAILERs, and BYLINEs. Checked for missing page GAPs. Sample: 10 minutes. Proofing: 30 minutes. Tag review and corrections: 60 minutes. DONE.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="A06982">
<STC T="S">17401</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99847457</BIBNO>
<VID>12493</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1"/>
<P><HI>The <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HI> TRAGEDY OF HEROD AND ANTIPATER: <HI>With the Death of faire Marriam.</HI></P>
<P>According to IOSEPHVS, the lear∣ned and famous <HI>Iewe.</HI></P>
<P><HI>As it hath beene, of late, diuers time<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> publiquely Acted</HI> (with great Applause) <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> the Red Bull, by the Company of his Maiesties REVELS.</P>
<P><HI>Written by</HI> <LIST>
<ITEM>GERVASE MARKHAM</ITEM>
<ITEM>WILLIAM SIMPSON.</ITEM>
</LIST> <HI>Gentlemen.</HI></P>
<P><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 paragraph" DISP="〈1 paragraph〉"/></P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="to the reader">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 paragraph" DISP="〈1 paragraph〉"/></HEAD>
<LG>
<L>READERS: whose hearts haue sparkled with <HI>Desire</HI></L>
<L>To be inflamed with <HI>Promethian</HI> Fire,</L>
<L>Fercht from <HI>Pernassus</HI> Shrine (the <HI>Muses</HI> Mount)</L>
<L>To You I write, that make so deare account</L>
<L>Eu'n of <HI>Arts</HI> meerest <HI>Shadowes;</HI> You contemne</L>
<L>The drossy <HI>Substance,</HI> highly priz'd by Men.</L>
<L>Of Earthy breeding; who can neuer gleane</L>
<L>The least Content from a <HI>trile Tragicle Scoene</HI></L>
<L>Of high and noble Nature; nor care they</L>
<L>To <HI>heare,</HI> or <HI>vnderstand;</HI> but <HI>see</HI> a Play:</L>
<L>For <HI>Tragoedy</HI> or <HI>History,</HI> you shall</L>
<L>Neuer finde these at any <HI>Stationers</HI> Stall</L>
<L>Bestow one Six-pence: but, for bald Discourses</L>
<L>Of <HI>Commicke Ribaldry,</HI> they'l draw their Purses.</L>
<L>Hence is the cause, that <HI>Stories</HI> (like to This)</L>
<L>Shall lie in darke Obscurity, and misse</L>
<L>The <HI>Printers Presse,</HI> t'adorne and set them forth</L>
<L>In the true Glories of their <HI>Natiue Worth;</HI></L>
<L>When <HI>Ca<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>rion-Comedies</HI> (not worth an Hayre)</L>
<L>Must be set out with EXCELLENT and RARE</L>
<L>Strange vndeseruing Titles: but, let these</L>
<L>Merit such liking as their Readers please.</L>
<L>Heere I haue sent and Printed to your view</L>
<L>A Story; which I dare be bold is <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></L>
<L>Now newly writ, and truely worthy</L>
<L>Gather'd from learn'd IOSEPHVS <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></L>
<L>Is, that it may your kinde <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></L>
<L>I then shall count my <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></L>
<L>So happily bestow'd <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></L>
<L>For your Content<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></HI></L>
</LG>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="prologue">
<PB REF="3"/>
<HEAD>THE PROLOGVE.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L>Tlmes eldest Daughter (Truth) presents our Play;</L>
<L>And, from forgotten Monuments of Clay,</L>
<L>Cals vp th'Heroicke Spirits of old Times,</L>
<L>Fam'd then as well for Vertues as blacke Crimes;</L>
<L>And with Her owne Tongue, and owne Phrase, to tell</L>
<L>The Actions they haue done; or ill, or well.</L>
<L><HI>IOSEPHVS</HI> th'ancient Writer, with a Pen</L>
<L>Lent by the Muses, giues new life to Men;</L>
<L>Who breath'd such Tragicke Accents forth toth' Eare</L>
<L>Of Hebrew Armies, which you now shall heare;</L>
<L>Please you to sit attentiue: Wit hath runne</L>
<L>In a Zodaicall Circle, like the Sunne,</L>
<L>Through all Inuention; which is growne so poore</L>
<L>Shee can shew nought, but what has beene before:</L>
<L>Yet Reuerend History, which vpon the Stage</L>
<L>Hath oft beene heard sp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ake; hopes, euen for Her Age,</L>
<L>Your strong hands will support Her; Shee must liue</L>
<L>Now by no heate, but what your beames doe giue:</L>
<L>To gaine which (though Her Scoenes seeme graue and hie)</L>
<L>Shee heere and there with a loose wing doth flye;</L>
<L>Striuing to make you merry: No other Bayes</L>
<L>She reaches at, but this; your Loues, your Praise.</L>
</LG>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 N="1" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="3"/>
<HEAD>The true TRAGEDY OF HEROD AND ANTIPATER.</HEAD>
<HEAD>Actus 1. Scoena 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter at one dore Alexandra in her petticoate; at another, Aristobulus the high Priest in his wastcoate or shirt, both amazedly.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu. Alexandra.</SPEAKER>
<L><SEG REND="decorInit">O</SEG> My thrice Princely Sonne; thou hast forgot</L>
<L>That Time's our Maister, and wee can dispo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></L>
<L>But meerely of the instant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eld. Arist.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam true:</L>
<L>Nor haue I lost a moment; yet I know,</L>
<L>No diligence appeares to those, whose hearts</L>
<L>Doe both desire and waite.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Enough, enough;</L>
<L>Come let's away, my heart is wing'd with haste</L>
<L>That out-flies thought or motion; Aegypt (sweete)</L>
<L>Hath safety in it, not Ierusalem.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eld. Arist.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe confesse it; yet this dangerous way</L>
<L>Of our escape, hath many feares about it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>There's pregnant reason for it, and our liues</L>
<L><PB REF="4"/>
Are markes that <HI>Herod</HI> shoots at: Who but sees</L>
<L>The wofull state of sad Ierusalem,</L>
<L>And how this Tyrant (like an angry Boare)</L>
<L>Roots vp the goodly Pines should couer him?</L>
<L>Hath he not slaine <HI>Antigonus,</HI> destroyd</L>
<L>Thy Father and thy Grandsire: (O my Lords,</L>
<L>My deare lou'd Lords, my Father and my Husband;)</L>
<L>Worthy <HI>Hircanus,</HI> noble <HI>Alexander;</HI></L>
<L>And at this instant lies hee not in waite</L>
<L>For our destructions? Beldame that I am</L>
<L>To prate at such a season; (holy Sweete)</L>
<L>Come let's away, our flight is so secure,</L>
<L>No Art can vndermine it; any pause</L>
<L>Opens our graues before vs: flye, O flye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eld. Arist.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe attend your Highnesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Harke, I heare</L>
<L>The steps of some pursues vs; prethee come,</L>
<L>Let <HI>Aegypt</HI> and not <HI>Iuda</HI> be our Tombe.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter at one dore Antipater at another Animis, with a band of Soldiers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Antip.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is this the diligence your duty shewes,</L>
<L>To runne this slothfull pace? By all I loue,</L>
<L>Y'are worthy of blame in high termes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Princely <HI>Antipater</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'are too improuident, and this neglect</L>
<L>Will draw your life in hazard; vnderstand,</L>
<L>Th'are Lyons and not Lambs you cope withall:</L>
<L>The Mother-Queene is s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>btile, and her Sonne</L>
<L>Of high and noble spirit; should they scape,</L>
<L>You fixe a Ramme to batter downe the life</L>
<L>Both of the King and Kingdome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ani.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gracious Sir,</L>
<L>Feare not my care; for nothing you can wish</L>
<L>Is able to outstrip my diligence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Antip.</SPEAKER>
<L>I but awake the duty which you owe</L>
<L>Vnto your King and Countrey; when that moues,</L>
<L>Children are strangers, Fathers are vnknowne,</L>
<L>And where our Princes health is questioned,</L>
<L><PB REF="4"/>
The liues we either borrow or doe lend</L>
<L>Must bee forgot and made ridiculous:</L>
<L>You vnderstand me, goe, dispatch, away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ani.</SPEAKER>
<L>With faith great as your longings.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Animis &amp; Soldiers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>So, why so;</L>
<L>Thus haue I started brauely, and maintain'd</L>
<L>My race with full speed to ambition;</L>
<L>Much of my way is smoothed by the deaths</L>
<L>Of proud <HI>Antigonus</HI> and <HI>Alexander,</HI></L>
<L>But chiefly of <HI>Hircanus,</HI> till hee went</L>
<L>My torch could neuer kindle; could I now</L>
<L>But dampe the high Priest <HI>Aristobulus,</HI></L>
<L>(As there's much water towards) and in it</L>
<L>Drowne his old politique Mother, halfe my way</L>
<L>Lies as my thoughts would wish it; and how ere</L>
<L>By birth I am a Bastard, yet my wit</L>
<L>Shall beare me 'boue the true-borne; for 'tis found,</L>
<L>Power makes all things lawfull, all things sound.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Cornets: and, Enter Herod, Marriam, Kiparim, Alexander, Aristobulus, Salumith, Pheroas, Ioseph and Attendants.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who sits on the Tribunall, sits on thorne,</L>
<L>And dangers doe surround him; for at it</L>
<L>Enuy stands euer gazing, and with darts</L>
<L>Headed with lightning strikes vnto the heart</L>
<L>Of euery noble action: What can Kings</L>
<L>Doe, that the rude not censure and peruert</L>
<L>To vilde interpretations? Nay, although</L>
<L>Iustice and mercy guard them; though mens faults</L>
<L>Are growne so odious, that euen Cruelty</L>
<L>Is a commended goodnesse, meere Distrust</L>
<L>A reasonable vertue; Secrecie,</L>
<L>Important and most needfull; and Suspect,</L>
<L>A worthy truth, which needs no witnesses:</L>
<L>Yet, in this case, (where men cannot erre twice)</L>
<L>What shall we doe, that shall scape Infamie?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fine dissimulation!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>O 'tis a hell to thinke on, that how ere</L>
<L><PB REF="5"/>
Our natures are inclin'd to pitty, yet</L>
<L>Our actions must be cruell (or so thought)</L>
<L>To guard our liues from danger; wicked men</L>
<L>With their sinnes so transforme vs. O my Loue,</L>
<L>This vnto thee I speake, whose tender heart</L>
<L>I know hath bitter thoughts, when it records</L>
<L>Thy Fathers and thy Grand-fathers mishaps:</L>
<L>'Tis true, I caus'd them dye; but (gentle Sweete)</L>
<L>Necessity, thy safety, mine, nay all the Lands,</L>
<L>Were my most iust assistants; and the act</L>
<L>Was noble, how ere blam'd of Cruelty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>My dearest Lord, doe not mistake my temper,</L>
<L>My Grand-father, and Father, when they fell,</L>
<L>How euer Nature taught mine eyes to weepe,</L>
<L>Yet in my loue to you I buried them;</L>
<L>They were rich Iewels once, but, set by you,</L>
<L>They haue nor price, nor lustre; 'tis mine eye</L>
<L>That pitties them, my heart doth honour you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>O y'are a goodnesse past equality,</L>
<L>And all the blessed times which are to come</L>
<L>Shall with more admiration then beleefe</L>
<L>Receiue th'incredible, but vndoubted truth,</L>
<L>Of your rare mildnesse, faith and temperance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>It shall indeed; and be this kisse a seale</L>
<L>Of our perpetuall loue-knot; yet (my Queene)</L>
<L>There are new Treasons hatching, which (beleeu't)</L>
<L>Wil stretch thy patience higher: <HI>Ioseph,</HI> reade</L>
<L>That strange and cunning Letter.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><P>Ioseph reads.</P>
<P>I write short <HI>ALEXANDRA,</HI> for feare of interception; that Herods cruelty extendeth to the death of thy Husband, and im∣prisonment of thy selfe, I lament: ayd I cannot send thee; but if by flight thou canst escape, Aegypt shall receiue thee: I am glad thy Sonne Aristobulus is high Priest, let him accompany thy Iourney: If I should deale for thee by force, I raise two mighty enemies, Rome and Iuda; thou art wise, fare as my selfe: Thine <HI>CLEOPATRA,</HI> Q. of Aegypt.</P></STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="5"/>
<SPEAKER>Kip.</SPEAKER>
<L>These are miraculous Treasons.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Subtile plots.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Strange interwinding mischiefes,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Say not so,</L>
<L>Giue them a gentler title; nothings read</L>
<L>That doth accuse my Mother or my Brother.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeed 'tis but an inuitation</L>
<L>Of others Loue, not their confederacy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Ari.</SPEAKER>
<L>Th' Aegyptian Queen perswades, but their consent</L>
<L>Is not conceiued heere.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Deere wife and Sonnes,</L>
<L>Loue hath a blindfold iudgement; would their hearts</L>
<L>Were harmelesse as your wishes; but heere comes</L>
<L>The man will reconcile vs: Captaine, speake,</L>
<L>Where's <HI>Alexandra?</HI> Where's <HI>Aristobulus?</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Animis with Soldiers, bringing two Trunks.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ani.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, they are fled.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fled! do not speake it; better thou hadst sunke</L>
<L>To hell, then bring that mischiefe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Antip.</SPEAKER>
<L>O the Diuell!</L>
<L>This was your hackney pace</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ani.</SPEAKER>
<L>By all that's true,</L>
<L>I haue not slackt a minute; they were gone</L>
<L>Ere I had my commission, and so fast,</L>
<L>My speed could not outstrip them; yet I tooke</L>
<L>This luggage and their Seruants, whence (no doubt)</L>
<L>Your Maiesty may gather new instructions.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whence I may gather my despaire and griefe;</L>
<L>Villaine, thou hast betray'd me; in their losse,</L>
<L>I'm lost to fate an danger: Silly Snaile;</L>
<L>Could Sloth haue crept so slowly? Why, thy way</L>
<L>Was smooth as glasse, and thou mightst haue surpriz'd</L>
<L>Them easier then to speake it. O you Gods,</L>
<L>What plummets hang at Vassals heeles; and how</L>
<L>Doth sleepe and dulnesse ceaze them! But I vow,</L>
<L>Thy life shall pay thy forfait.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ani.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gracious Sir:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="6"/>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Talk'st thou of grace; and in this act hast lost,</L>
<L>All things that's like, or neare it? Did not scorne</L>
<L>Hold me, my hand should kill thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good Sir, thinke—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>That y'are too rude to offer thus to thrust</L>
<L>'Twixt me and my resolution.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Antip.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not a word;</L>
<L>'Tis death t'outface this lightening.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lost, and fled, and gone, and all my hope</L>
<L>Turn'd topsie turuie downward? <HI>Ioseph,</HI> harke.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Herod whispers with Ioseph, and beckens all the rest vnto them, but Marriam, and Antipater.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Blest be the God of <HI>Iuda,</HI> which hath brought</L>
<L>My royall Mother, and my Brother safe,</L>
<L>Out of the hands of sad Captiuity.</L>
<L>O, I will offer Sacrifice each day,</L>
<L>And make that houre a Sabbath, which doth bring</L>
<L>Them safe from threatning danger.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Antip.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, <HI>Amen;</HI></L>
<L>With that prayer Ile ioyne euer, and inuoke</L>
<L>Prosperity to guard them;—but (in heart)</L>
<L>Wish that damnation, like a Thunder-bolt,</L>
<L>Would beat them into cynders.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis resolu'd,</L>
<L>Force shall compell what vertuously I would</L>
<L>Haue sought from milde intreaty; for those Trunks,</L>
<L>Goe throw them into <HI>Silo,</HI> let that Lake</L>
<L>Deuoure them and their treasures.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ios.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not so good,</L>
<L>You may, by that meanes, blind-fold cast away</L>
<L>What you would after purchase with your blood;</L>
<L>But cannot then recall it: Sir, conceiue;</L>
<L>There may be Complots, Letters, Stratagems,</L>
<L>And things we cannot dreame of.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kip.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, perhaps</L>
<L>Some new negotiations.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>er tongues,</L>
<L>That may discouer strange dissemblers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>True,</L>
<L>You haue preuail'd, breake vp those rotten Tombes,</L>
<L>Lets see what Ghosts they harbor. Ha, whats this?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Here they breake open the trunks, and finde Alexandra, and Aristobulus the elder.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>O me, my Mother and my Brother! Eyes</L>
<L>Drop out and see not their destruction.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="6"/>
<SPEAKER>Antip.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vnhappy chance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ios.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vnfortunate young-man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Arist.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis fate not to be shunned.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Woe the time.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's heere: the high Priest like a Iuggler?</L>
<L>Are these his holy Garments; this his Roabe,</L>
<L>His Brest-plate and his Ephod, his rich Coate,</L>
<L>His Miter and his Girdle? Can it be,</L>
<L>That this was once Queene of <HI>Ierusalem?</HI></L>
<L>O you immortall Gods, to what disguise</L>
<L>Will Treachery transforme vs!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rather thinke,</L>
<L>How sharpe a plague is Tyrannie: O King,</L>
<L>Remember 'tis the fiercest Beast, of all</L>
<L>That are accounted sauage; yet delights</L>
<L>In Flattery, which is the worst of them</L>
<L>That are tame and domestique: With these Fiends</L>
<L>My life can finde no pleasure; doe not then</L>
<L>Blame me to seeke my freedome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eld. Arist.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mighty Sir,</L>
<L>If Life bee th'onely Iewell Heauen can lend,</L>
<L>And that in the Creation was not made</L>
<L>A thing of equall purchase; how can wee</L>
<L>Offend, that but preserue it? You may say,</L>
<L>It hath deceiu'd vs; yet Sir, I will thinke</L>
<L>How ere it finish heere, 'tis but a stroke</L>
<L>To draw it forth vnto eternity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis a good resolution; for (beleeu't)</L>
<L>Your dayes on earth are finisht; treacherous plots</L>
<L>Like these, shall not ore take me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>But your Tyrannie</L>
<L>Shall out-runne all example: Sir, Despaire</L>
<L>Armes me with truth and boldnesse; I dare now</L>
<L>Tell you, of Kings, you are the wickedest;</L>
<L>And I, th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>in the ruines of my blood,</L>
<L>Read your destroying nature, and collect</L>
<L>Into a short briefe many Tragedies,</L>
<L>Acted vpon our family; what hope</L>
<L>Is left, that can assist vs?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="7"/>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are plaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Truth hath no need of figures: was't not you</L>
<L>That did betray <HI>Hircanus</HI> in his flight</L>
<L>To the Arabian Monarch; and when laid</L>
<L>In harmelesse sleepe then slew him? Did not you</L>
<L>Hire the bloody <HI>Cassius</HI> to cut off</L>
<L>My fathers head, (the lou'd <HI>Antigonus?</HI>)</L>
<L>Haue you not kild my Husband, troad my Sonnes</L>
<L>Into the mire, that you might safely walke</L>
<L>Ouer their heads vnto Ambition?</L>
<L>And can you hope, that wee haue any hope</L>
<L>In you, but desolation?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your despaire</L>
<L>Turne temperance into folly; Charity</L>
<L>Would more become the dying.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>E. Arist.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis confest;</L>
<L>Nor is it lost in this sad Argument:</L>
<L>We know our liues are forfeyt, take them Sir;</L>
<L>To dye, is the first contract that was made</L>
<L>Twixt Mankinde and the World; tis a debt,</L>
<L>For which there's no forgiuenesse, th'onely cause</L>
<L>For which we were created; and, indeed,</L>
<L>To die's mans nature, not his punishment;</L>
<L>What folly then would shun it? Boldly Sir,</L>
<L>Vse what your power hath conquer'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>So I will;</L>
<L>Your owne lips are your Iudges; and these hands,</L>
<L>Arm'd with these two Stillettoes at one blow,</L>
<L>Shall thus driue all feares from me; but vnite</L>
<STAGE>Offers to stab, lets the poniard fal, &amp; imbraces Ari. &amp; Alex.</STAGE>
<L>Two friends in mine imbraces; happy ones,</L>
<L>Exceediug happy ones; let not your feares</L>
<L>Draw to your eyes false figures, or make me</L>
<L>Appeare that which I am not: come, I loue you,</L>
<L>Dearely I loue you; all that I haue done</L>
<L>Constraint, and not my nature perfitted:</L>
<L>Be henceforth free for euer; <HI>Aegypt,</HI> nor</L>
<L>The World shall safelier guard you; as you stan<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></L>
<L>Thus shall you still support me; Holines</L>
<STAGE>Places Arist. on his right hand, and Q. Alex. on his left.</STAGE>
<L>Vpon my right hand; Mother you shall sit</L>
<L>Euer vpon my left hand; both shall be</L>
<L>Mine Armour, Counsell, and prosperity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="7"/>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<L>This grace is past example; <HI>Herod's</HI> a God.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis but their first step to felicity:</L>
<L>Antipater, your eare.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Herod whispers with Antipater, Antipater with Y. Alexander, and Prince Aristobulus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mother, the King is gracious.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Past beleefe,</L>
<L>Nor shall the memory lose me; this not fain'd,</L>
<L>Ile fixe my prayers vpon him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ios.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall doe</L>
<L>Wrong to your royall nature to suspect him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>E. Arist.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, 'tis true;</L>
<L>I hold his word a rocke to build vpon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. Arist.</SPEAKER>
<L>The sport is excellent, the wager firme,</L>
<L>My person shall maintaine it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>So shall mine.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Clap hands.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Antip.</SPEAKER>
<L>And if I shrinke, make me a weather-cocke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>How soone a foule day's cleered: Now to make</L>
<L>Your happinesse more constant; Brother, know,</L>
<L>The Temple of King Salomon which I</L>
<L>The other day defaced and threw downe</L>
<L>Low as the earth it stood on; once againe</L>
<L>I will erect with double excellence.</L>
<L><HI>Ioseph,</HI> my Brother, to your noble charge</L>
<L>I giue that holy building; see it fram'd</L>
<L>To th'height of Art and wonder; spare no gold,</L>
<L>Iewels, nor rich imbosture; I haue mines,</L>
<L>And all shall be exhausted; that the world</L>
<L>May boast, King <HI>Herod</HI> out-went <HI>Salomon.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ios.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, y'haue ingag'd me where my heart desir'd;</L>
<L>Doubt not my diligence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis knowne too well:</L>
<L>How now, what newes Centurion? How stands fate</L>
<L>Betweene <HI>Augustus</HI> and <HI>Marke Anthony?</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Hillus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hill.</SPEAKER>
<L>O royall Sir, deadly vnfortunate;</L>
<L>For, neuer was so sad a day before</L>
<STAGE>Antip. E. Arist. Y. Ari. P. Alex. whisper.</STAGE>
<L>Seene to ore-couer <HI>Aegypt:</HI> To be briefe</L>
<L><HI>Augustus</HI> hath the Conquest; <HI>Anthony</HI></L>
<L>Lies buried in the blood his warlike hand</L>
<L>Strucke from his royall bosome; the sad Queene</L>
<L><PB REF="8"/>
Oretakes him with like fury, and now both</L>
<L>Are turnd to dust and ashes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou hast spoke</L>
<L>Much sorrow in a few words.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hill.</SPEAKER>
<L>But hold still</L>
<L>Farre greater to vnburthen: Soone as chance</L>
<L>Had made <HI>Augustus</HI> happy, and orethrowne</L>
<L>Faire <HI>Cleopatra,</HI> and her <HI>Anthony;</HI></L>
<L>Hee viewes his spoyles, and 'mongst them findes the aide</L>
<L>Y'ad sent to interpose him: Now hee frownes,</L>
<L>Bends his inraged forehead, and protests,</L>
<L>That <HI>Iuda</HI> and <HI>Ierusalem</HI> shall curse</L>
<L>They euer heard the name of <HI>Anthony:</HI></L>
<L>And this hee spake with such an Emphasis,</L>
<L>As shooke my heart within me; yet gaue wings</L>
<L>Vnto my faith to tell you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, no more,</L>
<L>Th'ast split me with thy Thunder; I haue made</L>
<L><HI>Rome</HI> and the world my mortall enemies;</L>
<L>Yet vertue did transport me; but that guard</L>
<L>Is no guard now: Tell me, Centurion,</L>
<L>Where did you leaue <HI>Augustus?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hill.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, in <HI>Rhodes.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis a faire easie Iourney, I'm resolu'd;</L>
<L>Nor shall perswasion change me; hence Ile goe,</L>
<L>And as a Hermite throw at <HI>Caesars</HI> feete</L>
<L>My Crowne and person; if hee pitty them,</L>
<L>My peace is made; if otherwise,</L>
<L>My fault flies not beyond me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kip.</SPEAKER>
<L>O my Sonne,</L>
<L>This is a desperate hazard.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay tis more;</L>
<L>A tempting of your fortune.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be content,</L>
<L>Mother and Sister, nothing alters me;</L>
<L>Nor doe they loue me, that would draw my will</L>
<L>To any other compasse: <HI>Ioseph,</HI> to you</L>
<L>I leaue the Realmes protection, and the care</L>
<L>Or building vp the Temple: Nay, no teares,</L>
<STAGE>The women weepe.</STAGE>
<L>They prophesie my death, which doe but shew</L>
<L>A low deiected countnance; if I haue</L>
<L>Power in your hearts, this day I challenge you</L>
<L>To giue them vnto pastime, that the world</L>
<L>May see, we dread not fortune.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Antip.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis resolu'd;</L>
<L>And Ile be first to shew obedience.</L>
<L><PB REF="8"/>
Sir, 'twixt my Princely Brothers and my selfe,</L>
<L>I'ue made a match of Swimming, if you please</L>
<L>But to allow the Contract.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>How is't made?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Antip.</SPEAKER>
<L>That I and th'high Priest <HI>Aristobulus,</HI></L>
<L>Will swim more swift, more comely, and more wayes,</L>
<L>Then can my Princely Brothers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are all agreed?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eld. Arist.</SPEAKER>
<L>All, if your Maiesty consent thereto.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>For those young men it skils not; but Sir, you,</L>
<L>I'm curious of your danger.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>There's no feare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis a braue recreation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Arist.</SPEAKER>
<L>A fit skill</L>
<L>For Princes to delight in.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eld. Arist.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gracious Sir,</L>
<L>Let me consort my Brothers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be your will</L>
<L>Your owne director; I am satisfied.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why tis a match then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet looke well to your safeties; for my selfe,</L>
<L><HI>Rhodes</HI> is mine obiect: Dearest Loue, farewell;</L>
<L>This kisse seale my remembrance; Mothers, let</L>
<L>Your onely prayers assist me; for the rest,</L>
<L>Despaire not till my downfall; goe, away,</L>
<L>Reply not, if you loue me; only <HI>Antipater,</HI></L>
<STAGE>Exe. all but He∣rod and Antip.</STAGE>
<L>Stay and attend me further. Princely youth,</L>
<L>Of all the hopes that doe attend my life,</L>
<L>Thy Greatnesse is my greatest; nor would I</L>
<STAGE>Ioseph returnes and listens.</STAGE>
<L>Imba<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>que me in this desperate vessell thus,</L>
<L>Wer't not to raise thy fortunes: But tis now</L>
<L>No time for Courtship; onely, I must leaue</L>
<L>Two sad commandments with thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speak them Sir,</L>
<L>Without exception, you cannot deuise</L>
<L>What Ile not execute.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis nobly said:</L>
<L>Thou seest the high Priest <HI>Aristobulus,</HI></L>
<L>And knowst how like a heauy waight he hangs,</L>
<L>Pressing our fortunes downeward; if hee liue</L>
<L>Our liues haue no assurance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis resolu'd,</L>
<L>Hee neuer sees to morrow; soone at night,</L>
<L>When we doe swim our wager, Ile so teach</L>
<L>His Holinesse to diue, that on the earth</L>
<L>He nere shall tread to hurt vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou hast hit</L>
<L>The obiect that I lookt at.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ios.</SPEAKER>
<L>(But shot wide</L>
<L><PB REF="9"/>
Of goodnes, and all good thoughts.)</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>This performd,</L>
<L>There yet remaines another thing to doe,</L>
<L>Which neerelier doth concerne me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speake it Sir;</L>
<L>Your pleasure is mine Armour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Briefly thus,</L>
<L>If through my fortune, or <HI>Augustus</HI> wrath,</L>
<L>I perish in this Iourney; by that loue,</L>
<L>Which na<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>re, fauour, or my best deserts</L>
<L>Can kindle in thy bosome; I coniure</L>
<L>And binde thee on the first intelligence,</L>
<L>By poyson, sword, or any violent meanes,</L>
<L>To kill my Wife <HI>Marriam;</HI> let no man</L>
<L>But <HI>Herod</HI> tast her sweetnesse; which perform'd,</L>
<L>My soule in death shall loue thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thinke tis done;</L>
<L>By heauen the houre which tells me of your death,</L>
<L>Is th'oure of her destruction; I haue sworne,</L>
<L>And there's no fate can change me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be thy selfe,</L>
<L>Constant and vnremoued; so farewell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ios.</SPEAKER>
<L>Two fiends like these were neuer spit from Hell.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Herod and Ioseph seuerally.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe <HI>Herod,</HI> happy King; nay <HI>Herod,</HI> goe,</L>
<L>Vnhappy, cause so happy; happy King,</L>
<L>Whilst th'art a King; vnhappy when no King:</L>
<L>Hangs then mishap or hap vpon a King, or no King?</L>
<L>Then <HI>Herod,</HI> be no King; <HI>Antipater</HI> be King:</L>
<L>And what's a King? a God: and what are Gods, but Kings?</L>
<L><HI>Ioue,</HI> Prince of Gods, was petty King of paltry <HI>Creete;</HI></L>
<L>Men subiect are to Kings and Gods; but of the twaine,</L>
<L>Their Gods than Kings commands, they rather disobay;</L>
<L>Kings greater then; nay, better then, then Gods:</L>
<L>Then but a King or God, naught with <HI>Antipater;</HI></L>
<L>And rather King then God; no God; a King, a King.</L>
<L>When I complaine to Eccho but head-aking; it cries, a King:</L>
<L>When I, in mirth, am musique making; it sounds, a King:</L>
<L>Each sight, when I am waking; presents a King:</L>
<L>When I my rest am taking; I see a King.</L>
<L>Last night I saw, or seem'd to see; nay, sure I saw</L>
<L>A Crown hang ore my head; &amp; throgh the Crown a Sword:</L>
<L>I saw, I sigh'd, I cryed, O when? O when?</L>
<L><PB REF="9"/>
Fall Crowne; yea fall with Sword; fall both, so one may fall:</L>
<L>But why dreame I of falling, that must rise;</L>
<L>Nay runne, nay leape, nay flie vnto a Crowne?</L>
<L>Gyants heape hills on hills, to scale high Heauen;</L>
<L>I, heads on heads, to climbe a Kingdomes Skye:</L>
<L>But oh, I am a Sonne; a Sunne, O happy name;</L>
<L>A Sunne must shine alone, obscuring Moone, and Starres:</L>
<L>I, but I am a Bastard; what of that?</L>
<L>Men base by birth, in worth are seldome base;</L>
<L>And Natures Out-casts, still are Fortunes Darlings:</L>
<L><HI>Bacchus, Apollo, Mercury;</HI> Bastards, yet brauest Gods:</L>
<L>Then, why not I a God, a Demi-God, or Worthy?</L>
<L>You Gods, you Demi-Gods, you Worthies then assist me;</L>
<L>That, as our birth was like, our worth may beare like price:</L>
<L>If they refuse; come Deuils, and befriend me;</L>
<L>My breast lies open; come; come Furies and possesse it;</L>
<L>Hatch heere some monstrous brood, worthy of you and me;</L>
<L>Which all Posterities may know, but none beleeue;</L>
<L>Whereat the Sunne may not goe backe, as once it did,</L>
<L>At <HI>Atreus</HI> tyrannie; but fall and dye for euer:</L>
<L>Wherat the Heau'ns may quake, Hell blush, &amp; Nature trem∣ble;</L>
<L>And men (halfe mad) may stand amaz'd. So, so, it works, it works;</L>
<L>My breast swels to a Mountaine; and I breed</L>
<L>A Monster, past description; to whose birth,</L>
<L>Come Furies, and bee Mid-wiues. Harke! O harke!</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><P>Dumbe Shew.</P>
<P>Musique: and, Enter Egystus and Clitemnestra dancing a Cur∣ranto, which is broken off by the sound of Trumpets: then, enter Agamemnon, and diuers Noblemen in Triumph: Egystus whispers with Clitemnestra, and deliuers her a sleeuelesse shirt; then slips aside: Clitemnestra imbraces Agamemnon, he dis∣misses his Traine; shee offers him the shirt, he offers to put it on, and being intangled, Egystus and she kils him; then departs, leauing at Antipaters feete two Scrowles of paper.</P></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>So shall it be; shall it? no shalls; tis done, dispatcht:</L>
<L>Who can resolue, can doe; who can dispose, can better:</L>
<L>My way, seauen single persons, and two houses crosse;</L>
<L>Supported by a many headed beast:</L>
<L><PB REF="10"/>
O, had they all one head, or all their heads one necke,</L>
<L>Or all their necks one body, which one blow might broach;</L>
<L>But had they <HI>Hydra's</HI> heads, <HI>Gerions</HI> bodies; <HI>Hercules,</HI></L>
<L>By making them away, would make his way to Heauen:</L>
<L>But as an hunger-starued Tyger, betweene two Heifers,</L>
<L>Here yawnes, there gapes, in doubt where first to fasten;</L>
<L>So doubt I where to set my pawes, but care not where;</L>
<L>My Father shall be first, that order be obseru'd;</L>
<L>Whose death I wish, not worke, lest piety be wanting;</L>
<L><HI>Rome</HI> will I hope ease me of that disturbance:</L>
<L><HI>Herod</HI> is come <HI>Augustus,</HI> friend to thy foe, and so thy foe;</L>
<L>Keep him <HI>Augustus,</HI> nay kill him <HI>Augustus,</HI> or <HI>Ioue</HI> kill him &amp; thee;</L>
<L>Passe he by Land or Sea, or Hell, or vnder Heauen:</L>
<L>O Earth; food vnto him, or none, or noysome giue:</L>
<L>O Sea; his ships or sinke in sands, or drinke in waues:</L>
<L>O Heauen; or stop his breath, or lend contagious breath:</L>
<L>O Hell; for kindnesse, call him in thy wombe: In summe,</L>
<L>Gape Earth, swell Seas, fall Heauen, Hell swallow him:</L>
<L>But, let me see; what say my hellish Counsellors?</L>
<L><HI>Egystus</HI> wooes, and winnes, and weares a Crowne: a Queene</L>
<L>Receiues with loue (false loue) the Victor King; vna<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>m'd,</L>
<L>She cloaths him in her handi-worke, a shirt,</L>
<L>Which had no head or armes to issue out;</L>
<L>Intangled thus they slew him: let me see,</L>
<L>What haue they left? thus <HI>Clitemnestra</HI> writes;</L>
<L>Per scelera semper sceleribus tutum est iter;</L>
<L>Fond is the stay of sinne; sinne safest way to sinne;</L>
<L><HI>Egystus</HI> leaues this axiome;</L>
<L>Nec regna scotium ferre, nec tedae sciunt;</L>
<L>None, or alone; Kings can indure no Riuals;</L>
<L>I vnderstand you well; and so will worke;</L>
<L>Whetting against my Father both his Wife,</L>
<L>His Sister and her Husband; some by Feare,</L>
<L>Some by Beleefe, and some by Iealousie:</L>
<L>Thus rise I on their heads, and with their hands</L>
<L>Rip vp their naturall Bowels: Tis decreed,</L>
<L>The Plot is laid, Parts must bee playd,</L>
<L>No time delaid.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE><PB REF="10"/>
Enter Lime the Mason, Handsaw the Carpenter, and Durt the Labourer.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis a good handsome Plot, and full of Art;</L>
<L>But how like you my Modell for the Timber-worke?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pretty, pretty, if the seates be not too spacious.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dur.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, tis much the better, and fitter for the Scribes &amp;</L>
<L>Pharisies to sleepe vpon: but here comes the Lord <HI>Ioseph.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Ioseph.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ios.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well said my maisters, and how mounteth the braue Temple? may a man stand on the top of it and orelooke the Sunne?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Sunne is very high Sir; yet there is neuer an Almanacke-maker, but may lie on his backe and behold Capricorne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ios.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tut, any foolish Citizen may doe that which hath his wife for his maister: but stay; what's hee?</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Achitophel &amp; Disease, with a Banner full of ruptures.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ach.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come away <HI>Disease,</HI> and hang vp these my trophees,</L>
<L>Whilst I with gentle ayre, beat vpon the eares of passengers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dis.</SPEAKER>
<P>At hand Sir, and heere is your Ensigne; as for your Drugges, there is not one of them but is able to send a man to God or the Diuell in an instant.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Achitophel sings.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ACH.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come will you buy, for I haue heere</L>
<L>The rarest Gummes that euer were;</L>
<L>Gold is but drosse and Features dye,</L>
<L>Els Aesculapius tels a lie:</L>
<L>But I,</L>
<L>Come will you buy,</L>
<L>Haue Medicines for that Maladie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ios.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's hee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lim.</SPEAKER>
<P>O Sir, it is one that vndertakes to know more Sim∣ples, then euer grew in Paradise; tis <HI>Rabbi Achitophel.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ios.</SPEAKER>
<L>What, the famous Mountebanke?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dur.</SPEAKER>
<L>The same Sir.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Achitophel sings.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ACH.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is there a Lady in this place,</L>
<L>Would not bee mask't, but for her face;</L>
<L><PB REF="11"/>
O doe not blush, for heere is that</L>
<L>Will make your pale cheekes plumpe and fat.</L>
<L>Then why</L>
<L>Should I thus crye,</L>
<L>And none a Scruple of mee buye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ios.</SPEAKER>
<L>Reuerend Iew; I heare y'are fam'd for many rarities;</L>
<L>As Sculpture, Painting, and the setting forth</L>
<L>Of many things that are inscrutable;</L>
<L>Besides you are a learned rare Physitian.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ach.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know as much as ere <HI>Sambashaw</HI> did,</L>
<L>That was old <HI>Adams</HI> Schoolmaister; for, look you Sir:
<STAGE>Sings.</STAGE></L>
<LG>
<L>Heere is a rare Mercurian Pill,</L>
<L>An Anodine helps euery ill;</L>
<L>The Dissenterea, and the Gout,</L>
<L>And cures the sniueling in the Snout.</L>
<L>The Sicke,</L>
<L>Or any Cricke,</L>
<L>Straight cures this Diaphoreticke.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ios.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall haue imployment for you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ach.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Iew is all your Creature, and his skill</L>
<L>Hee'l willingly bestow vpon your gooduesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ios.</SPEAKER>
<L>O Sir, you shall not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dis</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes Sir, my Maister will willingly giue you his skill;</L>
<L>Yet, with this <HI>Memorandum,</HI> you must pay for his good will.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ios.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am no niggard, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dis.</SPEAKER>
<P>Besides, my Lord, there's neuer a Pibble in <HI>Iordan,</HI> but my Maister is able to make the Philosophers Stone of it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dur.</SPEAKER>
<L>O wonderfull! as how I pray you Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dis.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why by extraction, solution, reuerberation, coagu∣lation, fixation, viuiuication, mortification, &amp; <HI>multa alia.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ach.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace knaue, I say, these pearls must not feed Porkets.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<P>How, doe you make Swine of vs? I tell you we are as arrand Iewes as your selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ios.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more, y'are all for mine imployment; you for stone,</L>
<L>You for Painting, you for Timber-worke;</L>
<L>No man shall want his merit: Goe, away,</L>
<L><PB REF="11"/>
Apply your labours, there's a largesse for you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<L>O braue Lord <HI>Ioseph.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Sings.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ACH.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come to me Gallants you whose need,</L>
<L>The common Surgeons cannot reede;</L>
<L>Heere is a Balme will cure all sores,</L>
<L>Got in Broyles, or vnwholsome whores.</L>
<L>Come away,</L>
<L>For why the day,</L>
<L>Is past, and heere I cannot stay.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exe. all but <HI>Ioseph.</HI></STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Alexandra &amp; Marriam, Antipater &amp; Salumith alofe.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>O cease my <HI>Marriam,</HI> teares can doe no good;</L>
<L>This Murder's past example; to be drownd,</L>
<L>Drownd in a shallow murmure where the stones</L>
<L>Chid the faint water for not couering them.</L>
<L>O, 'twas a plot beyond the Diuell sure;</L>
<L>Man could not haue that mallice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam yes,</L>
<L>And 'twas some great one too that had his fist</L>
<L>Thrust in the blood of <HI>Aristobulus.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. Ale.</SPEAKER>
<L>For which blood Ile haue vengeance, &amp; my tears</L>
<L>Shall neuer drye till it bee perfited.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ios.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, forbeare complaining; would this were</L>
<L>The worst of Mischiefes iourney.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Know you worse?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ios.</SPEAKER>
<L>I dare not speake my knowledge, though my heart</L>
<L>Leapes twixt my lips to vtter Mysteries.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Antip.</SPEAKER>
<L>Note you that <HI>Salumith?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes. it hath pincht her on the petticoate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, as y'are noble, whatsoere you know</L>
<L>Of these mishaps, with freedome vtter it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vtter it;</L>
<L>For Heau'ns sake vtter it, noble, worthy Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ios.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, I dare not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>As you loue vertue speake it; let my teares</L>
<L>Winne so much from thy goodnesse; noble Sir,</L>
<L>Soule of thy Generation, thou honestest' mongst men:</L>
<L>O speake it, speake it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Note you this Courtship?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, tis Sorcery.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good Sweete, vnlocke these counsels.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="12"/>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>By all the bonds of Chastity and truth,</L>
<L>It shall proceede no further.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ios.</SPEAKER>
<L>You haue laid</L>
<L>Such strong Commandments on me I must yeeld:</L>
<L>Harke, your eares.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Whispers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Antip.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are they not kissing Madam?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes; may poyson flow betweene them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Antipater;</HI> he drowne him!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ios.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, be still; you shall heare greater mischiefe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Poyson me, if he perish! O you Gods,</L>
<L>What Treason lurkes in Greatnesse; this hath made</L>
<L>Wounds in my heart, through which his loue and name,</L>
<L>Is fled from me for euer!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ios.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis a fault</L>
<L>Which asks your deepest wisedome: come, let's in;</L>
<L>Ile tell you stranger Stories.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet I feare,</L>
<L>None that can draw more vengeance or despaire.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Antip.</SPEAKER>
<L>Awaken Madam, they are vanished.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not from mine outrage, that shall like a storme</L>
<L>Follow them and confound them; I will make</L>
<L>The world in blood, text downe my cru<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ltie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>I cannot blame you, tis strange impudence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile be reueng'd; by all my hopes I will,</L>
<L>Highly and deeply; shallow foole, no more;</L>
<L>Still waters drowne, the shallow doe but roare.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Sal.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile not be farre behinde, but helpe to send</L>
<L>All vnto hell; tis for a Crowne I stand,</L>
<L>And Crownes are oft the ruines of a Land.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ex. Ant.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Augustus, Decius, Lucullus, and Attendants.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aug.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thus haue we queld Rebellion; thus (like smoke)</L>
<L>Vanishes hence the name of <HI>Anthony:</HI></L>
<L>Only some Props remaine yet; which Ile rend</L>
<L>Vp by the roots and scatter: amongst which</L>
<L>Vngratefull <HI>Herod</HI> is a Principall;</L>
<L>On whom Ile shower my vengeance.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Mutius.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gracious Sir; the King of <HI>Iuda,</HI> like a Supplicant,</L>
<L>Desires accesse vnto your Maiestie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aug.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who, <HI>Herod?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, the same.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aug.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis a strange ouer-daring.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>An attempt wisedome would hardly runne to.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aug.</SPEAKER>
<L>Call him in;</L>
<L><PB REF="12"/>
Hee dares not come to braue vs; <HI>Rome</HI> hath power</L>
<L>To shake a stronger building; and his feares</L>
<L>Are glasses of his danger: no man looke</L>
<L>On <HI>Iuda,</HI> but with hatred.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Herod.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mighty Sir; to you, as him of whom I first receiu'd.</L>
<L>The Crowne of <HI>Iuda,</HI> humbly I returne it;</L>
<L>And thus arise. Know now (the great'st'mongst men)</L>
<L>Tis not for Life I plead, but Honesty,</L>
<L>For Vertue, Valour, Honour, Prowesse, Grace,</L>
<L>And all good mens acquaintance: I confesse,</L>
<L>I ayded <HI>Anthony;</HI> if for that I fall,</L>
<L>A true friends teares shall bee my Funerall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis a rare Gratulation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dec.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'm affraid</L>
<L>New feare will alter it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Obserue the Emperour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis true (great Sir) your sacred hand was first</L>
<L>Inuested mee in <HI>Iuda;</HI> gaue mee that</L>
<L>I can forsake with comfort: keepe it still;</L>
<L>Who from a Crowne is rid, is free from cares;</L>
<L>I prize the worth, lesse then two flaxine teares.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aug.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is a kinde of brauing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heare me forth;</L>
<L>And when y'aue heard; this, for extremitie:</L>
<L>Since first the time I wore the sorrowfull Wreath,</L>
<L>(For Crownes and Sorrowes are incorporate,</L>
<L>And hang like linkes, one wreathed in another)</L>
<L>Since first the Crowne I wore, you knew my grieues;</L>
<L>But nere relieu'd me by Person or by Deputy;</L>
<L>No, not when <HI>Asia</HI> and the <HI>Affricke</HI> strands</L>
<L>Ioyn'd both to ouer-throw me: onely, then</L>
<L>The euer-prais'd (now lost) <HI>Marke Anthony</HI></L>
<L>Thrust forth his hand and staid me; he kept firme</L>
<L>My foote that then was sliding; I, for this,</L>
<L>Sent him not ayde, but rent long purchased.</L>
<L>O (gracious Sir) view mine oblidgements well,</L>
<L>And you shall see vertue did gouerne me.</L>
<L>Why, did his life yet lie within my hands,</L>
<L>Thus would I straddle ore him as I stand;</L>
<L>Mine armes disseuer'd like two Rhodian Props;</L>
<L>And ere I bent, my Trunke should be the Base</L>
<L><PB REF="13"/>
For his dread foes to build Ambition on:</L>
<L>This would I doe; and, if this bee a Crime,</L>
<L>It is so good an one, I scorne my breath:</L>
<L>Who liues the liues the longest still must end in death;</L>
<L>And so must I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aug.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art thine owne Iudge <HI>Herod:</HI> call a Slaue,</L>
<L>A desperate Slaue; 'mongst all our Prisoners,</L>
<STAGE>Exit Mut.</STAGE>
<L>Chuse him that hath least mercy: you shall finde,</L>
<L>Your Friendship had a false grownd.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Mut. &amp; a Slaue.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Caesar,</HI> no; Vertue was the foundation, and you may</L>
<L>Batter, but not orethrow it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aug.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well Ile try</L>
<L>The vtmost of your fortitude: arme that Slaue;</L>
<L>And Sirrah, kill that Traytor; tis a worke</L>
<L>That brngs you home your Freedome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>1.</HI> Sla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gracious Sir, what is he I must murder?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aug.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis a King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>1.</HI> Sla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dec.</SPEAKER>
<L>Villaine, why star'st thou? Strike, I say, you Slaue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>1.</HI> Sl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Slaue, Ile not strike; knowst thou or he, or he, or <HI>Caesar</HI></L>
<L>What tis to bee a Murderer; nay, more,</L>
<L>The Murderer of a King; nay, most of all,</L>
<L>To murder God himselfe; (for such are Kings:)</L>
<L>O you dull bloody Romans; see, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>n's eyes</L>
<L>Are thousands of arm'd arm'd Angels; and each Ray</L>
<L>A flame of Lightning ready to deuoure</L>
<L>The hand thats lift gainst sacred Maiesty.</L>
<L><HI>Caesar,</HI> I'm no Italian; though thy Slaue,</L>
<L>I will not be thy Diuell; those are bred</L>
<L>Ith' Shambles, let them Butcher; fetch for this</L>
<L>Some from the Roman Gallowes; for they are</L>
<L>Hangmen that must performe it; and thou lookst</L>
<L>Like one: goe, take the Office, Ile not doo it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aug.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Slaue's affraid to strike him; timerous Coward:</L>
<L>Call another.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Mutius.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>1.</HI> Sla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Timerous! <HI>Caesar,</HI> no:</L>
<L>Were I to scale a Tower, or sacke a Towne,</L>
<L>I'de doo't; although the ruines fell like Quarries on me:</L>
<L>Timerous! <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>neare fear'd Mankinde; <HI>Caesar,</HI> know,</L>
<L>Nor earth nor Hell hath ought that can affright me:</L>
<L><PB REF="13"/>
I'ue buckled with proud <HI>Iulius</HI> thine Vncle, and was one</L>
<L>That, by expulsion, beate him from bright <HI>Albion:</HI></L>
<L>And yet to kill a King, I'm timerous.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ent. Mut. &amp; <HI>2.</HI> Sla.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aug.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let that Slaue haue the weapon: Sirrah, kill</L>
<L>That King, and haue thy freedome: wilt thou doo't?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>2.</HI> Sla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, for my liberty,</L>
<L>As soone as you can speake it: Shall I strike?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aug.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay, what's thy Country?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>2.</HI> Sla.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Rome, Rome;</HI> I was bred in one of those Colledges where Letchery and Murder are Pue-mates: Come, will you giue the word?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe not deferre it <HI>Caesar,</HI></L>
<L>I haue made peace with my Conscience long since.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aug.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why then strike.</L>
<L>Yet Villaine hold; art not amaz'd to doo't?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>2.</HI> Sla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Amaz'd, why?</L>
<L>To strike off these my shackles, such a blow</L>
<L>I would giue to my Father.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aug.</SPEAKER>
<L>But a worse</L>
<L>Shall fall vpon thy Carcasse: binde that Slaue,</L>
<L>And throw him headlong downe into the Sea;</L>
<L>The earth's too much infected.—<HI>Herod,</HI> thus</L>
<L>Mine armes giues thee thy freedome: take thy Crowne;</L>
<L>Weare it with safety; and but be to mee</L>
<L>Faithfull; Ile loue thee as did <HI>Anthony.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Caesar</HI> is royall; and, by this, hath bound</L>
<L>A faithfull Seruant to him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aug.</SPEAKER>
<L>For that wretch,</L>
<L>Giue him his liberty; since th'ast seru'd</L>
<L>Vertue, thou shalt serue <HI>Caesar;</HI> henceforth be</L>
<L>Commander ore a Legion: Those that know</L>
<L>Goodnesse; by Goodnesse euer greater grow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>1.</HI> Sla.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Caesar's</HI> a God in all things.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>nes.</STAGE>
<TRAILER>Finis Actus primae.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="2" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACT. 2. Scoena 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter at one Dore Marriam and Alexandra; at another Kiparim and Salumith, they meete and passe disdainfully.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kip.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lord how their poyson swels them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sure they'l burst, if this strong Chollicke hold them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="14"/>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mother, withdraw; the Greeke begins to scold.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>And why to scold, proud Madame?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, I want a tongue for your encounter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kip.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet this thing,</L>
<L>Of which thou art deriued, ought to know</L>
<L>Shee owes me some obeysance; though she was</L>
<L>Mother to him that wore the Crowne, I am</L>
<L>Mother to him that weares it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tut, pride loues not to distinguish: goodly Lord, not so much as how doe you forsooth; (euery foolish Citi∣zens salutation;) nor haile to the Sister of my Lord the King, (euery Court-Coxecombes Congee;) nor saue you sweet Lady, (Fooles and Physitians Orizons)</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>How this shewes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kip.</SPEAKER>
<L>It shewes that you are insolent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Insolent: hugge it sweetly, tis your owne;</L>
<L>And euery sinne besides th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>'s damnable:</L>
<L>Come, y'are despised Grecians; so prophane,</L>
<L>Ignoble and vnholy, that our Tribes</L>
<L>Are staind in your coniunctions; poore things, know,</L>
<L>Your titular King, in whom your glories dwell,</L>
<L>Is but a roy all murderer; your selues,</L>
<L>And his proud Bastard, bloody Substitutes:</L>
<L>O, I could paint you brauely; for my grieues</L>
<L>Haue all your perfect colours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come I could</L>
<L>Make you runn<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>dog-like backe, and from the ground</L>
<L>Licke vp the filth you vtterd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Neuer sure;</L>
<L>Sheele leaue it where she found it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, and you</L>
<L>Leaue vertue where you found it; harke you Queene,</L>
<L>You are vnchaft, and most incontinent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Incontinent: with whom?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>His picture lies within you; plucke it out,</L>
<L>And let your false heart follow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is Truths part to suffer; so must I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vengeance vpon such sufferance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, y'are a barbarous Creature.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kip.</SPEAKER>
<L>Base <HI>Edomite.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Slanderous Grecian.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Old Beldame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Young Cocatrice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="14"/>
<SPEAKER>Kip.</SPEAKER>
<L>S'death, I could teare thine eyes out.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Antip.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do but (This) that motion shall destroy thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Marry mew.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold in the name of Verue; heere's a braule</L>
<L>Able to inflame patience: Beautious Queene,</L>
<L>Diuinest <HI>Alexandra;</HI> what can moue</L>
<L>These stormes in this calme weather.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Flattering Sir,</L>
<L>You best can close vp mischiefe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>If I may,</L>
<L>Ile lay my life a subiect to your mercies;</L>
<L>Make me your footstooles to appease your wrathes;</L>
<L>My blood Ile make your sacrifice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more;</L>
<L>I that but now shed teares, now laugh: O God!</L>
<L>To see so braue a Maister-piece of Villany</L>
<L>By such a Bastard Issue bee compacted:</L>
<L>Thou make attonement? Hence Bastard, hence;</L>
<L>The dregges of Lust, the foule Disease of Wine,</L>
<L>That wert begot when sinne was reuelling:</L>
<L>Thou make attonemenr? No; goe lea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ne to drowne</L>
<L>The Lords elected people; heere stands shee</L>
<L>That lookes to tast thy poyson.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Miracles!</L>
<L>Wrest not my good thoughts (Madam) for I call</L>
<L>Iust Heauen to witnesse how I lou'd your Sonne;</L>
<L>And would my selfe haue dyed to ransome him;</L>
<L>But your misprision I impute to heate</L>
<L>And Chollericke spleene, which now misgouernes you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kip.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, you should thanke her for abusing you;</L>
<L>Wee are become her vassals.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thinke not so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, and cry vengeance for it; wicked one,</L>
<L>There's wier whips in making, and I know</L>
<L>Furies will soundly lash you; you, and you;</L>
<L>Both are m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>rkt out to perish; faith you are.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Ioseph.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ios.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now; what means this outrage? Peace for shame;</L>
<L>This talke fits Stewes and Brothels: Gome, no more;</L>
<L>Mother, your iudgement should be farre more wise;</L>
<L>And Madam, you should be more temperate:</L>
<L>A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> Princes hands, all iniuries should looke</L>
<L>Not for reuenge but pa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ience.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kip.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou which art made of Cowardise and feare;</L>
<L><PB REF="15"/>
Dost thou confirme their actions?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, tis fit;</L>
<L>Lust still must flatter falshood.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ios.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha; what's that? why Wife—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Call me not Wife;</L>
<L>The sound of death hath farre more Musique in it:</L>
<L>Wife? O, my fate! Wife vnto such a Letcher?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ios.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why <HI>Salumith.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile be no <HI>Salumith</HI> of thine, ther'es your Loue;</L>
<L>She whom you foster in her insolencies;</L>
<L>Shee's your <HI>Salumith:</HI> O crudulous women,</L>
<L>How easily are you guld, with a seducing kisse!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now it workes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>A faire word makes the Diuell seeme a Saint;</L>
<L>But Ile be reueng'd, and in so strange a course</L>
<L>As neuer woman tooke. D'yee perpetrate my goodnes?</L>
<L>There's your <HI>Salumith.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Admirable still.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kip.</SPEAKER>
<L>And there's th'old Hen her Mother,</L>
<L>A couple of season'd dishes, fall too, fall too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay Madam, y'are too bitter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ios.</SPEAKER>
<L>By Heauen &amp; happines, I know not what this meanes;</L>
<L>Yet were the King not sodainly return'd,</L>
<L>And crau'd our swift attendance; I would sift</L>
<L>And try this language strangely.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is the King return'd?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ios.</SPEAKER>
<L>He is, and safely.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kip.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then my hate, Ile giue thee fire to worke on.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>So will I; I'm arm'd with able mischiefe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>And my plots</L>
<L>Shall runne as fast to ayd and second you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ios.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ladies, shake hands with passion, and let's ioyne</L>
<L>To meete the King with royall cheerefulnesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, not I;</L>
<L>Let them that loue their horror seeke it still:</L>
<L>Goodnesse I want, with him is all thats ill.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>You may report our speeches; say, our ioy</L>
<L>Is, we haue left no more he can destroy.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exe. Q. Alex. &amp; Marriam.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ios.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is a violent passion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let it rule;</L>
<L>Repentance needes must follow.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="15"/>
Enter Herod, P. Alex. Y. Ari<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>. Pheroas, and Attendants.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Welcome, O welcome to <HI>Ierusalem;</HI></L>
<L>May <HI>Herod</HI> liue for euer fortunate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>We thank you: Mother &amp; Sister, rise; let no knee bow</L>
<L>But to the Gods of <HI>Greece;</HI> by whose support</L>
<L>Wee stand vnshakt and vnremoou'd: but (me thinkes)</L>
<L>In this great vniuersall Rhapsodie</L>
<L>Of comfort and amazement, I doe misse</L>
<L>Two faire companious of my happinesse:</L>
<L>Where is my louely <HI>Marriam?</HI> what withdrawes</L>
<L>Her Mother <HI>Alexandra?</HI> Sure, my heart</L>
<L>Lookt for their entertainment.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ios.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gracious Sir,</L>
<L>Th'vnfortunate destruction of her Sonne,</L>
<L>The high Priest <HI>Aristobulus</HI> (late drownd</L>
<L>Within t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> Riuer <HI>Rigill</HI>) so takes vp</L>
<L>Their hearts with powerfull sorrow, that their minds</L>
<L>Are borne with nothing but calamity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>That guest is soone remoued; goe, my Sonnes,</L>
<L>Informe your Grandmother and Mother-Queene,,</L>
<L>How much I long to see them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis a worke</L>
<L>Worthy our duties.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Ioseph,</HI> goe, attend;</L>
<L>There's need of your assistance.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ex. P. Alex. Y. Ari. &amp; Ios.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes; and all I feare too weake to draw them:</L>
<L>Royall Sir, you are abus'd in your credulity;</L>
<L>It is not griefe but malice, bitter spleene,</L>
<L>An anger I may call Treason, which keepes backe</L>
<L>These two from noble duties: Sir, they say</L>
<L>You doe vsurpe, and are a Murderer,</L>
<L>And teach all yours to murder; that you are</L>
<L>No lawfull King of <HI>Israel;</HI> but a <HI>Greeke</HI></L>
<L>Descended basely; drawne from polluted blood:</L>
<L>Prophane, vnholy; nay, (indeed) what not</L>
<L>That Rancor can imagine? Sir, I feare</L>
<L>Your life is plotted on; a wrath like theirs,</L>
<L>So lowd, so publique, nay so impudent;</L>
<L>Is not without assistance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Brauely vrg'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good Sister, thinke not so; a losse like theirs</L>
<L>Will make dumbe patience muteny; beleeu't,</L>
<L><PB REF="16"/>
It moues much in my owne brest; as for plots,</L>
<L>Alas, what can they dreame of?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Desperate things.</L>
<L>Things which may shake your foot-hold; for, I feare</L>
<L>The Queene is turnd an <HI>Aspis,</HI> and will spread</L>
<L>Her fatall poyson ore you; if you doate,</L>
<L>The Lethargie will kill you: Sir, tis said,</L>
<L>Nay, t'will be prou'd she is incontinent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Incontinent! with whom?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>With him I blush to mention; <HI>Ioseph</HI> Sir,</L>
<L><HI>Ioseph</HI> my Husband wrongs you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace for shame;</L>
<L>Your Iealousie doth foole you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kip.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, take heede</L>
<L>Affection doe not blinde you: tis a staine,</L>
<L>Almost the whole world finds out; and a truth,</L>
<L>Not hidden, but apparant; pray you Sir,</L>
<L>Speake you what is reported.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis not fit,</L>
<L>Nor dare I credit Rumor, chiefly when</L>
<L>It speakes of such great persons; yet tis true,</L>
<L>Many vilde things are vtterd; nay indeed</L>
<L>Some prou'd I wish were hidden: but alas,</L>
<L>Who knowes not Slander's euer impudent?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe not giue truth that title; for you know,</L>
<L>It will be prou'd by many witnesses.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thart iealous Sister, and than such a fiend,</L>
<L>There is no worse companion: come, no more;</L>
<L>Should all the Prophets, Patriarchs, and Priests</L>
<L>Lodg'd in the holy Bookes of Israel</L>
<L>Come forth and tell this message, I would stand</L>
<L>Boldly and interpose them; for I know,</L>
<L>There is no truth to guard them; no nor faith.</L>
<L>O my Diuinest <HI>Marriam,</HI> how art thou</L>
<L>And thy great sweetnesse iniur'd? Th'vnblowne Rose,</L>
<L>The mines of Chrystall, nor the Diamond,</L>
<L>Are halfe so chaft, so pure and innocent.</L>
<L>O poore forsaken Vertue, how art thou</L>
<L>Torne downe by thy despisers, and consum'd</L>
<L>By th'enuious flame of the malicious?</L>
<L>But I am come to guard thee, and restore</L>
<L>Thy goodnesse backe with interest; for I vow</L>
<L><PB REF="16"/>
To heare naught but thy praises: heere shee comes;</L>
<STAGE>Enter P. Alex. Y. Arist. Ioseph, Marriam, &amp; Alexandra.</STAGE>
<L>Welcome my dearest, sweetest, happiest,</L>
<L>All that my longings looke for; thus, and thus,</L>
<L>Like a rich Chaine, my loue shall hang about thee;</L>
<L>And make the whole world doe thee reuerence;</L>
<L>Nay weepe not Mother; come, I know your care,</L>
<L>And beare an equall burthen: heere, O heere</L>
<L>Is the true Tombe of <HI>Aristobulus.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>You can dissemble royally; but that</L>
<L>Cannot cure mine Impostume.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Say not so;</L>
<L>You must forget the worke of accident.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Of accident? of plotted Massacre;</L>
<L>Murder beyond example: but there's left</L>
<L>A Hell to reckon with.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good sweet, no more;</L>
<L>Let not your Iudgement wrong you to suspect</L>
<L>Mine Innocence vniustly; for, I vow,</L>
<L>Neuer came death so neare me; or did force</L>
<L>My teares in such aboundance; but you know,</L>
<L>Earth must not question Heauen: Yet to shew</L>
<L>My faire affection to your Princely Sonne;</L>
<L>Within an Vrne of Gold, Ile lodge his bones;</L>
<L>And to his Funerall Rites, adde such a Pompe,</L>
<L>As shall amaze Inuention; and besides,</L>
<L>There's not an eye in all <HI>Ierusalem,</HI></L>
<L>But shall drop sorrow for him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Funerals are</L>
<L>But wretched satisfactions.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kip.</SPEAKER>
<L>Note this pride.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, and her Daughters fullennesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why looks my louely <HI>Marriam</HI> downward, &amp; deiects</L>
<L>The glory of her bright eye? I had thought</L>
<L>My safe returne (which strikes a generall ioy</L>
<L>Through <HI>Iuda</HI> and <HI>Ierusalem,</HI> and makes</L>
<L>Mount <HI>Sion</HI> so triumphant) had not had</L>
<L>The power to kill her comforts: Louely one;</L>
<L>How haue I lost thy friendship; or, what Fiend</L>
<L>Sends this Diuorce betwixt vs?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your owne Dissimulation. Cruell Sir;</L>
<L>Y'aue dealt vniustly with me, and prophan'd</L>
<L><PB REF="17"/>
A Temple held you sacred.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>What, your selfe?</L>
<L>O doe not speake it; for to that blest Shrine</L>
<L>I haue beene so religious, that the world</L>
<L>Hath oft condemnd me of Idolatry:</L>
<L>And can you then accuse me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, and call</L>
<L>Your owne heart to be witnesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me then</L>
<L>Be strucke with fearefull Thunder.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, take heed;</L>
<L>Vengeance is quicke in falling.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let it come:</L>
<L>You call a Loue in question, that's as iust</L>
<L>As Equity or Goodnesse; by that power—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, you will now be periur'd; but Ile stay</L>
<L>That imputation from you: What became</L>
<L>Of your affection, when you bound that man;</L>
<L>If you miscarried in your worke at <HI>Rome,</HI></L>
<L>That he should see me poyson'd? Start you now?</L>
<L>O, twas a venom'd Complot.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, a word:</L>
<L>Y'are a faithlesse young man; and haue lost</L>
<L>The great hope I had in you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>By my life,</L>
<L>Hopes, and all fruitfull wishes; I'm of this</L>
<L>As Innocent as Silence: if my lips</L>
<L>Ere open'd to relate it; let me feele</L>
<L>Some sodaine fatall iudgement: Gracious Sir,</L>
<L>Search out this secret further, 'twill be found</L>
<L>There is more Treason breeding.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'm resolu'd.</L>
<L>Madam, you haue accus'd me; and I stand</L>
<L>So strongly on mine owne truth, that you must</L>
<L>Discouer your Informers: By that loue</L>
<L>Once you did faine to beare me; by that faith</L>
<L>Which should linke married couples; by the awe,</L>
<L>Duty and truth of Women; or if these</L>
<L>Be canceld with you fury; yet by that</L>
<L>Great power your King hath ore you, and to shun</L>
<L>The scourge of Torments, which I sollemnly</L>
<L>Will try to the extreamest; heere I bind,</L>
<L>Nay, doe command you, that vnfainedly</L>
<L>You tell me who inform'd you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>You haue laid</L>
<L>So great Commandments on me, that I dare</L>
<L>In no wise disobey you. Sir, it was</L>
<L><PB REF="17"/>
Lord <HI>Ioseph</HI> that inform'd me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha; <HI>Ioseph!</HI></L>
<L>O my abused confidence!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now it workes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kip.</SPEAKER>
<L>The fire begins to kindle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>But Ile bring</L>
<L>Fuell that shall inflame it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Ioseph?</HI> was't <HI>Ioseph?</HI> then tis time to feele</L>
<L>My cold dull vnbelieuing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ios.</SPEAKER>
<L>O pardon me;</L>
<L>It was my loue, not malice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, your lust,</L>
<L>And you shall buy it dearely: Call a Guard.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Animis, and a Guard.</STAGE>
<L>Haue I for this so often lost my selfe</L>
<L>Within the Labyrinth of her wanton eyes;</L>
<L>And am I now repaid with Treachery:</L>
<L>Ceaze on those wretched Creatures; <HI>Salumith,</HI></L>
<L>Stand forth, and what thy knowledge can approue</L>
<L>Against those Traytors, speake it; now mine eare</L>
<L>Lies open to my safety.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Brauely speake,</L>
<L>You shall haue strong supporters; now his eare</L>
<L>Is open, see you fill it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doubt me not.</L>
<L>Great Sir, with confidence as full of Truth,</L>
<L>As they are full of Treason; I auerre,</L>
<L>These, in your absence, haue abus'd your bed,</L>
<L>With most incestuous foule Adultery.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>All that's like goodnesse shield me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ios.</SPEAKER>
<L>Woman, looke vp;</L>
<L>The vault of Heauen is Marble; this vntruth</L>
<L>Will make it fall to kill thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let it come,</L>
<L>If I speake ought vniustly; all my words,</L>
<L>My blood and oath shall seale to.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Antipater, Pheroas, and Achitophel.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Antip.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good, let my loue perswade thee; doe not buze</L>
<L>Such foule things in his eares; his Maiestie</L>
<L>Is too much mou'd already.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good my Lord,</L>
<L>Let me discharge my duty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, for that,</L>
<L>I dare not to withstand; yet, questionlesse,</L>
<L>The Queene is not so wicked.—Goe, put home;</L>
<L>Y'aue all things to assist you:—Sirrah Iew,</L>
<L>Forget not thy preferment.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ach.</SPEAKER>
<L>Feare me not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now, what tumult's that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phe.</SPEAKER>
<L>O my dread Lord,</L>
<L><PB REF="18"/>
Grant me your gracious pardon; I must tell</L>
<L>A sad and heauy Story; yet most true:</L>
<L>And yet 'gainst such a person, as I feare</L>
<L>Your eare will not receiue it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speake; 'gainst whom?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Against the Queene.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>O sacred Truth, but thee,</L>
<L>I haue nor sword, nor armour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vtter it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Since your departure, to my hands she brought</L>
<L>This fatall Violl; saying, <HI>Pheroas,</HI></L>
<L>Thou art the Kings Cup-bearer; by my loue</L>
<L>I charge thee, when his Maiesty shall call</L>
<L>For wine, giue him this Potion; tis a draught</L>
<L>Shall crowne thee with great fortunes: I desir'd</L>
<L>To know the nature; shee, with solemne oathes,</L>
<L>Swore it was nothing but a wholsome drinke,</L>
<L>Compounded with such Art; that, tasting it,</L>
<L>You would doate of her beauty, and become</L>
<L>A very Slaue to her perfections:</L>
<L>I promis'd to performe it; yet my feare</L>
<L>Arguing with my Iudgement, made me try</L>
<L>The vertue on a Spaniel; and I found</L>
<L>It was an odious poyson.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wonderfull!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phe.</SPEAKER>
<L>After this triall, I demanded then,</L>
<L>From whom her Highnesse had it: she affirm'd,</L>
<L>From the Lord <HI>Ioseph;</HI> but by stricter search,</L>
<L>I found this Iew was he compounded it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ach.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe confesse the Queene of Israel</L>
<L>Commanded me to try my vtmost skill</L>
<L>In this most strong Confection; said it was</L>
<L>To proue the force of Simples: I, her Slaue,</L>
<L>Durst not to disobay her; yet suspect</L>
<L>Made me reueale it to this Noble-man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>How answer you this Treason?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Silently.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thats a confession.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, as good be dumbe,</L>
<L>As speake to eares are glewd vp; or a faith</L>
<L>Thats arm'd against beleeuing: but (great Sir)</L>
<L>If either of these open; then, beleeu't,</L>
<L>Was neuer wrong'd a greater innocence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="18"/>
<SPEAKER>Ios.</SPEAKER>
<L>Malice hath wrought vpon vs, and oretane</L>
<L>Our guiltlesse liues with vengeance: Hell it selfe</L>
<L>Is not more false then these are; yet, I know,</L>
<L>Nothing can saue vs but a Miracle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>The guilty euer plead thus; cursed chance,</L>
<L>To haue my Ioyes deuoure me: but, tis done;</L>
<L>Princes, your eares and Counsels.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Herod whispers with Ant. the Princes and Pheroas.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha! is't so,</L>
<L>Hath Mischiefe got the Conquest; then tis time</L>
<L>To change my disposition, and deceiue</L>
<L>Those which would else deceiue me; in this kinde,</L>
<L>It skils not whom we iniure, whom we blinde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, of my life all this is counterfait,</L>
<L>And this great Diuell inchants you; for these slaues,</L>
<L>They speake but what is taught them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Arist.</SPEAKER>
<L>On my life,</L>
<L>Our royall Mother's guiltlesse; doe not let</L>
<L>Their hatefull malice step betweene her life,</L>
<L>And your most gracious fauour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Princely youths,</L>
<L>Nature and loue deceiues you: wretched things,</L>
<L>What can you say to stay destruction?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>That w'are the Kings, and none are innocent,</L>
<L>Vnlesse he please to thinke so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Impudent!</L>
<L>Is that all thou canst vtter? Haue I liu'd</L>
<L>To see thee grow thus odious, to forsake</L>
<L>The chast imbracements of a royall bed,</L>
<L>For an incestuous Letcher; to become</L>
<L>The Peoples scorne, the honest Matrons curse,</L>
<L>The Tribes disgrace, and <HI>Israels</HI> obloquy;</L>
<L>Nay more, the whole worlds wonder, and a staine</L>
<L>Nere to be washt off from <HI>Ierusalem?</HI></L>
<L>O mine afflicted honor!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kip.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heere's a change.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Tempest neuer lookt for.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Packe for shame,</L>
<L>Runne to thine owne destruction: What, a Whore?</L>
<L>A poysoning Whore? a baudy Murderesse?</L>
<L>Nay, more; a treacherous Strumpet? O that Heauen</L>
<L>Had made mine anger Lightning, that it might</L>
<L><PB REF="19"/>
Destroy thee in a moment.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, stay;</L>
<L>Can your true goodnesse thinke me culpable?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is it not prou'd apparant?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then be dumbe,</L>
<L>Be dumbe for euer <HI>Marriam;</HI> if you thinke</L>
<L>I can be guilty, who is innocent?</L>
<L>Madam, you are my Mother; O call vp</L>
<L>Your worst imaginations, all the scapes</L>
<L>Both of mine Infance, Childhood or ripe yeares,</L>
<L>And if the smallest shadow in them all</L>
<L>Betoken such an error, curse me still,</L>
<L>Let me finde death with horror; otherwise,</L>
<L>Silence and patience helpe me. Sir, tis fit</L>
<L>You plead your owne cause; I am conquered.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ios.</SPEAKER>
<L>There's but one true Iudge ouer <HI>Israel,</HI></L>
<L>And hee knowes I am guiltlesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis the Plea</L>
<L>Of euery guilty person: <HI>Animis,</HI></L>
<L>Conuay those wicked creatures, with your Guard,</L>
<L>Vnto the market-place, and there in sight</L>
<L>Of all the people, cause the Hangman take</L>
<L>Their curst head from their bodies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay, great Sir,</L>
<L>Doe not an act t'amaze all <HI>Israel;</HI></L>
<L>O looke with mercies eyes vpon the Queene;</L>
<L>The Innocent Queene our Mother; let not Slaues</L>
<L>Blast her with false reproches; be a God</L>
<L>And finde out Truth by Miracle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Arist.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more? yes sure, if euery word I speake</L>
<L>Should naile me to destruction: Mighty Sir,</L>
<L>Fauour your owne repentance, doe not spill</L>
<L>The innocent bloud vniustly; for th'account</L>
<L>Is heauy as damnation: to your selfe,</L>
<L>And to your owne, become a <HI>Daniel.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile heare no more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>O sacred Sir, you must;</L>
<L>Vpon my knees I begge compassion;</L>
<L>Compassion for my Mother.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Arist.</SPEAKER>
<L>To this ground</L>
<L>Weele grow eternally; till you vouchsafe</L>
<L><PB REF="19"/>
To grant her mercy; or to giue her Cause</L>
<L>A larger course of tryall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Once againe,</L>
<L>I charge you to forget her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>How, forget</L>
<L>The chast wombe which did beare vs; or the paps</L>
<L>Which gaue vs sucke? Can there in Nature be</L>
<L>A Lethargie so frozen?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Arist.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, what's more;</L>
<L>Can we forget her holy Stocke, deriu'd</L>
<L>From all the blessed Patriarchs, in whom</L>
<L>You and our selues are glorious? O, dread Sir,</L>
<L>Haue mercy on her goodnesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mercy, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>How am I vext with importunity;</L>
<L>Away to Execution: if againe</L>
<L>I doe command tis fatall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Arist.</SPEAKER>
<L>And if we</L>
<L>Indure it, let vs perish; brother draw,</L>
<STAGE>The Princes draw.</STAGE>
<L>And let our good swords guard her: Sir, y'aue broke</L>
<L>A linke in Natures best chaine; and her death,</L>
<L>Conuerts vs to your mortall enemies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>What; am I brau'd by Traitors? Villaines, force</L>
<L>Way to the Execution, or you perish.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mother, hold life but one houre and wee'l rescue you.</L>
<STAGE>The Princes force through the guard; Antipater drawes &amp; stands before Herod; all the rest conuey away the Prisoners; Alexandra wringing her hands.</STAGE>
<L>Did euer Kings owne bowels thus become</L>
<L>The <HI>Typhon</HI> of sedition; or, can't be,</L>
<L>I could beget these Serpents? Ift be so</L>
<L>Vnder the <HI>Aetna</HI> of their damned pride,</L>
<L>Ile smoother and consume them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, I know</L>
<L>Your wisedome such, as can discerne what tis</L>
<L>At once to feare, to suffer, and to dye,</L>
<L>By th'hand of sterne ambition; which, ith' end,</L>
<L>Makes still her habitation like the place</L>
<L>Where poyson growes, so naked and so bare</L>
<L>That dust disdaines t'abide there.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Passing true;</L>
<L>But Ile root out that vengeance: yet againe,</L>
<L>When I awake my memory, to looke</L>
<L>Vpon her sweetnesse, goodnesse, and conceiue,</L>
<L>That no affaire, no wisedome, or fond zeale,</L>
<L><PB REF="20"/>
Which oft attainteth others, could touch her;</L>
<L>O then, me thinkes, I might at least haue breath'd,</L>
<L>Before I had condemn'd her; Iustice should</L>
<L>Ith darke of these confusions, borne a Torch</L>
<L>Before Truth and mine anger: but alas,</L>
<L>Folly and Rashnesse led me; and I'ue lost</L>
<L>All my delight at one throw. <HI>Antipater,</HI></L>
<L>Goe, runne, flye; O, stay the Execution.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Willingly. Yet please you first to thinke</L>
<L>Whether the act hurt not your Maiestie;</L>
<L>Kings, in these waighty causes, must not play</L>
<L>At fast and loose; their wordes are Oracles;</L>
<L>And iudgement should pursue them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good, no more; goe stay the Execution.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not on earth is there a man more willing;</L>
<L>Yet, when Kings condemne themselues of rashnesse,</L>
<L>Who can blame contempt to follow after?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lord to see how time is lost with talking.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Antip.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am gone.</L>
<STAGE>Offers to goe and returnes.</STAGE>
<L>Yet Sir, beleeu't; the Maiesty which strikes</L>
<L>Against contempt shall nere recouer it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant,</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, I can vanish quickly; yet, behold,</L>
<L>Heere's one can saue <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>y labour.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Pheroas,</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speake my Lord; where is my Queene?</L>
<L>O, where's my <HI>Marriam?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, she is dead.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dead? Be the world dead with her; for on earth</L>
<L>There's no life but her glory: yet declare</L>
<L>How dyed the wofull Lady?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Like a Saint.</L>
<L>Like did I say? O Sir, so farre beyond,</L>
<L>That neuer Saint came neere her president:</L>
<L>She did not goe, as one that had beene led</L>
<L>To take a violent parting; but as Fate</L>
<L>Had in her owne hands thrust her Destiny,</L>
<L>Saying, or liue or dye: whilst she, that knew</L>
<L>The one and th'others goodnesse, did agree</L>
<L>Onely to dye as th'act most excellent.</L>
<L>Her Mothers bitter railings, all the cries</L>
<L><PB REF="20"/>
Of the amazed People, mou'd not her;</L>
<L>No not one poore small twinckle of her eye:</L>
<L>But, with a constancie, that would outface</L>
<L>The brazen front of terror; she assends</L>
<L>Vp to the fatall Scaffold; and but once</L>
<L>Lookt round about the people: then lifts vp</L>
<L>Her snow-white hands to Heauen;</L>
<L>Talkes to it as if she had beene in it: then fals downe</L>
<L>Vpon her humble knees; which, as they bent,</L>
<L>You might behold humility retire</L>
<L>Downe to her heart; and left within her eyes</L>
<L>Nothing but sweetnesse flaming: whilst vpon</L>
<L>And round about her, Maiestie did hang,</L>
<L>And cloath her as a garment: to be briefe,</L>
<L>Shee tooke the stroke, not as a punishment;</L>
<L>But a reward; so Saint-like hence she went.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Enough, too much; th'ast slaine me <HI>Pheroas;</HI></L>
<L>O, I haue lost in her death more true ioyes,</L>
<L>Then Heauen can giue or, earth is worthy of:</L>
<L>I am a Traitor to my selfe and loue;</L>
<L>To Nature, Vertue, Beauty, Excellence;</L>
<L>I haue destroy'd the whole world; for but her,</L>
<L>It had no Soule, nor mouing; no delig<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>t,</L>
<L>No triumph, glory, or continuance:</L>
<L>I cannot liue to lose her; call her backe,</L>
<L>Or I shall dye complaining.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is strange</L>
<L>Can the dead be awaken'd?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Easily Sir,</L>
<L>My sighes shall breath life in her; and my voyce</L>
<L>Rouze her, as doth a Trumpet; nay, more lou'd</L>
<L>Then either winde or Thunder: canst thou thinke</L>
<L>That I can liue without her; she, to whom</L>
<L>The whole world was a Theater, where men</L>
<L>Sate viewing her good actions; she, that had</L>
<L>As much right vnto Paradise, as Kings</L>
<L>Ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e to their Courts and Kingdomes; shee that lent</L>
<L>Mintage to others beauties; for, none are</L>
<L>Or good, or faire, but such as lookt like her:</L>
<L>Shee, in whose body sweetly was contain'd</L>
<L><PB REF="21"/>
Th'Easterne Spicery, the Westerne treasure,</L>
<L>And all the world holds happy: may it be</L>
<L>That I can liue and want her? or, could I</L>
<L>With one sad breath destroy her? she, that had</L>
<L>(In her owne thoughts) read all that ere was writ,</L>
<L>To better, or instruct vs: Shee, that knew</L>
<L>Heauen so well on Earth; that, being there,</L>
<L>S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ee finds no more then she did thinke on heere;</L>
<L>And haue I kild her? She, whose very dreames</L>
<L>Were more deuout then our Petitions;</L>
<L>Haue I prophan'd that Temple? Fall, O fall</L>
<L>Downe to the gro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>nd and perish; nere looke vp,</L>
<L>But when or Blastings, Mildewes, Lightenings,</L>
<L>O<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> poysonous Serenes strike thee. <HI>Herod,</HI> heere,</L>
<L>O heere, digge vp thy graue with sorrow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fie, tis vnfit Greatnesse should yeeld to passion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'are a foole;</L>
<L>He that not mournes for her, will neuer mourne;</L>
<L>But is worse then the Diuell. <HI>Marriam,</HI></L>
<L>O <HI>Marriam;</HI> thou that through the Spheares</L>
<L>(As through so many golden Beads) hast runne,</L>
<L>In one poore moment, to felicity;</L>
<L>Looke downe vpon thy Vassall, me thy Slaue,</L>
<L>And see how much I languish: let thine eye</L>
<L>Guild my complaints, and cheere my misery.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phe.</SPEAKER>
<L>O oyall Sir, take better comfort;</L>
<L>There was nere on Earth a Creature worth your sorrow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, you <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ie; deadly and falsly; for she doth deserue</L>
<L>The teares of men and Angels: Sh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e, O shee,</L>
<L>Of who<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> the Ancients prophesied, when first</L>
<L>They made all Vertues Females; She, that was</L>
<L>The first and best faire Copie, from whose lines</L>
<L>The world might draw perfection: She, not worth</L>
<L>The teares of all thats liuing? D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>lnesse, goe;</L>
<L>Packe from my sight for euer: O, 'twas thou,</L>
<L>Thou that didst make me kill her: hence, auaunt;</L>
<L>By all that's good or holy; if, from hence</L>
<L>Thou ere presume to see me, or come neere</L>
<L><PB REF="21"/>
The place of my abiding; 'tis thy death,</L>
<L>As certaine as Fate spoke it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phe.</SPEAKER>
<L>O my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away; reply, and I will kill thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do not offend him further; vanish Sir.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Pheroas.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Animis.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ani.</SPEAKER>
<L>To Armes my Lord, to Armes: your Princely Sonnes,</L>
<L>Attended by the people, stand betweene</L>
<L>The Towne of <HI>Bethlem</HI> and <HI>Ierusalem;</HI></L>
<L>Their Ensignes spread, their Bowes bent, and their Swords</L>
<L>Wauing like wings of Eagles: Sir, they vow</L>
<L>Reuenge for their Mothers death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>On whom?</L>
<L>On you, the Citty; but especially,</L>
<L>Vpon the Prince <HI>Antipater.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more,</L>
<L>Th'are angry surges, which with one poore blast,</L>
<L>Ile make <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>all to the Center; troubled thoughts,</L>
<L>Rest till this storme be ouer: happy man,</L>
<L>Ile make thee tread vpon them; this day shall</L>
<L>Be thy Coronation; but their Funerall.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exe. all but Ant.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Twas a braue Lesson that <HI>Egystus</HI> taught,</L>
<L>And <HI>Clitemnestra</HI> writ religiously:</L>
<L><HI>Sinne safest way to sinne; None or alone;</HI> both excellent,</L>
<L>Yet <HI>Herod</HI> liues vnwrong'd and vnremou'd.</L>
<L>The Sonnes of <HI>Oedipus,</HI> in life, nor after death,</L>
<L>Agreed but once; which was, t'imprison <HI>Oedipus;</HI></L>
<L>An act of no small wonder: O, but Boyes,</L>
<L>Ile mount a world aboue you; t'imprison, is</L>
<L>Still to haue danger neere me: tut, tis death,</L>
<L>Death that my aymes doe shoote at: Ile inuent</L>
<L>What none shall alter: fie, tis nothing worth,</L>
<L>By Worth, by Birth, by Choyce, by Chance to bee a King;</L>
<L>But so to climbe I choose, as all may feare and wonder;</L>
<L>Feare to attempt the like, and wonder how I wrought it;</L>
<L>Curst be he (in this case) that craues his Fathers blessing;</L>
<L>My Throane must be my Fathers Monument;</L>
<L>My Raigne built on his ruine: but how? how? witlesse, how?</L>
<L>Aske how, and seeke a Crowne? By Poyson; no, by Sword;</L>
<L><PB REF="22"/>
Sword; no, by Subtilty: O Hell awake, awake;</L>
<L>And once for all instruct me.</L>
<STAGE><P>Dumbe Shew.</P>
<P>Musique: and, Enter Miscipsa, Iugurth, Adherball, Hiempsall, Miscipsa makes them ioyne hands, and giues each a Crowne, and departs: then in mounting the tribunall, Hiempsall and Adher∣ball sit close to keepe out Iugurth, he diuides them by force, Hiempsall offers to draw, and Iugurth stabs him; Adherball flies and comes in againe with the Roman Senators, they seeme to reconcile them; and being departed, Iugurth stabs Adherball, and leaues at Antipaters feete a Scrowle.</P></STAGE>
<L>O resolute <HI>Iugurth;</HI> what afford'st thou me?</L>
<L><HI>Non mordent mortui;</HI> Dead men doe not bite:</L>
<L>True, noble Bastard: <HI>Iugurth,</HI> in thy light</L>
<L>Thy Brothers dwelt; O <HI>Iugurth,</HI> so doe mine:</L>
<L>Thou kild'st them <HI>Iugurth; Iugurth,</HI> so must I.</L>
<L>Thus sing we seuerall Descant on one plain-song, <HI>Kill:</HI></L>
<L>Foure parts in one, the Meane excluded quite:</L>
<L>The Base sings deepely, <HI>Kill;</HI> the Counter-<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>nor, <HI>Kill;</HI></L>
<L>The Tenor, <HI>Kill, Kill;</HI> the Treble, <HI>Kill, Kill, Kill:</HI></L>
<L>In Diapason <HI>Kill</HI> is the Vnison, s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>auen times redoubled;</L>
<L>And so oft must I kill: as, first the King,</L>
<L>(His Wife is past) two Sonnes, two Brethren, and a Sister;</L>
<L>And thinke not but I can: can; nay, but I will:</L>
<L>I am no puny in these Documents:</L>
<L>The Tyger, tasting blood; finds it to sweet to leaue it:</L>
<L>The Hauke, once made to pre<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>, takes all delight in preying;</L>
<L>The Virgin, once deflour'd, thinks pleasure to grow cōmon;</L>
<L>And can I then stop in a middle way?</L>
<L>Cl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ze fou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ains, riuers dry; pluck vp the ro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ts bowes perish;</L>
<L>Banish the Sunne, the Moone and Starre doe vanish:</L>
<L>And, were it to obscure the world, and sp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>yle</L>
<L>Both Man and Beast, Nature, and euery thing;</L>
<L>Yet would I doo't; and why? I must, and will be King.</L>
<L>Kingly <HI>Antipater.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="22"/>
<SPEAKER>Iosephus</SPEAKER>
<L>Neuer grew Pride more high, more desperate;</L>
<L>Nor euer could the Arrogance of man</L>
<L>Finde out a Breast more large and spacious:</L>
<L>But Fate and he must wrestle. Let mee now</L>
<L>Intreat your worthy Patience, to containe</L>
<L>Much in Imagination; and, what Words</L>
<L>Cannot haue time to vtter; let your Eyes</L>
<L>Out of this dumbe Shew, tell your Memories.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><P>Dumbe Shew.</P>
<P>Enter at one dore, with Drums and Colours, P. Alexander, and Y. Aristobulus, with their Army; at another, Herod and An∣tipater, with their Army: as they are ready to encounter, Enter Augustus with his Romans betweene them; they all cast downe their weapons at his feet and kneels; he raises Herod and sets him in his Chayre makes Alexander and Aristobulus kisse his feet; which done, they offer to assaile Antipater, Herod steps between, Augustus reconciles them; then whispering with Herod, Au∣gustus takes three Garlands and crownes the three Sonnes, He∣rod placing Antipater in the midst, and so all depart, Antipater vsing ambitious countenances.</P></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iosephus</SPEAKER>
<L>The Sonnes of <HI>Marriam,</HI> hauing met the King,</L>
<L>Are ready for Encounter; but are staid</L>
<L>By th'awe of great <HI>Augustus,</HI> at whose feete</L>
<L>They cast their Liues and Weapons: hee, with frownes</L>
<L>Chides the two angry Princes; yet commands</L>
<L>The Father to forgiue them; peace is made:</L>
<L>Onely against <HI>Aniipater</HI> they bend</L>
<L>The fury of their courage; which the King</L>
<L>Withstands and reconciles them: all made sound;</L>
<L><HI>Augustus</HI> giues them Garlands, and installs</L>
<L>Them equall Captaines ouer <HI>Palestine:</HI></L>
<L>But yet <HI>Antipater,</HI> by <HI>Herods</HI> meanes,</L>
<L>Gets the precedence and Priority:</L>
<L>How in that <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>hrong he iustles; tis your Eyes,</L>
<L>And no<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> my Tongue must censure: this we hope</L>
<L>Our Scale is still assending; and you'le <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>nde</L>
<L>Better, and better; and the Best behinde.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<TRAILER>Finis Actus secundae</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="3" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="23"/>
<HEAD>ACT. 3. Scoena. 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Salumith, and Lyme the Mason.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>You must take my directions.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lym.</SPEAKER>
<L>Any thing your Ladiship will haue me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou shalt informe his Maiesty; his Sons hired thee, when his Highnes should approach to view the buildings, by seeming chance to throw some stone vpon him, which might crush him to pieces. Do this and thou shalt gaine by't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lym.</SPEAKER>
<P>A halter, or some worse thing; for (Madam) the least stone that is imployd about the Temple, is 20. Cubits broad, and 8. thicke, and thats able to break a mans necke without a halter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>No matter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lym.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, and it be no matter for breaking a neck (though it be an ill Ioynt to set) Ile venter a swearing for't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe, and liue rich and happy; hold, there's gold.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lym.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, if I can get my liuing by swearing and forswea∣ring; Ile neuer vse other occupation.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Handsaw.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>Neighbour <HI>Lyme;</HI> newes, newes, newes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lym.</SPEAKER>
<L>What newes, Neighbour <HI>Handsaw?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>Marry Sir, Charity has got a new coate; for I saw a</L>
<L>Beadle iust now whipping on Statute-lace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>And what's become of Liberality?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cry you m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>rcy Lady, faith she went like a Baud at a</L>
<L>Carts taile, roaring vp and downe; but her purse was empty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Th art deceiu'd her hand is euer open,</L>
<L>And to desert she<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>s free; behold else.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<P>This is more of Liberality, (as you call it) then I haue found, since I began first to build the Temple.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lym.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or I either.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall haue more,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e poure it on in showers; performe but my commandments.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<P>Madam, by my Handsaw &amp; Compasse, I will do any thing; say, speake, sweare, and forsweare any thing your Ladi∣ship can inuent or purchase.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hark your ea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>es.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Whisper.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hum, ha; pretty, pretty; Ile play my part t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> tittle; Neighbour, looke to yours: nay, and Ile doe it presently; for the King is now comming to the Temple, and I came to call you Neighbour; wee'l doe it there.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="23"/>
<SPEAKER>Lym.</SPEAKER>
<L>What else; a man may bee forsworne in any place,</L>
<L>Citty, Court or Country, has no difference.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>About it then; be constant wary and y'are for<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>unate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lym.</SPEAKER>
<P>Feare vs not, if you want any more to be forsworne, giue me your money, Ile presse a dozen <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>radefinen shall doe it as well as any Scribe in all <HI>Ierusalem.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>I or Publican either.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away then.</L>
<STAGE>Exe. Lym. &amp; Han.</STAGE>
<L>Thus catch we hearts with gold; thus Spiders can</L>
<L>Poyson poore Flyes, and kill the innocent man.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Antipater with a Letter, and Animis.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ani.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be swift as Lightning; for the cause requires it:</L>
<L>Such paper-plots are inuisible Goblins;</L>
<L>Pinching them most, which doe least iniury.</L>
<L>Y are arm'd with full instructions.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ani.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, I am.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Letters are <HI>Chrysanders,</HI> and not mine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ani.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know it well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away then, outflye Eagles; yet Sir, harke;</L>
<L>Carry your Countnance wisely, seeme to be</L>
<L>A Saint in thy deliuery.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ani.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, your care</L>
<L>Makes you too curious, feare me not.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Animis.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Within there.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Hillus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did your Excellence call?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>I did; what, is your Lesson got?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hil.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, vnto a sillable; my tongue</L>
<L>Hath po<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>son for your purpose, and I am</L>
<L>Confirm'd in euery circumstance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>The time, (at night;) the place, (the Bed-chamber;)</L>
<L>The manner, (arm'd;) the instruments, (their Swords.)</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tut, this is needlesse; Sir, my Quality</L>
<L>Needs not a twice instruction.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nobly said; hold, there's gold.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hil.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is a good perswader; right or wrong,</L>
<L>T<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>easure will make the dumbe man vse his tongue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>True; tis the sicke <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ans Balme, the Vsure<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>s Pledge,</L>
<L>And indeed all mens Maisters; goe away,</L>
<STAGE>Exit Hillus.</STAGE>
<L>The time's ripe for thy purpose; thus these Slaues</L>
<L>Runne post to Hell for shadowes; ha, <HI>Salumith:</HI></L>
<L>O my best Aunt and Mistris; y'are well met:</L>
<L><PB REF="24"/>
Neuer were times so tickle; nor, I thinke,</L>
<L>Stood innocence in more danger: would my life</L>
<L>Were lost, to thrust feares from you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhy, Princely Nephew, I'ue no cause to feare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis well you are so arm'd; indeed, a life</L>
<L>So good as yours, free, and religious,</L>
<L>Thinkes not on feare, or ill mens actions:</L>
<L>Yet Madam, still your state is slippery;</L>
<L>Belieue it while these Princes doe suruiue,</L>
<L>And dreame how you accus'd the Mother-Queene,</L>
<L>They still will practise 'gainst you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, and you;</L>
<L>The High-Priests death, and <HI>Marriams</HI> Tragedy,</L>
<L>VVill be obiected 'gainst you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis confest;</L>
<L>VV'are both marks of their vengeance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet so farre</L>
<L>Beyond them, Ile not feare them; heere's my hand,</L>
<L>I'ue markt them for destruction: since our fates</L>
<L>Haue equall danger; tis no reason but</L>
<L>They doe inioy like triumph; once againe,</L>
<L>Belieue it, they are sinking.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nobly said,</L>
<L>Mirror of Women, Angell, Goddesse, Saint.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Tryphon the Barber, with a Case of Instruments.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace, no more; heere comes mine Instrument.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>What, this; the Kings Barber, your doting Amorite?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>The same, obserue him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Try.</SPEAKER>
<L>O blessed Combe; thou spotlesse Iuory,</L>
<L>With which my Mistris <HI>Salumith</HI> once daind</L>
<L>To combe the curious felters of her hayre,</L>
<L>And lay each threed in comely equipage;</L>
<L>Sleepe heere in peace for euer; let no hand</L>
<L>(But mine henceforth) be euer so adacious,</L>
<L>Or daring as to touch thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pittifull foole, goe sleepe, or thoult runne mad els,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Try.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sizers, sweet Sizers; sharpe, but gentle ones;</L>
<L>That once did cut the Locks of <HI>Salumith;</HI></L>
<L>Making them in humility hang downe</L>
<L>On either side her cheekes, as 'twere to guard</L>
<L>The Roses, that there flourish: O, goe rest,</L>
<L>Rest in this peacefull Case; and let no hand</L>
<L><PB REF="24"/>
Of mortall race prophane you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sfoote, the Slaue</L>
<L>Will begger himselfe with buying new Instruments.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>O tis a piece of strange Idolatry.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Try.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tooth-pick, deare Tooth-pick; Eare-pick, both of you</L>
<L>Haue beene her sweet Companions; with the one</L>
<L>I'ue seene her picke her white Teeth; with the other</L>
<L>Wriggle so finely worme-like in her Eare;</L>
<L>That I haue wisht, with enuy, (pardon me)</L>
<L>I had beene made of your condition:</L>
<L>But tis too great a blessing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>What, to be made a Tooth-picke?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, youle spoyle all, if you interrupt him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Try.</SPEAKER>
<L>Salumith, <HI>O</HI> Salumith;</L>
<L>When first I saw thy golden Lockes to shine,</L>
<L>I brake my glasse; needing no Face, but thine:</L>
<L>When at those corrall Lips, I was a gazer;</L>
<L>Greedy of one sweet touch, I broke my Razor:</L>
<L>When to thy Cheekes, thou didst my poore Eyes call;</L>
<L>Away flew Sizers, Bason, Balls and all:</L>
<L>On y the Crisping-Irons I kept most deare;</L>
<L>To doe thee seruice heere and euery where.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not euery where good <HI>Triphon,</HI> some place still</L>
<L>Must be reseru'd for other purposes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Try.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bright Go-o-o-desse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well proceede;</L>
<L>What, at a stand? has true loue got the power,</L>
<L>To strike dumbe such a nimble wit?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Cry hem, pluck vp thy heart man? what, a polling shauing Squire, and strucke dead with a woman?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nothing so, he does but mocke, he loues not <HI>Salumith.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Try.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not loue you Lady? O strange blasphemy!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith, what wouldst thou do now but for a kisse of her hand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Try.</SPEAKER>
<L>What would I do? what not? O any thing.</L>
<L>Ile number all those Hayres my Sizers cut,</L>
<L>And dedicate those Numbers to her Shrine;</L>
<L>A Breath more loathsome then the Stench of <HI>Nile,</HI></L>
<L>Ile rectifie, and, for her sake, make pleasant;</L>
<L>A Face more black then any <HI>Aethiope,</HI></L>
<L>Ile scoure as white as Siluer; to attaine</L>
<L><PB REF="25"/>
But one touch of her finger, I'de beget</L>
<L>Things beyond wonder; stab, poyson, kill,</L>
<L>Breake mine owne necke, my friends, or any mans.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Spoke like a daring seruant; harke thine eare;</L>
<L>Doe this and haue thy wishes.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>They whisper.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Try.</SPEAKER>
<L>What, but this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more beleeue it: why, tis nothing man;</L>
<L>Only, it asks some seriousnes and Art,</L>
<L>By which to moue the King, and gaine beleefe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Try.</SPEAKER>
<L>But shall I haue a k<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>sse from that white hand,</L>
<L>Which gripes my heart within it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, you shall; tis there, pay your deuotion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>T<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>y.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then by this kisse Ile do it; h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ney kisse</L>
<STAGE>Kisses her hand.</STAGE>
<L>There's resol tion in thee, and I'm fixt</L>
<L>To doc it swiftly, quickly; from my lip</L>
<L>Thy sweet taste shall not part, till I haue spoke</L>
<L>All that your wishes looke for: boast of this;</L>
<L>Y'aue bought two Princes liues with one poore kisse.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Spoke like a noble Seruant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nephew, true;</L>
<L>Let him and's follies wrestle; from their birth</L>
<L>We will bring out our safeties; Villaines, we know</L>
<L>Are sometimes Stilts, on which great men must goe.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Herod with his sword drawne, in his other hand a Letter, driuing before him P. Alexander, and Y. Aristobulus, Animis, Hillus, Lime and Handsaw following Herod; Antip. steps betweene Herod and the Princes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. Alex. Y. Arist.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, as y'are royall, heare vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Villaines, Traytors, Vipers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>In the name</L>
<L>Of goodnesse and of good men; what hand dare</L>
<L>Be rais'd against his Soueraigne? Gracious Sir,</L>
<L>Let not your rage abuse you; there's none heere</L>
<L>That your word cannot slaughter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Giue me way;</L>
<L>Shall my owne blood destroy me? that I gaue</L>
<L>Ile sacrifice to Iustice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet Sir, hold.</L>
<L>Heare but our innocent answere.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Arist.</SPEAKER>
<L>If we proue</L>
<L>Guilty, let tortures ceaze vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>O my Lord,</L>
<L>Tis a becomming Iustice; heare them speake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>What, Villaines that are arm'd against me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="25"/>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis not so; Nephewes, deare Nephewes,</L>
<L>Throw at his Highnes feete, these ill becomming weapons;</L>
<L>In this case, they doe not guard but hurt you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>We obey; and, with our weapons offer vp our liues,</L>
<L>To haue our cause but heard indifferently.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Arist.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, there's no greater innocence on earth</L>
<L>Iniur'd then our alleageance: let but truth</L>
<L>Accuse vs in a shadow; spare vs not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>But truth accuse you? O strange impudence!</L>
<L>Th'art not of Brasse, but Adamant: seest thou this,</L>
<L>This man you hir'd with stone to murder me;</L>
<L>This man with timber; both you wrought to staine</L>
<L>The sacred building with foule Paricide. Is not this true?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lym. Han.</SPEAKER>
<P>Most true (my Lord) wee will both bee for∣sworne vnto it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Falshood, th'art grown a mighty one, when these;</L>
<L>These Slaues shall murder Princes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, not these</L>
<L>Your vilde acts doe destroy you: Speake, my Lord;</L>
<L>Did not you see these in the dead of night,</L>
<L>Arm'd with their weapons, watch at my Chamber doore,</L>
<L>Intending to assault me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis most true;</L>
<L>And had I not with threats and some exclaimes</L>
<L>Remou'd them, you had perisht.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wonderfull.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>O truth, for shame awaken; this Slaue will</L>
<L>Exile thee from all Mankinde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>What, doth this</L>
<L>Bristle your guilty spirits? No, Ile come</L>
<L>Neerer vnto your Treasons; heer's your hands,</L>
<L>Your own hands, most vnnaturall: Sister, see;</L>
<L>See, mine <HI>Antipater;</HI> (<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>or I know, you both</L>
<L>Are perfect in their hands and Characters)</L>
<L>This Letter did they traitrously conuey</L>
<L>Vnto <HI>Chrysander,</HI> which commands our Powers,</L>
<L>And Conquests won in <HI>Greece;</HI> inciting him</L>
<L>To breake his firme alleageance, and to ioyne</L>
<L>His strength with theirs, to worke our ouerthrow.</L>
<L>Speake, our Centurion; did not you receiue</L>
<L>This Letter from <HI>Chrysander?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ani.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, I did.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="26"/>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>And that it is their owne hands, witnesse you;</L>
<L>And you; and all that know them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am strooke dumbe with wonder; I should sweare</L>
<L>This were your own hands Nephews.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>By my hopes;</L>
<L>If it be false, tis strangely counterfeit;</L>
<L>The Slaue that did it had a cunning hand,</L>
<L>And neere acquaintance with you: but, deare Sir,</L>
<L>It shall be gracious in you to conceiue</L>
<L>The best of these misfortunes: who, that knowes</L>
<L>The world, knowes not her mischieues; and how Slaues</L>
<L>Are euer casting Mines vp; for my part,</L>
<L>(Though there's no likelihood) I will suppose,</L>
<L>This is, and may be counterfeit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>And so will I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>But neuer I, it is imposs<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ible.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, I beseech you, howsoere you lose</L>
<L>The force of Nature, or the touch of blood;</L>
<L>Lose not the vse of Iustice; that should liue,</L>
<L>When both the rest are rotten: all these proofes</L>
<L>Are false as Slander, and the wo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ke hew'd out</L>
<L>Only by malice; when w'are tane away,</L>
<L>Tis you your selfe next followes: why alasse,</L>
<L>We are your Armour; he that would strike home,</L>
<L>And hit you soundly, must vnbuckle vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Arist.</SPEAKER>
<L>Besides Sir, please you either send, or call</L>
<L><HI>Chrysander</HI> home (whom we haue euer held,</L>
<L>A noble, free, and worthy Gentleman)</L>
<L>And, if he doe accuse vs; we will throw</L>
<L>Our liues to death with willingnesse; nay more,</L>
<L>Plead guilty to their Slanders.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>In my thoughts</L>
<L>This is a noble motion; heare them Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>It will renowne your patience; Sacred Sir,</L>
<L>Let me begge for my Nephewes; you haue said</L>
<L>You tooke delight to heare me; heare me now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>S'foote, y'are too earnest, and will spoyle vs all;</L>
<L>Begge with a scuruy cold Parenthesis.</L>
<L>Sir, (though I know; in this case, minutes are</L>
<L>Irrecouerable losses) yet, you may</L>
<L>(If't please you) grant them their Petition.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="26"/>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'm resolu'd,</L>
<STAGE>Enter Tryphon.</STAGE>
<L><HI>Chrysander</HI> shall be sent for: ha, how now?</L>
<L>Why star'st thou? why art breathlesse?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Try.</SPEAKER>
<L>O my Lord,</L>
<L>My gracious Lord, heare me; I must disclose</L>
<L>A treason foule and odious: these your Sonnes,</L>
<L>Your Princely Sonnes, chiefly Prince <HI>Alexander,</HI></L>
<L>By fearefull threats, and golden promises,</L>
<L>Haue labour'd me, that when I should be cald,</L>
<L>To trim your Highnesse beard, or cut your hayre;</L>
<L>I then should lay my Razor to your throat,</L>
<L>And send you hence to Heauen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant. Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>O vnnaturall!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Villaine, speake this againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. Alex. Y. Arist.</SPEAKER>
<L>Villaine, speak truth, feare Iudgement.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Try.</SPEAKER>
<L>Briefly Sir, Prince <HI>Alexander,</HI> and <HI>Aristobulus</HI></L>
<L>Offer'd me heapes of gold to cut your throat,</L>
<L>When I should trim or shaue you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>From which, thus</L>
<L>Mine owne hand shall secure me; villaine, die,</L>
<STAGE>stabs Tryph.</STAGE>
<L>That knew'st a way to kill me; and henceforth,</L>
<L>What Slaue soeuer dare to fill mine eare</L>
<L>With tales of this foule nature, thus shall perish;</L>
<L>Ile not be tortur'd liuing: where's my Guard?</L>
<L>Handle those treacherous young men; and, with cordes,</L>
<L>Strangle them both immediately.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, O Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Arist.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heare vs; but heare vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Neuer, I am deafe;</L>
<L>Villaines, that hatch such execrable thoughts,</L>
<L>Vnfit for noble spirits, shall not breath:</L>
<L>Dispatch I say; for vnto time Ile raise</L>
<L>Such Trophees of Seuerity; that he</L>
<L>Which reads your Story with a bloody thought,</L>
<L>Shall tremble and forsake it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet that man</L>
<L>Seeing your Rigor, and our Innocence,</L>
<L>Shall turne his feare to pitty, and condemne</L>
<L>The malice of your rashnesse: Sir, to dye</L>
<L>Thus, as we doe, not guilty, is a death,</L>
<L>Of all, most blest, most glorious; for, it is</L>
<L>To braue death, not to feele it; and this end</L>
<L>Reuiues vs, but not kils vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Arist.</SPEAKER>
<L>Brother, true;</L>
<L>Let me imbrace thy goodnesse; for I know,</L>
<L><PB REF="27"/>
The last gaspe of a death thus innocent,</L>
<L>Hath no paine in it; and w'are sure to finde</L>
<L>Sweetnesse ith' shortnesse, all content of minde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pull, and dispatch them.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>They strangle the Princes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>This was well contriu'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>An act worth imitation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, mighty Sir,</L>
<L>You haue done Iustice brauely, on your head</L>
<L>Depends so many heads, and on your life</L>
<L>The liues of such aboundance; that, beleeu't,</L>
<L>Acts and Consents must not alone be fear'd;</L>
<L>But Words and Thoughts; nay very Visions,</L>
<L>In this case must be punish't: Ancient times,</L>
<L>(For Princes safeties) made our Dreames our Crimes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis true; and I am resolute to run a Course,</L>
<L>T'affright the proud'st Attempter; goe, conuay</L>
<L>Those bodies vnto Buriall: <HI>Antipater,</HI></L>
<L>Come neere me man; th'art now the only branch</L>
<L>Left of this aged Body; which, howere</L>
<L>Disdaind, for want of grafting; yet, Ile now</L>
<L>Make thee the chiefe, the best, and principall.</L>
<L>It is our pleasure, that with winged speed,</L>
<L>Forthwith you passe to <HI>Rome;</HI> and, in our name,</L>
<L>Salute the great <HI>Augustus;</HI> say, that age, griefe,</L>
<L>And some naturall sicknesse, hauing made</L>
<L>My minde vnfit for Gouernment; I craue,</L>
<L>He would confirme thee in the Royalty:</L>
<L>Which granted, I will instantly giue vp</L>
<L>To thee and to thy goodnesse, all I hold;</L>
<L>Either in Crowne, or Greatnesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gracious Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe not crosse my commandment; for I know</L>
<L>Thy sweet and modest temper: but away;</L>
<L>Fly in thy happy iourney; I presage,</L>
<L>Those which did hate my Youth, will loue mine Age.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heeresa b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>aue change, sweet Nephew; can you flye</L>
<L>Aboue the pit<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> you play in?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, sweet Aunt;</L>
<L>Nor in my flight will leaue you, could I shoote</L>
<L>Through Heauen, as through the ayre; yet would I beare</L>
<L>Thy goodnesse euer with me: how ere I rise,</L>
<L><PB REF="27"/>
Tis you alone shall rule <HI>Ierusalem.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, tis <HI>Antipater;</HI> goe, be fortunate:</L>
<L>I'ue other plots in working.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>So haue I:</L>
<L>The Kings death and her owne; till that be done,</L>
<L>Nothing is perfect; th'halfe way is but runne.</L>
<L>Ha! who's this? the noble <HI>Pheroas?</HI></L>
<STAGE>Enter Pheroas sickly.</STAGE>
<L>What chance makes my deare Vncle droope thus?</L>
<L>Doe not giue way to your discontentment.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pardon me, it is become my Maister; spacious mindes</L>
<L>Are not like little bosomes; they may presse</L>
<L>And crush disgraces inward; but the great,</L>
<L>Giues them full Field to fight in; and each stroke</L>
<L>Contempt doth strike is mortall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Say not so;</L>
<L>You may finde reparation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tell me where;</L>
<L>Not vpon earth; when reputation's gone,</L>
<L>Tis not in Kings to bring her backe againe:</L>
<L>I am a banisht out-cast, and what's more,</L>
<L>The scorne of those gaze on me: but a day</L>
<L>Will come, of Visitation, when the King</L>
<L>May wish these foule deeds vndone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, no more</L>
<L>W'are partners in your sorrowes; and how ere</L>
<L>The King doth yet smile on vs, we know well</L>
<L>The word of any Peasant hath full power</L>
<L>To turne vs topsie turuy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you there?</L>
<L>Nay, then you haue got feeling.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sensibly,</L>
<L>And feare, and will preuent it.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Achitophel singing, and Disease.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ACH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Come buy you lusty Gallants</L>
<L>These S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ples which I sell;</L>
<L>In all our dayes were neuer seene like these,</L>
<L>For beauty, strength, and smell:</L>
<L>Here's the King-cup, the Paunce, with the Violet,</L>
<L>The Rose that loues the shower,</L>
<L>The wholsome Gilliflower,</L>
<L>Both the Cowslip, Lilly,</L>
<L>And the Daffadilly;</L>
<L>With a thousand in my power.</L>
</LG>
<L><PB REF="28"/>
Why where are all my Customers? none come buy</L>
<L>Of the rare Iew that sels etern<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ty?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeed Maister I'm of your minde; for none of your</L>
<L>Drugges but sends a man to life euerlasting.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ach.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace knaue I say, here's in this little thing</L>
<L>A Iewell prizelesse, worthy of a King:</L>
<L>If any man so bold dare bee,</L>
<L>Vnseene, vnknowne to coape vvith me,</L>
<L>And giue the price which I demand;</L>
<L>Heere's treasure worth a Monarchs Land.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Harke how the Mou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ebanke sets out his ware.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phe.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, tis a noble Braggard; two dry'd frogs,</L>
<L>An ownce of Rats-bane, grease and Staues-aker,</L>
<L>Are all his ingredients.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace for shame,</L>
<L>Haue Charity before you; harke, obserue.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Achit. Sings.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ACH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Here's golden Amaranthus,</L>
<L>That true Loue can prouoke;</L>
<L>Of Horehound store, and poysoning Elebore,</L>
<L>With the Polipode of the Oake:</L>
<L>Here's chast Veruine and lustfull Eringo,</L>
<L>Health-preseruing Sage,</L>
<L>And Rue, which cures old Age;</L>
<L>With a world of others,</L>
<L>Making fruitfull Mothers:</L>
<L>All these attend mee as my Page.</L>
</LG>
<L>Come buy, come buy, vnknowne, vnseene,</L>
<L>The b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>st that is, or ere hath beene:</L>
<L>He tha, not asking what, dare coape,</L>
<L>May buy a wealth past thought, past hope.</L>
<L>Come buy, Come buy, &amp;c.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dis.</SPEAKER>
<P>Maister, faith giue mee leaue to make my Procla∣mation too, though not in rime; yet in as vnsensible meeter as may be.</P>
<L>If the Diuell any man prouoke,</L>
<L>To buy's owne mischiefe in a poake;</L>
<L>Or else, that hood-winckt he would climbe</L>
<L>Vp to the Gallowes ere his time;</L>
<L><PB REF="28"/>
If fooles would learne how to conuay</L>
<L>Their <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>riends the quite contrary way;</L>
<L>Come to my Maister, they shall haue</L>
<L>Their wish; for hee's a crafty knaue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ach.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sirrah, y'are saucy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fitter for your dish of knauery.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now <HI>Achitophel;</HI> what's this curious drugge</L>
<L>You make such boast of; may not I question it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ach.</SPEAKER>
<L>By no meanes Sir; he that will purchase this,</L>
<L>Must pitch and pay; but aske no questions.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not any?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ach.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, not any; doe you thinke</L>
<L>Perfection needs Encomiums?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dis.</SPEAKER>
<P>O my Lord, you may take my Maisters word at all times; for, being a Phisician, hee's the onely best member in a Common-wealth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>How proue you Physitians the best members?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dis.</SPEAKER>
<P>Because Madam, without them the world would in∣crease so fast, that one man could not liue by another.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Go to, y are a mad knaue: but come <HI>Achitophel,</HI></L>
<L>How prize you this rich Iewell? If't be fit</L>
<L>Only for Kings; tis for <HI>Antipater.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ach.</SPEAKER>
<L>The price is, two thousand Drachma's.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Once Ile proue mad for my priuate pleasure,</L>
<L>There's your price; giue me the I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ell;</L>
<L>Now it's bought &amp; sold, you may disc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ose the full perfection.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>h.</SPEAKER>
<L>There's reason f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>r my Lord, then know y'aue here</L>
<L>The strongest quickest killingst poyson, which</L>
<L>Learning or Art ere vtter'd; for one drop</L>
<L>Kils sooner then a Canon; yet so safe</L>
<L>And free from all suspition, that no eye</L>
<L>Shall see or swelling, pustule, or disease,</L>
<L>Rage or affrighting torment: but as death were</L>
<L>Kissing and not killing, hence they goe</L>
<L>Wrapt vp in happy Slumbers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis enough;</L>
<L>Goe, and as Art produces things like these,</L>
<L>Let me heare from you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ach.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Iew is all your Creature.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>chit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="29"/>
<SPEAKER>Dis.</SPEAKER>
<P>Though (my Lord) I did not trouble my braines, yet I bestir'd my stumps ere this worke was brought to passe; I know the waight of the Pestle and Morter, and though my hands lost some leather; yet they found labour worthy your Lordships remembrance.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, I vnderstand you, goe, there's gold.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Dis.</STAGE>
<L>Now my best Aunt and Vncle, see you this;</L>
<L>Heeres but a little substance; yet a strength</L>
<L>Able to beare a Kingdome euery way:</L>
<L>This shall bring safety to vs, and conduct</L>
<L><HI>Hered</HI> the way to Heauen: Vncle you</L>
<STAGE>Giues Pheroas the Poyson.</STAGE>
<L>Shall take it to your keeping; and as I</L>
<L>Direct you by my Letters, so imploy it;</L>
<L>How ere stormes yet hang ore vs, you shall finde,</L>
<L>I haue a Deity can calme the winde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Th'art excellent in all things; keepe thy way<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></L>
<L>What we admire, that we must obay.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<TRAILER>Finis Actus tertiae.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="4" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACT. 4. Scoena. 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Alexandra, and her Euenuch.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>But is it ce taine <HI>Pheroas</HI> is so sicke,</L>
<L>As Rumor doth giue out?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eue.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, he is;</L>
<L>Nor hath he euer since his Banishment</L>
<L>Cast vp his heauy count'nance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis most strange;</L>
<L>But iudgement still pursues him; yet Ile call</L>
<L>And visit his affliction; for although</L>
<L>His vvords accus'd my <HI>Marriam;</HI> tis his sinne</L>
<L>Not person, that I enuy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eue.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, here comes his Lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, you are wel encounter'd; I am sad</L>
<STAGE>Ent. Adda.</STAGE>
<L>That sadnesse thus afflicts you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ad.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'm bound vnto your goodnesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>How fares your noble Husband?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ad.</SPEAKER>
<L>Desperately ill;</L>
<L>His<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>cknesse Madam rageth like a Plague,</L>
<L>Once <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> neuer cured; tis his minde</L>
<L><PB REF="29"/>
That doth afflict his body; and that warre</L>
<L>Quickly brings on destruction.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whence should proceed these Passions?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ad</SPEAKER>
<L>All I can gather is his Banishment,</L>
<L>Which, drawing something to his Conscience,</L>
<L>Makes euery thing more mortall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Aduice and sufferance is a ready cure</L>
<L>For these distempered passions; and might I</L>
<L>But see him, I would boldly tender them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ad.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Highnesse may; for now he's comming forth</L>
<L>To change the ayre, not his affliction.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Pheroas sicke in a Chayre.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Leaue me, O leaue me to my selfe, that I may thinke</L>
<L>Vpon the tedious houres I'ue yet to liue.</L>
<L>O, what a Iourney hath that man to Heauen,</L>
<L>Whose Conscience is opprest with iniury;</L>
<L>Sinne, like so many Pullies hanging by,</L>
<L>To draw the Soule still downward: <HI>Herod;</HI> O <HI>Herod.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, what's this? sure I must sound him deeper:</L>
<L>How fare you Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phe.</SPEAKER>
<L>O Madam, Madam; I am full of miseries.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Discourse with Patience; she will comfort you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Patience? there is a worme hath bitten Patience off;</L>
<L>And, being entred, sucks my vitalls vp.</L>
<L><HI>Herod,</HI> loath'd <HI>Herod:</HI> O credulous <HI>Pheroas!</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why doe you call on <HI>Herod?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nothing now:</L>
<L>Was't not a strange thing, that he kild his Wife?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who doe you meane, <HI>Marriam?</HI></L>
<L>Indeed t'was easily done; but soundly sworne to.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phe.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, I feele a dagger.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let not her name offend you; she deseru'd</L>
<L>A death more horrid, and her end vvas iust:</L>
<L>O <HI>Pheroas,</HI> I hated her for that Act</L>
<L>More then the Scriech-Owle day; and vvould my selfe</L>
<L>Haue beene her Executioner; had not Law</L>
<L>Stept in twixt me and anger.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phe.</SPEAKER>
<L>O Madam, y'are deceiu'd; meerely decein'd:</L>
<L><PB REF="30"/>
I haue a Conscience tels me otherwise.</L>
<L>O my <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> leaue, torm<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> me not within,</L>
<L>Nor raise this strange rebellion: harke, they cry</L>
<L>Iudgement vpon a wretch; that wretch am I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>This sauors of distraction.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phe.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Hall, a hall; let all the deadly sinnes</L>
<L>Come in and here accuse me: Ile confesse,</L>
<L>Truth must no longer be obscur'd: why so;</L>
<L>All things are now prepar'd; the Iudge is set,</L>
<L>And wrangling Pleaders buzzing in his eares,</L>
<L>Makes Babel no confusion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whom doe you see Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Feare and a guilty Conscience; nay, what's more,</L>
<L>See where proud <HI>Herod</HI> and pale Enuy sits;</L>
<L>Poore <HI>Marriam</HI> standing at the Barre of death,</L>
<L>And her Accuser I, falsly opposing her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ad.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let not your passion worke thus.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Giue him leaue; Passion abates by venting.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eue.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is strange meditation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phe.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe confesse before the Mercy-seate</L>
<L>Of Men and Angels, I slew <HI>Marriam;</HI></L>
<L>'Twas I accus'd her falsly, I subornd,</L>
<L>Strucke her toth' heart with Slander; but her foes</L>
<L>Shall follow after when the H<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>bbub comes</L>
<L>And ouertakes me downward, downe below,</L>
<L>In Hell amongst the damned.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gentle Sir,</L>
<L>Name them which thus seduc'd you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pardon mee,</L>
<L>I dare not, nor I may not; you may guesse,</L>
<L>Their Characters are easie; for my selfe,</L>
<L>Let mine owne shame sleepe with me; I confesse,</L>
<L><HI>Marriam</HI> was chast as faire, all good, all vertuous.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>But yet, shee's dead.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phe.</SPEAKER>
<L>So are my Ioyes and comforts: O, till now</L>
<L>I had cleane lost my selfe; and as a man</L>
<L>Left in a Wildernesse, findes out no path</L>
<L>To carry him to safety; so was I</L>
<L>Distract, till this was vtter'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="30"/>
<SPEAKER>Q. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>You haue divulg'd a Mystery, whose truth</L>
<L>Shall sprinkle blood through all <HI>Ierusalem.</HI></L>
<L>O me, poore innocent <HI>Marriam,</HI> let thy soule</L>
<L>Looke downe on my reuengement; for thy sake,</L>
<L>I will so get all Greatnesse; faith I will.</L>
<L>Sir, I doe wish you may dye happy now;</L>
<L>Your free confession is a Sacrifice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, I thanke you; and belieu't for truth,</L>
<L>The hurly burly which but late I had</L>
<L>Is now appeas'd; Truth's a braue Secretary.</L>
<L>I could not rest before; yet now I feele</L>
<L>A calmenesse ouerspread me; and my minde,</L>
<L>Like a decayed Temple new adorn'd,</L>
<L>Shewes, as it nere was sullied.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'are happy Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, I am; for, with this peace of minde,</L>
<L>I finde my breath decaying; yet before</L>
<L>I take this long last Iourney, one thing more</L>
<L>I must disclose; then, all is perfitted.</L>
<L>Wife, reach me the Violl standing in my Study,</L>
<L>Of which I was so carefull, and did binde</L>
<L>Your selfe by Oath to looke to: goe, away;</L>
<STAGE>Exit Adda.</STAGE>
<L>Tis a new birth that Villany vvould bring forth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eue.</SPEAKER>
<L>More mischiefes yet in hatching?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>These actions leade you on to happinesse;</L>
<L>And for the penitent man, remission stands</L>
<L>Ready to fold him in her Christall armes:</L>
<L>Yet noble <HI>Pheroas,</HI> make me so much blest,</L>
<L>To know vvho plotte<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> <HI>Marriam's</HI> Ttagoe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>y</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Name it no more; ope not my vvound afresh;</L>
<L>Least, in th'incision, I should bleed to death:</L>
<L>I haue too much vpon me; adde to Fire,</L>
<L>Not Oyle, but Water; Seas will not raise his care,</L>
<L>Whose ship lies sanded on the hill Despaire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ad.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, here's the Violl.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Adda.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here's a little Compasse; but a mighty sound:</L>
<L>And in this little Thimble, lies strange Villany.</L>
<L>Madam, twas once prepared for the King;</L>
<L><PB REF="31"/>
And he from me deseru'd it; not from him</L>
<L>That bought it to destroy him: but Ile shew</L>
<L>Mercy to my Tormenters.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>And those deeds</L>
<L>Argue a pious Nature.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phe.</SPEAKER>
<L>If they doe;</L>
<L>Then thus I will expresse them: Wife, by all</L>
<L>The ties that I can challenge, or intreate</L>
<L>By oath, by faith, by loue and loyall duty,</L>
<L>I binde thee keepe this glasse till I be dead;</L>
<L>But, once departed, spill it on the ground,</L>
<L>Where nere treads liuing Creature; and (though vrg'd)</L>
<L>Deny thou euer sawst it; yea, though death</L>
<L>Be threatned to confesse it: this perform'd,</L>
<L>My peace is made with all things.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ad.</SPEAKER>
<L>By all the Bonds of loue and faith I will.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then <HI>Herod</HI> doe thy vvorst; I am beyond</L>
<L>The reach of all thine enuy; peace dwels heere;</L>
<L>And quiet Slumber sits vpon mine eyes:</L>
<L>I haue no Racks nor Batteries now vvithin,</L>
<L>As earst I had when I vvas troubled:</L>
<L>My nummed feete which late so leaden were,</L>
<L>I could not stand nor walke; haue now such vvarmth,</L>
<L>That I can trauell vnto Paradise;</L>
<L>And, vvith spread armes, incircle mercy to me:</L>
<L>I that accus'd the Queene, accuse my selfe,</L>
<L>And on her Altar lay my bleeding heart;</L>
<L>Where I haue found such mercy in my truth,</L>
<L>That <HI>Marriams</HI> selfe hath got me happy pardon:</L>
<L>For vvhich deare Sweet I thanke thee: now I come,</L>
<L>My life hath runne it's Circle, and's come round;</L>
<L>Mount Soule to Heauen; sinke sins vnto the ground.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Dies.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ad.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, he is gone, his life is withered:</L>
<L>What shall become of me? I'm lost for euer.</L>
<L>My Lord, my Husband; O, my <HI>Pheroas;</HI></L>
<L>Lift vp those eyes, they are too soone obscur'd</L>
<L>From her, that as her life did tender thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Haue patience; tis a fruitlesse Dialogue,</L>
<L>Since to the dead you speake; withdraw him hence,</L>
<L>His Conscience is vnburthened, he secure</L>
<L><PB REF="31"/>
On his long Iourney wander'd; and beleeu't,</L>
<L>The causers of his woe shall follow him;</L>
<L>By all that's good they shall; second me Fate,</L>
<L>And let reuenge once murder cruel hate.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Alex. &amp; Ad.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, Ile preuent you, <HI>Salumith</HI> shall know,</L>
<L>All your designes, and how your actions goe.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Eunuch.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Herod Niraleus, Animis, Hillus, and Attendants.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where is <HI>Niraleus?</HI> what, haue you tane suruey</L>
<L>Of all the holy Building? May't be said,</L>
<L><HI>Herod</HI> in it hath out-gone <HI>Salomon?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nir.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dread Sir, it may: nay and so farre out-gone,</L>
<L>As Sunshine petty Starre-light.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come discourse</L>
<L>The manner of the Building.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nir.</SPEAKER>
<L>Briefly thus,</L>
<L>The Temple which King <HI>Salomon</HI> set vp,</L>
<L>In honor of the God of <HI>Israel,</HI></L>
<L>(Being by your great Mightinesse defac'd)</L>
<L>Is thus by you restor'd. The generall Frame,</L>
<L>In height, in breadth, in length, is euery way</L>
<L>Fully an hundred Cubits; and besides,</L>
<L>Twenty lies hid in the Foundation:</L>
<L>The matter is white Marble; euery Stone</L>
<L>Twelue Cubits broad, and eight ith' outward part;</L>
<L>So curiously contriu'd, that not a hayre</L>
<L>Differs in all the Building: euery Gate</L>
<L>Is clos'd in gold, and so enchast and set</L>
<L>With precious Stones; that neuer, till this day,</L>
<L>Saw mortall man so rich a Iewelry:</L>
<L>The Tops and Thresholds, Siluer; and each Barre</L>
<L>Studded with knobs of shining Diamonds.</L>
<L>Close to the holy Building, stands a Court</L>
<L>Of square Proportion; euery way stretcht out</L>
<L>Seauen hundred and twenty Cubits: all the Wall</L>
<L>Is made of massie Siluer, and adornd</L>
<L>With Pillars of white Marble; from whose base</L>
<L>Toth' top are forty Cubits; and thereon</L>
<L>Mounted such curious Walkes and Galleries,</L>
<L>That thence you may behold the Fishes dance</L>
<L>Within the Riuer <HI>Cedron:</HI> all the Floore</L>
<L><PB REF="32"/>
Is pau'd with Marble, Touch, and Iuory;</L>
<L>And on the golden Gate, is finely wrought</L>
<L>A flaming Sword; which, by Inscription,</L>
<L>Threats death to all dare enter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's within?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nir.</SPEAKER>
<L>Within this Court, is fram'd a curious Vine</L>
<L>Of perfect Gold; the Body and large Armes,</L>
<L>Of shining Gold, brought from <HI>Arabia:</HI></L>
<L>The Sprayes and lesser Branches, are compact</L>
<L>Of <HI>Ophyr</HI> Gold; more red and radian<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>:</L>
<L>The Tops and Twines, whereon the Clusters hang,</L>
<L>Are yellow Gold; wrought in <HI>Assyria:</HI></L>
<L>The Fruit it selfe is Christall; and so ioynd,</L>
<L>That when the Sunne looks on them, they reflect</L>
<L>And vary in their colours seuerall wayes,</L>
<L>According to their Obiects. To conclude;</L>
<L>Such Art, such Wealth, and Wonder in the Frame</L>
<L>Is ioynd and wed together; that the World</L>
<L>Shall neuer see it equal'd: but this Truth</L>
<L>Shall still hang on it as a Prophesie:</L>
<L>Blush Art and Nature; none below the Sunne</L>
<L>Shall euer doe what <HI>Herod</HI> now hath done.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Enough, th'ast giuen me satisfaction; and forthwith,</L>
<L>In solemne wise Ile haue it consecrate</L>
<L>Vnto the God of <HI>Israel:</HI> how now;</L>
<L>Why comes our Sister thus amazedly.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Salumith, and the Eunuch.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, I beseech you, for your royall health,</L>
<L>And for the Kingdomes safety, you'l be pleas'd</L>
<L>To heare this <HI>E<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>uch</HI> speake; and howsoere</L>
<L>Yaue vow'd no more to heare Conspiracies:</L>
<L>Yet Sir, in this regard him; and admit,</L>
<L>He may make knowne what may endanger you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whence is the <HI>Eunuch?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Belonging to <HI>Alexandra.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let him speake freely.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>It pleas'd my Lady Sir, this other day,</L>
<L>(Hearing how desperately strong sicknesse rag'd</L>
<L>Vpon Prince <HI>Pheroas</HI>) for some speciall cause</L>
<L>To goe and visite him; she found him pain'd,</L>
<L><PB REF="32"/>
Both in his minde and body; vttering forth</L>
<L>Many distracted Speeches; some against</L>
<L>Your Highnesse person, most against himselfe;</L>
<L>Saying, he had maliciously accus'd</L>
<L>The late Queene most vniustly: in the end,</L>
<L>He makes his Lady from his Study bring</L>
<L>A Violl fild with Poyson; saying, this</L>
<L>Was for the King prepared; and by those</L>
<L>That had least cause to hurt him: vvhen he had</L>
<L>View'd it, and shew'd the venome; he bequeathes</L>
<L>The Violl to his Lady; giues her charge</L>
<L>Of safe and curious keeping, till his eyes</L>
<L>Were clos'd in death for euer; but, that done,</L>
<L>To cast it forth and spill it on the ground,</L>
<L>Where none that liues might know it: this scarse spoke,</L>
<L>His Soule forsakes his Body; but the Glasse</L>
<L>My Lady, and his sad Wife doth preserue,</L>
<L>I feare, for your destruction; <HI>Marriams</HI> Soule</L>
<L>Hath strong reuengement promis'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis enough;</L>
<L>Th'ast told me likely danger: <HI>Hillus</HI> with</L>
<L>Your Guard attach the Wife of <HI>Pheroas;</HI></L>
<L>Then search the house; and whatsoere you finde</L>
<L>Like Poyson, see you bring me: <HI>Animis,</HI></L>
<L>With your Guard ceaze my Mother; goe, away;</L>
<L>Be carefull, &amp; be happy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>An.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doubt vs not.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ex. An. &amp; Hil.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Still shall I thus be hunted, and compel'd</L>
<L>To turne head on mine owne blood? Is there left</L>
<L>Nothing to guard me but my Cruelty?</L>
<L>Then let my Passion conquer and keepe downe</L>
<L>All Mercy from appearing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, twill be</L>
<L>A royall Iustice in you: who not knowes</L>
<L>The <HI>Lybian</HI> Lyons neuer dare approach</L>
<L>The walls wheron their spoiles hang; Wolues we see</L>
<L>Fly from the sound of those Drums, which we know</L>
<L>Are headed with their owne Skins: Sir, beleeu't,</L>
<L>Seuerity brings safety.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis most true,</L>
<L>And I will hence begin to study it.</L>
<L>How now, whom haue you there?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="33"/>
Enter Hillus with his Guard, bringing in Adda in a Chaire.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, tis the Wise of the deceased <HI>Pheroas.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>By what meanes comes she thus disabled?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hil.</SPEAKER>
<L>By her owne fatall mischiefe: when she saw</L>
<L>I did ap<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>roach her Dwelling; first she barres</L>
<L>All Dores against my passage; then, her selfe</L>
<L>Mounts vp into a T<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>rret, which orelookes</L>
<L>What euer stands about it; thence she calls,</L>
<L>And asks me what I came for; I declar'd</L>
<L>The pleasure of your Greatnesse; and with tearmes</L>
<L>Fit for her royall Calling, wisht she would</L>
<L>Obey what I must finish: She returnes</L>
<L>An answer like her fury; said she would</L>
<L>Nor yeeld to you, nor mine authority.</L>
<L>Which anger being ouer; she cry'd see,</L>
<L>Thus will I flye to <HI>Herod;</HI> and that spoke,</L>
<L>Downe from the Turret did she throw her selfe</L>
<L>As if a VVhirle-winde tooke her: which perceiud,</L>
<L>I made the Soldiers catch her; yet the force</L>
<L>Came with such deadly violence, that some</L>
<L>She struck dead vnderneath her; and her selfe</L>
<L>Bruiz'd, as you see, and wounded: By our meanes</L>
<L>Hath yet so much life left, as may resolue,</L>
<L>VVhat we cannot discouer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>What of the Poyson?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hil.</SPEAKER>
<L>No where to be found.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Twas a strange desperate hazard.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>But a toy;</L>
<L>They which dare doe, dare suffer; desperate Soule,</L>
<L>Doe not play with more mischiefe; but confesse,</L>
<L>VVhere is the Poyson, which thy treacherous Lord</L>
<L>(Hauing for me prouided) did conuay</L>
<L>Vnto thy charge and keeping.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ad.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, I vow,</L>
<L>There nere was any giuen me; neither had</L>
<L>My Lord a thought so odious.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come tis false;</L>
<L>Nor can you now outstrip me; to denye,</L>
<L>Is but to adde to sorrow; or confesse,</L>
<L>Or drinke of more affliction.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, doe;</L>
<L>It will be too apparant, trust the King;</L>
<L>Ile sue and begge your safety.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nir.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis aduice</L>
<L><PB REF="33"/>
Worthy your best imbraces.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Quickly speake;</L>
<L>For I am sodaine in my Cruelty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ad.</SPEAKER>
<L>What shall I speake; but, that y'are tirannous,</L>
<L>Thus to compell a falshood; I protest,</L>
<L>He neuer gaue me any; nor know I</L>
<L>Of any hidden Poyson.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prepare her for the Torture: Shall my life</L>
<L>Lye in these rotten Caskets, and not I</L>
<L>Dare to consume or breake them? Wretched thing,</L>
<L>Ile make you speake louder then Tempests doe;</L>
<L>And true as Oracles; or else, beleeu't,</L>
<STAGE>They racke Adda.</STAGE>
<L>He cracke your strongest heart-strings: so, pull home;</L>
<L>Stretch her out like a Lutestring.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ad.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, as y'are a King haue mercy; hold, O hold.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speake truth, or there's no mercy; higher yet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ad.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, my weake strength cannot beare it; hold, O hold.</L>
<L>I will confesse and perish.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe it with truth there's safety, giue her ease.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ad.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe confesse the Poyson; that my Lord</L>
<L>Bequeath'd it to my keeping; that it was</L>
<L>Prepar'd to kill you: but (great Sir)</L>
<L>Neuer by him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who then became the Author?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ad.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, 'twas <HI>Antipater.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mischiefe on mischiefe,</L>
<L>How came shee by that knowledge?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Antipat<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>!</HI> how, from <HI>Antipater?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ad.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ere his departure vnto <HI>Rome,</HI> he came</L>
<L>And feasted with my Lord; declar'd his hopes;</L>
<L>And that betwixt him and the Crowne, did stand</L>
<L>Nothing but your weake life, and great <HI>Augustus</HI> fauour:</L>
<L>The latter got; the first he said should fall,</L>
<L>And vanish in a moment; to which end,</L>
<L>He had prepar'd that poyson; and besought</L>
<L>My Lord to keepe it safely; for he meant</L>
<L>At his returne to vse it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can you tell by whose meanes he attaind it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ad.</SPEAKER>
<L>He bought it of the Iew <HI>Achitophel.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>What did you with that Poyson?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="34"/>
<SPEAKER>Ad.</SPEAKER>
<L>As my dead Lord commanded; on the grownd</L>
<L>I cast most part thereof; only some drops</L>
<L>Left in the Viols bottome, with the Glasse,</L>
<L>(At her most strong intreaty) I bestow'd</L>
<L>On the Queene <HI>Alexandra.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take her downe;</L>
<L>This at the first had eas'd your misery:</L>
<L>Ha Sir, <HI>Antipater;</HI> all this <HI>Antipater?</HI></L>
<L>O Heauen! But tis no wonder.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nir.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, that Truth</L>
<L>Should thus come forth by Miracle; till now</L>
<L>Mischiefe hath gone safe guarded: but, I hope,</L>
<L>Your Highnesse vvill make vse on't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doubt me not.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Animis, bringing in Alexandra, Achitophel, &amp; Disease.</STAGE>
<L>Here comes my second trouble: vvhat the Iew?</L>
<L>You haue preuented sending for: false Queene,</L>
<L>That hast disgrac'd thy Sexe with Cruelty.</L>
<L>What Poyson's in your keeping?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not any Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not any: impudent?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ad.</SPEAKER>
<L>O Madam, tis</L>
<L>Too late now to excuse it; paine, O paine,</L>
<L>Tirannous paine hath torne all from my Bosome:</L>
<L>The Violl vvhich I gaue you, and the drops,</L>
<L>Is that his Highnesse vrges.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>I do confesse them;</L>
<L>Heere is the Violl and the drops: from this,</L>
<L>What can your malice gather?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>That your intent</L>
<L>Was, therewith to destroy me. O, you Gods!</L>
<L>What's life, when This can take it? This, this drop;</L>
<L>This little paltry nothing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, tis false</L>
<L>I neuer did intend your iniury.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>What not intend it? Blushlesse impudence!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you be made my Iudge, I know I'm then</L>
<L>Worse then all feare can make me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'are indeed</L>
<L>A mischiefe too long growing. Sirrah, Iew;</L>
<L>Was this your Composition?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ach.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twas a worke</L>
<L>My Art brought forth; but neuer did my thought</L>
<L>Touch at your Highnes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who made you to prepare it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ach.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Prince <HI>Antipater.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Villaine, th'art damn'd for that discouery.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ach.</SPEAKER>
<L>No matter; Ile haue royall company.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>And Sirrah, you had a finger in this worke too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="34"/>
<SPEAKER>Dis.</SPEAKER>
<L>No truly My Lord, I durst not dip my finger in your dish,</L>
<L>After great men is alwayes good manners.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nir.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then you knew it was prepared for the King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas, I knew my Maister had nothing too deare for his</L>
<L>Grace, and my Lord <HI>Antipater</HI> I know gaue a good price for it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Was this Poyson then prepar'd for me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dis.</SPEAKER>
<P>O Sir, by all likelihood; for euer your Physitian is like your Hauke; the greater the Fowle is that he kils, the greater is still both his reward and reputation.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis true, and you shall both finde it: goe, hang vp that</L>
<L>Peasant presently; and then cast him into <HI>Silo.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who me, hang vp me? that cannot be good payment.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why foole?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Because I shall neuer be able to acknowledge satisfaction.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away vvith him; and for that treacherous Iew,</L>
<STAGE>Ex. Dis.</STAGE>
<L>And you false-hearted Madam, both shall tast</L>
<L>Of that you vvould haue tendred; equally</L>
<L>Diuide that Bane into two cups of vvine,</L>
<L>And giue it them to drinke off; tis decreed,</L>
<L>What vvas prepar'd for me, shall make you bleed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis vvelcome Sir; a sodaine death, I know</L>
<L>Is terrible and fearfull; but indeed,</L>
<L>To those vvhich doe attend it, and doe stand</L>
<L>Constantly gazing on it; who doe liue,</L>
<L>Where it scarres none but Cowards; those can meet,</L>
<L>And kisse it as a sweet Companion:</L>
<L>Tis vnto those a Bugbeare, vvho do thinke</L>
<L>Neuer on Heauen, but for necessity.</L>
<L>Your Tyranny hath taught me other rules;</L>
<L>And this guest comes long lookt for: heere's a health</L>
<L>To all that honor Vertue; let suffice,</L>
<STAGE>Drinks the Poyson.</STAGE>
<L>Death doth oretake; but it doth not surprize.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ach.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well Madam, I must pledge you; yet before,</L>
<L>Ile doe the King some seruice: I confesse,</L>
<L>I did compound the poyson; 'twas prepar'd</L>
<L>To kill your Maiesty; the Plot was laid</L>
<L>Both by <HI>Antipater</HI> and <HI>Salumith:</HI></L>
<L>They equally subborn'd me; each bestow'd</L>
<L><PB REF="35"/>
Reward vpon mee, and encouragement:</L>
<L>T'was they which made me to accuse the Queene,</L>
<L>I must confesse vniustly; they, long since,</L>
<L>Haue shar'd you and the Kingdome: that tis true,</L>
<L>Be this last draught my witnesse; for no Slaue</L>
<L>Madly will carry falshood to his Graue.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Drinks the Poyson.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>But thou dost, and it will damne thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Say not so;</L>
<L>I know this smoake vvill kindle, and my care</L>
<L>Must now preuent my danger. <HI>Animis,</HI></L>
<STAGE>Exe. Ani. &amp; Sal.</STAGE>
<L>Guard you my Sister safely: <HI>Hillus,</HI> cause</L>
<L>Those bodies to be buried: you <HI>Niraleus,</HI></L>
<L>Shall make for <HI>Rome</HI> with all speed; thence, bring backe</L>
<L>That false, ingratefull, proud <HI>Antipater:</HI></L>
<L>Carry the matter close, but cunningly:</L>
<L>For that poore Soule, bid our Phisitians</L>
<L>With all care to respect her; for tis she</L>
<L>That onely can accuse our enemies.</L>
<L>Thus runnes the wheeles of State, now vp, now downe;</L>
<L>And none that liues findes safety in a Crowne.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE><P>Dumbe Shew.</P>
<P>Enter at one Doore, Augustus triumphant with his Romans; at another Antipater: he kneeles and giues Augustus Letters; which lookt on, Augustus raises him, sets him in his Chayre, and Crownes him, sweares him on his Sword, and deliuers him Letters: then, Enter Niraleus, he giues Antipater Letters; hee shewes them to Au∣gustus; then, imbracing, they take leaue and depart seuerally.</P></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iose.</SPEAKER>
<L>Once more, I must intreat you to bestow</L>
<L>Much on Imagination; and to thinke,</L>
<L>That now our Bastard hath attain'd the top</L>
<L>And height of his Ambition: You haue seene</L>
<L><HI>Augustus</HI> Crowne him; all his great Requests</L>
<L>Are summ'd and granted: therefore, now suppose</L>
<L>He is come home in Triumph; all his Plots</L>
<L>He holds as strong as Fate is, nothing feares;</L>
<L>(So braue his minde inchants him) how at last,</L>
<L>He falls to vtter ruine; sit, and see:</L>
<L>No man hath power to out-worke Destinie.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<TRAILER>Finis Actus quarti.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="5" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="35"/>
<HEAD>ACT. 5. Scoena. 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Antipater, and Niraleus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anti.</SPEAKER>
<L>O <HI>Niraleus;</HI> so liberall was the royall brested <HI>Casar,</HI></L>
<L>As farre exceeds all thought or iust expression.</L>
<L>When he establisht me <HI>Iudea's</HI> King,</L>
<L>His bounty did so farre extend it selfe,</L>
<L>That euen his Court appeard a Paradise;</L>
<L>The People like so many Demi-Kings;</L>
<L>Himselfe, the great Vice-gerent ore them all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nir.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Caesar</HI> is royall, and <HI>Antipater</HI> deseruing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Me thinks (as in a Mirror) still I see</L>
<L><HI>Augustus</HI> dealing yellow <HI>Arabian</HI> gold</L>
<L>Amongst the vulgar, in <HI>Antipaters</HI> name;</L>
<L>So louely were his lookes, so Angel-like his words</L>
<L>The very thought strikes m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> into a Rapture:</L>
<L>O, I could laugh my selfe breathlesse in conceit,</L>
<L>To thinke on those faire honors we receiu'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nir.</SPEAKER>
<L>Liue to deserue euer.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>3.</HI> Lords laughing, and pointing scornfully at Antipater.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>How now; what Motion-mongers are these? S'death, what meane they? Doe they make mee a Batchellor Cuckond? But that I would know the intent, I could be very angry: but Ile not minde 'em.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's he was carried in triumph through <HI>Rome.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<L>Poore Young-man, thy Greatnes must downe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<L>He scornd (being great) to looke on Pouerty;</L>
<L>But now Pouerty scornes Basenesse: farewell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Greatnesse will haue a cold welcome home.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<L>See how he lookes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pittifully pale.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doubt hee'l runne mad.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, let's leaue him. Ha, ha, ha.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Antip.</SPEAKER>
<L>Has Nature stampt me with Deformity?</L>
<L>Am I of late transform'd? Am I the Owle</L>
<L>So lately made, for Birds to wonder at? Is't so?</L>
<L>I thinke I am my selfe; I haue my Voyce,</L>
<L>My Legs, my Hands, my Head, Face, Eyes and Nose;</L>
<L>I'm disproportion'd no way that I know of:</L>
<L><PB REF="36"/>
Then why doe these Wood-cracks wonder at me?</L>
<L>I could be naturally vex't, and haue good cause for't:</L>
<L>But Ile be patient, walke, obserue: here comes a friend.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Animis, walking by Antipater.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ani.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord;—You are vndone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, noble <HI>Animis;</HI> what, gone so soone?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Noble <HI>Hillus.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Hillus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hil.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord;—Your <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>cke is broke.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha! whats that? strange entertainment: y'are vndone:</L>
<L>Whom should this be; for me it cannot be? No;</L>
<L>I am a King, and tis a hard matter to vndoe a King.</L>
<L>P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>sh; there's no Morall in these foolish words:</L>
<L>Your Necke is broke; a Banquerout's Sentence.</L>
<L>We are vnlimited, both in Wealth, and State;</L>
<L>As boundlesse as the Sea; freer in guift.</L>
<L>No; tis not their words can breed am<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>zement;</L>
<L>But their strange looks, gestures, and geerings at me:</L>
<L>Instruct me good <HI>Nirale<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>,</HI> thou art an honest man;</L>
<L>How shewes this disrespect? strangely: doe's it not?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nir.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nothing, nothing Sir; Courtiers you know are apish:</L>
<L>Tis onely some new Proiect they haue to entertaine you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Proiects for entertainment! Well, th'are strange;</L>
<L>And I finde something troubles mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nir.</SPEAKER>
<L>What ayle you Sir? D'yee faint? Y'are wondrous pale;</L>
<L>You change Colour strangely: D'yee bleed?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Drop; nothing, but a Drop.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nir.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis ominous.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>True; and I finde something that staggers me:</L>
<L>I will retire my selfe from Court to day.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nir.</SPEAKER>
<L>Retire from Court! O, name it not for shame;</L>
<L>Least you incurre a publike Scandall on you:</L>
<L>Why should you flye from that most couets you?</L>
<L>Will you obscure your Sunne-beames in their height?</L>
<L>Couer your Glories in their M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>rnings rise?</L>
<L>Those that now geered; then, will laugh outright;</L>
<L>When lookes can put <HI>Antipater</HI> to flight.</L>
<L>No, forage on; and, l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ke a daring Lion,</L>
<L>Single your Game; let not pale Feare dismay you:</L>
<L><PB REF="36"/>
Appeale for Iustice to Heroicke <HI>Herod,</HI></L>
<L>Gainst those that thus contemn'd your Soueraignty:</L>
<L>True Valour in the weakest Trench doth lie;</L>
<L>Then beare you brauely on, and scorne to flye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Th'ast new created me: I loue this Honor,</L>
<L>That is by merit purchas'd: second me then;</L>
<L>And let the worst of fortunes fall vpon me:</L>
<L>This G<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ard Ile keepe; grapling this Sword,</L>
<L>(Though wall'd with Pikes) Ile beat my passage through;</L>
<L>And to great <HI>Herod</HI> make my Supplication.</L>
<L>He that feares Enuy shall be sure to finde it:</L>
<L>But he securest, that the least doe's minde it.</L>
<L>Stay, a new Onset.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Animis, with a Guard.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ani.</SPEAKER>
<L>Great <HI>Antipater.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, that sounds nobly; why not this before?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ani.</SPEAKER>
<L>This cause and this Authority.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Wips forth his Sword. Niraleus:</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>What, betraid; and sleeping taken?</L>
<L>Slaues let me goe, Ile to the King for Iustice:</L>
<L>Ha yee caught the Lambe within the Lions Denne?</L>
<L>Cowardly wretches: O for my good Sword,</L>
<L>And liberty to gratulate your Trecheries.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nir.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Treasons must be first answer'd Sir;</L>
<L>Til then, you must to Prison.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, <HI>Niraleus;</HI> art thou my accuser?</L>
<L>Haue I within my bos<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>me kept a Snake,</L>
<L>To sting mee first? Trecherous Lords,</L>
<L>My Treasons?' gainst whom? or, by whom acted?</L>
<L>Innocence protect me: guide me to <HI>Herod,</HI></L>
<L>That, to his sacred person, I may tell</L>
<L>The Iniuries <HI>Antipater</HI> does suffer:</L>
<L>He comes; O happy houre: Iustice; Iustice Sir.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Herod, Hillus, and Attendants.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Iustice that you merit; hence away with him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>O sacred <HI>Herod,</HI> heare thy Vassall speake:</L>
<L>Consider what I am; thy Sonne: if my offences</L>
<L>Proue preiudiciall to thee; Ile lay my life</L>
<L>As foot-stoole to thy inercies: O, consider,</L>
<L><PB REF="37"/>
I neuer was that disobedient Sonne,</L>
<L>That did in any thing oppose his Father:</L>
<L>But with a greedinesse, still ranne to act,</L>
<L>Ere thy Command was past: if these Honours,</L>
<L>These titular glories, great <HI>Augustus</HI> gaue me;</L>
<L>If these offend my Soueraigne, cut them off;</L>
<L>Raze them from off my head; and let me be</L>
<L>Any thing, but <HI>Herods</HI> scorne; no misery</L>
<L>Can worke vpon me halfe that troubled griefe,</L>
<L>As does one frowne from those thy glorious eyes:</L>
<L>Let not those white haires now be staind with blood,</L>
<L>Blood of thine owne begetting; euery drop</L>
<L>In me, from thee had being; canst thou be so vnkind,</L>
<L>To cast thy selfe away? O sacred Sir,</L>
<L>I see compassion in your tender eyes;</L>
<L>Weeping for me, that mone your miseries.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Through what a Labyrinth is mercy led;</L>
<L>Rise in our fauo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>r euermore belou'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nir.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rise in your fauour! O <HI>Herod</HI> be more iust;</L>
<L>As thou art K<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ng; so be a God in Iustice;</L>
<L>The blood of Babes, c<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>yes sor thine equity:</L>
<L>Remember but his Strattagems forepast;</L>
<L>All which, acquitting, you are accessary.</L>
<L>Thinke first on <HI>Aristobul<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></HI> fell death;</L>
<L>Your two braue Sonnes, and noble <HI>Iosephs</HI> fall:</L>
<L>Next <HI>Pheroas</HI> your Brother; O, your natiue blood:</L>
<L>And <HI>Alexandra,</HI> that most innocent Lady;</L>
<L>Vni<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>stly and vntimely brought to death,</L>
<L>All through his poysnous Complots.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>All these are past and cannot be recal'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nir.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let not his smooth words Sir intice you to him;</L>
<L>In stillest Riuers are the greatest dangers:</L>
<L>If none of these can moue you to doe Iustice,</L>
<L>Whose Soules yet houering still doe cry Reuenge;</L>
<L>Ye<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> there is one whose cause must not be slipt;</L>
<L>Though Cannons roare yet must not you be deafe;</L>
<L>But (l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ke the glory you were made for) be</L>
<L>A King, a God in Iudgement, and in Iustice:</L>
<L><PB REF="37"/>
Sonnes are no longer Ours, then they are Natures;</L>
<L>When Nature leaues them, we may leaue our claime:</L>
<L>Be this your warrant, iustly to execute</L>
<L>Iudgement on him, that ha's vniustly murdred</L>
<L>Your Mother, Sons, Brothers, Sisters: if not for these;</L>
<L>Thinke vpon her as deare as was your life,</L>
<L>Your <HI>Marriam;</HI> you innocent, chast, faire <HI>Marriam;</HI></L>
<L>By his false witnesse, turn'd to vntimely dust:</L>
<L>O as y'are great, be good, gracious, and iust.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>All those forenamed were of no effect:</L>
<L>My <HI>Marriam;</HI> O my heart: hence with the Slaue;</L>
<L>Ile heare no more of his inchanting words.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Antip.</SPEAKER>
<L>O <HI>Herod,</HI> Kingly Father.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Antip. with a Guard.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away with him; Ile blot out all Affinity:</L>
<L>O <HI>Niraleus,</HI> he was so deeply rooted in our loue;</L>
<L>All those and thousands more could neuer worke</L>
<L>Me to haue sent him from my presence: but</L>
<L>My <HI>Marriam;</HI> O, the very name of her</L>
<L>Is like a passing-Knell, to a sicke man:</L>
<L>For, if to be a King, is to be wretched;</L>
<L>Then to be meane is to be glorious:</L>
<L>The tho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ght of <HI>Marriam,</HI> like a Feuer burnes,</L>
<L>Diffects me euery Nerue; I feele within</L>
<L>My cog<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ations beating, things long past</L>
<L>Are now present<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>d, now I suffer for them;</L>
<L>I m growne a Monster, and could chafe my selfe</L>
<L>Out of my selfe; I'm all on fire within:</L>
<L>O <HI>Marriam, Marriam,</HI> Mistris of my Soule;</L>
<L>I shall expire with breathing on thy name:</L>
<L>Thy deare remembrance burnes me: who attends?</L>
<L>Gi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e me some Fruit to coole me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nir.</SPEAKER>
<L>What, will you tast some Sirrop, or some grapes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, giue me an Apple.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nir.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here are faire ones Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lend me a knife to pare it: O <HI>Niraleus,</HI></L>
<L>I haue done cruell Iustice; is there left</L>
<L>A good thing to succeed me? All my Sonnes,</L>
<L>My Brothers, Sisters; nay, the very last</L>
<L>Of all my blood is vanisht.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="38"/>
<SPEAKER>Nir.</SPEAKER>
<L>Say not so; Your Childrens Children liue yet:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her</SPEAKER>
<L>Passing true, young <HI>Archelaus</HI> and <HI>Antipas;</HI></L>
<L>Beet yo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>r ch<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>rge to see them sent for home;</L>
<L>Something I m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>st act, worthy my Meditation;</L>
<L>Ile not liue to haue care dwell so neere me; one small pricke</L>
<L>With this will doe it: thus Ile trye it.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Stabs himselfe.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nir.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold, in the name of wonder; what haue you done Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nothing but sought to ease my misery;</L>
<L>A little more had done it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nir.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good Sir haue patience; a Surgeon there.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Patience, thou seest I haue, to kill my selfe;</L>
<L>I shall ere long rest in my <HI>Marriams</HI> armes:</L>
<L>I would not be a King another yeare,</L>
<L>For both the Crownes of <HI>Iuda</HI> and of <HI>Rome:</HI></L>
<L>Prouide my Bed, I'm faint and something sicke:</L>
<L><HI>Antipater,</HI> be close, Ile sift your knauery;</L>
<L>A King has eye-balls that can pierce through stone;</L>
<L>His very lookes, shall make the Slaue confesse,</L>
<L>Who's iust, and who's vniust: all is not well;</L>
<L>Lend me your hands, wee'l try who is the strongest;</L>
<L>A wager, of vs two, I liue the longest.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Antipater, Hillus and a Guard.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hil.</SPEAKER>
<L>These are (my Lord) your Lodgings; here you may</L>
<L>Rest at your noble pleasure; when you call,</L>
<L>W'are ready to attend you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why tis well;</L>
<L>Yet, if a man should aske this Chambers name,</L>
<L>You would call it a Prison.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis no lesse.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exe. Guard.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then Gentlemen I thanke you; take your ease.</L>
<L>Neuer till now hadst thou <HI>Antipater,</HI></L>
<L>True cause t'account with wisedome; all thy Life</L>
<L>Ha's beene but sport and Tennis-play: but this,</L>
<L>O this is <HI>Serio Ioco,</HI> such a Game,</L>
<L>As cals thy Life in question; nay, thy Fame;</L>
<L>Thy Vertue, Praise, and Reputation:</L>
<L>What art thou now? a Prisoner; that's a Slaue:</L>
<L>Nay, Slaue to Slaues; slauish extremity!</L>
<L>But now a King; but now a Cast-away;</L>
<L>Crown'd, and vncrown'd; and vndone euery way:</L>
<L><PB REF="38"/>
Where's now my hellish Counsellors? my hope?</L>
<L>My strong bewitcht perswasion? Rise, O rise;</L>
<L>And once more shew me my deliuerance:</L>
<L>Tut, all mute and hidden; tis the Diuels tricke</L>
<L>Sill to forsake men in their misery;</L>
<L>And I am pleas'd they doe so: let none share</L>
<L>Either in my downefall, or welfare.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Animis.</STAGE>
<L>Keeper, welcome: what newes hath ill lucke now?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ani.</SPEAKER>
<L>Strange Sir, and heauy; Rumour saith, the King</L>
<L>Hath slaine himselfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, cal'st thou that ill newes?</L>
<L>What, is he dead?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ani.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis strongly so reported.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou dost not mocke my Fortune; prethee speake,</L>
<L>Speake, and speake freely; thou hadst wont to loue</L>
<L>And ioy in what did please me: say; Is the King dead indeed?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ani.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vpon my life, tis firmely so reported.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Excellent, excellent; noble, happy newes;</L>
<L>Why, what heart could wish better? I am traunc't</L>
<L>And rapt with admiration; why, I knew</L>
<L>Fortune durst not forsake me: now hee's dead,</L>
<L>I may say, as the Diuell sayes, all's mine:</L>
<L>My hopes, my thoughts, my wishes; prethee ioy</L>
<L>Doe not too much orecome me: once againe,</L>
<L>Say, is he dead? is <HI>Herod</HI> vanished?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>An.</SPEAKER>
<L>Questionles, so talkes Rumour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Antip.</SPEAKER>
<L>Name it truth;</L>
<L>Doe not abuse a thing so excellent:</L>
<L>And now hee's dead; who thinkst thou is the King?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ani.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thinke your Greatnesse only.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, tis true;</L>
<L>Exceeding true; who, but <HI>Antipater:</HI></L>
<L>Hath not <HI>Augustus</HI> chose me? set the Crowne</L>
<L>Here? here, my <HI>Animis?</HI> hath not publique <HI>Rome</HI></L>
<L>Stil'd me the King of <HI>luda?</HI> is there left</L>
<L>Any of <HI>Casmonani;</HI> or the Seede</L>
<L>Which they doe call the holy <HI>Israel?</HI></L>
<L>No, I haue sent them packing; th'are as dead</L>
<L>As <HI>Herod</HI> and my feares are: O, my Ioyes,</L>
<L>How nimble haue you made me! To behold</L>
<L>The Hangman hang himselfe; would it not please</L>
<L><PB REF="39"/>
Those that stood neere the Gallowes: by my Life,</L>
<L>(Which this sweet newes hath lengthened) had I seene</L>
<L>The Old man kill himselfe; I thinke I should</L>
<L>Haue burst my sides with laughing: Come, let's goe;</L>
<L>Ile haue the Crowne imediately.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ani.</SPEAKER>
<L>Go, my Lord, whither?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vnto the Court, the City, any where;</L>
<L>Whither my pleasure leads me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ani.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pardon me;</L>
<L>I haue not that Commission.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>How; not that Commission? S'foot, dare any heart</L>
<L>Harbor a thought 'gainst me? Come, th'art wise;</L>
<L>Open thy Dores vnto me; I haue power</L>
<L>That knowes, and can requit thee; by this hand,</L>
<L>If thou withstandst my purpose; looke to be</L>
<L>Despis'd and wretched.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ani.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good my Lord, be pleas'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not to haue you dispute my sufferance:</L>
<L>Come will you let me goe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ani.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, I dare not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Expect a damned mischiefe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ani.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take better thoughts,</L>
<L>And good my Lord conceiue, this is but Newes;</L>
<L>It may be true, or false, or any way.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>You will not let me go then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ani.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would I could;</L>
<L>Yet if you will take patience, with all hast</L>
<L>Ile flye vnto the Court: if there I finde</L>
<L>The Newes be firme and certaine; I'm your Slaue:</L>
<L>You shall dispose your selfe, and me and all things.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Poxe of your purity, your Ginger-bread,</L>
<L>And nice, safe reseruations: but, since force</L>
<L>Makes me obay you; goe, away, be gone;</L>
<L>Flye as thou lookst for fauour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ani.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am vanisht.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Ani.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, what a thing is Man! how quickly made</L>
<L>And mar'd, and yet againe reedified,</L>
<L>All with a breath; to make vs know, in Kings,</L>
<L>Consists the great worke of Creation:</L>
<L>Why, I was lost but now; and now againe,</L>
<L>Am found as great as euer; thus can Fate</L>
<L>Change and rechange at pleasure; he that would</L>
<L>Haue kil'd, is kil'd in killing: foolish Fiends,</L>
<L>You are deceiu'd to leaue me; I shall liue</L>
<L>To make you bound to mine Iniquity;</L>
<L><PB REF="39"/>
Indeed I shall; and make Posterity</L>
<L>Cite onely my example; then (my Soule)</L>
<L>Sit, and sleepe out thy dangers.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Antipater sits downe and slumbers; then, Enter Herod, Augustus, Niraleus, Archelaus, Antipas, and Hillus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>O royall <HI>Caesar,</HI> this grace thus perform'd</L>
<L>In my poore Visitation; makes my Soule</L>
<L>A Bondslaue to thy Vertue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aug.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis no more</L>
<L>Then what your worth may challenge; onely Sir,</L>
<L>This violence on your person, by your selfe,</L>
<L>Must craue my reprehension.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis but fit:</L>
<L>Yet royall <HI>Caesar,</HI> what should Nature doe;</L>
<L>When, like to me, its growne vnnaturall?</L>
<L>Turn'd a deuouring Serpent; eating vp</L>
<L>The whole Frye it ingendred; nay, the armes</L>
<L>And branches of it's body. Sir, 'twas I</L>
<L>That kil'd the vertuous high Priest <HI>Aristobulus;</HI></L>
<STAGE>Enter E. Aristobulus, and Q. Alexandra like Ghosts.</STAGE>
<L>See where he comes bright Angel-like: O stay,</L>
<L>Doe not afflict me further: how he moues</L>
<L>Like gentle ayre about me: see, to him,</L>
<L>Enters his royall Mother; hold, O hold;</L>
<L>I doe confesse my vengeance, and will shed</L>
<L>My life-bloud to appease you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aug.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, this is</L>
<L>But fancy which torments you; here appeares</L>
<L>Nothing that's strange about vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>See my Sonnes;</L>
<STAGE>Enter P. Alexander, Y. Aristobulus, and Marriam.</STAGE>
<L>My louely Boyes; tis true, I murder'd you;</L>
<L>Come, take reuenge, and spare not: art thou there;</L>
<L>O, let me flye and catch thee: bee'st thou Flame,</L>
<L>Blastings, or mortall Sicknesse; yet I dare</L>
<L>Leape and imbrace my dearest <HI>Marriam:</HI></L>
<L><HI>Marriam,</HI> O <HI>Marriam;</HI> Vill<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>nes, let me goe;</L>
<L>You shall not hold me from her: O, a Sword,</L>
<L>A Sword for Heauens mercy; for, but death,</L>
<L>Nothing can ioyne me to her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aug.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is strange;</L>
<L>Nor haue I seene Passion more powerfull: See you hold him fast.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall I not reach my comfort? then, O come</L>
<L><PB REF="40"/>
You that my wrath hath iniur'd; sticke, sticke here</L>
<L>The Arrowes of your Poyson: so; it workes, it workes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nir.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Slumber ouertakes him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aug.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let him rest.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter, like Ghosts, Pheroas Achitophel, Disease &amp; Tryphon.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold, O hold; whither is courage vanish't? Poxe of feares,</L>
<L>And Dreames imaginations: shall I turne</L>
<L>Coward whilst I am sleeping? No, Ile laugh</L>
<L>Euen in my Graue, at all my Villames:</L>
<L>Yes, in despight of thee, and thee, and both</L>
<L>Your damned base Brauadoes: ha, ha, ha;</L>
<L>My Mountebanke and s Zany! How can Hell</L>
<L>Spare such neate skipping Raskals? What, my fine</L>
<L>Neate shauing amorous Barber! See, I dare</L>
<L>Face, and out-face yee all; I Death himselfe;</L>
<L>For, none of you, but dyed most worthily.</L>
<L>Ha, I am now transfigur'd: stand away;</L>
<L>Accuse me not you blessed Innocents:</L>
<L>O, you doe breake my brest vp, teare my Soule;</L>
<L>And burne Offence to an Anatomy:</L>
<L>I know my mischiefe slew you; giue me leaue,</L>
<L>And Ile become both Priest and Sacrifice:</L>
<L>They will not haue mine Offering: see, th'are gone;</L>
<L>And I am onely fool'd with Visions.</L>
<L>Sit, and sleepe out Phantasmas.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, ha, ha;</L>
<L>This Vision doth not scarre me; that you fell,</L>
<L>'Twas I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>stice and my Vertue; all your threats</L>
<L>Doe but augment my Triumph: go, pack hence;</L>
<STAGE>Exe. Ghosts, &amp; Enter Animis.</STAGE>
<L>I grieue for naught but iniur'd innocence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ani.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where is the King my Maister?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aug.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's thy will?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ani.</SPEAKER>
<L>Emperiall Sir, Tis from <HI>Antipater.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Antipater?</HI> speake forth, I heare thee; that's a sound</L>
<L>Euer craues mine attention.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ani.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gracious Sir,</L>
<L>The rumour of your death, when it had fild</L>
<L>The City; flew to him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, and then</L>
<L>How tooke he my departing? Come, I see</L>
<L>Strange things in thy deliuerance: speake, speake free;</L>
<L>How tooke he that sad Message?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ani.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not toth' heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aug.</SPEAKER>
<L>No 'twas enough the count'nance languished.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="40"/>
<SPEAKER>Ani.</SPEAKER>
<L>That was as light as any.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>On thy life</L>
<L>Tell me his whole demeanour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ani.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, in briefe;</L>
<L>When I had told the fatall Accident</L>
<L>Both of your wound and dying; sodaine mirth</L>
<L>Ranne through him like a Lightning; and he seemd</L>
<L>Onely a flame of Iest and Merriment:</L>
<L>His ioy was past example; and he swore,</L>
<L>His sinnes had made him King of <HI>Israel:</HI></L>
<L>What shall I say; if threatnings or reward</L>
<L>Could but haue bought his freedome; at my choyce</L>
<L>Lay all my heart could number.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace, no more;</L>
<L>I thinke what thou canst vtter: O, this Sonne,</L>
<L>This Bastard Sonne hath onely ruind me:</L>
<L>Hell neuer knew his equall; all my sinnes</L>
<L>Are but the seeds he planted: fie, O fie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aug.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do not afflict your selfe; tis Iustice now</L>
<L>Shall take the Cause in handling: Captaines harke,</L>
<L>And harke <HI>Niraleus,</HI> doe as I command;</L>
<L>Be vigilant and serious: goe, away.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Whisper, &amp; Exe. Animis, Niraleus &amp; the Guard.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>It shall be so; these Visions are to me,</L>
<L>Like Old-wiues Tales, or Dreames of Goblins;</L>
<L>And shall passe like them, scorn'd and iested at:</L>
<L>Why, what to me is Conscience? if I could</L>
<L>Neglect it in my whole Course; shall I now</L>
<L>Now when the Goale is gotten, stand affraid</L>
<L>Of such poore morall Shadowes? No, tis here,</L>
<L>Harden'd by Hell and Custome which shall keepe</L>
<L>And out-face all such Battry: I'm my selfe,</L>
<L>A King, a royall King; and that deare Ioy</L>
<L>Shall bury all Offences: <HI>Herod's</HI> dead;</L>
<L>And in his Graue, sleepe my distemperance.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Niraleus, Animis bearing a Crowne, and a Guard.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nir.</SPEAKER>
<L>Health to the King of <HI>Iuda.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, what's that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ani.</SPEAKER>
<L>Long life vnto the King <HI>Antipater.</HI></L>
<L>Is the newes true then? is the Old man dead?</L>
<L>The wretched poore Old man; and, haue my Starres</L>
<L>Made me the man I wisht for? O, you are</L>
<L><PB REF="41"/>
My Nightingales of comfort, and shall sing</L>
<L>Notes farre aboue your Fortunes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nir.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, hee's dead;</L>
<L>And in his death hath giuen you all, that <HI>Rome</HI></L>
<L>Before confirm'd vpon you; which we thus</L>
<L>Fixe on your sacred Temples; onely craue,</L>
<L>You will be pleas'd (as <HI>Herod</HI> did desire)</L>
<L>That ere you do ascend the Soueraigne Chayre,</L>
<L>First to behold his Body, and on it</L>
<L>Bestow one Teare or naturall Sacrifice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>O tis a Rent most ready; Teares in me</L>
<L>Are like Showers in the Spring time, euer blacke;</L>
<L>But neuer farre from Sunshine: Come, I haue</L>
<L>A longing heart and busie thoughts, which knowes</L>
<L>There's much to doe in little time: away:</L>
<L>I long to meet my glory; neuer hower</L>
<L>Was Crown'd with better fate, or stronger power.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Hillus, Officers with the Scaffold, &amp; the Executioner.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aug.</SPEAKER>
<L>This Preparation's honest; so dispatch,</L>
<L>And place these mortall Triumphs handsomely:</L>
<L>Sirrah, conceale your person; let no feare</L>
<L>Make his feare grow too early.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Exe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis, my Lord,</L>
<L>My part to couch like Mischiefe, close, but sure;</L>
<L>When I breake out I'm fatall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou speakst truth;</L>
<L>Would this day did not need thee: tis a world</L>
<L>To thinke how strong our cares are; and how weake</L>
<L>All things which doe but looke like comfort: there's</L>
<L>Not left in me a shadow; not a breath</L>
<L>Of any hope hereafter; this Bastards faith,</L>
<L>On which so much I doted, to be lost</L>
<L>Thus against kinde and nature; tis a sinne,</L>
<L>That teares my heart in pieces.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aug.</SPEAKER>
<L>Say not so;</L>
<L>Tis rather comfort well discouered:</L>
<L>But peace; see th'are approaching.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Sound Trumpets.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Antipater, Niraleus, Animis, and the Guard.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nir.</SPEAKER>
<L>Giue way, stand backe; roome for the King of <HI>Iuda.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, let them throng about me; and behold</L>
<L>Their glory, and Redeemer, Ha; what's this? a Vision?</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>tall Prodigie: the King is liuing: O, I'm lost</L>
<L><PB REF="41"/>
Past hope, and past imagination; by his side</L>
<L>The Emperour <HI>Augustus:</HI> then I see,</L>
<L>There is no way, but to destruction.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, to deserue destruction: wretched thing;</L>
<L>Thou scorne of all are scorned; see, I liue</L>
<L>Only to sound thy Iudgement: thou, that thought'st</L>
<L>To build thy Throane vpon my Sepulchre;</L>
<L>See how th'art dasht in pieces.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gracious Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aug.</SPEAKER>
<L>Labour not for excuses; you haue runne</L>
<L>A strange Cariere in Villany; and thrust</L>
<L>All goodnesse from you with such violence,</L>
<L>That Mercy dares not helpe you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet, my Lord,</L>
<L>Heare mine vnfaigned Answere.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>In thy brest</L>
<L>Was neuer thing lookt like Simplicity;</L>
<L>Thou hast made Goodnesse wretched, and defam'd</L>
<L>All vertuous things that grac'd Nobility;</L>
<L>Th'ast eate my blood vp; made my loathed life</L>
<L>Onely a Scale to reach Confusion;</L>
<L>Of these things I accuse thee; this I proue</L>
<L>Both by my Life, my Death, and Infamie;</L>
<L>And for this thou must perish: One, call forth</L>
<L>The Minister of death; and in my view,</L>
<L>Some minutes ere my dying; let me see</L>
<L>His head tane from his body.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, O Sir;</L>
<L>Thinke that you are a Father.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aug.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, a King,</L>
<L>And thence ordain'd for Iustice; to put backe</L>
<L>Ought of that heauenly Office, were to throw</L>
<L>Mountaines ith face of <HI>Iupiter;</HI> know y'are lost,</L>
<L>Lost to all Mankinde and Mortality:</L>
<L>Therefore to make your last houre better seeme,</L>
<L>Then all that went before it; what you know</L>
<L>Of Treasons vnreuealed; lay them forth:</L>
<L>The worke will well become you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is there no mercy?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aug.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not vpon earth; nor for <HI>Antipater.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then farewell Hope for euer; welcome Death;</L>
<L>I, that haue made thee as mine Instrument,</L>
<L>Will make thee my Companion; and, I thus</L>
<L>Ascend and come to meete thee: Here I am</L>
<L><PB REF="42"/>
A Monarch ouer all that looke on mee,</L>
<L>And doe despise what all you tremble at:</L>
<L>Sir, it is true, I meant your Tragedy;</L>
<L>Did quite roote out you<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> Issue; and if life</L>
<L>Had held, would haue wipte out your Memory:</L>
<L>This I confesse; and to this had no helpe;</L>
<L>But mine ill thoughts and wicked <HI>Salumiths.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aug.</SPEAKER>
<L>Was she assistant to you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, shee was.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aug.</SPEAKER>
<L>Produce her presently.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ani.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, tis too late;</L>
<L>The heart-strong Lady once imprisoned,</L>
<L>Forsooke all foode, all comfort, and with sighes,</L>
<L>Broke her poore heart in sunder.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>And that word</L>
<L>Hath brought mine vnto cracking; strike, O strike;</L>
<L>Dispatch the Execution; or mine eyes</L>
<L>Will not continue to behold the grace</L>
<L>Of the reuenge I thrist for.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Feare me not;</L>
<L>I am as swift in my desire of death,</L>
<L>As you are in your longings: Come, thou friend</L>
<L>To great mens Feares, and poore mens Miseries,</L>
<L>Strike, and strike home with boldnesse; here's a Life</L>
<L>Thy steele may quench, not conquer; for the thought</L>
<L>Exceeds all mortall Imitation:</L>
<L>Greatnesse grew in my Cradle; with my Blood,</L>
<L>Twas fed to mature ripenesse; on my Graue,</L>
<L>It shall, to all the Ages of the World,</L>
<L>Liue in eternall dreadfull Epitaphs:</L>
<L>This seruice men shall doe me; and my name</L>
<L>Remaine a Bug-beare to Ambition. Come; I am now prepar'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Exe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, will you please to kneele.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>What to thy vildnes? Slaue, Ile stand as high</L>
<L>And strong as is a Mountaine; strike, or perish.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Exe.</SPEAKER>
<L>I cannot then Sir doe mine Office.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Salumith betweene two Furies, wauing a Torch.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Poxe of your forme in these extremities.</L>
<L>What art thou there, poore tortur'd Wickednes?</L>
<L>And dost thou waft me to thee? Then, I come;</L>
<L>I stoope, I fall, I will doe any thing;</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> me as Destiny: O stay,</L>
<L><PB REF="42"/>
My quicke Soule shall oretake thee: for, but we,</L>
<L>Neuer two reacht the height of Villany.</L>
<L>Strike, O strike.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>O-o-o-</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Here the Executioner strikes, and Herod dies.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aug.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whence came that deadly groane.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nir.</SPEAKER>
<L>From the King; the blow the Hangman gaue <HI>Antipater,</HI></L>
<L>Tooke his life in the Instant: Sir, hee's dead.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aug.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Gods haue shewd their wonders; some withdraw</L>
<L>The Bodies and interre them: that; where none</L>
<L>May pittie or lament him: th'other so;</L>
<L>As all men may admire him: for the Crowne,</L>
<L>Thus I bestow it on young <HI>Archelaus:</HI></L>
<L><HI>Rome</HI> makes thee King of <HI>Iuda;</HI> and erects</L>
<L>Thy Chayre and Throane within <HI>Ierusalem.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Sound Trumpets.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<L>Long liue <HI>Archelaus,</HI> King of <HI>Ierusalem.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arch.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will be <HI>Caesars</HI> seruant; and my life,</L>
<L>I hope shall purge these woes from <HI>Israell.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aug.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis a sweet royall Promise; prosper in't;</L>
<L>Make Vertue thy Companion: for we see,</L>
<L>She builds their ruines, spring from Tyrannie.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt omnes.</STAGE>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
<BACK>
<DIV1 TYPE="epilogue">
<HEAD>The EPILOGVE.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L>Y'Aue heard a Tale, which not a noble Eare</L>
<L>But ha's drunke with deuotion; and how ere</L>
<L>It scant in phraze or action; yet it may</L>
<L>Ranke with some others, and be held a Play,</L>
<L>Though not the best, nor worst; yet wee hope</L>
<L>It keepes the middle passage; thats the scope</L>
<L>Of our Ambition: But, of this w'are bold,</L>
<L>A truer Story nere was writ, or told:</L>
<L>If Enuy hurt it, tis our Fates; and we</L>
<L>Begge but your hands, for the Recouerie.</L>
</LG>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BACK>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

