<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2003-12-17</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Jonathan Blaney</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, etc.). Checked for signatures. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, and UNCLEARs. Corrected 37 $s of 47. Converted 10 $s to GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="OXF". Checked spacing of foreign GAPs. Checked for EPIGRAPHs and ARGUMENTs. Checked for startqs, endqs, oes, q;s, and Qs. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Checked for CLOSERs, TRAILERs, and BYLINEs. DONE.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="A07063">
<STC T="S">17473</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99845536</BIBNO>
<VID>10441</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>THE
HISTORY OF
Antonio and
Mellida. The first part. As it hath beene sundry times acted,
by the children of <HI>Paules.</HI></P>
<P>Written by <HI>I. M.</HI></P>
<P>LONDON
¶Printed for <HI>Mathewe Lownes,</HI> and <HI>Thomas Fisher,</HI> and
are to be soulde in Saint Dunstans Church-yarde.
1602.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>To the onely rewarder, and most iust
poiser of vertuous merits, the most hono∣rably
renowned No-body, bountious Me∣caenas
of Poetry, and Lord Protector
of oppressed innocence,
Do, Dedicoque.</HEAD>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">S</SEG>INCE it hath flow'd with the current of my
humorous bloode, to affect (a little too much)
to be seriously fantasticall: here take (most re∣spected
Patron) the worthlesse present of my
slighter idlenes. If you vouchsaf not his protectiō
then, O thou sweetest perfectiō (Female beau<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tie) shield mee
from the stopping of vineger bottles. Which most wished fa∣uour
if it faile me; then, <HI>Sinequeo flectere superos, A∣cheronta
mouebo.</HI> But yet, <HI>Honours redeemer, vertues
aduancer, religions shelter, and pieties fosterer,</HI> Yet, yet
I faint not in despaire of thy gratious affection &amp; protection:
to which I onely shall euer rest most seruingmanlike, obsequi∣ously
making legs, and standing (after our free-borne English
garbe) bare headed.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Thy onely assied slaue, and admirer,
<HI>I M.</HI></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<PB REF="3"/>
<PB REF="3"/>
<HEAD>The Play called Antonio and
Mellida.</HEAD>
<DIV2 TYPE="introduction">
<HEAD>Induction.</HEAD>
<STAGE>¶Enter Galeatzo, Piero, Alberto, Antonio, Forobosco, Ba∣lurdo,
Matzagente, &amp; Feliche, with parts in their hands:
hauing cloakes cast ouer their apparell.</STAGE>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">C</SEG>Ome sirs, come: the musique will sounde
straight for entrance. Are yee readie, are
yee perfect?</P>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pier.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith, we can say our parts: but wee
are ignorant in what mould we must cast our Actors.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Albert.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whome doe you personate?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie. Piero,</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Duke of</HI> Venice.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, ho: then thus frame your exterior shape,</L>
<L>To hautie forme of elate maiestie;</L>
<L>As if you held the palsey shaking head</L>
<L>Of reeling chaunce, vnder your fortunes belt,</L>
<L>In strictest vassalage: growe big in thought,</L>
<L>As swolne with glory of succesfull armes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>If that be all, feare not, Ile sute it right.</L>
<L>Who can not be proud, stroak vp the haire, and strut!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Truth: such ranke custome is growne popular;</L>
<L>And now the vulgar fashion strides as wide,</L>
<L>And stalkes as proud, vpon the weakest stilts</L>
<L>Of the slight'st fortunes, as if <HI>Hercules,</HI></L>
<L>Or burly <HI>Atlas</HI> shouldred vp their state.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good: but whome act you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<P>The necessitie of the play forceth me to act two
parts; <HI>Andrugio,</HI> the distressed Duke of <HI>Genoa,</HI> and
<HI>Alberto,</HI> a <HI>Venetian</HI> gentleman, enamoured on the La∣die
<HI>Rossaline:</HI> whose <HI>fortunes</HI> being too weake to sus∣taine
the port of her, he prou'd alwaies desastrous in
loue: his worth being much vnderpoised by the vne∣uen
<PB REF="4"/>
scale, that currants all thinges by the outwarde
stamp of opiniō.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wel, and what dost thou play?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<P>The part of all the world.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<P>The part of all the world? What's that?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<P>The foole. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> in good deede law now, I play <HI>Ba∣lurdo,</HI>
a wealthie mountbanking Burgomasco's heire
of <HI>Venice.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha, ha: one, whose foppish nature might seem
great, only for wise mens recreation; and, like a Iuice∣lesse
barke, to preserue the sap of more strenuous spi∣rits.
A seruile hounde, that loues the sent of forerun∣ning
fashion, like an emptie hollow vault, still giuing
an eccho to wit: greedily champing what any other
well valued iudgement had before hand shew'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Foro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha, ha, ha: tolerably good, good faith sweet wag.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Vmh, why tolerably good, good faith sweet wag?
Go, goe; you flatter me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Foro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Right, I but dispose my speach to the habit of
my part.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, what plaies he?</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>To Feliche.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fe.</SPEAKER>
<P>The wolfe, that eats into the breast of Princes; that
breeds the Lethargy and falling sicknesse in honour;
makes Iustice looke asquint, and blinks the eye of me∣rited
rewarde from viewing desertfull vertue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whats all this Periphrasis? ha?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fe.</SPEAKER>
<P>The substance of a supple-chapt flatterer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<P>O, doth he play <HI>Forobosco,</HI> the Parasite? Good i-faith.
Sirrah, you must seeme now as glib and straight
in outward semblance, as a Ladies buske; though in∣wardly,
as crosse as a paire of Tailors legs: hauing a
tongue as nimble as his needle, with seruile patches of
glauering flattery, to stitch vp the bracks of vnworthi∣ly
honourd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="4"/>
<SPEAKER>Fo.</SPEAKER>
<P>I warrant you, I warrant you, you shall see mee
prooue the very Perewig to couer the balde pate of
brainelesse gentilitie.</P>
<P>Ho, I will so tickle the sense of <HI>bella gratiosa madonna,</HI>
with the titillation of Hyperbolicall praise, that Ile
strike it in the nick, in the very nick, chuck.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou promisest more, than I hope any Specta∣tor
giues faith of performance: but why looke you so
duskie? ha?</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>To Antonio.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>I was neuer worse fitted since the natiuitie of my
Actorshippe: I shalt be hist at, on my life now.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, what must you play?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith, I know not what: an Hermaphrodite; two
parts in one: my true person being <HI>Antonio,</HI> son to the
Duke of <HI>Genoa;</HI> though for the loue of <HI>Mellida, Pieros</HI>
daughter, I take this fained presence of an <HI>Amazon,</HI> cal∣ling
my selfe <HI>Florizell,</HI> and I know not what. I a voice
to play a lady! I shall nere doe it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<P>O, an <HI>Amazon</HI> should haue such a voice, <HI>virago</HI>-like,
Not play two parts in one? away, away: tis com∣mon
fashion. Nay if you cannot bear two subtle frōts
vnder one hood, I de or goe by, goe by; off this worlds
stage. O times impuritie!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>An.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, but whē vse hath taught me actiō, to hit the right
point of a Ladies part, I shall growe ignorant when I
must turne young Prince againe, how but to trusse my
hose.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fe.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tush neuer put them off: for women weare the breaches still.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<P>By the bright honour of a <HI>Millanoise,</HI> and the re∣splendent
fulgor of this steele, I will defende the femi∣nine
to death; and ding his spirit to the verge of hell,
that dates divulge a ladies prei<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>dico.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Ant &amp; Al.</STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="5"/>
<SPEAKER>Fel</SPEAKER>
<L>Rampum scrampum, mount tuftie <HI>Tamburlaine.</HI></L>
<L>What rattling thunder clappe breakes from his lips?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<P>O, 'tis natiue to his part. For, acting a moderne
<HI>Bragadoch</HI> vnder the person of <HI>Matzagente,</HI> the Duke of
<HI>Millaines</HI> sonne, it may seeme to suite with good fa∣shion
of coherence.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>But me thinks he speakes with a spruce Attick ac∣cent
of adulterate Spanish.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<P>So 'tis resolu'd. For, <HI>Millane</HI> being halfe Spanish,
halfe high Dutch, and halfe Italians, the blood of chi∣fest
houses, is corrupt and mungrel'd: so that you shal
see a fellow vaine-glorious, for a Spaniard; gluttonous,
for a Dutchman; proud, for an Italian; and a fantastick
Ideot, for all. Such a one conceipt this <HI>Matzagente.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fe.</SPEAKER>
<P>But I haue a part allotted mee, which I haue nei∣ther
able apprehension to conceipt, nor what I con∣ceipt
gratious abilitie to vtter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whoop, in the old cut? good shew vs a draught of thy spirit.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis steddie, and must seeme so impregnably
fortrest with his own cōtent, that no enuious thought
could euer inuade his spirit: neuer surueying any man
so vnmeasuredly happie, whome I thought not iustly
hatefull for some true impouerishment: neuer behol∣ding
any fauour of Madam <HI>Felicity</HI> gracing another,
which his well bounded content perswaded not to
hang in the front of his owne fortune: and therefore
as farre from enuying any man, as he valued all men
infinitely distant from accomplisht beatitude. These
natiue adiuncts appropriate to me the name of <HI>Feli∣che.</HI>
But last, good thy humour.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Alb.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>A.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis to be describ'd by signes &amp; tokens. For vnlesse I
were possest with a legiō of spirits, 'tis impossible to be
<PB REF="5"/>
perspicuous by any vtterance: For sometimes he must
take austere state, as for the person of <HI>Galeatzo,</HI> the
sonne of the duke of <HI>Florence,</HI> &amp; possesse his exteriour
presence with a formall maiestie: keepe popularitie
in distance, and on the sudden fling his honour so pro∣digally
into a common Arme, that hee may seeme to
giue vp his indiscretion to the mercy of vulgar cēsure:
Now as solemne as a trauailer, and as graue as a Puri∣tanes
ruffe: with the same breath as slight and scat∣terd
in his fashion as as as a a any thing. Now, as
sweet and neat as a Barbours casting-bottle; straight
as slouenly as the yeasty breast of an Ale-knight: now,
lamenting: then chafing: straight laughing: then</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feli.</SPEAKER>
<P>What then?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith I know not what: 'rad bene a right part
for <HI>Proteus</HI> or <HI>Gew:</HI> ho, blinde <HI>Gew</HI> would ha don't
rarely, rarely.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feli.</SPEAKER>
<P>I feare it is not possible to limme so many per∣sons
in so small a tablet as the compasse of our playes
afford.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>Right: therefore I haue heard that those per∣sons,
as he &amp; you <HI>Feliche,</HI> that are but slightly drawen
in this Comedie, should receiue more exact accom∣plishment
in a second Part: which, if this obtaine gra∣tious
acceptance, meanes to try his fortune.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feli.</SPEAKER>
<P>Peace, here comes the Prologue, cleare the
Stage.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="prologue">
<PB REF="6"/>
<HEAD>¶The Prologue.</HEAD>
<L>THE wreath of pleasure, and delicious sweetes,</L>
<L>Begirt the gentle front of this faire troope:</L>
<L>Select, and most respected Auditours,</L>
<L>For wits sake doe not dreame of miracles.</L>
<L>Alas, we shall but falter, if you lay</L>
<L>The least sad waight of an vnused hope,</L>
<L>Vpon our weakenesse: onely we giue vp</L>
<L>The woorthlesse present of flight idlenesse,</L>
<L>To your authentick censure; Othat our Muse</L>
<L>Had those abstruse and synowy faculties,</L>
<L>That with a straine of fresh inuention</L>
<L>She might presse out the raritie of Art;</L>
<L>The pur'st elixed ioyce of rich conceipt,</L>
<L>In your attentiue eares; that with the lip</L>
<L>Of gratious elocution, we might drinke</L>
<L>A sound carouse vnto your health of wit.</L>
<L>But O, the heathy drynesse of her braine,</L>
<L>Foyle to your fertile spirits, is asham'd</L>
<L>To breath her blushing numbers to such eares:</L>
<L>Yet (most ingenious) deigne to vaile our wants;</L>
<L>With sleeke acceptance, polish these rude Sceanes:</L>
<L>And if our slightnesse your large hope beguiles,</L>
<L>Check not with bended brow, but dimpled smiles.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Prologue.</STAGE>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 N="1" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="6"/>
<HEAD>ACTVS PRIMVS.</HEAD>
<STAGE>¶The Cornets sound a battle within.</STAGE>
<STAGE>¶Enter Antonio, disguised like an Amazon.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>An.</SPEAKER>
<L>HEART, wilt not break! &amp; thou abhorred life</L>
<L>Wilt thou still breath in my enraged bloud?</L>
<L>Vaines, synewes, arteries, why crack yee not?</L>
<L>Burst and diuul'st, with anguish of my griefe.</L>
<L>Can man by no meanes creepe out of himselfe,</L>
<L>And leaue the slough of viperous griefe behinde?</L>
<L><HI>Antonio,</HI> hast thou seene a fight at sea,</L>
<L>As horrid as the hideous day of doome;</L>
<L>Betwixt thy father, duke of <HI>Genoa,</HI></L>
<L>And proud <HI>Piero,</HI> the <HI>Venetian</HI> Prince?</L>
<L>In which the sea hath swolne with <HI>Genoas</HI> bloud,</L>
<L>And made spring tydes with the warme reeking gore,</L>
<L>That gusht from out our Gallies scupper holes;</L>
<L>In which, thy father, poore <HI>Andrugio,</HI></L>
<L>Lyes sunk, or leapt into the armes of chaunce,</L>
<L>Choakt with the laboring Oceans brackish fome;</L>
<L>Who euen, despite <HI>Pieros</HI> can cred hate,</L>
<L>Would with an armed hand haue seiz'd thy loue,</L>
<L>And linkt thee to the beautious <HI>Mellida.</HI></L>
<L>Haue I outliu'd the death of all these hopes?</L>
<L>Haue I felt anguish pourd into my heart,</L>
<L>Burning like <HI>Balsamum</HI> in tender wounds;</L>
<L>And yet dost liue! could not the fretting sea</L>
<L>Haue rowl'd me vp in wrinkles of his browe?</L>
<L><PB REF="7"/>
Is death growen coy? or grim confusion nice?</L>
<L>That it will not accompany a wretch,</L>
<L>But I must needs be cast on <HI>Venice</HI> shoare?</L>
<L>And try new fortunes with this strange disguise?</L>
<L>To purchase my adored <HI>Mellida.</HI></L>
<STAGE>The Cornets sound a flourish: cease.</STAGE>
<L>Harke how <HI>Piero's</HI> triumphs beat the ayre,</L>
<L>O rugged mischiefe how thou grat'st my heart!</L>
<L>Take spirit, blood, disguise, be confident:</L>
<L>Make a firme stand, here rests the hope of all,</L>
<L>Lower then hell, there is no depth to fall.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>The Cornets sound a Synnet: Enter Feliche and Alberto,
Castilio and Forobosco, a Page carying a shield: Piero
in Armour: Catzo and Dildo and Balurdo: All these
(sauing Piero) armed with Petronels: Beeing entred,
they make a stand in diuided foyles.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Piero.</SPEAKER>
<L>Victorious Fortune, with tryumphant hand,</L>
<L>Hurleth my glory 'bout this ball of earth,</L>
<L>Whil'st the <HI>Venetian</HI> Duke is heaued vp</L>
<L>On wings of faire successe, to ouer-looke</L>
<L>The low cast ruines of his enemies,</L>
<L>To see my selfe ador'd, and <HI>Genoa</HI> quake,</L>
<L>My fate is firmer then mischance can shake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feli.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stand, the ground trembleth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Piero.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hah? an earthquake?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ball.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, I smell a sound.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feli.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Piero</HI> stay, for I descry a fume,</L>
<L>Creeping from out the bosome of the deepe,</L>
<L>The breath of darkenesse, fatall when 'tis whist</L>
<L><PB REF="7"/>
In greatnes stomacke: this same smoake, call'd pride,</L>
<L>Take heede shee'le lift thee to improuidence,</L>
<L>And breake thy necke from steepe securitie,</L>
<L>Shee'le make thee grudge to let <HI>Iehoua</HI> share</L>
<L>In thy successefull battailes: O, shee's ominous,</L>
<L>Inticeth princes to deuour heauen,</L>
<L>Swallow omnipotence, out-stare dread fate,</L>
<L>Subdue <HI>Eternitie</HI> in giant thought,</L>
<L>Heaues vp their hurt with swelling, puft conceit,</L>
<L>Till their soules burst with venom'd <HI>Arrogance:</HI></L>
<L>Beware <HI>Piero, Rome</HI> it selfe hath tried,</L>
<L>Confusions traine blowes vp this <HI>Babell</HI> pride.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pier.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Pish,</HI> Dimitto superos, summa votorum attigi.</L>
<L><HI>Alberto,</HI> hast thou yeelded vp our fixt decree</L>
<L>Vnto the <HI>Genoan</HI> Embassadour?</L>
<L>Are they content if that their duke returne,</L>
<L>To send his, and his sonne <HI>Antonios</HI> head,</L>
<L>As pledges steept in bloud, to gaine their peace?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<L>With most obsequious, sleek-brow'd intertain,</L>
<L>They all embrace it as most gratious.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pier.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are Proclamations sent through <HI>Italy,</HI></L>
<L>That whosoeuer brings <HI>Andrugios</HI> head,</L>
<L>Oryoung <HI>Anthonios,</HI> shall be guerdoned</L>
<L>With twentie thousand double Pistolets,</L>
<L>And be indeened to <HI>Pieros</HI> loue?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Forob.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are sent euery way: sound policy.</L>
<L>Sweete Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Confusion to these limber Sycophants.</L>
<L>No sooner mischief's borne in regenty,</L>
<L>But flattery christens it with pollicy.</L>
<STAGE>tacite.
Pier,</STAGE>
<L><PB REF="8"/>
<HI>VVhy then:</HI> O me Celitum excelsissimum!</L>
<L>The intestine malice, and inueterate hate</L>
<L>I alwaies bore to that <HI>Andrugio,</HI></L>
<L>Glories in triumph ore his misery:</L>
<L>Nor shall that carpet-boy <HI>Antonio</HI></L>
<L>Match with my daughter, sweet cheekt <HI>Mellida.</HI></L>
<L>No, the publick power makes my faction strong.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ill, when publick power strēgthneth priuate wrōg.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis horse-like, not for man, to know his force.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis god-like, for a man to feele remorse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pish, I prosecute my families reuenge,</L>
<L>VVhich Ile pursue with such a burning chace</L>
<L>Till I haue dri'd vp all <HI>Andrugios</HI> bloud;</L>
<L>VVeake rage, that with slight pittie is withstoode.</L>
<STAGE>¶The Cornets sound a florish.</STAGE>
<L>VVhat meanes that fresh triumphall florish sound?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<L>The prince of <HI>Millane,</HI> and young <HI>Florence</HI> heir
Approach to gratulate your victorie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVeele girt them with an ample waste of loue;</L>
<L>Conduct them to our presence royally.</L>
<L>Let vollies of the great Artillery</L>
<L>From of our gallies banks play prodigall,</L>
<L>And soūd lowd welcome frō their bellowing mouths.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Piero tantùm.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>¶The Cornets sound a Cynet. Enter aboue, Mellida, Ros∣saline
and Flauia: Enter belowe, Galeatzo with atten∣dants:
Piero meeteth him, embraceth; at which the Cor∣nets
sound a florish: Piero and Galeatzo exeunt: the rest
stand still.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mell.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhat prince was that passed through my fa∣thers
guard?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="8"/>
<SPEAKER>Fla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Twas <HI>Galeatzo,</HI> the young <HI>Florentine.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<L>Troth, one that will besiege thy maidenhead,</L>
<L>Enter the wals yfaith (sweet <HI>Mellida</HI>)</L>
<L>If that thy flankers be not Canon proofe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mell.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh <HI>Mary Ambree,</HI> good, thy iudgement wench;</L>
<L>Thy bright electious cleere, what will he prooue?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ross.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hath a short finger aud a naked chinne;</L>
<L>A skipping eye, dare lay my iudgement (faith)</L>
<L>His loue is glibbery; there's no hold ont, wench:</L>
<L>Giue me a husband whose aspect is firme,</L>
<L>A full cheekt gallant, with a bouncing thigh:</L>
<L>Oh, he is the <HI>Paradizo dell madonne contento.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mell.</SPEAKER>
<L>Euen such a one was my <HI>Antonio.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>¶The Cornets sound a Cynet.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rossa.</SPEAKER>
<L>By my nine and thirteth seruant (sweete)</L>
<L>Thou art in loue, but stand on tiptoed faire,</L>
<L>Here comes Saint <HI>Tristram Tirlery whiffe</HI> yfaith.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>¶Enter Matzagente, Piero meetes him, embraceth; at which
the Cornets sound a florish: they two stand, vsing seeming
complements, whilst the Sceane passeth aboue.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mell.</SPEAKER>
<L>S. <HI>Marke,</HI> S. <HI>Marke,</HI> what kind of thing appears?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ross.</SPEAKER>
<L>For fancies passion, spit vpon him; figh:</L>
<L>His face is varnisht: in the name of loue,</L>
<L>VVhat country bred that creature?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mell.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhat is he <HI>Flauia?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fla.</SPEAKER>
<L>The heire of <HI>Millane, Segnior Matzagent.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ross.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Matzagent?</HI> now by my pleasures hope,</L>
<L>He is made like a tilting staffe; and lookes</L>
<L>For all the world like an ore-rosted pigge:</L>
<L>A great <HI>Tobacco</HI> taker too, thats flat.</L>
<L><PB REF="9"/>
For his eyes looke as if they had bene hung</L>
<L>In the smoake of his nose.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mell.</SPEAKER>
<L>What husband, wil he prooue sweete <HI>Rossaline?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ross.</SPEAKER>
<L>Auoid him: for he hath a dwindled legge,</L>
<L>A lowe forehead, and a thinne cole-black beard,</L>
<L>And will be iealous too, beleeue it sweete:</L>
<L>For his chin sweats, and hath a gander neck,</L>
<L>A thinne lippe, and a little monkish eye:</L>
<L>Pretious, what a slender waste he hath!</L>
<L>He lookes like a May-pole, or a notched stick:</L>
<L>Heele snap in two at euery little straine.</L>
<L>Giue me a husband that will fill mine armes,</L>
<L>Of steddie iudgement, quicke and nimble sense:</L>
<L>Fooles relish not a Ladies excellence.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt all on the lower Stage: at which the Cornets sound a
florish, and a peale of shot is giuen.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mell.</SPEAKER>
<L>The tryumph's ended, but looke <HI>Rossaline,</HI></L>
<L>What gloomy soule in strange accustrements</L>
<L>Walkes on the pauement.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rossa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good sweete lets to her, pree the <HI>Mellida.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mell.</SPEAKER>
<L>How couetous thou art of nouelties!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rossa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pish, tis our nature to desire things</L>
<L>That are thought strangers to the common cut.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mell.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am exceeding willing, but—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ross.</SPEAKER>
<L>But what? pree the goe downe, lets see her face:</L>
<L>God send that neither wit nor beauty wants</L>
<L>Those tempting sweets, affections Adamants.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come downe, she comes like: O, no Simile</L>
<L>Is pretious, choyce, or elegant enough</L>
<L>To illustrate her descent: leape heart, she comes,</L>
<L><PB REF="9"/>
She comes: smile heauen, and softest Southern winde</L>
<L>Kisse her cheeke gently with perfumed breath.</L>
<L>She comes: Creations puritie, admir'd.</L>
<L>Ador'd, amazing raritie, she comes.</L>
<L>O now <HI>Antonio</HI> presse thy spirit forth</L>
<L>In following passion, knit thy senses close,</L>
<L>Heape vp thy powers, double all thy man:</L>
<STAGE>¶Enter Mellida, Rossaline, and Flauia.</STAGE>
<L>She comes. O how her eyes dart wonder on my heart!</L>
<L>Mount bloode, soule to my lips, tast <HI>Hebes</HI> cup:</L>
<L>Stand firme on decke, when beauties close fight's vp.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ladie, your strange habit doth beget</L>
<L>Our pregnant thoughts, euen great of much desire,</L>
<L>To be acquaint with your condition.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rossa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good sweete Lady, without more ceremonies,</L>
<L>What country claims your birth, &amp; sweet your name?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<L>In hope your bountie will extend it selfe,</L>
<L>In selfe same nature of faire curtesie,</L>
<L>Ile shunne all nicenesse; my nam's <HI>Florizell,</HI></L>
<L>My country <HI>Scythia,</HI> I am <HI>Amazon,</HI></L>
<L>Cast on this shore by furie of the sea.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ross.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay faith, sweete creature, weele not vaile our names.</L>
<L>It pleas'd the Font to dip me <HI>Rossaline.</HI></L>
<L>That Ladie beares the name of <HI>Mellida,</HI></L>
<L>The duke of <HI>Venice</HI> daughter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, I am oblig'd to kisse your hand,</L>
<L>By imposition of a now dead man.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>To Mellida kissing her hand.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rossa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now by my troth, I long beyond all thought,</L>
<L>To know the man; sweet beauty deigne his name.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="10"/>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ladie, the circumstance is tedious.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<L>Troth not a whit; good faire, lets haue it all:</L>
<L>I loue not, I, to haue a iot left out,</L>
<L>If the tale come from a lou'd Orator.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vouchsafe me then your hush't obseruances.</L>
<L>Vehement in pursuite of strange nouelties,</L>
<L>After long trauaile through the <HI>Asian</HI> maine,</L>
<L>I shipt my hopefull thoughts for <HI>Britany;</HI></L>
<L>Longing to viewe great natures miracle,</L>
<L>The glorie of our sex, whose fame doth strike</L>
<L>Remotest eares with adoration.</L>
<L>Sayling some two monthes with inconstant winds,</L>
<L>We view'd the glistering <HI>Venetian</HI> forts;</L>
<L>To which we made: when loe, some three leagues off,</L>
<L>We might descry a horred spectacle:</L>
<L>The issue of black fury strow'd the sea,</L>
<L>With tattered carcasses of splitted ships,</L>
<L>Halfe sinking, burning, floating, topsie turuie.</L>
<L>Not farre from these sad ruines of fell rage,</L>
<L>We might behold a creature presse the waues;</L>
<L>Senselesse he sprauld, all notcht with gaping wounds:</L>
<L>To him we made, and (short) we tooke him vp:</L>
<L>The first word that he spake was, <HI>Mellida;</HI></L>
<L>And then he swouned.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mell.</SPEAKER>
<L>Aye me!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why sigh you, faire?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ross.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nothing but little humours: good sweet, on.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<L>His wounds being drest, and life recouered,</L>
<L>We gan discourse; when loe, the sea grewe mad,</L>
<L>His bowels rumbling with winde passion,</L>
<L><PB REF="10"/>
Straightswarthy darknesse popt out <HI>Phoebus</HI> eye,</L>
<L>And blurd the iocund face of bright cheekt day;</L>
<L>Whilst crudl'd fogges masked euen darknesse brow:</L>
<L>Heauen bad's good night, and the rocks gron'd</L>
<L>At the intestine vprore of the maine.</L>
<L>Now gustie flawes strook vp the very heeles</L>
<L>Of our maine mast, whilst the keene lightning shot</L>
<L>Through the black bowels of the quaking ayte:</L>
<L>Straight chops a waue, and in his sliftred panch</L>
<L>Downe fals our ship, and there he breaks his neck:</L>
<L>Which in an instant vp was belkt againe.</L>
<L>VVhen thus this martyrd soule began to sigh;</L>
<L>" Giue me your hand (quoth he) now doe you graspe</L>
<L>" Th'vnequall mirrour of ragg'd misery:</L>
<L>" Is't not a horrid storme? O, well shap't sweete,</L>
<L>" Could your quicke eye strike through these gashed woūds,</L>
<L>" You should beholde a heart, a heart, faire creature,</L>
<L>" Raging more wilde then is this franticke sea.</L>
<L>" VVolt doe me a fauour, if thou chance suruiue?</L>
<L>" But visit <HI>Venice,</HI> kisse the pretious white</L>
<L>" Of my most; nay all all Epithites are base</L>
<L>" To attribute to gratious <HI>Mellida:</HI></L>
<L>" Tell her the spirit of <HI>Antonio</HI></L>
<L>" VVisheth his last gaspe breath'd vpon her breast.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhy weepes soft hearted <HI>Florisell?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas, the flintie rocks groand at his plaints.</L>
<L>Tell her (quoth he) that her obdurate sire</L>
<L>Hath crackt his bosome; therewithall he wept,</L>
<L>And thus sigh't on. The sea is merciful;</L>
<L>Looke how it gapes to bury all my griefe</L>
<L><PB REF="11"/>
Well, thou shalt haue it, thou shalt be his toumbe:</L>
<L>My faith in my loue liue; in thee, dy woe,</L>
<L>Dye vnmatcht anguish, dye <HI>Antonio:</HI></L>
<L>With that he totterd from the reeling decke,</L>
<L>And downe he sunke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ross.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pleasures bodie, what makes my Lady weepe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mell.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nothing, sweet <HI>Rossaline,</HI> but the ayer's sharpe.</L>
<L>My fathers Palace, Madam, will be proud</L>
<L>To entertaine your presence, if youle daine</L>
<L>To make repose within. Aye me!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ladie our fashion is not curious.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ross.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith all the nobler, tis more generous.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mell.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall I then know how fortune fell at last,</L>
<L>What succour came, or what strange fate insew'd?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most willingly: but this same court is vast,</L>
<L>And publike to the staring multitude.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rossa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweet Lady, nay good sweet, now by my troth</L>
<L>VVeele be bedfellowes: durt on complement froth.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt; Rossaline giuing Antonio the way.</STAGE>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="2" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACTVS SECVNDVS.</HEAD>
<STAGE>¶Enter Catzo (with a Capon) eating, Dildo following
him.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dil.</SPEAKER>
<P>HAH <HI>Catzo,</HI> your master wants a cleane tren∣cher:
doe you heare?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Balurdo</SPEAKER>
<P>cals for your diminutiue attendance.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Catz.</SPEAKER>
<P>The belly hath no eares <HI>Dildo.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good pugge giue me some capon.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="11"/>
<SPEAKER>Catz.</SPEAKER>
<P>No capon, no not a bitte yee smooth bully; ca∣pon's
no meat for <HI>Dildo:</HI> milke, milke, yee glibbery vr∣chin,
is foode for infants.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Vpon mine honour</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cat.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your honour with a paugh? slid, now euery Iack
an Apes loads his backe with the golden coat of ho∣nour;
euery Asse puts on the Lyons skinne and roars
his honour, vpon your honour. By my Ladies panta∣ble,
I feare I shall liue to heare a Vintners boy cry; tis
rich neat Canary, vpon my honour.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dil.</SPEAKER>
<P>My stomack's vp.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cat.</SPEAKER>
<P>I think thou art hungry.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dil.</SPEAKER>
<P>The match of furie is lighted, fastned to the lin∣stock
of rage, and will presently set fire to the touch∣hole
of intemperance, discharging the double coulue∣ring
of my incensement in the face of thy opprobrious
speach.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cat.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile stop the barrell thus; god <HI>Dildo,</HI> set not fire to
the touch-hole.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dil.</SPEAKER>
<P>My rage is stopt, and I wil eate to the health of
the foole thy master <HI>Castilio.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cat.</SPEAKER>
<P>And I will suck the iuyce of the capon, to the
health of the Idiot thy master <HI>Balurdo.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith, our masters are like a case of Rapiers shea∣thed
in one scabberd of folly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cat.</SPEAKER>
<P>Right dutch blades. But was't not rare sport at
the sea-battle, whilst rounce robble hobble roard from
the ship sides, to viewe our masters pluck their plumes
and droppe their feathers, for feare of being men of
marke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="12"/>
<SPEAKER>Dill.</SPEAKER>
<P>Slud (cri'd <HI>Signior Balurdo</HI>) O for <HI>Don Bessiclers</HI>
armour, in the Mirror of Knighthood: what coil's here?
O for an armour, Canon proofe: O, more cable, more
fetherbeds, more fetherbeds, more cable, till hee had
as much as my cable hatband, to fence him.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>¶Enter Flauia in haste, with a rebato.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Catz.</SPEAKER>
<P>Buxome <HI>Flauia:</HI> can you sing? song, song.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fla.</SPEAKER>
<P>My sweete <HI>Dildo,</HI> I am not for you at this time:
Madam <HI>Rossaline</HI> stayes for a fresh ruffe to appeare in
the presence: sweete away.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Twill not be so put off, delicate, delicious, spark
eyed, sleek skind, slēder wasted, clean legd, rarely shap't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fla.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVho, Ile be at all your seruice another season:
nay faith ther's reason in all things.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dil.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVould I were reason then, that I might be in
all things.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cat.</SPEAKER>
<P>The breefe and the semiquauer is, wee must
haue the descant you made vpon our names, ere you
depart.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fla.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith, the song will seeme to come off hardly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Catz.</SPEAKER>
<P>Troth not a whit, if you seeme to come off
quickly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fla.</SPEAKER>
<P>Peart <HI>Catzo,</HI> knock it lustily then.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>CANTANT.</STAGE>
<STAGE>¶Enter Forcbosco, with two torches: Castilio singing fan∣tastically:
Rossaline running a Caranto pase, and Balur∣do:
Feliche following, wondring at them all.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Foro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Make place gentlemen; pages, hold torches,
the prince approacheth the presence.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dill.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhat squeaking cart-wheel haue we here? ha?
<PB REF="12"/>
Make place gentlemen, pages holde torches, the
prince approacheth the presence.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faugh, what a strong sent's here, some bodie
vseth to weare socks.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<P>By this faire candle light, tis not my feete, I ne∣uer
wore socks since I suckt pappe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ross.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sauourly put off.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hah, her wit stings, blisters, galles off the skinne
with the tart acrimony of her sharpe quicknesse: by
sweetenesse, she is the very <HI>Pallas</HI> that flewe out of <HI>Iu∣piters</HI>
brainepan. Delicious creature, vouchsafe mee
your seruice: by the puritie of bounty, I shall be proud
of such bondage.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ross.</SPEAKER>
<P>I vouchsafe it; be my slaue. <HI>Signior Balurdo,</HI> wilt
thou be my seruant too?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<P>O god: forsooth in very good earnest, law, you wold
make me as a man should say, as a man should say.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fe.</SPEAKER>
<P>Slud sweet beauty, will you deign him your seruice?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<P>O, your foole is your only seruant. But good <HI>Fe∣liche</HI>
why art thou so sad? a pennie for thy thought, mā.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feli.</SPEAKER>
<P>I sell not my thought so cheap: I valewe my
meditation at a higher rate.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ball.</SPEAKER>
<P>In good sober sadnesse, sweet mistris, you should
haue had my thought for a penny: by this crimson Sat∣ten
that cost eleuen shillings, thirteene pence, three
pence, halfe pennie a yard, that you should, law.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhat was thy thought, good seruant?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<P>Marrie forsooth, hovv manie strike of pease would
feed a hog far against Christide.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o.</SPEAKER>
<P>Paugh; seruant rub out my rheum, it soiles the pre∣sence.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="13"/>
<SPEAKER>Casti.</SPEAKER>
<P>By my wealthiest thought, you grace my shoo
with an vnmeasured honour: I will preserue the soale
of it, as a most sacred relique, for this seruice.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ross.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile spit in thy mouth, and thou wilt, to grace
thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Felich.</SPEAKER>
<L>O that the stomack of this queasie age</L>
<L>Digestes, or brookes such raw vnseasoned gobs,</L>
<L>And vomits not them forth! O slauish sots.</L>
<L>Seruant quoth you? faugh: if a dogge should craue</L>
<L>And beg her seruice, he should haue it straight:</L>
<L>Sheed giue him fauours too; to lick her feete,</L>
<L>Or fetch her fanne, or some such drudgery:</L>
<L>A good dogs office, which these amorists</L>
<L>Tryumph of: tis rare, well giue her more Asse,</L>
<L>More sot, as long as dropping of her nose</L>
<L>Is sworne rich pearle by such low slaues as those.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ross.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Flauia,</HI> attend me to attire me.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Rossaline and Flauia.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Balur.</SPEAKER>
<P>In sad good earnest, sir, you haue toucht the
very bare of naked truth; my silk stocking hath a good
glosse, and I thanke my planets, my legge is not alto∣gether
vnpropitiously shap't. There's a word: vnpro∣pitiously?
I thinke I shall speake vnpropitiously as well
as any courtier in <HI>Italy.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Foro.</SPEAKER>
<P>So helpe me your sweete bounty, you haue the
most gracefull presence, applasiue elecuty, amazing
volubility, polisht adornation, delicious affabilitie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whop: fut how he tickles yon trout vnder the
gilles! you shall see him take him by and by, with gro∣ping
flattery.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="13"/>
<SPEAKER>Foro.</SPEAKER>
<P>That euer rauisht the eare of wonder. By
your sweete selfe, then whome I knowe not a more
exquisite, illustrate, accomplished, pure, respected, a∣dor'd,
obserued, pretious, reall, magnanimous, boū∣tious:
if you haue an idle rich cast ierkin, or so, it shall
not be cast away, if; hah? heres a foreheade, an eye,
a heade, a haire, that would make a: or if you haue a∣ny
spare paire of siluer spurs, ile doe you as much
right in all kinde offices</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Of a kinde Parasite</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Foro.</SPEAKER>
<P>As any of my meane fortunes shall be able to</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Balur.</SPEAKER>
<P>As I am true Christian now, thou hast wonne
the spurres</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feli.</SPEAKER>
<L>For flattery.</L>
<L>O how I hate that same Egyptian louse;</L>
<L>A rotten maggot, that liues by stinking filth</L>
<L>Of tainted spirits: vengeance to such dogs,</L>
<L>That sprout by gnawing senselesse carion.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>¶Enter Alberto.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gallants, saw you my mistresse, the Ladie <HI>Ros∣saline?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Foro.</SPEAKER>
<P>My mistresse, the Ladie <HI>Rossaline,</HI> left the pre∣sence
euen now.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casti.</SPEAKER>
<P>My mistresse, the Ladie <HI>Rossaline,</HI> withdrewe
her gratious aspect euen now.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Balur.</SPEAKER>
<P>My mistresse, the Ladie <HI>Rossaline,</HI> withdrewe
her gratious aspect euen now.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Felich.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well said eccho.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<P>My mistresse, and his mistresse, and your mi∣stresse,
&amp; the dogs mistresse: pretious dear heauen, that</P>
<L><PB REF="14"/>
<HI>Alberto</HI> liues, to haue such riuals.</L>
<L>Slid, I haue bin searching euery priuate rome,</L>
<L>Corner, and secret angle of the court:</L>
<L>And yet, and yet, and yet she liues conceal'd.</L>
<L>Good sweete <HI>Feliche,</HI> tell me how to finde</L>
<L>My bright fac't mistresse out.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why man, cry out for lanthorne and candle∣light.
For tis your onely way, to finde your bright fla∣ming
wench, with your light burning torch: for most
commonly, these light creatures liue in darknesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Away you heretike, youle be burnt for</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Goe, you amorous hound, follow the sent of
your mistresse shooe; away.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Foro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Make a faire presence, boyes, aduance your
lightes:</P>
<P>The Princesse makes approach.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<P>And please the gods, now in very good deede,
law, you shal see me tickle the measures for the heauēs,
Doe my hangers showe?</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>¶Enter Piero, Antonio, Mellida, Rossaline, Galeatzo, Mat∣zagente,
Alberto, and Flauia. As they enter, Feliche, &amp;
Castilio make a ranke for the Duke to passe through. Foro∣bosco
vshers the Duke to his state: then whilst Piero spea∣keth
his first speach, Mellida is taken by Galeatzo and
Matzagente, to daunce; they supporting her: Rossa∣line,
in like maner, by Alberto and Balurdo: Flauia, by
Feliche and Castilio.</STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="14"/>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beautious Amazon, sit, and seat your thoughts</L>
<L>In the reposure of most soft content.</L>
<L>Sound musick there. Nay daughter, cleare your eyes,</L>
<L>From these dull fogs of mistie discontent:</L>
<L>Look sprightly girl. What? though <HI>Antonio's</HI> droun'd,</L>
<L>That peeuish dotard on thy excellence,</L>
<L>That hated issue of <HI>Andrugio:</HI></L>
<L>Yet maist thou tryumph in my victories;</L>
<L>Since, loe, the high borne bloodes of Italy</L>
<L>Sue for thy seate of loue.</L>
<STAGE>Let musique sound.</STAGE>
<L>Beautie and youth run descant on loues ground.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Matz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ladie, erect your gratious summetry:</L>
<L>Shine in the spheare of sweete affection:</L>
<L>Your eye as heauie, as the heart of night.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mell.</SPEAKER>
<P>My thoughts are as black as your bearde, my
fortunes as ill proportioned as your legs; and all the
powers of my minde, as leaden as your wit, and as
dustie as your face is swarthy.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith sweet, ile lay thee on the lips for that iest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mell.</SPEAKER>
<L>I pree thee intrude not on a dead mans right.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gal.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, but the liuings iust possession.</L>
<L>Thy lips, and loue, are mine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mell.</SPEAKER>
<L>You nere tooke seizin on them yet: forbeare:</L>
<L>There's not a vacant corner of my heart,</L>
<L>But all is fild with deade <HI>Antonios</HI> losse.</L>
<L>Then vrge no more; O leaue to loue at all;</L>
<L>Tis lesse disgracefull, not to mount, then fall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bright and refulgent Ladie, daine your eare:</L>
<L>You see this blade, had it a courtly lip,</L>
<L>It would diuulge my valour, plead my loue,</L>
<L><PB REF="15"/>
Iustle that skipping feeble amorist</L>
<L>Out of your loues seat; I am <HI>Matzagent.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gale.</SPEAKER>
<L>Harke thee, I pray thee taint not thy sweete eare</L>
<L>With that sots gabble; By thy beautious cheeke,</L>
<L>He is the flagging'st bulrush that ere droopt</L>
<L>With each slight mist of raine. But with pleas'd eye</L>
<L>Smile on my courtshippe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>What said you sir? alas my thought was fixt</L>
<L>Vpon another obiect. Good, forbeare:</L>
<L>I shall but weepe. Aye me, what bootes a teare!</L>
<L>Come, come, lets daunce. O musicke thou distill'st</L>
<L>More sweetnesse in vs then this iarring world:</L>
<L>Both time and measure from thy straines doe breath,</L>
<L>Whilst from the channell of this durt doth flowe</L>
<L>Nothing but timelesse griefe, vnmeasured woe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<L>O how impatience cramps my cracked veins,</L>
<L>And cruddles thicke my blood, with boiling rage!</L>
<L>O eyes, why leape you not like thunderbolts,</L>
<L>Or canon bullets in my riuals face;</L>
<L>Oy me infeliche misero, o lamenteuol fato!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alber.</SPEAKER>
<L>What meanes the Lady fal vpon the groūd?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ross.</SPEAKER>
<L>Belike the falling sicknesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<L>I cannot brooke this sight, my thoughts grow wilde:</L>
<L>Here lies a wretch, on whome heauen neuer smilde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ross.</SPEAKER>
<L>What seruant, nere a word, and I here man?</L>
<L>I would shoot some speach forth, to strike the time</L>
<L>With pleasing touch of amorous complement.</L>
<L>Say sweete, what keepes thy minde, what think'st thou</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nothing. on?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rossa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whats that nothing?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="15"/>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<L>A womans constancie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rossa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good, why, would'st thou haue vs sluts, &amp; ne∣uer
shift the vestur of our thoughts? Away for shame.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<L>O no, thart too constant to afflict my heart,</L>
<L>Too too firme fixed in vnmooued scorne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ross.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pish, pish; I fixed in vnmooued scorne?</L>
<L>Why, Ile loue thee to night.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<L>But whome to morrow?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ross.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith, as the toy puts me in the head.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<P>And pleased the marble heauens, now would I
might be the toy, to put you in the head, kindly to con∣ceipt
my my my: pray you giue in an Epithite for loue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Roaring, roaring.</P>
<P>O loue thou hast murdred me, made me a shadowe,
and you heare not <HI>Balurdo,</HI> but <HI>Balurdos</HI> ghost.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rossa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Can a ghost speake?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Scuruily, as I doe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ross.</SPEAKER>
<P>And walke?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<P>After their fashion.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ross.</SPEAKER>
<P>And eate apples?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<P>In a sort, in their garbe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feli.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pree thee <HI>Flauia</HI> be my mistresse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fla.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your reason, good <HI>Feliche?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith, I haue nineteene mistresses alreadie, and I
not much disdeigne that thou shold'st make vp the ful
score.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fla.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh, I heare you make common places of your
mistresses, to performe the office of memory by. Pray
you, in auncient times were not those satten hose? In
good faith, now they are new dyed, pinkt &amp; scoured,
<PB REF="16"/>
they showe as well as if they were new.</P>
<P>What, mute <HI>Balurdo?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feli.</SPEAKER>
<P>I in faith, &amp; twere not for printing, and painting,
my breech, and your face would be out of reparation.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, an faith, and twere not for printing, &amp; poin∣ting,
my breech, and your face would be out of repa∣ration.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good againe, Echo.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fla.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou art, by nature, too foule to be affected.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feli.</SPEAKER>
<L>And thou, by Art, too faire to be beloued.</L>
<L>By wits life, most sparke spirits, but hard chance.</L>
<L>La ty dine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gallants, the night growes old; &amp; downy sleep</L>
<L>Courts vs, to entertaine his company:</L>
<L>Our tyred lymbes, brus'd in the morning fight,</L>
<L>Intreat soft rest, and gentle husht repose.</L>
<L>Fill out Greeke wines; prepare fresh cressit-light:</L>
<L>Weele haue a banquet: Princes, then good night.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>¶The Cornets sound a Synnet, and the Duke goes out in
state. As they are going out, Antonio stayes Mellida:
the rest Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>An.</SPEAKER>
<L>What meanes these scattred looks? why tremble you?</L>
<L>Why quake your thoughts, in your distracted eyes?</L>
<L>Collect your spirits, Madam; what doe you see?</L>
<L>Dost not beholde a ghost?</L>
<L>Look, look where he stalks, wrapt vp in clouds of grief,</L>
<L>Darting his sowle, vpon thy wondring eyes.</L>
<L>Looke, he comes towards thee; see, he stretcheth out</L>
<L><PB REF="16"/>
His wretched armes to girt thy loued waste,</L>
<L>With a most wisht embrace: see'st him not yet?</L>
<L>Nor yet? Ha, <HI>Mellida;</HI> thou well maist erre:</L>
<L>For looke; he walkes not like <HI>Antonio:</HI></L>
<L>Like that <HI>Antonio,</HI> that this morning shone,</L>
<L>In glistering habilliments of armes,</L>
<L>To seize his loue, spight of her fathers spite:</L>
<L>But like himselfe, wretched, and miserable,</L>
<L>Banisht, forlorne, despairing, strook quite through,</L>
<L>With sinking griefe, rowld vp in seauen-fould doubles</L>
<L>Of plagues, vanquishable: harke, he speakes to thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mell.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas, I can not heare, nor see him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why? al this night about the roome he stalkt,</L>
<L>And groand, and houl'd, with raging passion,</L>
<L>To view his loue (life blood of all his hopes,</L>
<L>Crowne of his fortunes) clipt by strangers armes.</L>
<L>Looke but behinde thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, <HI>Antonio;</HI> my Lord, my Loue, my</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>An.</SPEAKER>
<L>Leaue passion, sweet; for time, place, aire, &amp; earth,</L>
<L>Are all our foes: feare, and be iealous; faire,</L>
<L>Lets fly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mell.</SPEAKER>
<L>Deare heart; ha, whether?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, tis no matter whether, but lets fly.</L>
<L>Ha! now I thinke ont, I haue nere a home:</L>
<L>No father, friend, no country to imbrace</L>
<L>These wretched limbes: the world, the All that is,</L>
<L>Is all my foe: a prince not worth a doite:</L>
<L>Onelie my head is hoised to high rate,</L>
<L>Worth twentie thousand double Pistolets,</L>
<L>To him that can but strike it from these shoulders.</L>
<L><PB REF="17"/>
But come sweete creature, thou shalt be my home;</L>
<L>My father, country, riches, and my friend:</L>
<L>My all, my soule; and thou and I will liue:</L>
<L>(Lets thinke like what) and thou and I will liue</L>
<L>Like vnmatcht mirrors of calamitie.</L>
<L>The iealous eare of night eaue-drops our talke.</L>
<L>Holde thee, thers a iewell; &amp; look thee, thers a note</L>
<L>That will direct thee when, where, how to fly;</L>
<L>Bid me adieu.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mell.</SPEAKER>
<L>Farewell bleak misery.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay sweet, lets kisse before you goe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Farewell deare soule.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Farewell my life, my heart.</L>
</SP>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="3" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACTVS TERTIVS.</HEAD>
<STAGE>¶Enter Andrugio in armour, Lucio with a sheepeheard
gowne in his hand, and a Page.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Andr.</SPEAKER>
<L>IS not yon gleame, the shuddering morne that flakes,</L>
<L>With siluer tinctur, the east vierge of heauen?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lu.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thinke it is, so please your excellence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Andr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away, I haue no excellence to please.</L>
<L>Pree the obserue the custome of the world,</L>
<L>That onely flatters greatnesse, States exalts.</L>
<L>And please my excellence! O <HI>Lucio.</HI></L>
<L>Thou hast bin euer held respected deare,</L>
<L>Euen pretious to <HI>Andrugios</HI> in most loue.</L>
<L>Good, flatter not. Nay, if thou giu'st not faith</L>
<L>That I am wretched, O read that, read that.</L>
<LETTER>
<PB REF="17"/>
<HEAD>Piero Sforza, to the Italian
Princes, fortune.</HEAD>
<P>EXCELLENT, the iust ouerthrowe, <HI>Andrugio</HI>
tooke in the <HI>Venetian</HI> gulfe, hath so assured the <HI>Geno∣waies</HI>
of the iustice of his cause, and the hatefulnesse of his
person, that they haue banisht him and all his family: and,
for confirmation of their peace with vs, haue vowed, that if
he, or his sonne, can be attached, to send vs both their heads.
Wee therefore, by force of our vnited league, forbid you to
harbour him, or his blood: but if you apprehend his person,
we intreat you to send him, or his head, to vs. For wee vowe
by the honour of our blood, to recompence any man that
bringeth his head, with twentie thousand double Pistolets,
and the indeering to our choysest loue.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED><HI>From</HI> Venice: PIERO SFORZA.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</LETTER>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Andr.</SPEAKER>
<L>My thoughts are fixt in contemplation</L>
<L>Why this huge earth, this monstrous animal,</L>
<L>That eates her children, should not haue eyes &amp; ears.</L>
<L>Philosophie maintaines that Natur's wise,</L>
<L>And formes no vselesse or vnperfect thing.</L>
<L>Did Nature make the earth, or the earth Nature?</L>
<L>For earthly durt makes all things, makes the man,</L>
<L>Moulds me vp honour; and like a cunning Dutchmā,</L>
<L>Paints me a puppit euen with seeming breath,</L>
<L>And giues a sot appearance of a soule,</L>
<L>Goe to, goe to; thou liest Philosophy.</L>
<L><PB REF="18"/>
Nature formes things vnperfect, vselesse, vaine.</L>
<L>Why made she not the earth with eyes and eares?</L>
<L>That she might see desert, and heare mens plaints:</L>
<L>That when a soule is splitted, sunke with griefe,</L>
<L>He might fall thus, vpon the breast of earth;</L>
<L>And in her eare, halloo his misery:</L>
<L>Exclaming thus. O thou all bearing earth,</L>
<L>Which men doe gape for, till thou cramst their mouths,</L>
<L>And choakst their throts with dust: O chaune thy brest,</L>
<L>And let me sinke into thee. Looke who knocks;</L>
<L><HI>Andrugio</HI> cals. But O, she's deafe and blinde.</L>
<L>A wretch, but leane reliefe on earth can finde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweet Lord, abandon passion, and disarme.</L>
<L>Since by the fortune of the tumbling sea,</L>
<L>We are rowl'd vp, vpon the <HI>Venice</HI> marsh,</L>
<L>Lets clip all fortune, least more lowring fate</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>More lowring fate? O <HI>Lucio,</HI> choak that breath.</L>
<L>Now I defie chaunce. Fortunes browe hath frown'd,</L>
<L>Euen to the vtmost wrinkle it can bend:</L>
<L>Her venom's spit. Alas, what country rests,</L>
<L>What sonne, what comfort that she can depriue?</L>
<L>Tryumphes not <HI>Venice</HI> in my ouerthrow?</L>
<L>Gapes not my natiue country for my blood?</L>
<L>Lies not my sonne tomb'd in the swelling maine?</L>
<L>And yet more lowring fate? There's nothing left</L>
<L>Vnto <HI>Andrugio,</HI> but <HI>Andrugio:</HI></L>
<L>And that nor mischief, force, distresse, nor hel can take.</L>
<L>Fortune my fortunes, not my minde shall shake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speake like your selfe: but giue me leaue, my Lord,</L>
<L>To wish your safetie. If you are but seene,</L>
<L><PB REF="18"/>
Your armes display you; therefore put them off,</L>
<L>And take</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would'st thou haue me go vnarm'd among my foes?</L>
<L>Being besieg'd by passion, entring lists,</L>
<L>To combat with despaire and mightie griefe:</L>
<L>My soule beleaguerd with the crushing strength</L>
<L>Of sharpe impatience. Ha <HI>Lucio,</HI> goe vnarm'd?</L>
<L>Come soule, resume the valour of thy brith;</L>
<L>My selfe, my selfe will dare all opposits:</L>
<L>Ile muster forces, an vnuanquisht power:</L>
<L>Cornets of horse shall presse th'vngratefull earth;</L>
<L>This hollow wombed masse shall inly grone,</L>
<L>And murmur to sustaine the waight of armes:</L>
<L>Gastly amazement, with vpstarted haire,</L>
<L>Shall hurry on before, and vsher vs,</L>
<L>Whil'st trumpets clamour, with a sound of death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace, good my Lord, your speach is al too light.</L>
<L>Alas, suruey your fortunes, looke what's left</L>
<L>Of all your forces, and your vtmost hopes?</L>
<L>A weake old man, a Page, and your poore selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Andrugio</HI> liues, and a faire cause of armes,</L>
<L>Why that's an armie all inuincible.</L>
<L>He who hath that, hath a battalion</L>
<L>Royal, armour of proofe, huge troups of barbed steeds,</L>
<L>Maine squares of pikes, millions of harguebush.</L>
<L>O, a faire cause stands firme, and will abide.</L>
<L>Legions of Angels fight vpon her side.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then, noble spirit, slide in strange disguise,</L>
<L>Vnto some gratious Prince, and soiourne there,</L>
<L>Till time, and fortune giue reuenge firme meanes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="19"/>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, ile not trust the honour of a man:</L>
<L>Golde is growne great, and makes <HI>perfidiousnesse</HI></L>
<L>A common water in most Princes Courts:</L>
<L>He's in the Chekle-roule: Ile not trust my blood;</L>
<L>I know none breathing, but will cogge a dye</L>
<L>For twentie thousand double Pistolets.</L>
<L>How goes the time?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<P>I saw no sunne to day.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>No sun wil shine, where poor <HI>Andrugio</HI> breaths,</L>
<L>My soule growes heauie: boy let's haue a song:</L>
<L>Weele sing yet, faith, euen despite of fate.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>CANTANT.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis a good boy, &amp; by my troth, well sung.</L>
<L>O, and thou felt'st my griefe, I warrant thee,</L>
<L>Thou would'st haue strook diuision to the height;</L>
<L>And made the life of musicke breath: hold boy: why so?</L>
<L>For Gods sake call me not <HI>Andrugio,</HI></L>
<L>That I may soone forget what I haue bin.</L>
<L>For heauens name, name not <HI>Antonio;</HI></L>
<L>That I may not remember he was mine.</L>
<L>Well, ere yon sunne set, ile shew my selfe my selfe,</L>
<L>Worthy my blood. I was a Duke; that's all.</L>
<L>No matter whether, but from whence we fall.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>¶Enter Feliche walking, vnbrac't.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fe.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Castilio? Alberto? Balurdo?</HI> none vp?</L>
<L><HI>Forobosco?</HI> Flattery, nor thou vp yet:</L>
<L>Then there's no Courtier stirring: that's firme truth?</L>
<L>I cannot sleepe: <HI>Feliche</HI> seldome rests</L>
<L><PB REF="19"/>
In these court lodgings. I haue walkt all night,</L>
<L>To see if the nocturnall court delights</L>
<L>Could force me enuie their felicitie:</L>
<L>And by plaine troth; I will confesse plaine troth:</L>
<L>I enuie nothing, but the Trauense light.</L>
<L>O, had it eyes, and eares, and tongues, it might</L>
<L>See sport, heare speach of most strange surquedries.</L>
<L>O, if that candle-light were made a Poet,</L>
<L>He would prooue a rare firking Satyrist,</L>
<L>And drawe the core forth of impostum'd sin.</L>
<L>Well, I thanke heauen yet, that my content</L>
<L>Can enuie nothing, but poore candle-light.</L>
<L>As for the other glistering copper spangs,</L>
<L>That glisten in the tyer of the Court,</L>
<L>Praise God, I eyther hate, or pittie them.</L>
<L>Well here ile sleepe till that the sceane of vp</L>
<L>Is past at Court. O calme husht rich content,</L>
<L>Is there a being blessednesse without thee?</L>
<L>How soft thou down'st the couch where thou dost rest,</L>
<L>Nectar to life, thou sweet Ambrosian feast.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>¶Enter Catilio and his Page: Castilio with a casting bottle
of sweete water in his hand, sprinkling himselfe.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<L>Am not I a most sweete youth now?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, when your throat's perfum'd; your verie words</L>
<L>Doe smell of Amber greece. O stay sir, stay;</L>
<L>Sprinkle some sweete water to your shooes heeles,</L>
<L>That your mistresse may swear you haue a sweet foot.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good, very good, very passing passing good.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="20"/>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fut, what trebble minikin squeaks there, ha? good?
very good, very very good?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casti.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will warble to the delicious concaue of my</L>
<L>Mistresse eare: and strike her thoughts with</L>
<L>The pleasing touch of my voice.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>CANTANT.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Feliche,</HI> health, fortune, mirth, and wine,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<L>To thee my loue diuine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<L>I drinke to thee, sweeting.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Plague on thee for an Asse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now thou hast seene the Court; by the perfec∣ction
of it, dost not enuie it?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<L>I wonder it doth not enuie me.</L>
<L>Why man, I haue bene borne vpon the spirits wings,</L>
<L>The soules swift <HI>Pegasus,</HI> the fantasie:</L>
<L>And from the height of contemplation,</L>
<L>Haue view'd the feeble ioynts men totter on.</L>
<L>I enuie none; but hate, or pittie all.</L>
<L>For when I viewe, with an intentiue thought,</L>
<L>That creature faire; but proud; him rich, but sot:</L>
<L>Th'other wittie; but vnmeasured arrogant:</L>
<L>Him great; yet boundlesse in ambition:</L>
<L>Him high borne; but of base life: to' ther feard;</L>
<L>Yet feared feares, and fears most, to be most loued:</L>
<L>Him wise; but made a foole for publick vse:</L>
<L>Th'other learned, but selfe-opinionate:</L>
<L>When I discourse all these, and see my selfe</L>
<L>Nor faire, nor rich, nor wittie, great, nor fear'd:</L>
<L><PB REF="20"/>
Yet amply suted, with all full content:</L>
<L>Lord, how I clap my hands, and smooth my brow,</L>
<L>Rubbing my quiet bosome, tossing vp</L>
<L>A gratefull spirit to omnipotence!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, ha: but if thou knew'st my happinesse,</L>
<L>Thou wouldst euen grate away thy soule to dust,</L>
<L>In enuy of my sweete beatitude:</L>
<L>I can not sleepe for kisses; I can not rest</L>
<L>For Ladies letters, that importune me</L>
<L>With such vnused vehemence of loue,</L>
<L>Straight to solicit them, that</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feli.</SPEAKER>
<L>Confusion seize me, but I thinke thou lyest.</L>
<L>Why should I not be sought to then aswell?</L>
<L>Fut, me thinks, I am as like a man▪</L>
<L>Troth, I haue a good head of haire, a cheeke</L>
<L>Not as yet wan'd; a legge, faith, in the full.</L>
<L>I ha not a red beard, take not tobacco much:</L>
<L>And S'lid, for other parts of manlinesse</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pew waw, you nere accourted them in
pompe:</L>
<L>Put your good parts in presence, gratiously.</L>
<L>Ha, and you had, why they would ha come of, sprung</L>
<L>To your armes: and su'd, and prai'd, and vow'd;</L>
<L>And opened all their sweetnesse to your loue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<L>There are a number of such things, as then</L>
<L>Haue often vrg'd me to such loose beliefe:</L>
<L>But S'lid you all doe lye, you all doe lie.</L>
<L>I haue put on good cloathes, and smugd my face,</L>
<L>Strook a faire wench, with a smart speaking eye:</L>
<L>Courted in all sorts, blunt, and passionate;</L>
<L><PB REF="21"/>
Had opportunitie put them to the ah:</L>
<L>And, by this light, I finde them wondrous chaste,</L>
<L>Impregnable; perchance a kisse, or so:</L>
<L>But for the rest, O most inexorable.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay then ifaith, pree thee looke here.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>¶Shewes him the superscription of a seeming Letter.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<L>To her most esteemed, lou'd, and generous seruant, Sig.</L>
<L>Castilio Balthazar.</L>
<L>Pree the from whome comes this? faith I must see.</L>
<STAGE>From her that is deuoted to thee, in most priuate sweetes of
loue; Rossaline.</STAGE>
<L>Nay, god's my comfort, I must see the rest;</L>
<L>I must, <HI>sans</HI> ceremonie, faith I must.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Feliche takes away the letter by force.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<P>O, you spoyle my ruffe, vnset my haire; good
away.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Item for strait canuas, thirteene pence, halfe
penny. Item for an elle and a halfe of taffata to couer
your olde canuas dubblet, foureteen shillings, &amp; three
pence. S'light, this a tailors bill.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<L>In sooth it is the outside of her letter; on which</L>
<L>I tooke the copie of a tailors bill.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dil.</SPEAKER>
<P>But tis not crost, I am sure of that. Lord haue
mercie on him, his credit hath giuen vp the last gaspe.
Faith ile leaue him; for hee lookes as melancholy as
a wench the first night she</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feli.</SPEAKER>
<P>Honest musk-cod, twill not be so stitched toge∣ther;
take that, and that, and belie no Ladies loue:
sweare no more by Iesu: this Madam, that Ladie;
hence goe, forsweare the presence, trauaile three years
<PB REF="21"/>
to bury this bastinado: auoide, puffe paste, auoide.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<P>And tell not my Ladie mother. Well, as I am
true gentleman, if she had not wild me on her blessing,
not to spoyle my face; if I could not finde in my heart
to fight, would I might nere eate a Potatoe pye more.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>¶Enter Balurdo, backward; Dildo following him with a
looking glasse in one hand, &amp; a candle in the other hand:
Flauia following him backward, with a looking glasse in
one hand, and a candle in the other; Rossaline following
her. Balurdo and Rossaline stand setting of faces: and so
the Sceane begins.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<P>More foole, more rare fooles! O, for time and
place, long enough, and large enough, to acte these
fooles! Here might be made a rare Scene of folly, if
the plat could beare it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<P>By the suger-candy sky, holde vp the glasse
higher, that I may see to sweare in fashion. O, one loofe
more would ha made them shine; gods neakes, they
would haue shone like my mystresse browe. Euen so
the Duke frownes for all this Cursond world: oh that
gerne kils, it kils. By my golden What's the richest
thing about me?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your teeth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<P>By my golden teeth, hold vp; that I may put in:
hold vp, I say, that I may see to put on my gloues.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dil.</SPEAKER>
<P>O, delicious sweet cheekt master, if you discharge
but one glance from the leuell of that set face: O, you
will strike a wench; youle make any wench loue you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="22"/>
<SPEAKER>Balur.</SPEAKER>
<P>By Iesu, I think I am as elegant a Courtier,
as How lik'st thou my suite?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Catz.</SPEAKER>
<P>All, beyond all, no peregal: you are wondred at,
for an asse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, <HI>Dildo,</HI> no christen creature shall knowe
hereafter, what I will doe for thee heretofore.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here wants a little white, <HI>Flauia.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dil.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, but master, you haue one little falt; you sleepe
open mouth'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ball.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pewe, thou iestst. In good sadnesse, Ile haue a
looking glasse nail'd to the the testarn of the bed, that
I may see when I sleep, whether tis so, or not; take heed
you lye not: goe to, take heede you lie not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fla.</SPEAKER>
<P>By my troth, you looke as like the princesse, now
I, but her lip is lip is a little redder, a very little
redder: but by the helpe of Art, or Nature, ere I chāge
my perewigge, mine shall be as red.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fla.</SPEAKER>
<P>O, I, that face, that eye, that smile, that writhing of
your bodie, that wanton dandling of your fan, becoms
prethely, so sweethly, tis euen the goodest Ladie that
breathes, the most amiable Faith the fringe of
your sattin peticote is ript. Good faith madam, they say
you are the most bounteous Lady to your women, that
euer O most delitious beautie! Good Madam
let me kith it.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>¶Enter Piero.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feli.</SPEAKER>
<P>Rare sport, rare sport! A female foole, and a fe∣male
flatterer▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ross.</SPEAKER>
<P>Bodie a mee, the Duke: away the glasse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>Take vp your paper, <HI>Rossaline.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="22"/>
<SPEAKER>Rossa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not mine, my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not yours, my Ladie? Ile see what tis.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<P>And how does my sweete mistresse? O Ladie
deare, euen as tis an olde say, Tis an old horse can nei∣ther
wighy, nor wagge his taile: euen so doe I holde
my set face still: euen so, tis a bad courtier that can nei∣ther
discourse, nor blow his nose.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>Meet me at <HI>Abrahams,</HI> the Iewes, where I bought
my Amazons disguise. A shippe lies in the port, ready
bound for England; make haste, come priuate.</P>
<STAGE>¶Enter Castilio, Forobosco.</STAGE>
<P><HI>Antonio, Forobosco, Alberto, Feliche, Castilio, Balurdo?</HI> run,
keepe the Palace, post to the ports, goe to my daugh∣ters
chamber: whether now? scud to the Iewes, stay,
runne to the gates, stop the gundolets, let none passe
the marsh, doe all at once. <HI>Antonio?</HI> his head, his head.
Keep you the Court, the rest stand still, or runne, or
goe, or shoute, or search, or scud, or call, or hang, or
doe doe doe, su su su, somthing: I know not who who
who, what I do do do, nor who who who, where
I am.</P>
<L>O trista traditriche, rea, ribalda fortuna,</L>
<L>Negando mi vindetta mi causa fera morte,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha ha ha. I could breake my splene at his im∣patience.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alma &amp; gratiosa fortuna sia<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e fauor evole,</L>
<L>Et fortunati siano vnoti del mia dulce Mellida, Mel∣lida.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas <HI>Antonio,</HI> I haue lost thy note.</L>
<L><PB REF="23"/>
A number mount my staires; ile straight returne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Antonio,</L>
<L>Be not affright, sweete Prince; appease thy feare,</L>
<L>Buckle thy spirits vp, put all thy wits</L>
<L>In wimble action, or thou art surpriz'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<L>I care not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Art mad, or desperate? or</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Both, both, all, all: I pree thee let mee ly;</L>
<L>Spight of you all, I can, and I will dy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are distraught; O, this is madnesse breath.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>An.</SPEAKER>
<L>Each man take hence life, but no man death:</L>
<L>Hee's a good fellow, and keepes open house:</L>
<L>A thousand thousand waies lead to his gate,</L>
<L>To his wide mouth'd porch: when niggard life</L>
<L>Hath but one little, little wicket through.</L>
<L>We wring our selues into this wretched world,</L>
<L>To pule, and weepe, exclaime, to curse and raile,</L>
<L>To fret, and ban the fates, to strike the earth</L>
<L>As I doe now. <HI>Antonio,</HI> curse thy birth,</L>
<L>And die.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, heauens my comfort, now you are peruerse;</L>
<L>You know I alwaies lou'd you; pree thee liue.</L>
<L>Wilt thou strike deade thy friends, drawe mourning
teares</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>An.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas, <HI>Feliche,</HI> I ha nere a friend;</L>
<L>No country, father, brother, kinsman left</L>
<L>To weepe my fate, or sigh my funerall:</L>
<L>I roule but vp and downe, and fill a seat</L>
<L>In the darke caue of dusky misery.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feli.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fore heauen, the Duke comes: hold you, take my key,</L>
<L><PB REF="23"/>
Slinke to my chamber, looke you; that is it:</L>
<L>There shall you finde a suite I wore at sea:</L>
<L>Take it, and slippe away. Nay, pretious,</L>
<L>If youle be peeuish, by this light, Ile sweare,</L>
<L>Thou rail'dst vpon thy loue before thou dyedst,</L>
<L>And call'd her strumpet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sheele not credit thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tut, that's all one: ile defame thy loue;</L>
<L>And make thy deade trunke held in vile regard.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wilt needs haue it so? why then <HI>Antonio,</HI></L>
<L>Viue esperanza, in despetto dell fato.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>¶Enter Piero, Galeatzo, Matzagente, Forobosco, Ba∣lurdo,
and Castilio, with weapons.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Piero.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, my sweet Princes, was't not brauely found?</L>
<L>Euen there I found the note, euen there it lay.</L>
<L>I kisse the place for ioy, that there it lay.</L>
<L>This way he went, here let vs make a stand:</L>
<L>Ile keepe this gate my selfe: O gallant youth!</L>
<L>Ile drinke carouse vnto your countries health,</L>
<STAGE>¶Enter Antonio.</STAGE>
<L>Euen in <HI>Antonio's</HI> scull.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Lord blesse vs: his breath is more fearefull then
a Sergeants voice, when he cries; I arrest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stoppe <HI>Antonio,</HI> keepe, keepe <HI>Antonio.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Piero.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where, where man, where?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here, here: let me me pursue him downe the
marsh.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold, there's my signet, take a gundelet:</L>
<L><PB REF="24"/>
Bring me his head, his head, and by mine honour,</L>
<L>Ile make thee the wealthiest Mariner that breathes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile sweate my bloode out, till I haue him safe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speake heartily ifaith, good Mariner.</L>
<L>O, wee will mount in tryumph: soone, at night,</L>
<L>Ile set his head vp. Lets thinke where.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Vp on his shoulders, that's the fittest place for
it. If it be not as fit as if it were made for them; say, <HI>Ba∣lurdo,</HI>
thou art a sot, an asse.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>¶Enter Mellida in Pages attire, dauncing.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sprightly, ifaith. In troth he's somwhat like</L>
<L>My daughter <HI>Mellida:</HI> but alas poore soule,</L>
<L>Her honour heeles, god knowes, are halfe so light.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Escap't I am, spite of my fathers spight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ho, this will warme my bosome ere I sleepe.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>¶Enter Flauia running.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fla.</SPEAKER>
<L>O my Lord, your daughter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, I, my daughter's safe enough, I warrant thee.</L>
<L>This vengeance on the boy will lengthen out</L>
<L>My daies vnmeasuredly.</L>
<L>It shall be chronicled, time to come;</L>
<L><HI>Piero Sforza</HI> slewe <HI>Andrugio's</HI> sonne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fla.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, but my Lord, your daughter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, I, my good wench, she is safe enough.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fla.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, then, my Lord, you know she's run away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Run away, away, how run away?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fla.</SPEAKER>
<L>She's vanisht in an instante, none knowes whe∣ther.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pursue, pursue, fly, run, post, scud away.</L>
<STAGE>¶Feliche sing; And was not good king Salomon.</STAGE>
<L>Fly, call, run, rowe, ride, cry, shout, hurry, haste:</L>
<L><PB REF="24"/>
Haste, hurry, shoute, cry, ride, rowe, run, call, fly</L>
<L>Backward and forward, euery way about.</L>
<L>Maldetta fortuna <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hy condura sorta</L>
<L>Che faro, che diro, pur fugir tanto mal!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<L>Twas you that struck me euen now: was it not?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<L>It was I that struck you euen now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<L>You bastinadoed me, <HI>I</HI> take it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<L>I bastinadoed you, and you tooke it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith sir, I haue the richest Tobacco in the court
for you; I would be glad to make you satisfaction, if I
haue wronged you. <HI>I</HI> would not the Sun should set v∣pon
your anger; giue me your hand.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Content faith, so thou'lt breede no more such lies.
I hate not man, but mans lewd qualities.</P>
</SP>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="4" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACTVS QVARTVS.</HEAD>
<STAGE>¶Enter Antonio, in his sea gowne running.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>STOP, stop <HI>Antonio,</HI> stay <HI>Antonio.</HI></L>
<L>Vaine breath, vaine breath, <HI>Antonio's</HI> lost;</L>
<L>He can not finde himselfe, not seize himselfe.</L>
<L>Alas, this that you see, is not <HI>Antonio,</HI></L>
<L>His spirit houers in <HI>Piero's</HI> Court,</L>
<L>Hurling about his agill faculties,</L>
<L>To apprehend the sight of <HI>Mellida:</HI></L>
<L>But poore, poore soule, wanting apt instruments</L>
<L>To speake or see, stands dumbe and blinde, sad spirit,</L>
<L>Roul'd vp in gloomie clouds as black as ayer,</L>
<L>Through which the rustie coach of Night is drawne:</L>
<L>Tis so, ile giue you instance that tis so.</L>
<L><PB REF="25"/>
Conceipt you me. As hauing clasp't a rose</L>
<L>Within my palme, the rose being tane away,</L>
<L>My hand retaines a little breath of sweete:</L>
<L>So may mans trunke; his spirit slipt awaie,</L>
<L>Holds still a faint perfume of his sweet ghest.</L>
<L>Tis so; for when discursiue powers fl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e out,</L>
<L>And rome in progresse, through the boūds of heauen,</L>
<L>The soule it selfe gallops along with them,</L>
<L>As chiefetaine of this winged troope of thought,</L>
<L>Whilst the dull lodge of spirit standeth waste,</L>
<L>Vntill the soule returne from What wast I said?</L>
<L>O, this is naught, but speckling melancholie.</L>
<L>I haue beene</L>
<L>That Morpheus tender skinp Cosen germane</L>
<L>Beare with me good</L>
<L><HI>Mellida:</HI> clod vpon clod thus fall.</L>
<L>Hell is beneath; yet heauen is ouer all.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>¶Enter Andrugio, Lucio, Cole, and Norwod.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come <HI>Lucio,</HI> lets goe eat: what hast thou got?</L>
<L>Rootes, rootes? alas, they are seeded, new cut vp.</L>
<L>O, thou hast wronged Nature, <HI>Lucio:</HI></L>
<L>But bootes not much; thou but pursu'st the world,</L>
<L>That cuts off vertue, fore it comes to growth,</L>
<L>Least it should seed, and so orerun her sonne,</L>
<L>Dull pore-blinde error. Giue me water, boy.</L>
<L>There is no poison in't I hope, they say</L>
<L>That lukes in massie plate: and yet the earth</L>
<L>Is so infected with a generall plague,</L>
<L>That hee's most wise, that thinks there's no man foole:</L>
<L><PB REF="25"/>
Right prudent, that esteemes no creature iust:</L>
<L>Great policy the least things to mistrust.</L>
<L>Giue me Assay How we mock greatnesse now!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lu.</SPEAKER>
<L>A strong conceipt is rich, so most men deeme:</L>
<L>If not to be, tis comfort yet to seeme.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why man, I neuer was a Prince till now.</L>
<L>Tis not the bared pate, the bended knees,</L>
<L>Guilt tipstaues, Tyrrian purple, chaires of state,</L>
<L>Troopes of pide butterflies, that flutter still</L>
<L>In greatnesse summer, that confirme a prince:</L>
<L>Tis not the vnsauory breath of multitudes,</L>
<L>Showting and clapping, with confused dinne;</L>
<L>That makes a Prince. No <HI>Lucio,</HI> he's a king,</L>
<L>A true right king, that dares doe aught, saue wrong,</L>
<L>Feares nothing mortall, but to be vniust,</L>
<L>Who is not blowne vp with the flattering puffes</L>
<L>Of spungy Sycophants: Who stands vnmou'd,</L>
<L>Despight the iustling of opinion:</L>
<L>Who can enioy himselfe, maugre the throng</L>
<L>That striue to presse his quiet out of him:</L>
<L>Who sits vpon <HI>Ioues</HI> footestoole, as I doe,</L>
<L>Adoring, not affecting, maiestie:</L>
<L>Whose brow is wreathed with the siluer crowne</L>
<L>Of cleare content: this, <HI>Lucio,</HI> is a king.</L>
<L>And of this empire, euery man's possest,</L>
<L>That's worth his soule.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lu.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, the <HI>Genowaies</HI> had wont to say</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>Name not the <HI>Genowaies:</HI> that very word</L>
<L>Vnkings me quite, makes me vile passions slaue.</L>
<L>O, you that made open the glibbery Ice</L>
<L><PB REF="26"/>
Of vulgar fauour, viewe <HI>Andrugio.</HI></L>
<L>Was neuer Prince with more applause confirm'd,</L>
<L>With louder shouts of tryumph launched out</L>
<L>Into the surgy maine of gouernment:</L>
<L>Was neuer Prince with more despight cast out,</L>
<L>Left shipwrackt, banisht, on more guiltlesse ground.</L>
<L>O rotten props of the craz'd multitude,</L>
<L>How you stil double, faulter, vnder the lightest chance</L>
<L>That straines your vaines. Alas, one battle lost,</L>
<L>Your whorish loue, your drunken healths, your houts
and shouts,</L>
<L>Your smooth God saue's, and all your diuels last</L>
<L>That tempts our quiet, to your hell of throngs.</L>
<L>Spit on me <HI>Lucio,</HI> for I am turnd slaue:</L>
<L>Obserue how passion domineres ore me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lu.</SPEAKER>
<L>No wonder, noble Lord, hauing lost a sonne,</L>
<L>A country, crowne, and</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>I <HI>Lucio,</HI> hauing lost a sonne, a sonne,</L>
<L>A country, house, crowne, sonne. <HI>O lares, misereri lares.</HI></L>
<L>Which shall I first deplore? My sonne, my sonne,</L>
<L>My deare sweete boy, my deare <HI>Antonio.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Antonio?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, eccho, I; I meane <HI>Antonio.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Antonio, <HI>who meanes</HI> Antonio?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where art? what art? know'st thou <HI>Antonio?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>Liues hee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>No.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where lies hee deade?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="26"/>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Andr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Art thou <HI>Antonio?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thinke I am.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dost thou but think? What, dost not know thy selfe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>He is a foole that thinks he knowes himselfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vpon thy faith to heauen, giue thy name.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>I were not worthy of <HI>Andrugio's</HI> blood,</L>
<L>If I denied my name's <HI>Antonio.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>I were not worthy to be call'd thy father,</L>
<L>If I denied my name <HI>Andrugio.</HI></L>
<L>And dost thou liue? O, let me kisse thy cheeke,</L>
<L>And deaw thy browe with trickling drops of ioy.</L>
<L>Now heauens will be done: for I haue liu'd</L>
<L>To see my ioy, my sonne <HI>Antonio.</HI></L>
<L>Giue my thy hand; now fortune doe thy worst,</L>
<L>His blood, that lapt thy spirit in the wombe,</L>
<L>Thus (in his loue) will make his armes thy tombe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Blesse not the bodie with your twining armes,</L>
<L>Which is accurst of heauen. O, what black sinne</L>
<L>Hath bin committed by our auntient house,</L>
<L>Whose scalding vengeance lights vpon our heads,</L>
<L>That thus the world, and fortune casts vs out,</L>
<L>As loathed obiects, ruines branded slaues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe not expostulate the heauens will:</L>
<L>But, O, remember to forget thy selfe:</L>
<L>Forget remembrance what thou once hast bin.</L>
<L>Come, creepe with me from out this open ayre.</L>
<L>Euen trees haue tongues, and will betray our life.</L>
<L>I am a raising of our house, my boy:</L>
<L><PB REF="27"/>
Which fortune will not enuie, tis so meane,</L>
<L>And like the world (all durt) there shalt thou rippe</L>
<L>The inwards of thy fortunes, in mine eares,</L>
<L>Whilst I sit weeping, blinde with passions teares:</L>
<L>Then ile begin, and weele such order keepe,</L>
<L>That one shall still tell greefes, the other weepe.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>¶Exit Andrugio, leauing Antonio, and his Page.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile follow you. Boy, pree thee stay a little.</L>
<L>Thou hast had a good voice, if this colde marshe,</L>
<L>Wherein we lurke, haue not corrupted it.</L>
<STAGE>¶Enter Mellida, standing out of sight, in her Pages suite.</STAGE>
<L>I pree thee sing, but sirra (marke you me)</L>
<L>Let each nore breath the heart of passion,</L>
<L>The sad extracture of extreamest griefe.</L>
<L>Make me a straine; speake, groning like a bell,</L>
<L>That towles departing soules.</L>
<L>Breath me a point that may inforce me weepe,</L>
<L>To wring my hands, to breake my cursed breast,</L>
<L>Raue, and exclaime, lie groueling on the earth,</L>
<L>Straight start vp frantick, crying, <HI>Mellida.</HI></L>
<L>Sing but, <HI>Antonio</HI> hath lost <HI>Mellida,</HI></L>
<L>And thou shalt see mee (like a man possest)</L>
<L>Howle out such passion, that euen this brinish marsh</L>
<L>Will squease out teares, from out his spungy cheekes,</L>
<L>The rocks euen groane, and</L>
<L>Pree thee, pree thee sing:</L>
<L>Or I shall nere ha done when I am in.</L>
<L>Tis harder for me end, then to begin.</L>
<STAGE>¶The boy runnes a note, Antonio breakes it.</STAGE>
<L>For looke thee boy, my griefe that hath no end,</L>
<L><PB REF="27"/>
I may begin to playne, but pree thee sing.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>CANTANT.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mell.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heauen keepe you sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>An.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heauen keepe you from me, sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mell.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must be acquainted with you, sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wherefore? Art thou infected with misery,</L>
<L>Sear'd with the anguish of calamitie?</L>
<L>Art thou true sorrow, hearty griefe, canst weepe?</L>
<L>I am not for thee if thou canst not raue,</L>
<STAGE>¶Antonio fals on the ground.</STAGE>
<L>Fall flat on the ground, and thus exclaime on heauen;</L>
<L>O trifling Nature, why enspiredst thou breath</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mell.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay sir, I thinke you named <HI>Mellida.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Know'st thou <HI>Mellida?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hast thou seene <HI>Mellida?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mell.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then hast thou seene the glory of her sex,</L>
<L>The musick of Nature, the vnequall'd lustre</L>
<L>Of vnmatched excellence, the vnited sweete</L>
<L>Of heauens graces, the most adored beautie,</L>
<L>That euer strooke amazement in the world.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mell.</SPEAKER>
<L>You seeme to loue her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>With my very soule.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mell.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shele not requite it: all her loue is fixt</L>
<L>Vpon a gallant, on <HI>Antonio,</HI></L>
<L>The Duke of <HI>Genoas</HI> sonne. I was her Page:</L>
<L>And often as I waited, she would sigh;</L>
<L><PB REF="28"/>
O, deere <HI>Antonio;</HI> and to strengthen thought,</L>
<L>Would clip my neck, and kisse, and kisse me thus.</L>
<L>Therefore leaue louing her: fa, faith me thinks,</L>
<L>Her beautie is not halfe so rauishing</L>
<L>As you discourse of; she hath a freckled face,</L>
<L>A lowe forehead, and a lumpish eye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>O heauen, that I should heare such blasphemie.</L>
<L>Boy, rogue, thou liest, and</L>
<L>Spauento dell mio core dolce Mellida,</L>
<L>Di graua morte restor<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> vero dolce Mellida,</L>
<L>Celesta saluatrice sovrana Mellida</L>
<L>Del mio sperar; trofeo vero Mellida.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Diletta &amp; soaue anima mia Antonio,</L>
<L>Godeuole belezza cortese Antonio.</L>
<L>Signior mio &amp; virginal amore bell' Antonio</L>
<L>Gusto delli mei sensi, car' Antonio.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>O suamisce il cor in vn soaue baccio,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Murono i sensi nel desiato dessio:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nel Cielo puo lesser belta pia chiara.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nel mondo pol esser belta pia chiara?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dammi vn baccio da quella bocca beata,</L>
<L>Bassiammi, coglier l' aur a odorata</L>
<L>Che in sua neggia in quello dolce labra.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dammi pimpero del tuo gradit' amore</L>
<L>Che beame, cosempiterno honore,</L>
<L>Cosi, cosimi conuerra morir.</L>
<L>Good sweet, scout ore the marsh: for my heart trembls</L>
<L>At euery little breath that strikes my eare,</L>
<L>When thou returnest: and ile discourse</L>
<L>How I deceiu'd the Court: then thou shall tell</L>
<L><PB REF="28"/>
How thou escapt'st the watch: weele point our speech</L>
<L>With amorous kissing, kissing cōmaes, and euen suck</L>
<L>The liquid breath from out each others lips.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dul clod, no man but such sweeet fauour clips.</L>
<L>I goe, and yet my panting blood perswades me stay.</L>
<L>Turne coward in her sight? away, away.</L>
<P>I thinke confusion of <HI>Babell</HI> is falne vpon these louers,
that they change their language, but I feare mee, my
master hauing but fained the person of a woman, hath
got their vnfained imperfection, and is growne double
tongu'd: as for <HI>Mellida,</HI> she were no woman, if shee
could not yeelde strange language. But howsoeuer, if I
should sit in iudgement, tis an errour easier to be par∣doned
by the auditors, then excused by the authours;
and yet some priuate respect may rebate the edge of
the keener censure.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>¶Enter Piero, Castilio, Matzagente, Forobosco, Feliche,
Galeatzo, Balurdo, and his Page, at another dore.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>This way shee took: search, my sweet gentlemē.
How now <HI>Balurdo,</HI> canst thou meete with any body?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<P>As I am true gentleman, I made my horse sweat,
that he hath nere a dry thread on him: and I can meete
with no liuing creature, but men &amp; beastes, In good
sadnesse, I would haue sworne I had seene <HI>Mellida</HI> e∣uen
now: for I sawe a thing stirre vnder a hedge, and I
peep't, and I spyed a thing: and I peer'd, and I tweerd
vnderneath: and truly a right wise man might haue
beene deceiued: for it was</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="29"/>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>What, in the name of heauen?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>A dun cowe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sh'ad nere a kettle on her head?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Boy, didst thou see a yong Lady passe this way?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why speake you not?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gods neakes, proud elfe, giue the Duke roue∣rence,
stand bare with a</P>
<P>Whogh! heauens blesse me: <HI>Mellida, Mellida.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where man, where?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Balur.</SPEAKER>
<P>Turnd man, turnd man: women weare the
breaches, loe here,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Light and vnduteous! kneele not, peeuish elfe,</L>
<L>Speake not, entreate not, shame vnto my house,</L>
<L>Curse to my honour. Where's <HI>Antonio?</HI></L>
<L>Thou traitresse to my hate, what is he shipt</L>
<L>For England now? well whimpering harlot, hence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mell.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good father</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good me no goods. Seest thou that sprightly
youth? ere thou canst tearme to morrow morning old,
thou shalt call him thy husband, Lord and loue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ay me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Blirt on your ay mees, gard her safely hence.</L>
<L>Drag her away, ile be your gard to night.</L>
<L>Young Prince, mount vp your spirits, and prepare</L>
<L>To solemnize your Nuptials eue with popme.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gal.</SPEAKER>
<L>The time is scant: now nimble wits appeare:</L>
<L><HI>Phoebus</HI> begins gleame, the welkin's cleare.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt all, but Balurdo and his Page.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now nimble wits appeare: ile my selfe appeare,</L>
<L><HI>Balurdo's</HI> selfe, that in quick wit doth surpasse,</L>
<L><PB REF="29"/>
Will shew the substance of a compleat</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Asse, asse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile mount my courser, and most gallantly prick</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gallantly prick is too long, and stands hardly
in the verse, sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile speake pure rime, and will so brauely pranke
it, that ile tosse loue like a pranke, pranke it: a rime for
pranke it?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Blankit.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<P>That ile tosse loue, like a dogge in a blanket: ha
ha, in deede law. I thinke, ha ha; I thinke ha ha, I think
I shall tickle the Muses. And I strike it not deade, say,
<HI>Balurdo,</HI> thou art an arrant sot.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dil.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Balurdo,</HI> thou art an arrant sot.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>¶Enter Andrugio and Antonio wreathed together,
Lucio.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now, come vnited force of chap-falne death:</L>
<L>Come, power of fretting anguish, leaue distresse.</L>
<L>O, thus infoulded, we haue breasts of proofe,</L>
<L>Gainst all the venom'd stings of misery.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant:</SPEAKER>
<L>Father, now I haue an antidote,</L>
<L>Gainst all the poyson that the world can breath.</L>
<L>My <HI>Mellida,</HI> my <HI>Mellida</HI> doth blesse</L>
<L>This bleak waste with her presence. How now boy,</L>
<L>Why dost thou weepe? alas, where's <HI>Mellida?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ay me, my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>A sodden horror doth inuade my blood,</L>
<L>My sinewes tremble, and my panting heart</L>
<L>Scuds round about my bosome so goe out,</L>
<L><PB REF="30"/>
Dreading the assailant, horrid passion.</L>
<L>O, be no tyrant, kill me with one blowe.</L>
<L>Speake quickly, briefely boy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Her father found, and seis'd her, she is gone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>Son, heat thy bloode, be not frose vp with grief.</L>
<L>Courage, sweet boy, sinke not beneath the waight</L>
<L>Of crushing mischiefe. O where's thy dantlesse heart</L>
<L>Thy fathers spirit! I renounce thy blood,</L>
<L>If thou forsake thy valour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lu.</SPEAKER>
<L>See how his grief speakes in his flow-pac't steps:</L>
<L>Alas, tis more than he can vtter, let him goe.</L>
<L>Dumbe solitary path best sureth woe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>Giue me my armes, my armour <HI>Lucio.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Deare Lord, what means this rage, when lacking vse</L>
<L>Scarce safes your life, will you in armour rise?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fortune feares valour, presseth cowardize.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then valour gets applause, when it hath place,</L>
<L>And meanes to blaze it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nunquam potest non esse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Patience, my Lord, may bring your ils some end.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>What patience, friend, can ruin'd hopes attēd?</L>
<L>Come, let me die like old <HI>Andrugio:</HI></L>
<L>Worthy my birth. O blood-true-honour'd graues</L>
<L>Are farre more blessed then base life of slaues. <HI>Exeunt.</HI></L>
</SP>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="5" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACTVS QVINTVS.</HEAD>
<STAGE>¶Enter Balurdo, a Painter with two pictures, and
Dildo.</STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="30"/>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<P>AND are you a painter sir, can you drawe, can
you drawe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pay.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeede lawe? now so can my fathers forehore
horse. And are these the workmanshippe of your
hands?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Payn.</SPEAKER>
<P>I did lymne them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Lymne them? a good word, lymne them: whose
picture is this? <HI>Anno Domini</HI> 1599. Beleeue mee,
master <HI>Anno Domini</HI> was of a good settled age when
you lymn'd him. 1599. yeares old? Lets see the other.
<HI>Etatis suae</HI> 24. Bir Ladie he is somwhat younger. Belike
master <HI>Etatis suae</HI> was <HI>Anno Dominies</HI> sonne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is not your master a</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dil.</SPEAKER>
<P>He hath a little procliuitie to him</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Procliuitie, good youth? I thank you for your
courtly procliuitie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Approach good sir. I did send for you to drawe
me a deuise, an <HI>Imprezza,</HI> by <HI>Sinecdoche a Mott.</HI> By
<HI>Phoebus</HI> crymson taffata mantle, I thinke I speake as
melodiously, looke you sir, how thinke you ont? I wold
haue you paint mee, for my deuice, a good fat legge of
ewe mutton, swimming in stewde broth of plummes
(boy keele your mouth, it runnes ouer) and the word
shall be; <HI>Holde my dish, whilst I spill my pottage.</HI> Sure, in
my conscience, twould be the most sweete deuice,
now.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Twould sent of kitchin-stuffe too much.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gods neakes, now I remember mee, I ha
<PB REF="31"/>
the rarest deuise in my head that euer breathed. Can
you paint me a driueling reeling song, &amp; let the word
be, Vh.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Payn.</SPEAKER>
<P>A belch.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<P>O, no no: Vh, paint me vh, or nothing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pay.</SPEAKER>
<P>It can not be done sir, but by a seeming kinde of
drunkennesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<P>No? well, let me haue a good maff<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e ring, with
your owne poesie grauen in it, that must sing a small
trebble, worde for word, thus; <HI>And if you will my
true louer be,</HI></P>
<P>Come followe mee to the greene wodde.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pa.</SPEAKER>
<L>O Lord, sir, I can not make a picture sing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>B.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why? z'lid, I haue seen painted things sing as sweet:</L>
<L>But I hau't will tickle it, for a conceipt ifaith.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>¶Enter Feliche, and Alberto.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<L>O deare <HI>Feliche,</HI> giue me thy deuice.</L>
<L>How shall I purchase loue of <HI>Rossaline?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<L>S'will, flatter her soundly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Her loue is such, I can not flatter her:</L>
<L>Bu with my vtmost vehemence of speach,</L>
<L>I haue ador'd her beauties.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hast writ good mouing vnaffected rimes to
her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, yes, <HI>Feliche,</HI> but she scornes my writ.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hast thou presented her with sumptuous gifts?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas, my fortunes are too weake to offer them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fell.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, then I haue it, Ile tell thee what to doe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<L>What, good <HI>Feliche?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe and hang thy selfe, I say, goe hang thy selfe,</L>
<L><PB REF="31"/>
If that thou canst not giue, goe hang thy selfe:</L>
<L>Ile rime thee dead, or verse thee to the rope.</L>
<L>How thinkst thou of a Poet that sung thus;</L>
<L>Munera sola pacant, sola addunt munera formam:</L>
<L>Munere solicites Pallada, Cypris erit.</L>
<L>Munera, munera.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile goe and breath my woes vnto the rocks,</L>
<L>And spend my griefe vpon the deafest seas.</L>
<L>Ile weepe my passion to the senselesse trees,</L>
<L>And load most solitarie ayre with plaints.</L>
<L>For wods, trees, sea, or rocky <HI>Appenine,</HI></L>
<L>Is not so ruthlesse as my <HI>Rossaline.</HI></L>
<L>Farewell deare friend, expect no more of mee,</L>
<L>Here ends my part, in this loues Comedy.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Alb.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Paynter.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now master <HI>Balurdo,</HI> whether are you going, ha?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Signior <HI>Feliche,</HI> how doe you faith, &amp; by my
troth, how doe you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whether art thou going, bully?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>And as heauen helpe mee, how doe you?</L>
<L>How, doe you ifaith he?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whether art going man?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<P>O god, to the Court, ile be willing to giue you
grace and good countnance, if I may but see you in
the presence.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<P>O to court? farewell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<P>If you see one in a yellow taffata dubblet, cut
vpon carnation valure, a greene hat, a blewe paire of
veluet hose, a gilt rapier, and an orange <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>ny pair of
worsted silke stockings, thats I, thats I.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="32"/>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Very good, farewell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ho, you shall knowe me as easily, I ha bought
mee a newe greene feather with a red sprig, you shall
see my wrought shirt hang out at my breeches, you
shall know me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Very good, very good, farewell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ball.</SPEAKER>
<P>Marrie in the maske twill be somewhat harde.
But if you heare any bodie speake so wittily, that hee
makes all the roome laugh; that's I, that's I. Farewell
good Signior.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>¶Enter Forobosco, Castilio, a boy carying a gilt harpe: Pi∣ero,
Mellida in night apparrell, Rossaline, Flauia, two
Pages.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pier.</SPEAKER>
<L>Aduance the musiques prize, now capring wits,</L>
<L>Rise to your highest mount; let choyce delight</L>
<L>Garland the browe of this tryumphant night.</L>
<L>Sfoote, a sits like Lucifer himselfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rossa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good sweete Duke, first let their voyces, strain
for musicks price. Giue mee the golden harpe: faith
with your fauour, ile be vmperesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sweet neece cōtent: boyes cleare your voice &amp; sing.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>1. CANTAT.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rossa.</SPEAKER>
<P>By this gould, I had rather haue a seruant with a
short nose, and a thinne haire, then haue such a high
stretcht minikin voice.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faire neece, your reason?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="32"/>
<SPEAKER>Ross.</SPEAKER>
<P>By the sweete of loue, I should feare extreame∣ly
that he were an Eunuch.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sparke spirit, how like you his voice?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ross.</SPEAKER>
<L>Spark spirit, how like you his voice?</L>
<P>So helpe me, youth, thy voice squeakes like a dry cork
shoe: come, come; lets heare the next.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>2. CANTAT.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>Trust me, a good strong meane, Well sung my
boy.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>¶Enter Balurdo.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hold, hold, hold: are yee blind, could you not see
my voice comming for the harpe. And I knock not di∣uision
on the head, take hence the harpe, make mee a
slip, and let me goe but for nine pence. Sir <HI>Marke,</HI> strike
vp for master <HI>Balurdo.</HI></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>3. CANTAT.</STAGE>
<L>Iudgemēt gentlemen, iudgemēt. Wast not aboue line?</L>
<L>I appeale to your mouthes that heard my song.</L>
<L>Doe me right, and dub me knight <HI>Balurdo.</HI></L>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<P>Kneele downe, and ile dub thee knight of the
golden harpe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeed law, doe, and ile make you Ladie of the siluer fiddlestick,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ross.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come, kneele, kneele.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>¶Enter a Page to Balurdo,</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<P>My troth, I thank you, it hath neuer a whistle in't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Naie, good sweet cuz raise vp your drooping eies,
<PB REF="33"/>
&amp; I were at the point of To haue &amp; to hold, from this
day forward, I would be asham'd to looke thus lum∣pish.
What my prettie Cuz, tis but the losse of an od
maidenhead: shall's daunce? thou art so sad, harke in
mine eare. I was about to say, but ile forbeare.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<P>I come, I come, more then most hunny-suckle
sweete Ladies, pine not for my presence, ile returne
in pompe. Well spoke sir <HI>Ieffrey Balurdo.</HI> As I am a true
knight, I feele honourable eloquence begin to grope
mee alreadie.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith, mad neece, I wonder when thou wilt
marrie?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rossa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith, kinde vncle, when men abandon ielosy,
forsake taking of Tobacco, and cease to weare their
beardes so rudely long. Oh, to haue a husband with
a mouth continually smoaking, with a bush of furs on
the ridge of his chinne, readie still to slop into his fo∣ming
chaps; ah, tis more than most intollerable.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pier.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay faith, sweete neece, I was mightie strong
in thought we should haue shut vp night with an ould
Comedie: the Prince of <HI>Millane</HI> shall haue <HI>Mellida,</HI> &amp;
thou shouldst haue</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<P>No bodie, good sweete vncle. I tell you, sir, I
haue 39. seruants, and my munkey that makes the for∣tieth.
Now I loue al of them lightly for something, but
affect none of them seriously for any thing. One's a
passionate foole, and hee flatters mee aboue beliefe:
the second's a teastie ape, and hee railes at me beyond
reason: the third's as graue as some Censor, and hee
strokes vp his mustachoes three times, and makes six
<PB REF="33"/>
plots of set faces, before he speakes one wise word: the
fourth's as dry, as the burre of an heartichoke; the fifth
paints, and hath alwaies a good colour for what hee
speakes: the sixt</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>Stay, stay, sweet neece, what makes you thus sus∣pect
young gallants worth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ross.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh, when I see one were a perewig, I dreade his
haire; another wallowe in a greate sloppe, I mistrust
the proportion of his thigh; and wears a ruffled boot,
I feare the fashion of his legge. Thus, something in each
thing, one tricke in euery thing makes me mistrust im∣perfection
in all parts; and there's the full point of my
addiction.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>The Cornets sound a cynet.</STAGE>
<STAGE>¶Enter Galeatzo, Matzagente, and Balurdo in
maskery.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pier.</SPEAKER>
<L>The roome's too scant: boyes, stand in there, close.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>In faith, faire sir, I am too sad to daunce.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>How's that, how's that? too sad? By heauen dance,</L>
<L>And grace him to, or, goe to, I say no more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mell.</SPEAKER>
<L>A burning glasse, the word <HI>splendente Phoebo?</HI></L>
<L>Tis too curious, I conceipt it not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith, ile tel thee. Ile no longer burne, then youle
shine and smile vpon my loue. For looke yee fairest, by
your pure sweets,</P>
<L>I doe not dote vpon your excellence.</L>
<L>And faith, vnlesse you shed your brightest beames</L>
<L>Of sunny fauour, and acceptiue grace</L>
<L>Vpon my tender loue, I doe not burne:</L>
<P>Marry but shine, and ile reflect your beames,
<PB REF="34"/>
with feruent ardor. Faith I wold be loath to flatter thee
faire soule, because I loue, not doat, court like thy hus∣band;
which thy father sweares, to morrowe morne I
must be. This is all, and now from henceforth, trust me
<HI>Mellida,</HI> Ile not speake one wise word to thee more.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mell.</SPEAKER>
<P>I trust yee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gal.</SPEAKER>
<P>By my troth, Ile speak pure foole to thee now.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<P>You will speake the liker your selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good faith, Ile accept of the cockescombe, so
you will not refuse the bable.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay good sweet, keepe them both, I am ena∣mour'd
of neither.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Goe to, I must take you downe for this. Lende
me your eare.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<P>A glowe worme, the word? <HI>Splendescit tantùm te∣nebris.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Matz.</SPEAKER>
<P>O, Ladie, the glowe worme figurates my valour:
which shineth brightest in most darke, dismall and hor∣rid
atchieuements.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ross.</SPEAKER>
<P>Or rather, your glowe worme represents your
wit, which only seems to haue fire in it, though indeed
tis but an <HI>ignis fatuus,</HI> and shines onely in the darke
deade night of fooles admiration.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Matz.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ladie, my wit hath spurs, if it wete dispos'd to
ride you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ross.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith sir, your wits spurs haue but walking ro∣wels;
dull, blunt, they will not drawe blood: the gen∣tlemen
vshers may admit them the Presence, for anie
wrong they can doe to Ladies.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Truely, I haue strained a note aboue Ela, for a de∣uise;
<PB REF="34"/>
looke you, tis a faire rul'd singing booke: the
word, <HI>Perfect, if it were prickt.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fla.</SPEAKER>
<P>Though you are mask't, I can guesse who you
are by your wit. You are not the exquisite <HI>Balurdo,</HI> the
most rarely shap't <HI>Balurdo.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who, I? No I am not sir <HI>Ieffrey Balurdo.</HI> I am not
as well knowne by my wit, as an alehouse by a red lat∣tice.
I am not worthy to loue and be belou'd of <HI>Flauia.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fla.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will not scorne to fauour such good parts, as
are applauded in your rarest selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Truely, you speake wisely, and like a Iantlewo∣man
of foureteene yeares of age. You know the stone
called <HI>lapis;</HI> the nearer it comes to the fire, the hotter
it is: and the bird, which the Geometricians cal <HI>Auis,</HI>
the farther it is from the earth, the nearer it is to the
heauen: and loue, the nigher it is to the flame, the
more remote (ther's a word, remote) the more remote
it is from the frost, Your wit is quicke, a little thinge
pleaseth a young Ladie, and a smal fauour contenteth
an ould Courtier; and so, sweete mistresse I trusse my
codpeece point.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>¶Enter Feliche.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pier.</SPEAKER>
<P>What might import this florish? bring vs word.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Stand away: here's such a companie of flibotes,
hulling about this galleasse of greatnesse, that there's
no boarding him.</P>
<P>Doe you heare yon thing call'd, Duke?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>How now blunt <HI>Feliche,</HI> what's the newes?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yonder's a knight, hath brought <HI>Andrugio's</HI>
head, &amp; craues admittance to your chaire of state.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>¶Cornets sound a Cynet: enter Andrugio in armour.</STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="35"/>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Conduct him with attendance sumptuous,</L>
<L>Sound all the pleasing instruments of ioy:</L>
<L>Make tryumph, stand on tiptoe whil'st wee meete:</L>
<L>O sight most gratious, O reuenge most sweete!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<P>We vowe, by the honour of our birth, to recompence
any man that brngeth Andrugio's head, with twentie thou∣sand
double Pistolets, and the endeering to our choysest loue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>We still with most vnmou'd resolu'd confirme</L>
<L>Our large munificence: and here breath</L>
<L>A sad and solemne protestation:</L>
<L>When I recall this vowe, O, let our house</L>
<L>Be euen commaunded, staind, and trampled on,</L>
<L>As worthlesse rubbish of nobilitie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then, here, <HI>Piero,</HI> is <HI>Andrugios</HI> head,</L>
<L>Royally casked in a helme of steele:</L>
<L>Giue me thy loue, and take it. My dauntlesse soule</L>
<L>Hath that vnbounded vigor in his spirits,</L>
<L>That it can beare more ranke indignitie,</L>
<L>With lesse impatience, then thy cancred hate</L>
<L>Can sting and venome his vntainted worth,</L>
<L>With the most viperous sound of malice. Strike,</L>
<L>O, let no glimse of honour light thy thoughts,</L>
<L>If there be any heat of royall breath</L>
<L>Creeping in thy vaines, O stifle it.</L>
<L>Be still thy selfe, bloodie and trecherous.</L>
<L>Fame not thy house with an admired acte</L>
<L>Of princely pittie. <HI>Piero,</HI> I am come,</L>
<L>To soyle thy house with an eternall blot</L>
<L>Of sauage crueltie; strike, or bid me strike.</L>
<L>I pray my death; that thy nere dying shame</L>
<L><PB REF="35"/>
Might liue immortall to posteritie.</L>
<L>Come, be a princely hangman, stoppe my breath.</L>
<L>O dread thou shame, no more then I dread death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are amaz'd, our royall spirits numm'd,</L>
<L>In stiffe astonisht wonder at thy prowesse,</L>
<L>Most mightie, valiant, and high towring heart.</L>
<L>We blush, and turne our hate vpon our selues,</L>
<L>For hating such an vnpeer'd excellence.</L>
<L>I ioy my state: him whome I loath'd before,</L>
<L>That now I honour, loue; nay more, adore.</L>
<STAGE>¶The still Flutes sound a mournfull Cynet. Enter
a Cofin.</STAGE>
<L>But stay: what tragick spectacle appeares,</L>
<L>Whose bodie beare you in that mournefull hearse?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lu.</SPEAKER>
<P>The breathlesse trunke of young <HI>Antonio.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mell.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Antonio</HI> (aye me) my Lord, my loue, my</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweete pretious issue of most honor'd blood,</L>
<L>Rich hope, ripe vertue, O vntimely losse.</L>
<L>Come hither friend. Pree thee doe not weepe:</L>
<L>Why, I am glad hee's deade, he shall not see</L>
<L>His fathers vanquisht, by his enemie.</L>
<L>Euen in princely honour, nay pree thee speake.</L>
<L>How dy'd the wretched boy?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lu.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hope he dyed yet like my sonne, ifaith.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas, my Lord</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>He died vnforst, I trust, and valiantly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Poore gentleman, being</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did his hand shake, or his eye looke dull,</L>
<L>His thoughts reele, fearefull when he struck the stroke?</L>
<L><PB REF="36"/>
And if they did, Ile rend them out the hearse,</L>
<L>Rip vp his cearecloth, mangle his bleake face;</L>
<L>That when he comes to heauen, the powers diuine</L>
<L>Shall nere take notice that he was my sonne.</L>
<L>Ile quite disclaime his birth: nay pree thee speake:</L>
<L>And twere not hoopt with steel, my brest wold break.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>O that my spirit in a sigh could mount,</L>
<L>Into the Spheare, where thy sweet soule doth rest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>O that my teares, bedeawing thy wan cheeke,</L>
<L>Could make new spirit sprout in thy could blood.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal▪</SPEAKER>
<L>Verely, he lookes as pittifully, as a poore <HI>Iohn:</HI> as</L>
<L>I am true knight, I could weepe like a ston'd horse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>Villaine, tis thou hast murdred my sonne.</L>
<L>Thy vnrelenting spirit (thou black dogge,</L>
<L>That took'st no passion of his fatall loue)</L>
<L>Hath forst him giue his life vntimely end.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh that my life, her loue, my dearest blood</L>
<L>Would but redeeme one minute of his breath.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>I seize that breath. Stād not amaz'd, great states:</L>
<L>I rise from death, that neuer liu'd till now.</L>
<L><HI>Piero,</HI> keepe thy vowe, and I enioy</L>
<L>More vnexpressed height of happinesse,</L>
<L>Then power of thought can reach: if not, loe here</L>
<L>There stands my toumbe, and here a pleasing stage:</L>
<L>Most wisht spectators of my Tragedie,</L>
<L>To this end haue I fain'd, that her faire eye,</L>
<L>For whome I liu'd, might blesse me ere I die.</L>
<L><HI>Mell,</HI> Can breath depaint my vncōceiued thoughts?</L>
<L>Can words describe my infinite delight,</L>
<L>Of seeing thee, my Lord <HI>Antonio?</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="36"/>
O no; conceipt, breath, passion, words be dumbe,</L>
<L>Whil'st I instill the deawe of my sweete blisse,</L>
<L>In the soft pressure of a melting kisse;</L>
<L>Sic, sic iuuat ire sub vmbras.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faire sonne (now Ile be proud to call thee sonne)</L>
<L>Enioy me thus; my verie breast is thine:</L>
<L>Possesse me freely, I am wholly thine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant▪</SPEAKER>
<P>Deare father▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweet son, sweet son; I can speake no more:</L>
<L>My ioyes passion flowes aboue the shoare,</L>
<L>And choakes the current of my speach.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Young <HI>Florence</HI> prince, to you my lips must beg,</L>
<L>For a remittance of your interest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gal.</SPEAKER>
<L>In your faire daughter, with all my thought,</L>
<L>So helpe me faith, the naked truth Ile vnfold;</L>
<L>He that was nere hot, will soone be cold.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>No man els makes claime vnto her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Matz.</SPEAKER>
<L>The valiant speake truth in briefe: no</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Trulie, for sir <HI>Ieffrey Balurdo,</HI> he disclaimes to haue
had anie thing in her,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then here I giue her to <HI>Antonio.</HI></L>
<L>Royall, valiant, most respected prince,</L>
<L>Let's clippe our hands; Ile thus obserue my vowe;</L>
<L>I promis'd twentie thousand double Pistolets,</L>
<L>With the indeering to my dearest loue,</L>
<L>To him that brought thy head; thine be the golde,</L>
<L>To solemnize our houses vnitie:</L>
<L>My loue be thine, the all I haue be thine.</L>
<L>Fill vs fresh wine, the forme weele take by this:</L>
<L>Weele drinke a health, while they two sip a kisse.</L>
<L><PB REF="37"/>
Now, there remaines no discord that can sound</L>
<L>Harsh accents to the eare of our accord:</L>
<L>So please your neece to match.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ross.</SPEAKER>
<P>Troth vncle, when my sweet fac't cuz hath tolde
me how she likes the thing, call'd wedlock; may be Ile
take a suruey of the checkroll of my seruants; &amp; he that
hath the best parts of, Ile pricke him downe for my
husband.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<P>For passion of loue now, remember me to my
mistresse, Lady <HI>Rossaline,</HI> when she is pricking down the
good parts of her seruants. As I am true knight, I grow
stiffe: I shall carry it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will.</L>
<L>Sound Lidian wires, once make a pleasing note,</L>
<L>On Nectar streames of your sweete ayres, to flote.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here ends the comick crosses of true loue:</L>
<L>Oh may the passage most succesfull proue.</L>
</SP>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
<BACK>
<DIV1 TYPE="epilogue">
<HEAD>Epilogus.</HEAD>
<P>GEntlemen, though I remaine an armed Epilogue, I
stand not as a peremptory chalenger of desert, either for
him that composed the Comedy, or for vs that acted it: but
a most submissiue supplyant for both. What imperfection you
haue seene in vs, leaue with vs, &amp; weele amend it; what hath
pleased you, take with you, &amp; cherish it. You shall not be more
ready to embrace any thing cōmendable, then we will endea∣uour
to amend all things reproueable. What we are, is by your
fauour. What we shall be, rests all in your applausiue incou∣ragements.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<PB REF="37"/>
</DIV1>
</BACK>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

