<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2002-08-16</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Mona Logarbo</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TEMPHEAD, checked ID, and added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate.
Checked for N=""s.
Checked for GROUP tags.
Proofed title page.
Checked <SUP>s</SUP>.
Checked I / J.
Reviewed structure. Replaced SALUTE on PB REF="3" with SIGNED.
Made illustration on PB REF="38" its own DIV1, placing it in its sequential position in the text. No need to move it after the HEAD tag. Removed all LG tags: these are not used in drama unless the characters happen to speak in distinct verse units or there are distinct verse groups within the play, such as interpolated songs or poems, for example. The LG tag is not used to indicate change of speaker.
Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Removed second PB REF="78" since there is no image for it.
Checked for duplicate pages.
Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, —, q;s, and UNCLEARs.
Corrected all <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" RESP="keyers" DISP="•"/>s and <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" RESP="keyers" DISP="〈◊〉"/>s by inserting vendor-responsible GAP DESC and in some instances by inserting the appropriate letter(s) and\or GAP DESC.
Checked for &amp;cs with incorrect spacing.
Checked for LBs.
Checked for startqs, endqs and Qs.
Checked proofsheets and made corrections.
Sample: 8 minutes. Proofing: 25 minutes. Tag review and corrections: 150
minutes. DONE 08-16-02.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2012-03</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Paul Schaffner</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>
Keyed in missing text made newly available by PQ rescan of source.
Removed GAP 'missing' tags.
Adjusted REF values to match current state of image set.
Added quiring info.
Resolved more than 700 illegibles and corrected numerous errors as noticed.
Corrected some missed or mistaken speech cues.
Added Act and Scene divisions based largely on the Ellis-Fermor edition (1930).</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A07004">
<STC T="S">17425</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99857253</BIBNO>
<VID>22946</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/><FW><MILESTONE N="A1r"/></FW>
<P>Tamburlaine the Great. Who, from a Scythian Shephearde, by his rare and woonderfull Conquests, became a most puissant and migh∣tye Monarque. And (for his tyranny, and terrour in Warre) was tearmed, The Scourge of God.</P>
<P>Deuided into two Tragicall Dis∣courses, as they were sundrie times shewed vpon Stages in the Citie of London.</P>
<P>By the right honorable the Lord Admyrall, his seruantes.</P>
<P>Now first, and newlie published.</P>
<P>LONDON. Printed by <HI>Richard Ihones:</HI> at the signe of the Rose and Crowne neere Hol∣borne Bridge. 1590.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="printer to the reader">
<PB REF="2" MS="y"/><FW><MILESTONE N="A1v"/></FW>
<PB REF="2"/><FW><MILESTONE N="A2r"/></FW>
<HEAD>To the Gentlemen Rea∣ders: and others that take pleasure in reading Histories.</HEAD>
<P>GEntlemen, and curteous Readers whoso∣euer: I haue here published in print for your sakes, the two tragical Discourses of the Scythian Shepheard, <HI>Tamburlaine,</HI> that became so great a Conquerour, and so mightie a Monarque: My hope is, that they wil be now no lesse acceptable vnto you to read after your serious affaires and studies, then they haue bene (lately) delightfull for many of you to see, when the same were shewed in London vpon stages: I haue (purposely) omitted and left out some fond and friuolous Iestures, digressing (and in my poore opinion) far vnmeet for the matter, which I thought, might seeme more tedious vnto the wise, than any way els to be regarded, though (happly) they haue bene of some vaine cōceited fondlings greatly gaped at, what times they were shewed vpon the stage in their gra∣ced deformities: neuertheles now, to be mixtu∣red in print with such matter of worth, it wuld
<PB REF="3"/><FW><MILESTONE N="A2v"/></FW>
prooue a great disgrace to so honorable &amp; stare∣ly a historie: Great folly were it in me, to com∣mend vnto your wisedomes, either the elo∣quence of the Authour that writ them, or the worthinesse of the matter it selfe; I therefore leaue vnto your learned censures, both the one and the other, and my selfe the poore printer of them vnto your most curteous and fauourable protection; which if you vouchsafe to accept, you shall euermore binde mee to imploy what trauell and seruice I can, to the adua uncing and pleasuring of your excellent degree.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Yours, most humble at com∣maundement, R. I. Printer</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="play">
<PB REF="3"/><FW><MILESTONE N="A3r"/></FW>
<HEAD>The two tragical Dis∣courses of mighty Tamburlaine, the Scythian Shepheard. &amp;c.</HEAD>
<DIV2 TYPE="prologue">
<HEAD>The Prologue.</HEAD>
<L>FRom iygging vaines of riming mother wits,</L>
<L>And such conceits as clownage keepes in pay,</L>
<L>Weele lead you to the stately tent of War.</L>
<L>Where you shall heare the Scythian Tamburlaine:</L>
<L>Threatning the world with high astounding tearms</L>
<L>And scourging kingdoms with his cōquering sword</L>
<L>View but his picture in this tragicke glasse,</L>
<L>And then applaud his fortunes as you please.</L>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus. 1.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scaena. 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Mycetes, Cosroe, Meander, Theridamas, Ortygius, Ceneus, with others.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mycetes.</SPEAKER>
<L>BRother <HI>Cosroe,</HI> I find my selfe agreeud,</L>
<L>Yet insufficient to expresse the same:</L>
<L>For it requires a great and thundring speech:</L>
<L>Good brother tell the cause vnto my Lords,</L>
<L>I know you haue a better wit than I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vnhappie <HI>Persea,</HI> that in former age</L>
<L>Hast bene the seat of mightie Conquerors,</L>
<L>That in their prowesse and their pollicies,</L>
<L>Haue triumpht ouer <HI>Affrike,</HI> and the bounds</L>
<L>Of <HI>Europe,</HI> wher the Sun dares scarce appeare,</L>
<L>For freezing meteors and coniealed colde:</L>
<L>Now to be rulde and gouerned by a man,</L>
<L>At whose byrth-day <HI>Cynthia</HI> with <HI>Saturne</HI> ioinde,</L>
<L>And <HI>Ioue,</HI> the Sun and <HI>Mercurie</HI> denied</L>
<PB REF="4"/><FW><MILESTONE N="A3v"/></FW><!-- this page keyed by pfs -->
<L>To shed his influence in his fickle braine,</L>
<L>Now Turkes and Tartars shake their swords at th<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" RESP="murp" DISP="••"/></L>
<L>Meaning to mangle all thy Prouinces,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mycet.</SPEAKER>
<L>Brother, I see your meaning well enough.</L>
<L>And thorough your Planets I perceiue you thinke,</L>
<L>I am not wise enough to be a kinge,</L>
<L>But I refer me to my noble men,</L>
<L>That knowe my wit, and can be witnesses:</L>
<L>I might command you to be slaine for this,</L>
<L><HI>Meander,</HI> might I not?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meand.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not for so small a fault my soueraigne Lord</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mycet.</SPEAKER>
<L>I meane it not, but yet I know I might,</L>
<L>Yet liue, yea, liue, <HI>Mycetes</HI> wils it so:</L>
<L><HI>Meander,</HI> thou my faithfull Counsellor,</L>
<L>Declare the cause of my conceiued griefe,</L>
<L>Which is (God knowes) about that <HI>Tamburlaine.</HI></L>
<L>That like a Foxe in midst of haruest time,</L>
<L>Dooth pray vpnon my flockes of Passengers.</L>
<L>And as I heare, doth meane to pull my plumes,</L>
<L>Therefore tis good and meete for to be wise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meand.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oft haue I heard your Maiestie complain,</L>
<L>Of <HI>Tamburlaine,</HI> that sturdie Scythian thiefe,</L>
<L>That robs your merchants of <HI>Persepolis,</HI></L>
<L>Treading by land vnto the Westerne Isles,</L>
<L>And in your confines with his lawlesse traine,</L>
<L>Daily commits inciuill outrages.</L>
<L>Hoping (misled by dreaming prophesies)</L>
<L>To raigne in <HI>Asia,</HI> and with barbarous Armes,</L>
<L>To make himselfe the Monarch of the East:</L>
<L>But ere he march in <HI>Asia,</HI> or display</L>
<L>His vagrant Ensigne in the Persean fields,</L>
<L>Your Grace hath taken order by <HI>Theridimas,</HI></L>
<PB REF="4"/><FW><MILESTONE N="A4r"/></FW><!-- this page keyed by pfs -->
<L>Chardg'd with a thousand horse, to apprehend</L>
<L>And bring him Captiue to your Highnese throne,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Myce.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ful true thou speakst, &amp; like thy selfe my lord</L>
<L>Whom I may tearme a <HI>Damon</HI> for thy loue.</L>
<L>Therefore tis best, if so it lik you all,</L>
<L>To send my thousand horse incontinent,</L>
<L>To apprehend that paltrie Scythian.</L>
<L>How like you this, my honorable Lords?</L>
<L>Is it not a kingly resolution?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cosr.</SPEAKER>
<L>It cannot choose, because it comes from you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Myce.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then heare thy charge, valiant <HI>Theridimas</HI></L>
<L>The chiefest Captaine of Mycetes hoste,</L>
<L>The hope of <HI>Persea,</HI> and the verie legges</L>
<L>Whereon our state doth leane, as on a staffe,</L>
<L>That holds vs vp, and foiles our neighbour foes,</L>
<L>Thou shalt be leader of this thousand horse,</L>
<L>Whose foming galle with rage and high disdaine,</L>
<L>Haue sworne the death of wicked <HI>Tamburlaine.</HI></L>
<L>Go growning foorth, but come thou smyling home,</L>
<L>As did Sir <HI>Paris</HI> with the Grecian Dame,</L>
<L>Returne with speed, time passeth swift away,</L>
<L>Our life is fraile, and we may die to day.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ther.</SPEAKER>
<L>Before the Moone renew her borrowed light,</L>
<L>Doubt not my Lord and gratious Soueraigne,</L>
<L>But <HI>Tamburlaine,</HI> and that Tartarian rout,</L>
<L>Shall either perish by our warlike hands,</L>
<L>Or plead for mercie at your highnesse feet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Myce.</SPEAKER>
<L>Go, stout <HI>Theridimas,</HI> thy words are swords</L>
<L>And with thy lookes thou conquerest all thy foes:</L>
<L>I long to see thee back returne from thence,</L>
<L>That I may view these milk-white steeds of mine.</L>
<L>All loden with the heads of killed men,</L>
<PB REF="5"/><FW><MILESTONE N="A4v"/></FW>
<L>And from their knees, euen to their hoofes below,</L>
<L>Besmer'd with blood, that makes a dainty show.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>The.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then now my Lord, I humbly take my leaue.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Myc.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Therid.</HI> farewel ten thousand times,</L>
<L>Ah, <HI>Menaphon,</HI> why staiest thou thus behind,</L>
<L>When other men prease forward for renowne?</L>
<L>Go <HI>Menaphon,</HI> go into <HI>Scythia,</HI></L>
<L>And foot by foot follow <HI>Theridamas:</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, pray you let him stay, a greater</L>
<L>Fits Menaphon, than warring with a Thiefe:</L>
<L>Create him Prorex of <HI>Affrica,</HI></L>
<L>That he may win the Babylonians hearts,</L>
<L>Which will reuolt from Persean gouernment,</L>
<L>Vnlesse they haue a wiser king than you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Myc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vnlesse they haue a wiser king than you?</L>
<L>These are his words, <HI>Meander</HI> set them downe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cos.</SPEAKER>
<L>And ad this to them, that all <HI>Asia</HI></L>
<L>Lament to see the follie of their King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Myc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well here I sweare by this my royal seat.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cos.</SPEAKER>
<L>You may doe well to kisse it then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Myc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Embost with silke as best beseemes my state.</L>
<L>To be reueng'd for these contemptuous words.</L>
<L>O where is dutie and allegeance now?</L>
<L>Fled to the Caspean or the Ocean maine?</L>
<L>What, shall I call thee brother? No, a foe,</L>
<L>Monster of Nature, shame vnto thy stocke,</L>
<L>That dar'st presume thy Soueraigne for to mocke.</L>
<L><HI>Meander</HI> come, I am abus'd <HI>Meander.</HI></L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Manent Cosroe &amp; Menaphon.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mena.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now my Lord, what, mated and amaz'd</L>
<L>To heare the king thus thraten like himselfe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ah <HI>Menaphon,</HI> I passe not for his threates,</L>
<PB REF="5"/><FW><MILESTONE N="A5r"/></FW>
<L>The plot is laid by Persean Noble men,</L>
<L>And Captaines of the Medean garrisons,</L>
<L>To crowne me Emperour of <HI>Asia,</HI></L>
<L>But this it is that doth excruciate</L>
<L>The verie substance of my vexed soule!</L>
<L>To see our neighbours that were woont to quake</L>
<L>And tremble at the Persean Monarkes name,</L>
<L>Now sits and laughs our regiment to scorne,</L>
<L>And that which might resolue me into teares:</L>
<L>Men from the farthest Equinoctiall line,</L>
<L>Haue swarm'd in troopes into the Easterne <HI>India:</HI></L>
<L>Lading their shippes with golde and pretious stones:</L>
<L>And made their spoiles from all our prouinces.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mena.</SPEAKER>
<L>This should intreat your highnesse to reioice,</L>
<L>Since Fortune giues you opportunity,</L>
<L>To gaine the tytle of a Conquerour,</L>
<L>By curing of this maimed Emperie,</L>
<L><HI>Affrike</HI> and <HI>Europe</HI> bordering on your land,</L>
<L>And continent to your Dominions:</L>
<L>How easely may you with a mightie hoste,</L>
<L>Passe into <HI>Graecia,</HI> as did <HI>Cyrus</HI> once.</L>
<L>And cause them to withdraw their forces home,</L>
<L>Least you subdue the pride of Christendome!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cos.</SPEAKER>
<L>But <HI>Menaph.</HI> what means this trumpets sound</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mena.</SPEAKER>
<L>Behold, my Lord <HI>Ortigius,</HI> and the rest,</L>
<L>Bringing the Crowne to make you Emperour.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Ortigius &amp; Conerus bearing a Crowne with others.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ort.</SPEAKER>
<L>Magnificent and mightie Prince <HI>Cosroe,</HI></L>
<L>We in the name of other Persean states,</L>
<L>And commons of this mightie Monarchie,</L>
<L>Present thee with th'Emperiall Diadem.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="6"/><FW><MILESTONE N="A5v"/></FW>
<SPEAKER>Cene.</SPEAKER>
<L>The warlike Souldiers, &amp; the Gentlemen,</L>
<L>That heretofore haue fild <HI>Persepolis</HI></L>
<L>With Affrike Captaines, taken in the field:</L>
<L>Whoose ransome made them martch in coates of gold,</L>
<L>With costlie iewels hanging at their eares,</L>
<L>And shining stones vpon their loftie Crestes,</L>
<L>Now liuing idle in the walled townes,</L>
<L>Wanting both pay and martiall discipline.</L>
<L>Begin in troopes to threaten ciuill warre.</L>
<L>And openly exclaime against the King.</L>
<L>Therefore to stay all sodaine mutinies,</L>
<L>We will inuest your Highnesse Emperour:</L>
<L>Whereat the Souldiers will conceiue more ioy,</L>
<L>Then did the Macedonians at the spoile</L>
<L>Of great <HI>Darius</HI> and his wealthy hoast.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cosr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wel, since I see the state of <HI>Persea</HI> droope,</L>
<L>And languish in my brothers gouernment:</L>
<L>I willingly receiue th'mperiall crowne,</L>
<L>And vow to weare it for my countries good:</L>
<L>In spight of them shall malice my estate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ortyg.</SPEAKER>
<L>And in assurance of desir'd successe,</L>
<L>We here doo crowne thee Monarch of the East,</L>
<L>Emperour of <HI>Asia,</HI> and of <HI>Persea,</HI></L>
<L>Great Lord of <HI>Medea</HI> and <HI>Armenia:</HI></L>
<L>Duke of <HI>Affrica</HI> and <HI>Albania,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Mesopotamia</HI> and of <HI>Parthia,</HI></L>
<L>East <HI>India</HI> and the late discouered Isles,</L>
<L>Chiefe Lord of all the wide vast <HI>Euxine</HI> sea,</L>
<L>And of the euer raging Caspian Lake:</L>
<L>Long liue <HI>Cosroe</HI> mighty Emperour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cosr.</SPEAKER>
<L>And <HI>Ioue</HI> may neuer let me longer liue,</L>
<L>Then I may seeke to gratifie your loue,</L>
<PB REF="6"/><FW><MILESTONE N="A6r"/></FW>
<L>And cause the souldiers that thus honour me,</L>
<L>To triumph ouer many Prouinces.</L>
<L>By whose desires of discipline in Armes,</L>
<L>I doubt not shortly but to raigne sole king,</L>
<L>And with the Armie of <HI>Theridamas,</HI></L>
<L>Whether we presently will flie (my Lords)</L>
<L>To rest secure against my brothers force.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ortyg</SPEAKER>
<L>We knew my Lord, before we brought the crowne,</L>
<L>Intending your inuestion so neere,</L>
<L>The residence of your dispised brother,</L>
<L>The Lord would not be too exasperate,</L>
<L>To iniure or suppresse your woorthy tytle.</L>
<L>Or if they would, there are in readines</L>
<L>Ten thousand horse to carie you from hence,</L>
<L>In spite of all suspected enemies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cosr.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know it wel my Lord, &amp; thanke you all,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ortyg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sound vp the trumpets then,</L>
<L>God saue the King.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Actus. 1. Scoena. 2:</HEAD>
<STAGE>Tamburlaine leading Zenocrate: Techelles, Vsu∣measane, other Lords and Souldiers loden with treasure.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>COme lady, let not this appal your thoughts</L>
<L>The iewels and the treasure we haue tane</L>
<L>Shall be reseru'd, and you in better state,</L>
<L>Than if you were arriu'd in <HI>Siria.</HI></L>
<L>Euen in the circle of your Fathers armes:</L>
<L>The mightie Souldan of <HI>Egyptia.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Zeno.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ah Shepheard, pity my distressed plight,</L>
<PB REF="7"/><FW><MILESTONE N="A6v"/></FW>
<L>(If as thou seem'st, thou art so meane a man)</L>
<L>And seeke not to inrich thy followers,</L>
<L>By lawlesse rapine from a silly maide.</L>
<L>Who traueiling with these Medean Lords</L>
<L>To <HI>Memphis,</HI> from my vncles country of <HI>Medea,</HI></L>
<L>Where all my youth I haue vene gouerned,</L>
<L>Haue past the armie of the mightie Turke:</L>
<L>Bearing his priuie signet and his hand:</L>
<L>To safe conduct vs thorow <HI>Affrica:</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mag.</SPEAKER>
<L>And since we haue arriu'd in <HI>Scythia,</HI></L>
<L>Besides rich presents from the puisant <HI>Cham,</HI></L>
<L>We haue his highnesse letters to command</L>
<L>Aide and assistance if we stand in need.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>But now you see these letters &amp; commandes,</L>
<L>Are countermanded by a greater man:</L>
<L>And through my prouinces you must expect</L>
<L>Letters of conduct from my mightinesse,</L>
<L>If you intend to keep your treasure safe.</L>
<L>But since I loue to liue at liberty,</L>
<L>As easely may you get the Souldans crowne,</L>
<L>As any prizes out of my precinct.</L>
<L>For they are friends that help to weane my state,</L>
<L>Till men and kingdomes help to strengthen it:</L>
<L>And must maintaine my life exempt from seruitude.</L>
<L>But tell me Maddam, is your grace betroth'd:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Zen.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am (my Lord,) for so you do import.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am a Lord, for so my deeds shall prooue,</L>
<L>And yet a shepheard by my Parentage:</L>
<L>But Lady, this faire face and heauenly hew,</L>
<L>Mud grace his bed that conquers <HI>Asia:</HI></L>
<L>And meanes to be a terrour to the world,</L>
<L>Measuring the limits of his Emperie</L>
<PB REF="7"/><FW><MILESTONE N="A7r"/></FW>
<L>By East and west, as <HI>Phaebus</HI> doth his course:</L>
<L>Lie here ye weedes that I disdaine to weare,</L>
<L>This compleat armor, and this curtle-axe</L>
<L>Are adiuncts more beseeming <HI>Tamburlaine.</HI></L>
<L>And Maddam, whatsoeuer you esteeme</L>
<L>Of this successe, and losse vnvallued,</L>
<L>Both may inuest you Empresse of the East:</L>
<L>And these that seeme but silly country Swaines,</L>
<L>May haue the leading of so great an host,</L>
<L>As with their waight shall make the mountains quake.</L>
<L>Euen as when windy exhalations,</L>
<L>Fighting for passage, tilt within the earth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tec.</SPEAKER>
<L>As princely Lions when they rouse themselues,</L>
<L>Stretching their pawes, and threatning heardes of Beastes.</L>
<L>So in his Armour looketh <HI>Tamburlaine:</HI></L>
<L>Me thinks I see kings kneeling at his feet,</L>
<L>And he with frowning browes and fiery <UNCLEAR>lookes</UNCLEAR>,</L>
<L>Spurning their crownes from off their captiue heads.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vsum.</SPEAKER>
<L>And making thee and me <HI>Techelles,</HI> kinges,</L>
<L>That euen to death will follow <HI>Tamburlaine.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nobly resolu'd, sweet friends and followers,</L>
<L>These Lords (perhaps) do scorne our estimates:</L>
<L>And thinke we prattle with distempered spirits,</L>
<L>But since they measure our deserts so meane,</L>
<L>That in conceit bear Empires on our speares,</L>
<L>Affecting thoughts coequall with the cloudes,</L>
<L>They shall be kept our forced followers,</L>
<L>Till with their eies thee view vs Emperours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Zen.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Gods, defenders of the innocent,</L>
<L>Will neuer prosper your intended driftes,</L>
<L><UNCLEAR>That thus oppresse</UNCLEAR> poore friendles passengers.</L>
<PB REF="8"/><FW><MILESTONE N="A7v"/></FW>
<L>Therefore at least admit vs libertie,</L>
<L>Euen as thou hop'st to be eternized,</L>
<L>By liuing <HI>Asias</HI> mightie Emperour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agid.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hope our Ladies treasure and our owne,</L>
<L>May serue for ransome to our liberties:</L>
<L>Returne our Mules and emptie Camels backe,</L>
<L>That we may traueile into <HI>Siria,</HI></L>
<L>Where her betrothed Lord <HI>Alcidamus,</HI></L>
<L>Expects th'arriuall of her highnesse person.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mag.</SPEAKER>
<L>And wheresoeuer we repose our selues,</L>
<L>We will report but well of <HI>Tamburlaine.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Disdaines <HI>Zenocrate</HI> to liue with me?</L>
<L>Or you my Lordes to be my followers?</L>
<L>Thinke you I way this treasure more than you?</L>
<L>Not all the Gold in Indias welthy armes,</L>
<L>Shall buy the meanest souldier in my traine.</L>
<L><HI>Zenocrate,</HI> louelier than the Loue of <HI>Ioue,</HI></L>
<L>Brighter than is the siluer Rhodolfe,</L>
<L>Fairet than whitcst snow on Scythian hils,</L>
<L>Thy person is more woorth to <HI>Tamburlaine,</HI></L>
<L>Than the possession of the Persean Crowne.</L>
<L>Which gratious startes haue promist at my birth,</L>
<L>A hundreth Tartars shall attend on thee,</L>
<L>Mountrf on Steeds, swifter than <HI>Pegasus.</HI></L>
<L>Thy Garments shall be made of Medean silke,</L>
<L>Enchast with precious iuelles of mine owne:</L>
<L>More rich and valurous than <HI>Zenocrates.</HI></L>
<L>With milke-white Hartes vpon an Iuorie sled,</L>
<L>Thou shalt be drawen amidst the frosen Pooles,</L>
<L>And scale the ysie mountaines lofty tops:</L>
<L>Which with thy beautie will be soone resolu'd.</L>
<L>My martiall prises with fiue hundred men,</L>
<PB REF="8"/><FW><MILESTONE N="A8r"/></FW>
<L>Wun on the fiftie headed <HI>Vuolgas</HI> waues.</L>
<L>Shall all we offer to <HI>Zenocrate,</HI></L>
<L>And then my selfe to faire Zenocrate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tech.</SPEAKER>
<L>What now? In loue?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Techelles, women must be flaterrd.</L>
<L>But this is she with whom I am in loue.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter a Souldier.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sould.</SPEAKER>
<L>Newes, newes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now, what's the matter?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sould.</SPEAKER>
<L>A thousand Persean horsmen are at hand,</L>
<L>Sent from the King to ouercome vs all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now my Lords of <HI>Egypt</HI> &amp; <HI>Zenocrate?</HI></L>
<L>Now must your iewels be restor'd againe:</L>
<L>And I that triumpht so be ouercome.</L>
<L>How say you Lordings, Is not this your hope?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agid.</SPEAKER>
<L>We hope your selfe wil willingly restore thē.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Such hope, such fortune haue the thousand horse.</L>
<L>Soft ye my Lords and sweet <HI>Zenocrate.</HI></L>
<L>You must be forced from me ere you goe:</L>
<L>A thousand horsmen: We fiue hundred foote?</L>
<L>An ods too great, for vs to stand against:</L>
<L>But are they rich: And is their armour good?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sould.</SPEAKER>
<L>Their plumed helmes are wrought with beaten golde.</L>
<L>Their swords enameld, and about their neckes</L>
<L>Hangs massie chaines of golde downe to the waste,</L>
<L>In euery part exceeding braue and rich.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then shall we fight couragiously with them.</L>
<L>Or looke you, I should play the Orator?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tech.</SPEAKER>
<L>No: cowards and fainthearted runawaies,</L>
<L>Looke for orations when the foe is neere.</L>
<L>Our swordes shall play the Orators for vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="9"/><FW><MILESTONE N="A8v"/></FW>
<SPEAKER>Vsum.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come let vs meet them at the mountain foot,</L>
<L>And with a sodaine and an hot alarme</L>
<L>Driue all their horses headlong down the hill.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tech.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come let vs martch.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay <HI>Techelles,</HI> aske a parlee first,</L>
<STAGE>The Souldiers enter.</STAGE>
<L>Open the Males, yet guard the treasure sure,</L>
<L>Lay out our golden wedges to the view,</L>
<L>That their reflexions may amaze the Perseans.</L>
<L>And looke we friendly on them when they come:</L>
<L>But if they offer word or violence,</L>
<L>Weele fight fiue hundred men at armes to one,</L>
<L>Before we part with our possession.</L>
<L>And gainst the Generall we will lift our swords.</L>
<L>And either lanch his greedy thirsting throat,</L>
<L>Or take him prisoner, and his chaine shall serue</L>
<L>For Manackles, till he be ransom'd home.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tech,</SPEAKER>
<L>I heare them come, shal we encounter them?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Keep all your standings, and not stir a foote,</L>
<L>My selfe will bide the danger of the brunt.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Theridamas with others.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ther.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where is this Scythian <HI>Tamberlaine?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whō seekst thou Persean? I am <HI>Taburlain.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ther.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Tamburlaine?</HI> A Scythian Shepheard, so imbellished</L>
<L>With Natures pride, and richest furniture,</L>
<L>His looks do menace heauen and dare the Gods,</L>
<L>His fierie eies are fixt vpon the earth.</L>
<L>As if he now deuis'd some Stratageme:</L>
<L>Or meant to pierce <HI>Auernas</HI> darksome vaults.</L>
<PB REF="9"/><FW><MILESTONE N="B1r"/></FW>
<L>To pull the triple headed dog from hell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Noble and milde this Persean seemes to be,</L>
<L>If outward habit iudge the inward man,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tech.</SPEAKER>
<L>His deep affections make him passionate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>With what a maiesty he rears his looks:</L>
<L>In thee (thou valiant man of Persea)</L>
<L>I see the folly of thy Emperour:</L>
<L>Art thou but Captaine of a thousand horse,</L>
<L>That vy Characters grauen in thy browes,</L>
<L>And by thy martiall face and stout aspect,</L>
<L>Deseru'st to haue the leading of an hoste?</L>
<L>Forsake thy king and do but ioine with me</L>
<L>And we will triumph ouer all the world.</L>
<L>I hold the Fates bound fast in yron chaines,</L>
<L>And with my hand turne Fortunes wheel about,</L>
<L>And sooner shall the Sun fall from his Spheare,</L>
<L>Than <HI>Tamburlaine</HI> be slaine or ouercome.</L>
<L>Draw foorth thy sword, thou mighty man at Armes,</L>
<L>Intending but to rase my charmed skin:</L>
<L>And <HI>Ioue</HI> himselfe will stretch his hand from heauen.</L>
<L>To ward the blow, and shield me safe from harme,</L>
<L>See how he raines down heaps of gold in showers.</L>
<L>As if he meant to giue my Souldiers pay,</L>
<L>And as a sure and grounded argument,</L>
<L>That I shall be the Monark of the East.</L>
<L>He sends this Sculdans daughter rich and braue,</L>
<L>To be my Queen and portly Emperesse,</L>
<L>If thou wilt stay with me, renowmed man,</L>
<L>And lead thy thousand horse with my conduct,</L>
<L>Besides thy share of this Egyptian prise,</L>
<L>Those thousand horse shall sweat with martiall spoile</L>
<L>Of conquered kingdomes, and of Cities sackt,</L>
<PB REF="10"/><FW><MILESTONE N="B1v"/></FW>
<L>Both we wil walke vpon the lofty clifts,</L>
<L>And Christian Merchants that with Russian stems</L>
<L>Plow vp huge furrowes in the Caspian sea.</L>
<L>Shall vaile to vs, as Lords of all the Lake.</L>
<L>Both we will raigne as Consuls of the earth,</L>
<L>And mightie kings shall be our Senators,</L>
<L><HI>Ioue</HI> sometime masked in a Shepheards weed,</L>
<L>And by those steps that he hath scal'd the heauens,</L>
<L>May we become immortall like the Gods.</L>
<L>Ioine with me now in this my meane estate,</L>
<L>(I cal it meane, because being yet obscure,</L>
<L>The Nations far remoou'd admyre me not)</L>
<L>And when my name and honor shall be spread,</L>
<L>As far as <HI>Boreas</HI> claps his brazen wings,</L>
<L>Or faire <HI>Botëes</HI> sends his cheerefull light.</L>
<L>Then shalt thou be Competitor with me,</L>
<L>And sit with <HI>Tambulaine.</HI> in all his maiestie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ther.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not <HI>Hermes</HI> Prolocutor to the Gods,</L>
<L>Could vse perswasions more patheticall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor are <HI>Apollos</HI> Oracles more true,</L>
<L>Then thou shalt find my vaunts substantiall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tec.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are his friends, and if the Persean king</L>
<L>Should offer present Duke domes to our state,</L>
<L>We thinke it losse to make exchange for that,</L>
<L>We are assured of by our friends successe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vsum.</SPEAKER>
<L>And kingdomes at the least we all expect.</L>
<L>Befides the honor in assured conquestes:</L>
<L>Where kings shall crouch vnto our conquering swords,</L>
<L>And hostes of souldiers stand amaz'd at vs,</L>
<L>When with their fearfull tongues they shall cenfesse</L>
<L>Theise are the men that all the world admires,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ther.</SPEAKER>
<L>What stronge enchantments tice my yeelding soule</L>
<PB REF="10"/><FW><MILESTONE N="B2r"/></FW>
<L>Are these resolued noble Scythians?</L>
<L>But shall I prooue a Traitor to my King?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, but the trustie friend of <HI>Tamburlaine.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ther.</SPEAKER>
<L>Won with thy words, &amp; conquered with thy looks,</L>
<L>I yeeld my selfe, my men &amp; horse to thee:</L>
<L>To be partaker of thy good or ill,</L>
<L>As long as life maintaines <HI>Theridamas.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Theridamas</HI> my friend, take here my hand.</L>
<L>Which is as much as if I swore by heauen,</L>
<L>And call'd' the Gods to witnesse of my vow,</L>
<L>Thus shall my heart be still combinde with thine,</L>
<L>Vntill our bodies turne to Elements:</L>
<L>And both our soules aspire celestiall thrones.</L>
<L><HI>Techelles,</HI> and <HI>Casane,</HI> welcome him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tech.</SPEAKER>
<L>Welcome renowmed Persean to vs all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Long may theridamas remaine with vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>These are my friends in whō I more reioice,</L>
<L>Than dooth the King of Persea in his Crowne:</L>
<L>And by the loue of <HI>Pyllades</HI> and <HI>Orestes,</HI></L>
<L>Whose statutes we adore in Scythia,</L>
<L>Thy selfe and them shall neuer part from me,</L>
<L>Before I crowne you kings in <HI>Asia.</HI></L>
<L>Make much of them gentle <HI>Theridamas,</HI></L>
<L>And they will neuer leaue thee till the death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ther.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor thee, nor them, thrice noble <HI>Tambutlain</HI></L>
<L>Shal want my heart to be with gladnes pierc'd</L>
<L>To do you honor and securitie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>A thousand thankes worthy <HI>theridamas:</HI></L>
<L>And now faire Madam, and my noble Lords,</L>
<L>If you will willingly remaine with me,</L>
<L>You shall haue herors, as your merits be:</L>
<L>Or els you shall be forc'd w<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" RESP="murp" DISP="••"/>h slauerie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="11"/><FW><MILESTONE N="B2v"/></FW>
<SPEAKER>Agid.</SPEAKER>
<L>We yeeld vnto thee happie <HI>Tamburlaine</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>For you then Maddam, I am out of doubt</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Zeno.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must be pleasde perforce, wretched <HI>Zenocrate.</HI></L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus. 2.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scaena. 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Cosroe, Menaphon, Ortygius, Ceneus, with other Souldiers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cosroe.</SPEAKER>
<L>THus farre are we towards <HI>Theridamas,</HI></L>
<L>And valiant <HI>Tamburlaine,</HI> the man of fame,</L>
<L>The man that in the forhead of his fortune,</L>
<L>Beares figures of renowne and myracle:</L>
<L>But tell me, that hast seene him, <HI>Menaphon,</HI></L>
<L>What stature wields he, and what personage:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mena.</SPEAKER>
<L>Of stature tall, and straightly fashioned,</L>
<L>Like his desire, lift vpwards and diuine,</L>
<L>Sa large of lims, his ioints so strongly knit,</L>
<L>Such breadth of shoulders as might mainely beare</L>
<L>Olde Atlas burthen, twixt his manly pitch,</L>
<L>A pearle more worth, then all the world is plaste:</L>
<L>Wherein by curious soueraintie of Art,</L>
<L>Are firt his piercing instruments of sight:</L>
<L>Whose fiery cyrcles beare encompassed</L>
<L>A heauen of heauenly bodies in their Spheares:</L>
<L>That guides his steps and actions to the throne.</L>
<L>Where honor sits inuested royally:</L>
<L>Pale of complexion: wrought in him with passion,</L>
<L>Thrirsting with souerainty with loue of armes,</L>
<L>His lofty browes in foldes, do figure death,</L>
<PB REF="11"/><FW><MILESTONE N="B3r"/></FW>
<L>And in their smoothnesse, amitie and life:</L>
<L>About them hangs a knot of Amber heire.</L>
<L>Wrapped in curles, as fierce <HI>Achilles</HI> was,</L>
<L>On which the breath of heauen delights to play,</L>
<L>Making it daunce with wanton maiestie:</L>
<L>His armes and singers long and snowy,</L>
<L>Betokening valour and excesse of strength:</L>
<L>In euery part proportioned like the man,</L>
<L>Should make the world subdued to <HI>Tamburlaine.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cos</SPEAKER>
<L>Wel hast thou pourtraid in thy tearms of life,</L>
<L>The face and personage of a woondrous man:</L>
<L>Nature doth striue with Fortune and his stars,</L>
<L>To make him famous in accomplisht woorth:</L>
<L>And well his merits show him to be made:</L>
<L>His Fortunes m<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" RESP="murp" DISP="•"/>ister, and the king of men.</L>
<L>That could perswade at such a sodaine pinch,</L>
<L>With reasons of his valour and his life,</L>
<L>A thousand sworne and ouermatching foes:</L>
<L>Then when our powers in points of swords are ioin'd</L>
<L>And closde in compasse of the killing bullet,</L>
<L>Though straight the passage and the port be made,</L>
<L>That leads to Pallace of my brothers life,</L>
<L>Proud is his fortune if we pierce it not.</L>
<L>And when the princely Persean Diadem,</L>
<L>Shall ouerway his wearie witlesse head,</L>
<L>And fall like mellowed fruit, with shakes of death,</L>
<L>In faire <HI>Persea</HI> noble <HI>tamburlaine</HI></L>
<L>Shall be my Regent, and remaine as King:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ort.</SPEAKER>
<L>In happy hower we haue set the Crowne</L>
<L>Vpon your kingly head, that seeks our honor,</L>
<L>In ioyning with the man, ordain'd by heauen</L>
<L>To further euery action to the best.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="12"/><FW><MILESTONE N="B3v"/></FW>
<SPEAKER>Cen.</SPEAKER>
<L>He that with Shepheards and a litle spoile,</L>
<L>Durst in disdaine of wrong and tyrannie,</L>
<L>Defend his freedome gainst a Monarchie.</L>
<L>What will he doe supported by a king:</L>
<L>Leading a troope of Gentlemen and Lords,</L>
<L>And stuft with trasure for his highest thoughts,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cos.</SPEAKER>
<L>And such shall wait on worthy <HI>Tamburlaine.</HI></L>
<L>Our army will be forty thousand strong,</L>
<L>When <HI>Tamburlain</HI> and braue <HI>Theridamas</HI></L>
<L>Haue met vs by the riuer <HI>Araris:</HI></L>
<L>And all conioin'd to meet the witlesse King.</L>
<L>That now is marching neer to Parthia.</L>
<L>And with vnwilling souldiers faintly arm'd,</L>
<L>To seeke reuenge on me and <HI>Tamburlaine.</HI></L>
<L>To whom sweet <HI>Menaphon,</HI> direct me straight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mena.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will my Lord.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Act. 2. Scaena. 2,</HEAD>
<STAGE>Mycetes, Meander, with other Lords and Souldiers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mycetes.</SPEAKER>
<L>COme my <HI>Meander,</HI> let vs to this geere,</L>
<L>I tel you true my heart is swolne with wrath,</L>
<L>On this same theeuish villaine <HI>tamburlaine.</HI></L>
<L>And of that false <HI>Cosroe,</HI> my traiterous brothet</L>
<L>Would it not grieue a King to be so abusde.</L>
<L>And haue a thousand horsmen tane away?</L>
<L>And which is worst to haue his Diadem</L>
<L>Sought for by such scalde knaucs as loue him net.</L>
<L>I thinke it would: wel then, by heauens I sweare,</L>
<L><HI>Aurora</HI> shall not peepe out of her doores,</L>
<PB REF="12"/><FW><MILESTONE N="B4r"/></FW>
<L>But I will haue <HI>Cosroe</HI> by the head,</L>
<L>And kill proud <HI>Tamburlaine</HI> with point of sword.</L>
<L>Tell you the rest <HI>(Meander)</HI> I haue said.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mean.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then hauing past Armenian desarts now,</L>
<L>And pitch our tents vnder the Georgean hilles.</L>
<L>Whose tops are couered with Tartarian thieues,</L>
<L>That lie in ambush, waiting for a pray:</L>
<L>What should we doe but bid them battaile straight,</L>
<L>And rid the world of those detested troopes;</L>
<L>Least if we let them lynger here a while,</L>
<L>They gather strength by power of fresh supplies.</L>
<L>This countrie swarntes with vile eutragious men,</L>
<L>That liue by rapine and by lawlesse spoile,</L>
<L>Fit Souldiers for the wicked <HI>Tamburlaine.</HI></L>
<L>And he that could with giftes and promises.</L>
<L>Inueigle him that lead a thousand horse,</L>
<L>And make him false his faith vnto his King,</L>
<L>Will quickly win such as are like himselfe.</L>
<L>Therefore cheere vp your mindes, prepare to fight,</L>
<L>He that can take or slaughter <HI>tamburlaine,</HI></L>
<L>Shall rule the Prouince of <HI>Albania.</HI></L>
<L>Who brings that Traitors head theridamas,</L>
<L>Shal haue a gouernment in <HI>Medea:</HI></L>
<L>Beside the spoile of him and all his traine:</L>
<L>But if <HI>Cosroe</HI> (as our Spials say,</L>
<L>And as we know) remaines with tamburlaine,</L>
<L>His Highnesse pleasure is that he should liue,</L>
<L>And be reclaim'd with princely lenitie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>A Spy.</SPEAKER>
<L>An hundred horsmen of my company</L>
<L>Srowting abroad vpon these champion plaines,</L>
<L>Haue vtew'd the army of the Scythians,</L>
<L>Which make reports it far exceeds the Kings.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="13"/><FW><MILESTONE N="B4v"/></FW>
<SPEAKER>Mean.</SPEAKER>
<L>Suppose they be in number infinit,</L>
<L>Yet being void of Martiall discipline,</L>
<L>All running headlong after greedy spoiles:</L>
<L>And more regarding gaine than victory:</L>
<L>Like to the cruell brothers of the earth,</L>
<L>Sprong of the teeth of Dragons venomous,</L>
<L>Their carelesse swords shal lanch their fellowes threats</L>
<L>And make vs triumph in their ouerthrow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Myc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Was there such brethren, sweet <HI>Meander,</HI> say</L>
<L>That sprong of teeth of Dragons venomous.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meand.</SPEAKER>
<L>So Poets say, my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Myce.</SPEAKER>
<L>And tis a prety toy to be a Poet.</L>
<L>Wel, wel <HI>(Meander)</HI> thou art deeply read:</L>
<L>And hauing thee, I haue a iewell sure:</L>
<L>Go en my Lord, and giue your charge I say,</L>
<L>Thy wit will make vs Conquerors to day.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mean.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then noble souldiors, to intrap these theeues,</L>
<L>That liue confounded in disordered troopes,</L>
<L>If wealth or riches may preuaile with them,</L>
<L>We haue our Cammels laden all with gold:</L>
<L>Which you that be but common souldiers,</L>
<L>Shall fling in euery corner of the field:</L>
<L>And while the base borne Tartars take it vp,</L>
<L>You fighting more for honor than for gold,</L>
<L>Shall massacre those greedy minded slaues.</L>
<L>And when their scattered armie is subdu'd:</L>
<L>And you march on their slaughtered carkasses,</L>
<L>Share equally the gold that bought their liues,</L>
<L>And liue like Gentlemen in <HI>Persea,</HI></L>
<L>Strike vp the Drum and martch corragiously,</L>
<L>Fortune her selfe dooth sit vpon our Crests.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Myc.</SPEAKER>
<L>He tels you true, my maisters, so he does.</L>
<L>Drum{is}, why sound ye not whē <HI>Meand.</HI> speak{is}.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt</STAGE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<PB REF="13"/><FW><MILESTONE N="B5r"/></FW>
<HEAD>Actus. 2. Scaena. 3.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Cosroe, Tamburlaine, Theridamas, Techelles, Vsu∣measane, Ortygius. with others.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cosroe.</SPEAKER>
<L>NOw worthy <HI>Tamburlaine,</HI> haue I reposde,</L>
<L>In thy approoued Fortunes all my hope,</L>
<L>What thinkst thou man, shal come of our at∣temptes.</L>
<L>For euen as from assured oracle,</L>
<L>I take thy doome for satisfaction.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>And so mistake you not a whit my Lord.</L>
<L>For Fates and Oracles, heauen haue sworne,</L>
<L>To roialise the deedes of <HI>tamburlaine:</HI></L>
<L>And make them blest that share in his attemptes.</L>
<L>And doubt you not, but if you fauour me,</L>
<L>And let my Fortunes and my valour sway,</L>
<L>To some direction in your martiall deeds,</L>
<L>The world will striue with hostes of men at armes.</L>
<L>To swarme vnto the Ensigne I support,</L>
<L>The host of <HI>Xerxes,</HI> which by fame is said</L>
<L>To drinke the mightie Parthian <HI>Araris,</HI></L>
<L>Was but a handful to that we will haue.</L>
<L>Our quiuering Lances shaking in the aire,</L>
<L>And bullets like <HI>Ioues</HI> dreadfull Thunderbolts,</L>
<L>Enrolde in flames and fiery smoldering mistes,</L>
<L>Shall threat the Gods more than Cyclopian warres,</L>
<L>And with our Sun-bright armour as we march,</L>
<L>Weel chase the Stars from heauen, and dim their eies</L>
<L>That stand and muse at our admyred armes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>therid.</SPEAKER>
<L>You see my Lord, what woorking woordes he hath.</L>
<PB REF="14"/><FW><MILESTONE N="B5v"/></FW>
<L>But when you see his actions stop his speech,</L>
<L>Your speech will stay, or so extol his worth,</L>
<L>As I shall be commended and excusde</L>
<L>For turning my poore charge to his direction.</L>
<L>And these his two renowmed friends my Lord,</L>
<L>Would make one thrust and striue to be retain'd</L>
<L>In such a great degree of amitie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tech.</SPEAKER>
<L>With dutie not with amitie we yeeld</L>
<L>Our vtmost seruice to the faire <HI>Cosroe.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Which I esteeme as portion of my crown.</L>
<L><HI>Vsumeasane</HI> and <HI>techelles</HI> both,</L>
<L>When she that rules in <HI>Rhamnis</HI> golden gates,</L>
<L>And makes a passage for all prosperous Armes:</L>
<L>Shall make me solely Emperour of <HI>Asia,</HI></L>
<L>Then shall your meeds and vallours be aduaunst</L>
<L>To roomes of honour and Nobilitie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then haste <HI>Cosroe</HI> to be king alone.</L>
<L>That I with these my friends and all my men,</L>
<L>May triumph in our long expected Fate,</L>
<L>The King your Brother is now hard at hand,</L>
<L>Meete with the foole, and rid your royall shoulders</L>
<L>Of such a burthen, as outwaies the sands</L>
<L>And all the craggie rockes of Caspea.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mess.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, we haue discouered the enemie</L>
<L>Ready to chardge you with a mighty armie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come tamburlain, now whet thy winged sword</L>
<L>And lift thy lofty arme into the cloudes,</L>
<L>That it may reach the King of Perseas crowne,</L>
<L>And set it safe on my victorious head.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>See where it is, the keenest Cutle-axe.</L>
<L>That ere made passage thorow Persean Armes,</L>
<L>These are the wings shall make it flie as swift,</L>
<PB REF="14"/><FW><MILESTONE N="B6r"/></FW>
<L>As dooth the lightening: or the breath of heauen,</L>
<L>And kill as sure as it swiftly flies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy words assure me of kind successe:</L>
<L>Go valiant Souldier, go before and charge</L>
<L>The fainting army of that foolish King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tamb.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Vsumeasane</HI> and <HI>techelles</HI> come,</L>
<L>We are enough to scarre the enemy,</L>
<L>And more than needes to make an Emperour.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="scene" N="[4]">
<STAGE>To the Battaile, and Mycetes comes out alone with his Crowne in his hand offering to hide it.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Myc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Accurst be he that first inuented war,</L>
<L>They knew not, ah, they knew not simple men,</L>
<L>How those were hit by pelting Cannon shot,</L>
<L>Stand staggering like a quiuering Aspen leafe,</L>
<L>Fearing the force of <HI>Boreas</HI> boistrous blasts.</L>
<L>In what a lamentable case were I,</L>
<L>If Nature had not giuen me wisedomes lore?</L>
<L>For Kings are clouts that euery man shoots at,</L>
<L>Our Crowne the pin that thousands seeke to cleaue,</L>
<L>Therefore in pollicie I thinke it good</L>
<L>To hide it close: a goodly Stratagem,</L>
<L>And far from any man that is a foole.</L>
<L>So shall not I be knowen, or if I bee,</L>
<L>They cannot take away my crowne from me.</L>
<L>Here will I hide it in this simple hole.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Tamburlain.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>What fearful coward stragling from the camp</L>
<L>When Kings themselues are present in the field.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Myc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou liest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Base villaine, darst thou giue the lie?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Myc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away, I am the King: go, touch me not.</L>
<PB REF="15"/><FW><MILESTONE N="B6v"/></FW>
<L>Thou breakst the law of Armes vnlesse thou kneele.</L>
<L>And cry me mercie, noble King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you the witty King of <HI>Persea?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Myce.</SPEAKER>
<L>I marie am I: haue you any suite to me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would intreat you to speak but three wise wordes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Myce.</SPEAKER>
<L>So I can when I see my time.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is this your Crowne?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Myce.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, Didst thou euer see a fairer?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>You will not sell it, wil ye?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Myce.</SPEAKER>
<L>Such another word, and I, will haue thee executed.</L>
<L>Come giue it me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, I tooke it prisoner.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Myce.</SPEAKER>
<L>You lie, I gaue it you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then tis mine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Myce.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, I meane, I let you keep it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wel, I meane you shall haue it againe.</L>
<L>Here take it for a while, I lend it thee,</L>
<L>Till I may see thee hem'd with armed men.</L>
<L>Then shalt thou see me pull it from thy head:</L>
<L>Thou art no match for mightie <HI>Tamburlaine.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Myce.</SPEAKER>
<L>O Gods, is this <HI>tamburlaine</HI> the thiefe,</L>
<L>I marueile much he stole it not away.</L>
<STAGE>Sound trumpets to the battell, and he runs in.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="scene" N="[5]">
<STAGE>Cosroe, Tamburlaine, Theridamas, Menaphon, Meander, Ortygius, Techelles. Vsumeasane, with others.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Holde thee <HI>Cosroe,</HI> weare two imperiall Crownes.</L>
<PB REF="15"/><FW><MILESTONE N="B7r"/></FW>
<L>Thinks thee Inuested now as royally,</L>
<L>Euen by the mighty hand of tamburlaine,</L>
<L>As if as many kinges as could encompasse thee,</L>
<L>With greatest pompe had crown'd thee Emperour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cosr.</SPEAKER>
<L>So do I thrice renowined man at armes,</L>
<L>And none shall keepe the crowne but <HI>tamburlaine:</HI></L>
<L>Thee doo I make my Regent of Persea,</L>
<L>And Generall Lieftenant of my Armies.</L>
<L><HI>Meander,</HI> you that were our brothers Guide,</L>
<L>And chiefest Counsailor in all his acts,</L>
<L>Since he is yeelded to the stroke of War,</L>
<L>On your submission we with thanks excuse,</L>
<L>And giue you equall place in our affaires.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mean.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most happy Emperour in humblest tearms</L>
<L>I vow my seruice to your Maiestie.</L>
<L>With vtmost vertue of my faith and dutie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cosr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thanks good <HI>Meander,</HI> then <HI>Cosroe</HI> raign</L>
<L>And gouerne Persea in her former pomp:</L>
<L>Now send Ambassage to thy neighbor Kings,</L>
<L>And let them know the Persean King is chang'd:</L>
<L>From one that knew not what a King should do,</L>
<L>To one that can commaund what longs thereto:</L>
<L>And now we will to faire <HI>Persepolis,</HI></L>
<L>With twenty thousand expert souldiers.</L>
<L>The Lords and Captaines of my brothers campe,</L>
<L>With litle slaughter take <HI>Meanders</HI> course,</L>
<L>And gladly yeeld them to my gracious rule:</L>
<L><HI>Ortigius</HI> and <HI>menaphon,</HI> my trustie friendes,</L>
<L>Now will I gratify your former good,</L>
<L>And grace your calling with a greater sway.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ort.</SPEAKER>
<L>And as we euer and at your behoofe,</L>
<L>And sought your state, all honor it deseru'd,</L>
<PB REF="16"/><FW><MILESTONE N="B7v"/></FW><!-- this page keyed by pfs -->
<L>So will we with our powers and our liues,</L>
<L>Indeuor to preserue and prosper it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cos.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will not thank thee (sweet <HI>Ortigius</HI>)</L>
<L>Better replies shall prooue my purposes.</L>
<L>And now, Lord <HI>tamburlaine,</HI> my brothers Campe</L>
<L>I leaue to thee, and to <HI>theridamas,</HI></L>
<L>To follow me to faire <HI>Persepolis.</HI></L>
<L>Then will we march to all those Indian Mines,</L>
<L>My witlesse brother to the Christians lost:</L>
<L>And ransome them with fame and vsurie.</L>
<L>And till thou ouertake me <HI>tamburlaine,</HI></L>
<L>(Staying to order all the scattered troopes)</L>
<L>Farewell Lord Regent, and his happie friends,</L>
<L>I long to sit vpon my brothers throne,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mena.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Maiestie shall shortly haue your wish.</L>
<L>And ride in triumph through <HI>Persepolis.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Manent Tamb. Tech. Ther. Vsum.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>And ride in triumph through <HI>Persepolis</HI>?</L>
<L>Is it not braue to be a King, <HI>techelles</HI>?</L>
<L><HI>Vsumeasane</HI> and <HI>theridamas,</HI></L>
<L>Is it not passing braue to be a King,</L>
<L>And ride in triumph through <HI>Persepolis</HI>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tech.</SPEAKER>
<L>O my Lord, tis sweet and full of pompe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vsum.</SPEAKER>
<L>To be a King, is halfe to be a God.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ther.</SPEAKER>
<L>A God is not so glorious as a King:</L>
<L>I thinke the pleasure they enioy in heauen</L>
<L>Can not compare with kingly ioyes in earth,</L>
<L>To weare a Crowne enchac'd with pearle and golde,</L>
<L>Whose vertues carie with it life and death,</L>
<L>To aske, and haue: command, and be obeied.</L>
<L>When looks breed loue, with lookes to gaine the prize;</L>
<L>Such power attractiue shines in princes eies.</L>
</SP>
<PB REF="16"/><FW><MILESTONE N="B8r"/></FW><!-- this page keyed by pfs -->
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why say <HI>theridamas,</HI> wilt thou be a king?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>the.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, though I praise it, I can liue without it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>What saies my other friends, wil you be kings?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tec.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, if I could with all my heart my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, that's wel said <HI>techelles,</HI> so would I,</L>
<L>And so would you my maisters, would you not?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vsum.</SPEAKER>
<L>What then my Lord?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why then <HI>Casanes</HI> shall we wish for ought</L>
<L>The world affoords in greatest noueltie,</L>
<L>And rest attmplesse faint and destitute?</L>
<L>Me thinks we should not, I am strongly moou'd,</L>
<L>That if I should desire the Persean Crowne,</L>
<L>I could attaine it with a woondrous ease,</L>
<L>And would not all our souldiers soone consent,</L>
<L>If we should aime at such a dignitie?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ther.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know they would with our perswasions.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why then <HI>theridamas,</HI> Ile first assay,</L>
<L>To get the Persean Kingdome to my selfe:</L>
<L>Then thou for <HI>Parthia,</HI> they for <HI>Scythia</HI> and <HI>Medea.</HI></L>
<L>And if I prosper, all shall be as sure,</L>
<L>As if the Turke, the Pope, <HI>Affrike</HI> and <HI>Greece,</HI></L>
<L>Came creeping to vs with their crownes apace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tech.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then shall we send to this triumphing King,</L>
<L>And bid him battell for his nouell Crowne?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vsum.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay quickly then, before his roome be hot.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Twil prooue a pretie iest (in faith) my friends.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>the.</SPEAKER>
<L>A iest to chardge on twenty thousand men?</L>
<L>I iudge the purchase more important far.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Iudge by thy selfe <HI>theridamas,</HI> not me,</L>
<L>For presently <HI>techelles</HI> here shal haste,</L>
<L>To bid him battaile ere he passe too farre,</L>
<L>And lose more labor than the gaine will quight.</L>
<PB REF="17"/><FW><MILESTONE N="B8v"/></FW><!-- this page keyed by pfs -->
<L>Then shalt thou see the Scythian <HI>tamburlaine,</HI></L>
<L>Make but a iest to win the Persean crowne.</L>
<L><HI>techelles,</HI> take a thousand horse with thee,</L>
<L>And bid him turne his back to war with vs,</L>
<L>That onely made him King to make vs sport.</L>
<L>We will not steale vpon him cowardly,</L>
<L>But giue him warning and more warriours.</L>
<L>Haste the <HI>techelles,</HI> we will follow thee.</L>
<L>What saith <HI>theridamas</HI>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ther.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe on for me.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="scene" N="6">
<HEAD>Actus. 2. Scaena. 6.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Cosroe, Meander, Ortygius, Menaphon, with other Souldiers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cos.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhat means this diuelish shepheard to aspire</L>
<L>With such a Giantly presumption.</L>
<L>To cast vp hils against the face of heauen:</L>
<L>And dare the force of angrie <HI>Iupiter.</HI></L>
<L>But as he thrust them vnderneath the hils,</L>
<L>And prest out fire from their burning iawes:</L>
<L>So will I send this monstrous slaue to hell,</L>
<L>Where flames shall euer feed vpon his soule.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>mean.</SPEAKER>
<L>Some powers diuine, or els infernall, mixt</L>
<L>Their angry seeds at his conception:</L>
<L>For he was neuer sprong of humaine race,</L>
<L>Since with the spirit of his fearefull pride,</L>
<L>He dares so doubtlesly resolue of rule.</L>
<L>And by profession be ambitous.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ort.</SPEAKER>
<L>What God or Feend, or spirit of the earth,</L>
<L>Or Monster turned to a manly shape,</L>
<PB REF="17"/><FW><MILESTONE N="C1r"/></FW><!-- this page keyed by pfs -->
<L>Or of what mould or mettel he be made,</L>
<L>What star or state soeuer gouerne him,</L>
<L>Let vs put on our meet incountring mindes,</L>
<L>And in detesting such a diuelish Thiefe,</L>
<L>In loue of honor &amp; defence of right,</L>
<L>Be arm'd against the hate of such a foe,</L>
<L>Whether from earth, or hell, or heauen he grow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nobly resolu'd, my good <HI>Ortygius.</HI></L>
<L>And since we all haue suckt one wholsome aire,</L>
<L>And with the same proportion of Elements,</L>
<L>Resolue, I hope we are resembled,</L>
<L>Vowing our loues to equall death and life,</L>
<L>Let's cheere our souldiers to incounter him,</L>
<L>That grieuous image of ingratitude:</L>
<L>That fiery thirster after Soueraingtie:</L>
<L>And burne him in the fury of that flame,</L>
<L>That none can quence but blood and Emperie.</L>
<L>Resolue my Lords and louing souldiers now,</L>
<L>To saue your King and country from decay:</L>
<L>Then strike vp Drum, and all the Starres that make</L>
<L>The loathsome Circle of my dated life,</L>
<L>Direct my weapon to his barbarous heart,</L>
<L>That thus opposeth him against the Gods,</L>
<L>And scornes the Powers that gouerne <HI>Persea.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter to the Battell, &amp; after the battell, enter Cosroe
wounded, Theridamas, tamburlaine, Techelles, Vsumeasane, with others.</STAGE>

<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Barbarous and bloody <HI>Tamburlaine,</HI></L>
<L>Thus to depriue me of my crowne and life.</L>
<L>Treacherous and false <HI>theridamas,</HI></L>
<PB REF="18"/><FW><MILESTONE N="C1v"/></FW><!-- this page keyed by pfs -->
<L>Euen at the morning of my happy state,</L>
<L>Scarce being seated in my royall throne,</L>
<L>To worke my downfall and vntimely end.</L>
<L>An vncouth paine torments my grieued soule,</L>
<L>And death arrests the organe of my voice.</L>
<L>Who entring at the breach thy sword hath made,</L>
<L>Sacks euery vaine and artier of my heart,</L>
<L>Bloody and insatiate <HI>Tamburlain.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>The thirst of raigne and sweetnes of a crown,</L>
<L>That causde the eldest sonne of heauenly <HI>Ops,</HI></L>
<L>To thrust his doting father from his chaire,</L>
<L>And place himselfe in the Emperiall heauen,</L>
<L>Moou'd me to manage armes against they state,</L>
<L>What better president than mightie <HI>Ioue</HI>?</L>
<L>Nature that fram'd vs of foure Elements,</L>
<L>Warring within our breasts for regiment,</L>
<L>Doth teach vs all to haue aspyring minds:</L>
<L>Our soules, whose faculties can comprehend</L>
<L>The wondrous Architecture of the world:</L>
<L>And measure euery wandring plannets course.</L>
<L>Still climing after knowledge infinite,</L>
<L>And alwaies moouing as the restles Spheares.</L>
<L>Wils vs to weare our selues and neuer rest.</L>
<L>Vntil we reach the ripest fruit of all.</L>
<L>That perfect blisse and sole felicitie.</L>
<L>The sweet fruition of an earthly crowne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ther.</SPEAKER>
<L>And that made me to ioine with <HI>tamburlain</HI></L>
<L>For he is grosse and like the massie earth,</L>
<L>That mooues not vpwards, nor by princely deeds</L>
<L>Doth meane to soare aboue the highest sort.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tec.</SPEAKER>
<L>And that made vs the friends of <HI>Tamburlaine.</HI></L>
<L>To lift our swords against the Persean King.</L>
</SP>
<PB REF="18"/><FW><MILESTONE N="C2r"/></FW><!-- this page keyed by pfs -->
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vsum.</SPEAKER>
<L>For as when <HI>Ioue</HI> did thrust old <HI>Saturn</HI> down.</L>
<L><HI>Neptune</HI> and <HI>Dis</HI> gain'd each of them a Crowne.</L>
<L>So do we hope to raign in <HI>Asia,</HI></L>
<L>If <HI>tamburlain</HI> be plac'd in Persea.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cos.</SPEAKER>
<L>The strangest men that euer nature made,</L>
<L>I know not how to take their tyrannies.</L>
<L>My bloodlesse body waxeth chill and colde,</L>
<L>And with my blood my life slides through my wound.</L>
<L>My soule begins to take her flight to hell.</L>
<L>And sommons all my sences to depart:</L>
<L>The heat and moisture which did feed each other,</L>
<L>For want of nourishment to feed them both.</L>
<L>Is drie and cold, and now dooth gastly death</L>
<L>With greedy tallents gripe my bleeding hart,</L>
<L>And like a Harpyr tires on my life.</L>
<L><HI>Theridamas</HI> and <HI>Tamburlaine,</HI> I die,</L>
<L>And fearefull vengeance light vpon you both.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>He takes the Crowne and puts it on.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not all the curses which the furies breathe,</L>
<L>Shall make me leaue so rich a prize as this:</L>
<L><HI>Teridamas, techelles,</HI> and the rest,</L>
<L>Who thinke you now is king of <HI>Persea</HI>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Tamburlaine, tamburlaine.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Though <HI>Mars</HI> himselfe the angrie God of armes,</L>
<L>And all the earthly Potentates conspire,</L>
<L>To dispossesse me of this Diadem:</L>
<L>Yet will I weare it in despight of them,</L>
<L>As great commander of the Easterne world,</L>
<L>If you but say that <HI>tamburlaine</HI> shall raigne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Long liue <HI>tamburlaine,</HI> and raigne in <HI>Asia.</HI></L>
</SP>
<PB REF="19"/><FW><MILESTONE N="C2v"/></FW>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>So, now it is more surer on my head,</L>
<L>Than if the Gods had held a Parliament:</L>
<L>And all pronounst me king of Persea.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<TRAILER>Finis Actus 2.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus. 3.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scaena. 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Baiazeth, the kings of Fess. Moroco, and Argier. with others, in great pompe.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Baiazeth.</SPEAKER>
<L>GReat Kings of <HI>Barbary,</HI> and my portly Bassoes,</L>
<L>We heare, the Tartars &amp; the Easterne theeues</L>
<L>Vnder the conduct of one <HI>Tamburlaine,</HI></L>
<L>Presume a bickering with your Emperour:</L>
<L>And thinks to rouse vs from our dreadful siege</L>
<L>Of the famous Grecian <HI>Constantinople.</HI></L>
<L>You know our Armie is inuincible:</L>
<L>As many circumcised Turkes we haue,</L>
<L>And warlike bands of Christians renied,</L>
<L>As hath the Ocean or the Terrene sea</L>
<L>Small drops of water, when the Maon begins</L>
<L>To ioine in one her semi-circled hornes:</L>
<L>Yet would we not be brau'd with forrain power,</L>
<L>Nor raise our siege before the Gretians yeeld.</L>
<L>Or breathles lie before the citie walles.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fess.</SPEAKER>
<L>Renowmed Emperour, and mighty Generall</L>
<L>What if you sent the Bassoes of your guard.</L>
<L>To charge him to remaine in <HI>Asia.</HI></L>
<L>Or els to threaten death and deadly armes,</L>
<L>As from the mouth of mighty <HI>Baiazeth.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bai.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hie thee my Bassoe fast to <HI>Persea,</HI></L>
<L>Tell him thy Lord the Turkish Emperour,</L>
<L>Dread Lord of <HI>Affrike, Europe</HI> and <HI>Asia.</HI></L>
<PB REF="19"/><FW><MILESTONE N="C3r"/></FW>
<L>Great King and conquerour of Grecia,</L>
<L>The Ocean, Terrene, and the cole-blacke sea,</L>
<L>The high and higest Monarke of the world.</L>
<L>Wils and Commands (for say not I intreat)</L>
<L>Not once to set his foot in <HI>Affrica,</HI></L>
<L>Or spread his collours in Grecia.</L>
<L>Least he incurre the furie of my wrath.</L>
<L>Tell him, I am content to take a truce,</L>
<L>Because I heare he beares a valiant mind.</L>
<L>But if presuming on his silly power,</L>
<L>He be so mad to manage Armes with me,</L>
<L>Then stay thou with him, say I bid thee so.</L>
<L>And if before the Sun haue measured heauen</L>
<L>With triple circuit thou regreet vs not,</L>
<L>We meane to take his mornings next arise.</L>
<L>For messenger, he will not be reclaim'd,</L>
<L>And meane to fetch thee in despight of him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most great and puisant Monarke of the earth,</L>
<L>Your Bassoe will accomplish your behest:</L>
<L>And show your pleasure to the Persean.</L>
<L>As fits the Legate of the stately Turk.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Bass.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arg.</SPEAKER>
<L>They say he is the King of <HI>Persea.</HI></L>
<L>But if he dare attempt to stir your siege,</L>
<L>Twere requisite he should be ten times more,</L>
<L>For all flesh quakes at your magnificence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bai.</SPEAKER>
<L>True <HI>(Argier)</HI> and tremble at my lookes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Moro.</SPEAKER>
<L>The spring is hindred by your smoothering host,</L>
<L>For neither rain can fall vpon the earth,</L>
<L>Nor Sun reflere his vertuous beames thereon.</L>
<L>The ground is mantled with such multitudes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bai.</SPEAKER>
<L>All this is true as holy <HI>Mahomet,</HI></L>
<L>And all the trees are blasted with our breathes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="20"/><FW><MILESTONE N="C3v"/></FW>
<SPEAKER>Fess.</SPEAKER>
<L>What thinks your greatnes best to be atchieu'd</L>
<L>In pursuit of the Cities ouerthrow?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bai.</SPEAKER>
<L>I wil the captiue Pioners of <HI>Argier,</HI></L>
<L>Cut of the water, that by leaden pipes</L>
<L>Runs to the citie from the mountain <HI>Carnon,</HI></L>
<L>Two thousand horse shall forrage vp and downe,</L>
<L>That no reliefe or succour come by Land.</L>
<L>And all the sea my Gallies countermaund.</L>
<L>Then shall our footmen lie within the trench,</L>
<L>And with their Cannons mouth'd like <HI>Orcus gulfe</HI></L>
<L>Batter the walles, and we will enter in:</L>
<L>And thus the Grccians shall be conquered.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Actus. 3. Scaena. 2.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Agidas, Zenocrate, Anippe, with others.</STAGE>
<L>MAdam <HI>Zenocrate,</HI> may I presume</L>
<L>To know the cause of these vnquiet fits:</L>
<L>That worke such trouble to your woonted rest:</L>
<L>Tis more then pitty such a heauenly face</L>
<L>Should by hearts sorrow wax so wan and pale.</L>
<L>When your offensiue rape by <HI>tamburlaine,</HI></L>
<L>(Which of your whole displeasures should be most)</L>
<L>Hath seem'd to be digested long agoe.</L>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Zen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Although it be digested long agoe</L>
<L>As his exceding fauours haue deseru'd,</L>
<L>And might content the Queene of heauen as well:</L>
<L>As it hath chang'd my first conceiu'd disdaine.</L>
<L>Yet since a farther passion feeds my thoughts,</L>
<L>With ceasclesse and discorsolate conceits.</L>
<PB REF="20"/><FW><MILESTONE N="C4r"/></FW>
<L>Which dies my lookes so liuelesse as they are.</L>
<L>And might, if my extreams had fuil euents,</L>
<L>Make me the gastly counterfeit of death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Eternall heauen sooner be dissolu'd.</L>
<L>And all that pierceth <HI>Phoebes</HI> siluer eie,</L>
<L>Before such hap fall to <HI>zenocrate.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>zen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ah, life, and soule still houer in his Breast.</L>
<L>And leaue my body sencelesse as the earth.</L>
<L>Or els vnite you to his life and soule,</L>
<L>That I may liue and die with <HI>tamburlain.</HI></L>
<STAGE>Enter Tamburlaine with Techelles and others.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agid.</SPEAKER>
<L>With <HI>tamburlaine?</HI> Ah faire <HI>zenocrate.</HI></L>
<L>Let not a man so vile and barbarous,</L>
<L>That holds you from your father in despight,</L>
<L>And keeps you from the honors of a Queene.</L>
<L>Being supposde his worthlesse Concubine.</L>
<L>Be honored with your loue, but for necessity.</L>
<L>So now the mighty Souldan heares of you,</L>
<L>Your Highnesse needs not doubt but in short time,</L>
<L>He will with <HI>Tamburlaines</HI> destruction</L>
<L>Redeeme you from this deadly seruitude.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Zen.</SPEAKER>
<L>leaue to wound me with these words.</L>
<L>And speake of <HI>tamburlaine</HI> as he deserues:</L>
<L>The entertainment we haue had of him,</L>
<L>Is far from villanie or seruitude.</L>
<L>And might in noble minds be counted princely.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agid.</SPEAKER>
<L>How can you fancie one that lookes so fierce,</L>
<L>Onelie disposed to martiall Stratagems?</L>
<L>Who when he shall embrace you in his armes,</L>
<L>Will tell how many thousand men he slew.</L>
<PB REF="21"/><FW><MILESTONE N="C4v"/></FW>
<L>And when you looke for amorous discourse,</L>
<L>Will rattle foorth his facts of war and blood.</L>
<L>Too harsh a subiect for your dainty eares.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Zen.</SPEAKER>
<L>As looks the sun through <HI>Nilus</HI> flowing stream,</L>
<L>Or when the morning holds him in her armes.</L>
<L>So lookes my Lordly loue, faire <HI>tamburlaine:</HI></L>
<L>His talke much sweeter than the Muses song,</L>
<L>They sung for honor gainst <HI>Pierides.</HI></L>
<L>Or when <HI>Minerua</HI> did with <HI>Neptune</HI> striue,</L>
<L>And higher would I reare my estimate,</L>
<L>Than <HI>Iuno</HI> sister to the highest God.</L>
<L>If I were matcht with mightie <HI>tamburlaine,</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet be not so inconstant in your loue,</L>
<L>But let the yong Arabian liue in hope,</L>
<L>After your rescue to eioy his choise.</L>
<L>You see though first the King of <HI>Persea</HI></L>
<L>(Being a Shepheard) seem'd to loue you much,</L>
<L>Now in his maiesty he leaues those lookes,</L>
<L>Those words of fauour, and those comfortings,</L>
<L>And giues no more than common courtesies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Zen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thence rise the tears that so distain my checks,</L>
<L>Fearing his loue through my vnworthynesse.</L>
<STAGE>Tamburlaine goes to her, &amp; takes her away louing∣ly by the hand, looking wrathfully on Agidas, and sayes nothing.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Betraide by fortune and suspitious loue.</L>
<L>Threatned with frowning wrath and iealousie.</L>
<L>Surpriz d with feare of hideous reuenge.</L>
<L>I stand agast: but most astonied</L>
<L>To see his choller shut in secrete thoughtes,</L>
<L>And wrapt in silence of his angry soule.</L>
<PB REF="21"/><FW><MILESTONE N="C5r"/></FW>
<L>Vpon his browes was pourtraid vgly death,</L>
<L>And in his eies the furie of his hart.</L>
<L>That shine as Comets, menacing reuenge,</L>
<L>And casts a pale complexion on his cheeks.</L>
<L>As when the Sea-man sees the <HI>Hyades</HI></L>
<L>Gather an armye of Cemerian clouds,</L>
<L>(<HI>Auster</HI> and <HI>Aquilon</HI> with winged Steads</L>
<L>All sweating, tilt about the watery heauens,</L>
<L>With shiuering speares enforcing thunderclaps.</L>
<L>And from their shieldes strike flames of lightening)</L>
<L>All fearefull foldes his sailes, and sounds the maine,</L>
<L>Lifting his prayers to the heauens for aid,</L>
<L>Against the terrour of the winds and waues.</L>
<L>So fares <HI>Agydas</HI> for the late felt frownes</L>
<L>That sent a tempest to my daunted thoughtes,</L>
<L>And makes my soule deuine her ouerthrow.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Techelles with a naked dagger.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tech.</SPEAKER>
<L>See you <HI>Agidas</HI> how the King salutes you.</L>
<L>He bids you prophesie what it imports.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agid.</SPEAKER>
<L>I prophecied before and now I prooue,</L>
<L>The killing frownes of iealousie and loue.</L>
<L>He needed not with words confirme my feare,</L>
<L>For words are vaine where working tooles present</L>
<L>The naked action of my threatned end.</L>
<L>It saies, <HI>Agydas,</HI> thou shalt surely die.</L>
<L>And of extremities elect the least,</L>
<L>More honor and lesse paine it may procure,</L>
<L>Tody by this resolued hand of thine,</L>
<L>Than stay the torments he and heauen haue sworne.</L>
<L>Then haste <HI>Agydas,</HI> and preuent the plagues:</L>
<L>Which thy prolonged Fates may draw on thee:</L>
<L>Go wander free from feare of Tyrants rage.</L>
<PB REF="22"/><FW><MILESTONE N="C5v"/></FW>
<L>Remooued from the Torments and the hell:</L>
<L>Wherewith he may excruciate thy soule.</L>
<L>And let <HI>Agidas</HI> by <HI>Agidas</HI> die.</L>
<L>And with this stab slumber eternally.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tech.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Vsumeasane,</HI> see how right the man</L>
<L>Hath hit the meaning of my Lord the King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vsum.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith, and <HI>techelles,</HI> it was manly done;</L>
<L>And since he was so wise and honorable,</L>
<L>Let vs affoord him now the bearing hence.</L>
<L>And craue his triple worthy buriall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tech.</SPEAKER>
<L>Agreed <HI>Casane,</HI> we wil honor him.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Act. 3. Scaena. 3,</HEAD>
<STAGE>Tamburlain, Techelles, Vsumeasane, Theridamas, Bassoe, Zenocrate, with others.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tamburlaine.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>BAssoe,</HI> by this thy Lord and maister knowes,</L>
<L>I meane to meet him in <HI>Bithynia:</HI></L>
<L>see how he comes? Tush. Turkes are ful of brags</L>
<L>And menace more than they can wel performe:</L>
<L>He meet me in the field and fetch thee hence?</L>
<L>Alas (poore Turke) his fortune is to weake,</L>
<L>T'incounter with the strength of <HI>Tamburlaine.</HI></L>
<L>View well my Camp, and speake indifferently,</L>
<L>Doo not my captaines and my souldiers looke</L>
<L>As if they meant to conquer <HI>Affrica.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Basl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your men are valiant but their number few,</L>
<L>And cannot terrefie his mightie hoste,</L>
<L>My Lord, the great Commander of the worlde,</L>
<L>Besides fifteene contributorie kings,</L>
<L>Hath now in armes ten thousand Ianisaries,</L>
<L>Mounted on lusty Mauritanian Steeds.</L>
<PB REF="22"/><FW><MILESTONE N="C6r"/></FW>
<L>Brought to the war by men of <HI>Tripoly.</HI></L>
<L>Two hundred thousand footmen that haue seru'd</L>
<L>In two set battels fought in Grecia:</L>
<L>And for the expedition of this war,</L>
<L>If he think good, can from his garrisons,</L>
<L>Withdraw as many more to follow him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tech.</SPEAKER>
<L>The more he brings, the greater is the spoile,</L>
<L>For when they perish by our warlike hands,</L>
<L>We meane to seate our footmen on their Steeds.</L>
<L>And rifle all those stately Ianisars.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>But wil those Kings accompany your Lord?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<L>Such as his Highnesse please, but some must stay</L>
<L>To rule the prouinces he late subdude.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thē fight couragiously, their crowns are yours</L>
<L>This hand shal set them on your conquering heads:</L>
<L>That made me Emperour of <HI>Asia.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vsum.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let him bring missions infinite of men,</L>
<L>Vnpeopling Westerne <HI>Affrica</HI> and <HI>Greece:</HI></L>
<L>Yet we assure vs of the victorie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ther.</SPEAKER>
<L>Euen he that in a trice vanquisht two kings,</L>
<L>More mighty than the Turkish Emperour:</L>
<L>Shall rouse him out of Europe, and pursue</L>
<L>His scattered armie til they yeeld or die.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wel said <HI>theridamas,</HI> speake in that mood,</L>
<L>For Wil and Shall best fitteth <HI>Tamburlain,</HI></L>
<L>Whose smiling stars giues him assured hope</L>
<L>Of martiall triumph, ere he meete his foes:</L>
<L>I that am tearm'd the Scourge and Wrath of God,</L>
<L>The onely feare and terrour of the world,</L>
<L>Wil first subdue the Turke, and then inlarge</L>
<L>Those Christian Captiues, which you keep as slaues,</L>
<L>Burdening their bodies with your heauie chames.</L>
<PB REF="23"/><FW><MILESTONE N="C6v"/></FW>
<L>And feeding them with thin and slender fare,</L>
<L>That naked rowe about the Terrene sea.</L>
<L>And when they chance to breath and rest a space,</L>
<L>Are punisht with Bastones so grieuously,</L>
<L>That they lie panting on the Gallies side.</L>
<L>And striue for life at euery stroke they giue,</L>
<L>These are the cruell pirates of <HI>Argeire,</HI></L>
<L>That damned traine, the scum of <HI>Affrica.</HI></L>
<L>Inhabited with stragling Runnagates,</L>
<L>That make quick hauock of the Christian blood.</L>
<L>But as I liue that towne shall curse the time</L>
<L>That <HI>Tamburlaine</HI> set foot in Affrica:</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Baiazeth with his Bassoes and contri∣butorie Kinges.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bai.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bassoes and Ianisaries of my Guard,</L>
<L>Attend vpon the person of your Lord,</L>
<L>The greatest Potentate of <HI>Affrica.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Techelles,</HI> and the rest prepare your swordes</L>
<L>I meane t'incounter with that <HI>Baiazeth.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bai.</SPEAKER>
<L>Kings of <HI>Fesse, Moroccus</HI> and <HI>Argier,</HI></L>
<L>He cals me <HI>Baiazeth,</HI> whom you call Lord.</L>
<L>Note the presemption of this Scythian slaue:</L>
<L>I tell thee villaine, those that lead my horse</L>
<L>Haue to their names tytles of dignity,</L>
<L>And dar'st thou bluntly call me <HI>Baiazeth?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>And know thou Turke, that those which lead my horse,</L>
<L>Shall lead thee Captiue thorow Affrica.</L>
<L>And dar'st thou bluntly call me <HI>tamburlaine?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bai.</SPEAKER>
<L>By <HI>Mahomet,</HI> my Kinsmans sepulcher.</L>
<PB REF="23"/><FW><MILESTONE N="C7r"/></FW>
<L>And by the holy <HI>Alcaron</HI> I sweare,</L>
<L>He shall be made a chast and lustlesse Eunuk<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" RESP="murp" DISP="•"/>,</L>
<L>And in my Sarell tend my Concubines:</L>
<L>And all his Captaincs that thus stoutly stand,</L>
<L>Shall draw the chariot of my Emperesse.</L>
<L>Whom I haue brought to see their ouerthrow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>By this my sword that conquer'd <HI>Persea,</HI></L>
<L>Thy fall shall make me famous through the world:</L>
<L>I will not tell thee how Ile handle thee,</L>
<L>But euery common souldier of my Camp</L>
<L>Shall smile to see thy miserable state.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fess.</SPEAKER>
<L>What meanes the mighty Turkish Emperor</L>
<L>To talk with one so base as <HI>tamburlaine.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Moro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ye Moores and valiant men of <HI>Barbary.</HI></L>
<L>How can ye suffer these indignities.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Leaue words and let them feele your lances pointes.</L>
<L>Which glided through the bowels of the Greekes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bai.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wel said my stout contributory kings,</L>
<L>Your threefold armie and my hugie hoste,</L>
<L>Shall swallow vp these base borne Perseans,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tech.</SPEAKER>
<L>Puissant, renowmed and mighty <HI>tamburlain,</HI></L>
<L>Why stay we thus prolonging all their liues'?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ther.</SPEAKER>
<L>I long to see those crownes won by our swords</L>
<L>That we may raigne as kings of Affrica.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vsum.</SPEAKER>
<L>What Coward wold not fight for such a prize?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fight all couragiously and be you kings.</L>
<L>I speake it, and my words are oracles.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bai.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Zabina,</HI> mother of three brauer boies,</L>
<L>Than <HI>Hercules,</HI> that in his infancie</L>
<L>Did pash the iawes of Serpents venomous:</L>
<L>Whose hands are made to gripe a warlike Lance.</L>
<PB REF="24"/><FW><MILESTONE N="C7v"/></FW>
<L>Their shoulders broad, for complet armour fit,</L>
<L>Their lims more large and of a bigger size</L>
<L>Than all the brats ysprong from <HI>Typhons</HI> loins:</L>
<L>Who, when they come vnto their fathers age,</L>
<L>Will batter Turrets with their manly sists.</L>
<L>And on thy head weare my Emperiall crowne,</L>
<L>Vntill I bring this sturdy <HI>tamburlain,</HI></L>
<L>And all his Captains bound in captiue chaines.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>zab.</SPEAKER>
<L>Such good successe happen to <HI>Baiazeth,</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>zenocrate,</HI> the loueliest Maide aliue,</L>
<L>Fairer than rockes of pearle and pretious stone,</L>
<L>The onely Paragon of <HI>tamburlaine,</HI></L>
<L>Whose eies are brighter than the Lamps of heauen.</L>
<L>And speech more pleasant than sweet harmony:</L>
<L>That with thy lookes canst cleare the darkened Sky:</L>
<L>And calme the rage of thundring <HI>Iupiter:</HI></L>
<L>Sit downe by her: adorned with my Crowne,</L>
<L>As if thou wert the Empresse of the world.</L>
<L>Stir not <HI>zenocrate</HI> vntill thou see</L>
<L>Me martch victoriously with all my men,</L>
<L>Triumphing cuer him and these his kings.</L>
<L>Which I will bring as Vassals to thy feete.</L>
<L>Til then take thou my crowne, vaunt of my worth,</L>
<L>And manage words with her as we will armes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>zen.</SPEAKER>
<L>And may my Loue, the king of <HI>Persea</HI></L>
<L>Returne with victorie, and free from wound.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bai.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now shalt thou feel the force of Turkish arms,</L>
<L>Which lately made all Europe quake for searc:</L>
<L>I haue of Turkes, Arabians, Moores and Iewes</L>
<L>Enough to couer all <HI>Bythinia,</HI></L>
<L>Let thousands die, their slaughtered Carkasses</L>
<PB REF="24"/><FW><MILESTONE N="C8r"/></FW>
<L>Shal serue for walles and bulwarkes to the rest:</L>
<L>And as the heads of <HI>Hydra,</HI> so my power</L>
<L>Subdued, shall stand as mighty as before:</L>
<L>If they should yeeld their necks vnto the sword,</L>
<L>Thy souldiers armes could not endure to strike</L>
<L>So many blowes as I haue heads for thee.</L>
<L>Thou knowest not (foolish hardy <HI>Tamburlaine)</HI></L>
<L>What tis to meet me in the open field,</L>
<L>That leaue no ground for thee to martch vpon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our conquering swords shall marshal vs the way</L>
<L>We vse to march vpon the slaughtered foe:</L>
<L>Trampling their bowels with our horses hooffes:</L>
<L>Braue horses, bred on the white Tartarian hils:</L>
<L>My Campe is like to <HI>Iulius Caesars</HI> hoste,</L>
<L>That neuer fought but had the victorie:</L>
<L>Nor in <HI>Pharsalia</HI> was there such hot war,</L>
<L>As these my followers willingly would haue:</L>
<L>Legions of Spirits fleeting in the aire,</L>
<L>Direct our Bullets and our weapons pointes</L>
<L>And make our strokes to wound the sencelesse lure,</L>
<L>And when she sees our bloody Collours spread.</L>
<L>Then Victorie begins to take her flight,</L>
<L>Resting her selfe vpon my milk-white Tent:</L>
<L>But come my Lords, to weapons let vs fall.</L>
<L>The field is ours, the Turk, his wife and all.</L>
<STAGE>Exit, with his followers.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bai.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come Kings and Bassoes let vs glut our swords</L>
<L>That thirst to drinke the feble Perseans blood.</L>
<STAGE>Exit, with his followers.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>zab.</SPEAKER>
<L>Base Concubine, must thou be plac'd by me</L>
<L>That am the Empresse of the mighty Turke?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>zen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Disdainful Turkesse and vnreuerend Bosse,</L>
<PB REF="25"/><FW><MILESTONE N="C8v"/></FW>
<L>Call'st thou me Concubine that am betroath'd</L>
<L>Vnto the great and mighty <HI>tamburlaine</HI>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Zab.</SPEAKER>
<L>To <HI>tamburlaine</HI> the great Tartarian thiefe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Zen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou wilt repent these lauish words of thine,</L>
<L>When thy great Bassoe, maister and thy selfe.</L>
<L>Must plead for mercie at his kingly feet,</L>
<L>And sue to me to be your Aduocates.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Zab.</SPEAKER>
<L>And sue to thee? I tell thee shamelesse girle,</L>
<L>Thou shalt be Landresse to my waiting maid.</L>
<L>How lik'st thou her <HI>Ebea,</HI> will she serue?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ebea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madame, she thinks perhaps she is too fine.</L>
<L>But I shall turne her into other weedes.</L>
<L>And make her daintie fingers fall to woorke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Zen.</SPEAKER>
<L>hearst thou <HI>Anippe,</HI> how thy drudge doth talk,</L>
<L>And how my slaue, her mistresse menaceth.</L>
<L>Both for their sausinesse shall be employed,</L>
<L>To dresse the common souldiers meat and drink.</L>
<L>For we will scorne they should come nere our selues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anip.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet somtimes let your highnesse send for thē</L>
<L>To do the work my chamber maid disdaines.</L>
<STAGE>They sound the battell within, and stay</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Zen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ye Gods and powers that gouerne Persea.</L>
<L>And made my lordly Loue her worthy King:</L>
<L>Now strengthen him against the Turkish <HI>Baiazeth,</HI></L>
<L>And let his foes like flockes of fearfull Roes,</L>
<L>Pursude by hunters, flie his angrie lookes,</L>
<L>That I may see him issue Conquerour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Zab.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now <HI>Mahomet,</HI> solicit God himselfe,</L>
<L>And make him raine down murthering shot frō heauen</L>
<L>To dash the Scythians braines, and strike them dead,</L>
<L>That dare to manage armes with him,</L>
<L>That offered iewels to thy sacred shrine.</L>
<PB REF="25"/><FW><MILESTONE N="D1r"/></FW>
<L>When first he war'd against the Christians.</L>
<STAGE>To the battell againe.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Zen.</SPEAKER>
<L>By this the Turks lie weltring in their blood sound,</L>
<L>And <HI>tamburlaine</HI> is Lord of <HI>Affrica:</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Zab.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art deceiu'd, I heard the Trumpets</L>
<L>As when my Emperour ouerthrew the Greeks:</L>
<L>And led them Captiue into Affrica.</L>
<L>Straight will I vse thee as thy pride deserues:</L>
<L>Prepare thy selfe to liue and die my slaue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Zen.</SPEAKER>
<L>If <HI>Mahomet</HI> should come from heauen and sweare,</L>
<L>My royall Lord is slaine or conquered.</L>
<L>Yet should he not perswade me otherwise.</L>
<L>But that he liues and will be Conquerour.</L>
<STAGE>Baiazeth flies, and he pursues him. The battell short, and they enter, Baiazeth is ouercome.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now king of Bassoes, who is Conqueror?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bai.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou, by the fortune of this damned foile,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Where are your stout contributorie kings?</P>
<STAGE>Enter Techelles, Theridamas, Vsumeasane.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tech.</SPEAKER>
<P>We haue their crownes their bodies strowe the fielde.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Each man a crown? why kingly fought ifaith</L>
<L>Deliuer them into my treasurie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Zen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now let me offer to my gracious Lord.</L>
<L>His royall Crowne againe, so highly won:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay take the Turkish Crown from her, <HI>zen.</HI></L>
<L>And crowne me Emperour of Affrica.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Zab.</SPEAKER>
<L>No <HI>tamburlain,</HI> though now thou gat the best</L>
<L>Thou shalt not yet be Lord of Affrica.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="26"/><FW><MILESTONE N="D1v"/></FW>
<SPEAKER>ther.</SPEAKER>
<L>Giue her the Crowne Turkesse you wer best.</L>
<STAGE>He takes it from her, and giues it Zenocrate,</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>zab.</SPEAKER>
<L>Iniurious villaines, thieues, runnagates,</L>
<L>How dare you thus abuse my Maiesty?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ther.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here Madam, you are Empresse, she is none,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not now <HI>theridamas,</HI> her time is past:</L>
<L>The pillers that haue bolstered vp those tearmes,</L>
<L>Are falne in clusters at my conquering feet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>zab.</SPEAKER>
<L>Though he be prisoner, he may be ransomed:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not all the world shall ransom <HI>Baiazeth.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bai.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ah faire <HI>zabina,</HI> we haue lost the field.</L>
<L>And neuer had the Turkish Emperour</L>
<L>So great a foile by any forraine foe.</L>
<L>Now will the Christian nusc reants be glad,</L>
<L>Ringing with ioy their superstitious belles:</L>
<L>And making bonfires for my ouerthrow.</L>
<L>But ere I die those foule Idolaters</L>
<L>Shall make me bonfires with their filthy bones,</L>
<L>For though the glorie of this day be lost.</L>
<L><HI>Affrik</HI> and <HI>Greece</HI> haue garrisons enough</L>
<L>To make me Soueraigne of the earth againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Those walled garrisons wil I subdue,</L>
<L>And write my selfe great Lord of <HI>Affrica:</HI></L>
<L>So from the East vnto the furthest West,</L>
<L>Shall <HI>tamburlain</HI> extend his puisant arme.</L>
<L>The Galles and those pilling Briggandines,</L>
<L>That yeerely saile to the Venetian gulfe,</L>
<L>And houer in the straightes for Christians wracke,</L>
<L>Shall lie at anchor in the Isle <HI>Asant.</HI></L>
<L>Vntill the Persean Fleete and men of war,</L>
<L>Sailing along the Orientall sea,</L>
<L>Haue fetcht about the Indian continent:</L>
<PB REF="26"/><FW><MILESTONE N="D2r"/></FW>
<L>Euen from <HI>Persepolis</HI> to <HI>Mexico,</HI></L>
<L>And thence vnto the straightes of <HI>Iubalter:</HI></L>
<L>Where they shall meete, and ioine their force in <UNCLEAR>one</UNCLEAR></L>
<L>Keeping in aw the Bay of <HI>Portingale.</HI></L>
<L>And all the Ocean by the British shore:</L>
<L>And by this meanes Ile win the world at last.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bai.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet set a ransome on me tamburlaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>What, thinkst thou tamburlain esteems thy gold,</L>
<L>Ile make the kings of <HI>India</HI> ere I die,</L>
<L>Offer their mines (to sew for peace) to me,</L>
<L>And dig for treasure to appease my wrath:</L>
<L>Come bind them both and one lead in the Turke.</L>
<L>The Turkesse let my Loues maid lead away.</L>
<STAGE>They bind them.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bai.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ah villaines, dare ye touch my sacred armes.</L>
<L>O <HI>Mahomet,</HI> Oh sleepie <HI>Mahomet.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>zab.</SPEAKER>
<L>O cursed <HI>Mahomet</HI> that makest vs thus</L>
<L>The slaues to Scythians rude and barbarous.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come bring them in, &amp; for this happy cōquest</L>
<L>Triumph, and solemnize a martiall feast.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<TRAILER>Finis Actus tertii.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus. 4.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scaena. 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Souldan of Egipt with three or four Lords, Capolin Souldan.</STAGE>
<L>AWake ye men of <HI>Memphis,</HI> heare the clange</L>
<L>Of Scythian trumpets, heare the Basiliskes,</L>
<L>That roaring, shake <HI>Damascus</HI> turrets downe,</L>
<L>The rogue of <HI>Volga</HI> holds <HI>zenocrate,</HI></L>
<L>The Souldans <UNCLEAR>daughter</UNCLEAR> for his Concubine,</L>
<L>And with a troope of theeues and vagabondes.</L>
<PB REF="27"/><FW><MILESTONE N="D2v"/></FW>
<L>Hath spread his collours to our high disgrace:</L>
<L>While you faint-hearted base Egyptians,</L>
<L>Lie slumbering on the flowrie bankes of <HI>Nile,</HI></L>
<L>As Crocodiles that vnaffrighted rest,</L>
<L>While thundring Cannons rattle on their Skins.</L>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mess.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay (mightie Souldan) did your greatnes see</L>
<L>The frowning lookes of fiery <HI>Tamburlaine,</HI></L>
<L>That with his terrour and imperious eies,</L>
<L>Commandes the hearts of his associates,</L>
<L>It might amaze your royall maiesty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Villain. I tell thee, were that tamburlaine,</L>
<L>As monstrous as <HI>Gorgon,</HI> prince of Hell,</L>
<L>The Souldane would not start a foot from him.</L>
<L>But speake, what power hath he?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mess.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mightie Lord,</L>
<L>Three hundred thousand men in armour clad,</L>
<L>Vpon their pransing Steeds, didainfully</L>
<L>With wanton paces trampling on the ground.</L>
<L>Fiue hundred thousand footmen threatning shot,</L>
<L>Shaking their swords, their speares and yron bils,</L>
<L>Enuironing their Standard round, that stood</L>
<L>As bristle-pointed as a thorny wood.</L>
<L>Their warlike Engins and munition</L>
<L>Exceed the forces of their martial men.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay could their nūbers counteruail the stars</L>
<L>Or euer drisling drops of Aprill snowers,</L>
<L>Or withered leaues that Autume shaketh downe.</L>
<L>Yet would the Souldane by his conquering power:</L>
<L>So scatter and consume them in his rage,</L>
<L>That not a man should liue to rue their fall,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>So might your highnesse, had you time to sort</L>
<L>Your fighting men, and raise your royall hoste.</L>
<PB REF="27"/><FW><MILESTONE N="D3r"/></FW>
<L>But tamburlaine, by expedition</L>
<L>Aduantage takes of your vnreadinesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let him take all th'aduantages he can,</L>
<L>Were all the world conspird to sight for him,</L>
<L>Nay, were he Deuill, as he is no man,</L>
<L>Yet in reuenge of faire <HI>Zenocrate,</HI></L>
<L>Whom he detameth in despight of vs,</L>
<L>This arme should send him downe to <HI>Erebus.</HI></L>
<L>To shroud his shame in darknes of the night.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mess.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pleaseth your mightinesse to vnderstand,</L>
<L>His resolution far exceedeth all:</L>
<L>The first day when he pitcheth downe his tentes,</L>
<L>White is their hew, and on his siluer crest</L>
<L>A snowy Feather spangled white he beares,</L>
<L>To signify the mildnesse of his minde.</L>
<L>That satiate with spoile refuseth blood:</L>
<L>But when <HI>Aurora</HI> mounts the second time,</L>
<L>As red as scarlet is his furniture,</L>
<L>Then must his kindled wrath bee quencht with blood.</L>
<L>Not sparing any that can manage armes:</L>
<L>But if these threats mooue not submission.</L>
<L>Black are his collours, blacke Pauilion,</L>
<L>His speare, his shield, his horse, his armour, plumes,</L>
<L>And Ietty Feathers menace death and hell,</L>
<L>Without respect of Sex, degree or age.</L>
<L>He raceth all his foes with fire and sword.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mercilesse villaine, Pesant ignorant,</L>
<L>Of lawfull armes, or martiall discipline:</L>
<L>Pillage and murder are his vsuall trades.</L>
<L>The slaue vsurps the glorious name of war.</L>
<L>See <HI>Capolin</HI> the faire Arabian king,</L>
<L>That hath bene disapointed by this slaue:</L>
<PB REF="28"/><FW><MILESTONE N="D3v"/></FW>
<L>Of my faire daughter, and his princely Loue:</L>
<L>May haue fresh warning to go war with vs,</L>
<L>And be reueng'd for her dispardgement.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Actus. 4. Scaena. 2.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Tamburlain, Techelles, Theridamas, Vsumeasane, Zenocrate, Anippe, two Moores drawing Baia∣zeth in his cage, and his wife following him.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>BRing out my foot-stoole.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>They take him out of the cage.</STAGE>
<SP><SPEAKER>Bai</SPEAKER> 
<L>Ye holy Priests of heauenly <HI>Mahomet,</HI></L>
<L>That sacrificing slice and cut your flesh,</L>
<L>Staining his Altars with your purple blood:</L>
<L>Make heauen to frowne and euery fired starre</L>
<L>To sucke vp poison from the moorish Fens,</L>
<L>And poure it in this glorious Tyrants throat.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>The chiefest God first moouer of that Spheare,</L>
<L>Enchacd with thousands euer shining lamps,</L>
<L>Will sooner burne the glorious frame of Heauen.</L>
<L>Then it should so conspire my ouerthrow.</L>
<L>But Villaine, thou that wishest this to me,</L>
<L>Fall prostrate on the lowe disdainefull earth.</L>
<L>And be the foot-stoole of great <HI>Tamburlain,</HI></L>
<L>That I may rise into my royall throne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bai.</SPEAKER>
<L>First shalt thou rip my bowels with thy sword,</L>
<L>And sacrifice my heart to death and hell,</L>
<L>Before I yeeld to such a slauery.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Base villain, vassall, slaue to <HI>Tamburlaine:</HI></L>
<L>Vnworthy to imbrace or touch the ground.</L>
<L>That beares the honor of my royall waight.</L>
<PB REF="28"/><FW><MILESTONE N="D4r"/></FW>
<L>Stoop villaine, stoope, stoope for so he bids,</L>
<L>That may command thee peecemeale to be torne,</L>
<L>Or scattered like the lofty Cedar trees,</L>
<L>Strocke with the voice of thundring <HI>Iupiter.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bai.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then as I look downe to the damned Feends.</L>
<L>Feends looke on me, and thou dread God of hell.</L>
<L>With Evan Scepter strike this hatefull earth,</L>
<L>And make it swallow both of vs at once.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>He gets vp vpon him to his chaire.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now cleare the triple region of the aire,</L>
<L>And let the maiestie of heauen beholde</L>
<L>Their Scourge and Terrour treade on Emperours,</L>
<L>Smile Stars that raign'd at my natiuity:</L>
<L>And dim the brightnesse of their neighbor Lamps,</L>
<L>Disdaine to borrow light of <HI>Cynthia,</HI></L>
<L>For I the chiefest Lamp of all the earth,</L>
<L>First rising in the East with milde aspect,</L>
<L>But fired now in the Meridian line,</L>
<L>Will send vp fire to your turning Spheares,</L>
<L>And cause the Sun to borrowe light of you.</L>
<L>My sword stroke fire from his coat of steele,</L>
<L>Euen in <HI>Bythinia,</HI> when I took this Turke:</L>
<L>As when a fiery exhalation</L>
<L>Wrapt in the bowels of a freezing cloude,</L>
<L>Fighting for passage, make the Welkin cracke,</L>
<L>And casts a flash of lightning to the earth.</L>
<L>But ere I martch to wealthy <HI>Persea,</HI></L>
<L>Or leaue <HI>Damascus</HI> and th'Egyptian fields,</L>
<L>As was the fame of <HI>Clymeus</HI> brain-sicke sonne,</L>
<L>That almost brent the Axeltree of heauen,</L>
<PB REF="29"/><FW><MILESTONE N="D4v"/></FW>
<L>So shall our swords, our lances and our shot.</L>
<L>Fill all the aire with fiery meteors.</L>
<L>Then when the Sky shal waxe as red as blood,</L>
<L>It shall be said, I made it red my selfe,</L>
<L>To make me think of nought but blood and war.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Zab.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vnworthy king, that by thy crueltie,</L>
<L>Vnlawfully vsurpest the Persean seat:</L>
<L>Dar'st thou that neuer saw an Emperour,</L>
<L>Before thou met my husband in the field,</L>
<L>Being thy Captiue, thus abuse his state,</L>
<L>Keeping his kingly body in a Cage,</L>
<L>That rooffes of golde, and sun-bright Pallaces,</L>
<L>Should haue prepar'd to entertaine his Grace?</L>
<L>And treading him beneath thy loathsome feet,</L>
<L>Whose feet the kings of <HI>Affrica</HI> haue kist.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tech.</SPEAKER>
<L>You must deuise some tormēt worsse, my Lord</L>
<L>To make these captiues reine their lauish tongues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>zenocrate,</HI> looke better to your slaue:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>zen.</SPEAKER>
<L>She is my Handmaids slaue, and she shal looke</L>
<L>That these abuses flow not from her tongue:</L>
<L>Chide her <HI>Anippe.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anip.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let these be warnings for you then my slaue,</L>
<L>How you abuse the person of the king:</L>
<L>Or els I sweare to haue you whipt stark nak'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bai.</SPEAKER>
<L>Great <HI>tamburlaine,</HI> great in my ouerthrow,</L>
<L>Ambitious pride shall make thee fall as low.</L>
<L>For treading on the back of <HI>Baiazeth,</HI></L>
<L>That should be horsed on fower mightie kings.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy names and tytles, and thy dignities</L>
<L>Are fled from <HI>Baiazeth,</HI> and remaine with me,</L>
<L>That will maintaine it against a world of Kings.</L>
<L>Put him in againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="29"/><FW><MILESTONE N="D5r"/></FW>
<SPEAKER>Bai.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is this a place for mighty <HI>Baiazeth?</HI></L>
<L>Confusion light on him that helps thee thus.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>There whiles he liues, shal <HI>Baiezeth</HI> be kept,</L>
<L>And where I goe be thus in triumph drawne:</L>
<L>And thou his wife shalt feed him with the scraps</L>
<L>My seruitures shall bring the from my boord.</L>
<L>For he that giues him other food than this:</L>
<L>Shall sit by him and starue to death himselfe.</L>
<L>This is my minde, and I will haue it so.</L>
<L>Not all the Kings and Emperours of the Earth:</L>
<L>If they would lay their crownes before my feet,</L>
<L>Shall ransome him, or take him from his cage.</L>
<L>The ages that shall talk of <HI>Tamburlain,</HI></L>
<L>Euen from this day to <HI>Platoes</HI> wondrous yeare,</L>
<L>Shall talke how I haue handled <HI>Baiazeth.</HI></L>
<L>These Mores that drew him from Bythinia,</L>
<L>To faire <HI>Damascus,</HI> where we now remaine,</L>
<L>Shall lead him with vs wheresoere we goe.</L>
<L><HI>Techelles,</HI> and my louing followers,</L>
<L>Now may we see <HI>Damascus</HI> lofty towers,</L>
<L>Like to the shadowes of <HI>Pyramides,</HI></L>
<L>That with their beauties grac'd the Memphion fields▪</L>
<L>The golden stature of their feathered bird</L>
<L>That spreads her wings vpon the citie wals,</L>
<L>Shall not defend it from our battering shot.</L>
<L>The townes-men maske in silke and cloath of gold.</L>
<L>And euery house is as a treasurie.</L>
<L>The men, the treasure, and the towne is ours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ther.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your tentes of white now pitch'd before the gates</L>
<L>And gentle flags of amitie displaid.</L>
<L>I doubt not but the Gouernour will yeeld,</L>
<L>Offering <HI>Damascus</HI> to your Maiesty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="30"/><FW><MILESTONE N="D5v"/></FW>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>So shall he haue his life, and all the rest.</L>
<L>But if he stay vntil the bloody flag</L>
<L>Be once aduanc'd on my vermilion Tent,</L>
<L>He dies, and those that kept vs out so long.</L>
<L>And when they see me march in black aray,</L>
<L>With mournfull streamers hanging down their heads,</L>
<L>Were in that citie all the world contain'd.</L>
<L>Not one should scape: but perish by our swords.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>zen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet would you haue some pitie for my sake,</L>
<L>Because it is my countries, and my Fathers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not for the world <HI>Zenocrate,</HI> if I haue sworn:</L>
<L>Come bring in the Turke.</L>
<STAGE>Excunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Act. 4. Scaena. 3,</HEAD>
<STAGE>Souldane, Arabia, Capoline, with steaming collor: and Souldiers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Souldan.</SPEAKER>
<L>ME thinks we martch as <HI>Meliager</HI> did,</L>
<L>Enuironed with braue Argolian knightes:</L>
<L>To chace the sauage Caldonian Boare,</L>
<L>Or <HI>Cephalus</HI> with lustie The bane youths.</L>
<L>Against the Woolfe that angrie <HI>Themis</HI> sent.</L>
<L>To waste and spoile the sweet Aonian fieldes.</L>
<L>A monster of fiue hundred thousand heades,</L>
<L>Compact of Rapine, Pyracie, and spoile.</L>
<L>The Scum of men, the hate and Scourge of God,</L>
<L>Raues in <HI>Egyptia,</HI> and annoyeth vs.</L>
<L>My Lord it is the bloody <HI>Tamburlaine.</HI></L>
<L>A sturdy Felon and a base-bred Thiefe.</L>
<L>By murder raised to the Perse an Crowne.</L>
<L>That dares controll vs in our Territories.</L>
<PB REF="30"/><FW><MILESTONE N="D6r"/></FW>
<L>To tame the pride of this presumotuous Beast,</L>
<L>Ioine your Arabians with the Souldans power:</L>
<L>Let vs vnite our royall bandes in one,</L>
<L>And hasten to remooue <HI>Damascus</HI> siege.</L>
<L>It is a blemish to the Maiestie</L>
<L>And high estate of mightie Emperours,</L>
<L>That such a base vsurping vagabond</L>
<L>Should braue a king, or weare a princely crowne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ara.</SPEAKER>
<L>Renowmed Souldane, haue ye lately heard</L>
<L>The ouerthrow of mightie <HI>Baiazeth,</HI></L>
<L>About the confines of <HI>Bythinia?</HI></L>
<L>The slauerie wherewith he persecutes</L>
<L>The noble Turke and his great Emperesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soul.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue, and sorrow for his bad successe:</L>
<L>But noble Lord of great <HI>Arabia,</HI></L>
<L>Be so perswaded, that the Souldan is</L>
<L>No more dismaide with tidings of his fall,</L>
<L>Than in the hauen when the Pilot stands</L>
<L>And viewes a strangers ship rent in the winds,</L>
<L>And shiuered against a craggie rocke,</L>
<L>Yet in compassion of his wretched state,</L>
<L>A sacred vow to heauen and him I make,</L>
<L>Confirming it with <HI>lbis</HI> holy name,</L>
<L>That <HI>Tamburlaine</HI> shall rue the day, the hower,</L>
<L>Wherein he wrought such ignominious wrong.</L>
<L>Vnto the hallowed person of a prince,</L>
<L>Or kept the faire <HI>zenocrate</HI> so long.</L>
<L>As Co<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" RESP="keyers" DISP="•"/>tubine, I feare to feed his <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" RESP="keyers" DISP="•"/>ust.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ara.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let griefe and furie hasten on reuenge,</L>
<L>Let <HI>Tamburlaine</HI> for his offences feele</L>
<L>Such plagues as heauen and we can poure on him.</L>
<L>I long to breake my speare vpon his crest,</L>
<PB REF="31"/><FW><MILESTONE N="D6v"/></FW>
<L>And prooue the waight of his victorious arme:</L>
<L>For Fame I feare hath bene too prodigall:</L>
<L>In sounding through the world his partiall praise:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soul.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Capolin,</HI> hast thou suruaid our powers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Great Emperours of <HI>Egypt</HI> and <HI>Arabia.</HI></L>
<L>The number of your hostes vnited is,</L>
<L>A hundred and fifty thousand horse,</L>
<L>Two hundred thousand foot, braue men at armes,</L>
<L>Couragious and full of hardinesse:</L>
<L>As frolike as the hunters in the chace:</L>
<L>Of sauage beastes amid the desart woods.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arab.</SPEAKER>
<L>My mind presageth fortunate successe,</L>
<L>And <HI>tamburlaine,</HI> my spirit doth foresee</L>
<L>The vtter ruine of thy <UNCLEAR>men</UNCLEAR> and thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then reare your standardes, let your soun∣ding Drummes</L>
<L>Direct our Souldiers to <HI>Damascus</HI> walles.</L>
<L>Now <HI>Tamburlaine,</HI> the mightie Souldane comes,</L>
<L>And leads with him the great <HI>Arabian</HI> King.</L>
<L>To dim thy basenesse and obscurity.</L>
<L>Famous for nothing but for theft and spoile,</L>
<L>To race and scatter thy inglorious crue,</L>
<L>Of Scythians and slauish Persians.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="5 (recte 4)" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Actus: 4. Scaena 5.</HEAD>
<STAGE>The Banquet, and to it commeth Tamburlain al in scarlet, Theridamas. Techelles, Vsumeasane, the Turke, with others.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>NOw hang our bloody collours by <HI>Damascus.</HI></L>
<L>Reflexing hewes of blood vpon their heads.</L>
<PB REF="31"/><FW><MILESTONE N="D7r"/></FW>
<L>While they walke quiuering on their citie walles,</L>
<L>Halfe dead for feare before they feele my wrath:</L>
<L>Then let vs freely banquet and carouse</L>
<L>Full bowles of wine vnto the God of war,</L>
<L>That meanes to fill your helmets full of golde▪</L>
<L>And make <HI>Damascus</HI> spoiles as rich to you,</L>
<L>As was to <HI>Iason Colchos</HI> golden fleece.</L>
<L>And now <HI>Baiazeth,</HI> hast thou any stomacke?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bai.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, such a stomacke (cruel <HI>tamburlane</HI>) as I could</L>
<L>Willingly feed vpon thy blood-raw hart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, thine owne is easier to come by, plucke out that,</L>
<L>And twil serue thee and thy wife: Wel <HI>zenocrate,</HI></L>
<L><HI>techelles,</HI> and the rest, fall to your victuals.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bai.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fall to, and neuer may your meat digest,</L>
<L>Ye Furies that can maske inuisible,</L>
<L>Diue to the bottome of <HI>Auernas</HI> poole,</L>
<L>And in your hands bring hellish poison vp.</L>
<L>And squease it in the cup of <HI>tamburlain.</HI></L>
<L>Or winged snakes of <HI>Lerna</HI> cast your stings,</L>
<L>And leaue your venoms in this Tyrants dish.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>zab.</SPEAKER>
<L>And may this banquet prooue as omenous,</L>
<L>As <HI>Prognes</HI> to th'adulterous Thracian King.</L>
<L>That fed vpon the substance of his child.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>zen.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, how can you suffer these outragious curses</L>
<L>By these slaues of yours?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>To let them see (diuine <HI>zenocrate</HI>)</L>
<L>I glorie in the curses of my foes.</L>
<L>Hauing the power frō the Emperiall heauen,</L>
<L>To turne them al vpon their proper heades.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tech.</SPEAKER>
<P>I pray you giue them leaue Madam, this speech is a goodly refreshing to them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="32"/><FW><MILESTONE N="D7v"/></FW>
<SPEAKER>Ther.</SPEAKER>
<P>But if his highnesse would let them be fed, it would doe them more good.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sirra, why fall you not too, are you so daintily brought vp, you cannot eat your owne flesh?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bai.</SPEAKER>
<P>First legions of deuils shall teare thee in peeces.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vsum.</SPEAKER>
<P>Villain, knowest thou to whom thou speakest</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<P>O let him alone: here, eat sir, take it from my swords point, or Ile thrust it to thy heart.</P>
<STAGE>He takes it and stamps vpon it.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ther</SPEAKER>
<P>He stamps it vnder his feet my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Take it vp Villaine and eat it, or I will make thee slice the brawnes of thy armes into carbonadoes, and eat them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>vsu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, twere better he kild his wife, &amp; then she shall be sure not to be staru'd, &amp; he be prouided for a moneths victuall before hand.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here is my dagger, dispatch her while she is fat, for if she liue but a while longer, shee will fall into a comsumption with freatting, and then she will not bee woorth the eating.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ther.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doost thou think that <HI>Mahomet</HI> wil suffer this</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tech.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis like he wil, when he cannot let it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Go to, fal to your meat: what not a bit? belike he hath not bene watered to day, giue him some drinke.</P>
<STAGE>They giue him water to drinke, and he flings it on the ground.</STAGE>
<P>Faste and welcome sir, while hunger make you eat. How now <HI>zenocrate,</HI> dooth not the Turke and his wife make a goodly showe at a banquet?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Zen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes. my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ther</SPEAKER>
<P>Me thinks, tis a great deale better than a con∣sort of musicke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="32"/><FW><MILESTONE N="D8r"/></FW>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yet musicke woulde doe well to cheere vp ze∣<HI>nocrate:</HI> pray thee tel, why art thou so sad? If thou wilt haue a song, the Turke shall straine his voice: but why is it?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Zen.</SPEAKER>
<L>My lord, to see my fathers towne besieg'd,</L>
<L>The countrie wasted where my selfe was borne,</L>
<L>How can it but afflict my verie soule?</L>
<L>If any loue remaine in you my Lord,</L>
<L>Or if my loue vnto your maiesty</L>
<L>May merit fauour at your highnesse handes,</L>
<L>Then raise your siege from faire <HI>Damascus</HI> walles,</L>
<L>And with my father take a frindly truce.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tamb.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Zenocrate,</HI> were Egypt <HI>Ioues</HI> owne land,</L>
<L>Yet would I with my sword make <HI>Ioue</HI> to sto<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" RESP="murp" DISP="•"/>pe,</L>
<L>I will confute those blind Geographers</L>
<L>That make a triple region in the world,</L>
<L>Excluding Regions which I meane to trace</L>
<L>And with this pen reduce them to a Map.</L>
<L>Calling the Prouinces, Citties and townes</L>
<L>After my name and thine <HI>zenocrate:</HI></L>
<L>Here at <HI>Damascus</HI> will I make the Point</L>
<L>That shall begin the Perpendicular.</L>
<L>And wouldst thou haue me buy thy Fathers loue</L>
<L>With such a losse? Tell me <HI>zenocrate</HI>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Zen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Honor still waight on happy <HI>tamburlaine:</HI></L>
<L>Yet giue me leaue to plead for him my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Content thy selfe, his person shall be safe.</L>
<L>And all the friendes of faire <HI>Zenocrate,</HI></L>
<L>If with their liues they will be pleasde to yeeld,</L>
<L>Or may be forc'd to make me Emperour.</L>
<L>For Egypt and Arabia must be mine.</L>
<PB REF="33"/><FW><MILESTONE N="D8v"/></FW>
<L>Feed you slaue, thou maist thinke thy selfe happie to be fed from my trencher.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bai.</SPEAKER>
<L>My empty stomacke ful of idle heat,</L>
<L>Drawes bloody humours from my feeble partes,</L>
<L>Preseruing life, by hasting cruell death.</L>
<L>My vaines are pale, my sinowes hard and drie,</L>
<L>My iointes benumb'd, vnlesse I eat, I die.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Zab.</SPEAKER>
<L>Eat <HI>Baiazeth,</HI> Let vs liue in spite of them,</L>
<L>Looking some happie power will pitie and inlarge vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here Turk, wilt thou haue a cleane trencher?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bai.</SPEAKER>
<L>I Tyrant, and more meat.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Soft sir, you must be dieted, too much eating will make you surfeit.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ther.</SPEAKER>
<P>So it would my lord, specially hauing so smal a walke, and so litle exercise.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter a second course of Crownes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Theridamas, techelles</HI> and <HI>Casane,</HI> here are the cates you desire to finger, are they not?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ther.</SPEAKER>
<P>I (my Lord) but none saue kinges must feede with these.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tech.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis enough for vs to see them, and for tam∣burlaine onely to enioy them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wel, Here is now to the Souldane of <HI>Egypt</HI> the King of <HI>Arabia,</HI> and the Gouernour of <HI>Damascus.</HI> Now take these three crownes, and pledge me, my con∣tributorie Kings.</P>
<P>I crowne you here (<HI>Theridamas</HI>) King of <HI>Argier: Techelles</HI> King of <HI>Fesse,</HI> and <HI>Vsumeasane</HI> King of <HI>Morocus.</HI> How say you to this (Turke) these are not your contributorie kings.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="33"/><FW><MILESTONE N="E1r"/></FW>
<SPEAKER>Bai.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nor shall they long be thine, I warrant them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Kings of <HI>Argier, Morocus,</HI> and of <HI>Fesse.</HI></L>
<L>You that haue martcht with happy <HI>Tamburlaine,</HI></L>
<L>As far as from the frozen place of heauen.</L>
<L>Vnto the watry mornings ruddy hower.</L>
<L>And thence by land vnto the Torrid Zone,</L>
<L>Deserue these tytles I endow you with.</L>
<L>By value and by magnanimity.</L>
<L>Your byrthes shall be no blemish to your fame.</L>
<L>For vertue is the fount whence honor springs.</L>
<L>And they are worthy she inuesteth kings.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ther.</SPEAKER>
<L>And since your highnesse hath so well vouchsaft,</L>
<L>If we deserue them not with higher meeds</L>
<L>Then erst our states and actions haue retain'd,</L>
<L>Take them away againe and make vs slaues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wel said <HI>Theridamas,</HI> when holy Fates</L>
<L>Shall stablish me in strong <HI>Egyptia.</HI></L>
<L>We meane to traueile to th'Antatique Pole,</L>
<L>Conquering the people vnderneath our feet.</L>
<L>And be renowm'd, as neuer Emperours were.</L>
<L><HI>zenocrate,</HI> I will not crowne thee yet,</L>
<L>Vntil with greater honors I be grac'd.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<TRAILER>Finis Actus quarti.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus: 5.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scaena. 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE>The Gouernour of Damasco, with three or foure Citizens, and foure Virgins with branches of Laurell in their hands.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gouernour.</SPEAKER>
<L>STil doth this man or rather God of war,</L>
<L>Batt<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" RESP="murp" DISP="•"/>r our walles, and beat our Turrets downe</L>
<PB REF="34"/><FW><MILESTONE N="E1v"/></FW><!-- this page keyed by pfs -->
<L>And to resist with longer stubbornesse,</L>
<L>Or hope of rescue from the Souldans power,</L>
<L>Were but to bring our wilfull ouerthrow,</L>
<L>And make vs desperate of our threatned liues:</L>
<L>We see his tents haue now bene altered,</L>
<L>With terrours to the last and cruelst hew:</L>
<L>His cole-blacke collours euery where aduaunst,</L>
<L>Threaten our citie with a generall spoile:</L>
<L>And if we should with common rites of Armes,</L>
<L>Offer our safeties to his clemencie,</L>
<L>I feare the custome proper to his sword,</L>
<L>Which he obserues as parcell of his fame:</L>
<L>Intending so to terrifie the world,</L>
<L>By any innouation or remorse,</L>
<L>Will neuer be dispenc'd with til our deaths,</L>
<L>Therfore, for these our harmlesse virgines sakes,</L>
<L>Whose honors and whose liues relie on him:</L>
<L>Let vs haue hope that their vnspotted praiers</L>
<L>Their blubbered cheekes and hartie humble mones</L>
<L>Will melt his furie into some remorse:</L>
<L>And vse vs like a louing Conquerour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Virg.</SPEAKER>
<L>If humble suites or imprecations,</L>
<L>(vttered with teares of wretchednesse and blood,</L>
<L>Shead from the heads and hearts of all our Sex.</L>
<L>Some made your wiues, and some your children)</L>
<L>Might haue intreated your obdurate breasts.</L>
<L>To entertaine some care of our securities.</L>
<L>Whiles only danger beat vpon our walles,</L>
<L>These more than dangerous warrants of our deat<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" RESP="murp" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Had neuer bene erected as they bee,</L>
<L>Nor you depend on such weake helps as we</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Go.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wel, louely Virgins, think our count<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" RESP="murp" DISP="••"/>s care</L>
<PB REF="34"/><FW><MILESTONE N="E2r"/></FW><!-- this page keyed by pfs -->
<L>Our loue of honor loth to be enthral'd</L>
<L>To forraine powers, and rough imperious yokes:</L>
<L>Would not with too much cowardize or feare,</L>
<L>Before all hope of rescue were denied,</L>
<L>Submit your selues and vs to seruitude.</L>
<L>Therefore in that your safeties and our owne</L>
<L>Your honors, liberties and liues were weigh'd</L>
<L>In equall care and ballance with our owne,</L>
<L>Endure as we the malice of our stars.</L>
<L>The wrath of <HI>Tamburlain,</HI> and power of warres.</L>
<L>Or be the means the ouerweighing heauens</L>
<L>Haue kept to quallifie these hot extreames.</L>
<L>And bring vs pardon in your chearfull lookes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Virg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then here before the maiesty of heauen,</L>
<L>And holy <HI>Patrones</HI> of <HI>Egyptia,</HI></L>
<L>With knees and hearts submissiue we intreate,</L>
<L>Grace to our words and pitie to our lookes</L>
<L>That this deuise may prooue propitious,</L>
<L>And through the eies and eares of <HI>tamburlaine,</HI></L>
<L>Conuey euents of mercie to his heart:</L>
<L>Graunt that these signes of victorie we yeeld</L>
<L>May bind the temples of his conquering head,</L>
<L>To hide the folded furrowes of his browes,</L>
<L>And shadow his displeased countenance,</L>
<L>With happy looks of ruthe and lenity,</L>
<L>Leaue vs my Lord, and louing countrimen,</L>
<L>What simple Virgins may perswade, we will.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Go.</SPEAKER>
<L>Garewell (sweet Virgins) on whose safe return</L>
<L>Depends our citie, libertie, and liues.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<PB REF="35"/><FW><MILESTONE N="E2v"/></FW>
<HEAD>Actus. 5. Scaena. 2.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Tamburlaine. Techelles Theridamas, Vsumeasan, with others: Tamburlaine all in blacke, and veri<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" RESP="murp" DISP="•"/> melancholy.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>WHat, are the Turtles fraide out of their neastes?</L>
<L>Alas poore fooles, must you be first shal feele</L>
<L>The sworne destruction of <HI>Damascus.</HI></L>
<L>They know my custome: could they not as well</L>
<L>Haue sent ye out, when first my milkwhite flags</L>
<L>Through which sweet mercie threw her gentle beams</L>
<L>Reflexing them on your disdainfull cies:</L>
<L>As now when furie and incensed hate</L>
<L>Flings slaughtering terrour from my coleblack tents.</L>
<L>And tels for trueth, submissions comes too late.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Virgin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most happy King and Emperour of the earth.</L>
<L>Image of Honor and Nobilitie.</L>
<L>For whome the Powers diuine haue made the world.</L>
<L>And on whose throne the holy Graces sit.</L>
<L>In whose sweete person is compriz'd the Sum</L>
<L>Of natures Skill and heauenly maiestie.</L>
<L>Pittie our plightes, O pitie poore <HI>Damascus:</HI></L>
<L>Pitie olde age, within whose siluer haires</L>
<L>Honor and reuerence euermore haue raign'd,</L>
<L>Pitie the mariage bed, where many a Lord</L>
<L>In prime and glorie of his louing ioy.</L>
<L>Embraceth now with teares of ruth and blood,</L>
<L>The iealous bodie of his fearfull wife,</L>
<L>Whose cheekes and hearts so punisht with conceit,</L>
<PB REF="35"/><FW><MILESTONE N="E3r"/></FW>
<L>To thinke thy puisant neuer staied arme</L>
<L>Will part their bodies, and preuent their soules</L>
<L>From heauens of comfort, yet their age might beare,</L>
<L>Now waxe all pale and withered to the death,</L>
<L>As well for griefe our ruthlesse Gouernour</L>
<L>Haue thus refusde the mercie of thy hand,</L>
<L>(Whose scepter Angels kisse, and Furies dread)</L>
<L>As for their liberties, their loues or liues,</L>
<L>O then for these, and such as we our selues,</L>
<L>For vs, for infants, and for all our bloods,</L>
<L>That neuer nourisht thought against thy rule,</L>
<L>Pitie, O pitie, (sacred Emperour)</L>
<L>The prostrate seruice of this wretched towne.</L>
<L>And take in signe thereof this gilded wreath,</L>
<L>Whereto ech man of rule hath giuen his hand,</L>
<L>And wisht as worthy subiects happy meanes,</L>
<L>To be inuesters of thy royall browes,</L>
<L>Euen with the true Egyptian Diadem.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Virgins, in vaine ye labo<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" RESP="murp" DISP="••"/> to preuent</L>
<L>That which mine honor sweares shal be perform'd:</L>
<L>Behold my sword, what see you at the point?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Virg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nothing but feare and fatall steele my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your fearfull minds are thicke and mistie then</L>
<L>For there sits Death, there sits imperious Death.</L>
<L>Keeping his circuit by the slicing edge.</L>
<L>But I'am pleasde you shall not see him there,</L>
<L>He now is seated on my horsmens speares:</L>
<L>And on their points his fleshlesse bodie feches.</L>
<L><HI>Techelles,</HI> straight goe charge a few of them</L>
<L>To chardge these Dames, and shew my seruant death:</L>
<L>Sitting in scarlet on their armed speares.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<L>O pitie vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="36"/><FW><MILESTONE N="E3v"/></FW>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away with them I say and shew them death.</L>
<STAGE>They take them away.</STAGE>
<L>I will not spare these proud Egyptians.</L>
<L>Nor change my Martiall obseruations,</L>
<L>For all the wealth of Gehons golden waues.</L>
<L>Or for the loue of <HI>Venus,</HI> would she leaue</L>
<L>The angrie God of Armes, and lie with me.</L>
<L>They haue refusde the offer of their liues,</L>
<L>And know my customes are as peremptory</L>
<L>As wrathfull Planets, death, or destinie.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Techelles.</STAGE>
<L>What, haue your horsmen shewen the virgins Death?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tech.</SPEAKER>
<L>They haue my Lord, and on <HI>Damascus</HI> wals</L>
<L>Haue hoisted vp their slaughtered carcases.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>A sight as banefull to their soules I think</L>
<L>As are Thessalian drugs or Mithradate.</L>
<L>But goe my Lords, put the rest to the sword.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<L>Ah faire <HI>Zenocrate,</HI> diuine <HI>Zenocrate,</HI></L>
<L>Faire is too foule an Epithite for thee,</L>
<L>That in thy passion for thy countries loue,</L>
<L>And feare to see thy kingly Fathers harme,</L>
<L>With haire discheweld wip'st thy watery cheeks:</L>
<L>And like to <HI>Flora</HI> in her mornings pride,</L>
<L>Shaking her siluer treshes in the aire.</L>
<L>Rain'st on the earth resolued pearle in showers,</L>
<L>And sprinklest Saphyrs on thy shining face,</L>
<L>Wher Beauty, mother to the Muses sits,</L>
<L>And comments vollumes with her Yuory pen:</L>
<L>Taking instructions from thy flowing eies,</L>
<L>Eies when that <HI>Ebena</HI> steps to heauen.</L>
<L>In silence of thy solemn Euenings walk.</L>
<L>Making the mantle of the richest night.</L>
<PB REF="36"/><FW><MILESTONE N="E4r"/></FW>
<L>The Moone, the Planets, and the Meteors light,</L>
<L>There Angels in their christal armours fight</L>
<L>A doubtfull battell with my tempted thoughtes,</L>
<L>For Egypts freedom and the Souldans life:</L>
<L>His life that so consumes <HI>Zenocrate,</HI></L>
<L>Whose sorrowes lay more siege vnto my saule,</L>
<L>Than all my Army to <HI>Damascus</HI> walles.</L>
<L>And neither Perseans Soueraign, nor the Turk</L>
<L>Troubled my sences with conceit of foile,</L>
<L>So much by much, as dooth <HI>zenocrate.</HI></L>
<L>What is beauty saith my sufferings then?</L>
<L>If all the pens that euer poets held,</L>
<L>Had fed the feeling of their maisters thoughts,</L>
<L>And euery sweetnes that inspir'd their harts,</L>
<L>Their minds, and muses on admyred theames:</L>
<L>If all the heauenly Quintessence they still</L>
<L>From their immortall flowers of Poesy,</L>
<L>Wherein as in a myrrour we perceiue</L>
<L>The highest reaches of a humaine wit.</L>
<L>If these had made one Poems period</L>
<L>And all combin'd in Beauties worthinesse,</L>
<L>Yet should ther houer in their restlesse heads,</L>
<L>One thought, one grace, one woonder at the least,</L>
<L>Which into words no vertue can digest:</L>
<L>But how vnseemly is it for my Sex</L>
<L>My discipline of armes and Chiualrie,</L>
<L>My nature and the terrour of my name.</L>
<L>To harbour thoughts effeminate and faint?</L>
<L>Saue onely that in / Beauties iust applause,</L>
<L>With whose instinct the soule of man is toucht.</L>
<L>And euery warriour that is rapt with loue,</L>
<L>Of fame, of valour, and of victory</L>
<PB REF="37"/><FW><MILESTONE N="E4v"/></FW>
<L>Must needs haue beauty beat on his conceites,</L>
<L>I thus conceiuing and subduing both:</L>
<L>That which hath stopt the tempest of the Gods,</L>
<L>Euen from the fiery spangled vaile of heauen,</L>
<L>To feele the louely warmth of shepheards flames,</L>
<L>And martch in cottages of strowed weeds,</L>
<L>Shal giue the world to note for all my byrth,</L>
<L>That Vertue solely is the sum of glorie,</L>
<L>And fashions men with true nobility.</L>
<L>Who's within there? <STAGE>Enter two or three.</STAGE>
Hath <HI>Baiazeth</HI> bene fed to day?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>An.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tamb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Bring him forth, &amp; let vs know if the towne be ransackt.</P>
<STAGE>Enter Techelles, Theridamas, Vsumeasan &amp; others.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tech</SPEAKER>
<L>The town is ours my Lord, and fresh supply</L>
<L>Of conquest, and of spoile is offered vs:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thats wel <HI>techelles,</HI> what's the newes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tech.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Souldan and the Arabian king together</L>
<L>Martch on vs with such eager violence,</L>
<L>As if there were no way but one with vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more there is not I warrant thee <HI>techelles</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>They bring in the Turke.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ther.</SPEAKER>
<L>We know the victorie is ours my Lord,</L>
<L>But let vs saue the reuerend Souldans life,</L>
<L>For faire <HI>Zenocrate,</HI> that so laments his state.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>That will we chiefly see vnto, <HI>theridamas.</HI></L>
<L>For sweet <HI>zenocrate,</HI> whose worthinesse</L>
<L>Deserues a conquest ouer euery hart:</L>
<PB REF="37"/><FW><MILESTONE N="E5r"/></FW>
<L>And now my footstoole, if I loose the field,</L>
<L>You hope of libertie and restitution:</L>
<L>Here let him stay my maysters from the tents,</L>
<L>Till we haue made vs ready for the field.</L>
<L>Pray for vs <HI>Baiazeth,</HI> we are going.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bai.</SPEAKER>
<L>Go, neuer to returne with victorie:</L>
<L>Millions of men encompasse thee about.</L>
<L>And gore thy body with as many wounds,</L>
<L>Sharpe forked arrowes light vpon thy horse:</L>
<L>Furies from the blacke <HI>Cocitus</HI> lake,</L>
<L>Breake vp the earth, and with their firebrands,</L>
<L>Enforce thee run vpon the banefull pikes.</L>
<L>Volleyes of shot pierce through thy charmed Skin.</L>
<L>And euery bullet dipt in poisoned drugs,</L>
<L>Or roaring Cannons seuer all thy ioints.</L>
<L>Making thee mount as high as Eagles soare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>zab.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let all the swords and Lances in the field,</L>
<L>Stick in his breast, as in their proper roomes,</L>
<L>At euery pore let blood comme dropping foorth.</L>
<L>That lingring paines may massacre his heart.</L>
<L>And madnesse send his danmed soule to hell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bai.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ah faire <HI>zabina,</HI> we may curse his power,</L>
<L>The heauens may frowne, the earth for anger quake,</L>
<L>But such a Star hath influence in his sword,</L>
<L>As rules the Skies, and countermands the Gods,</L>
<L>More than Cymerian <HI>Stix</HI> or Distinie:</L>
<L>And then shall we in this detested guyse,</L>
<L>With shame, with hungar, and with horror aie</L>
<L>Griping our bowels with retorqued thoughtes,</L>
<L>And haue no hope to end our extasies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>zab.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then is there left no <HI>Mahomet,</HI> no God,</L>
<L>No Feend, no Fortune, nor no hope of end?</L>
<PB REF="38"/><FW><MILESTONE N="E5v"/></FW>
<L>To our infamous monstrous slaueries:</L>
<L>Gape earth, and let the Feends infernall view,</L>
<L>As hell, as hoplesse and as full of feare</L>
<L>As are the blasted banks of <HI>Erebus:</HI></L>
<L>Where shaking ghosts with euer howling grones,</L>
<L>Houer about the vgly Ferriman, to get a passage to <HI>E∣lisiā</HI></L>
<L>why should we liue, O wretches, beggars slaues</L>
<L>Why liue we <HI>Baiazeth,</HI> and build vp neasts,</L>
<L>So high within the region of the aire,</L>
<L>By liuing long in this oppression,</L>
<L>That all the world will see and laugh to scorne.</L>
<L>The former triumphes of our mightines,</L>
<L>In this obscure infernall seruitude:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bai.</SPEAKER>
<L>O life more loathsome to my vexed thoughts,</L>
<L>Than noisome parbreak of the Stygian Snakes,</L>
<L>Which fils the nookes of Hell with standing aire,</L>
<L>Infecting all the Ghosts with curelesse griefs:</L>
<L>O dreary Engines of my loathed sight,</L>
<L>That sees my crowne, my honor and my name,</L>
<L>Thrust vnder yoke and thraldom of a thiefe.</L>
<L>Why feed ye still on daies accursed beams,</L>
<L>And sink not quite into my tortur'd soule.</L>
<L>You see my wife, my Queene and Emperesse,</L>
<L>Brought vp and propped by the hand of fame,</L>
<L>Queen of fifteene contributory Queens,</L>
<L>Now throwen to roomes of blacke abiection,</L>
<L>Smear'd with blots of basest drudgery:</L>
<L>And Villanesse to shame, disdaine, and misery:</L>
<L>Accursed <HI>Baiazeth,</HI> whose words of ruth,</L>
<L>That would with pity chear <HI>zabinas</HI> heart:</L>
<L>And make our soules resolue in ceasles teares,</L>
<L>Sharp hunger bites vpon and gripes the root:</L>
<PB REF="38"/><FW><MILESTONE N="E6r"/></FW>
<L>From whence the issues of my thoughts doe breake,</L>
<L>O poore <HI>zabina,</HI> O my Queen, my Queen,</L>
<L>Fetch me some water for my burning breast,</L>
<L>To coole and comfort me with longer date,</L>
<L>That in the shortned sequel of my life,</L>
<L>I may poure foorth my soule into thine armes,</L>
<L>With words of loue: whose moaning entercourse</L>
<L>Hath hetherto bin staid, with wrath and hate</L>
<L>Of our expreslesse band inflictions:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>zab.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweet <HI>Baiazeth,</HI> I will prolong thy life,</L>
<L>As long as any blood or sparke of breath</L>
<L>Can quench or coole the torments of my griefe.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>She goes out:</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bai.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now <HI>Baiazeth,</HI> abridge thy banefull daies,</L>
<L>And beat thy braines out of thy conquer'd head:</L>
<L>Since other meanes are all forbidden me,</L>
<L>That may be ministers of my decay.</L>
<L>O highest Lamp of euerliuing <HI>Ioue,</HI></L>
<L>Accursed day infected with my griefs,</L>
<L>Hide now thy stained face in endles night,</L>
<L>And shut the windowes of the lightsome heauens,</L>
<L>Let vgly darknesse with her rusty coach</L>
<L>Engyrt with tempests wrapt in pitchy clouds,</L>
<L>Smother the earth with neuer fading mistes:</L>
<L>And let her horses from their nostrels breathe</L>
<L>Rebellious winds and dreadfull thunderclaps:</L>
<L>That in this terrour <HI>tamburlaine</HI> may liue.</L>
<L>And my pin'd soule resolu'd in liquid ay,</L>
<L>May styl excruciat his tormented thoughts.</L>
<L>Then let the stony dart of sencelesse colde,</L>
<L>Pierce through the center of my withered heart,</L>
<L>And make a passage for my loathed life.</L>
<STAGE>He brains himself against the cage.</STAGE>
</SP>
<PB REF="39"/><FW><MILESTONE N="E6v"/></FW>
<STAGE>Enter Zabina.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Zab.</SPEAKER>
<L>What do mine eies behold, my husband dead?</L>
<L>His Skul al riuin in twain, his braines dasht out?:</L>
<L>The braines of <HI>Baiazeth,</HI> my Lord and Soueraigne?:</L>
<L>O <HI>Baiazeth,</HI> my husband and my Lord,</L>
<P>O <HI>Baiazet,</HI> O Turk, O Emperor, giue him his liquor Not I, bring milk and fire, and my blood I bring him againe, teare me in peeces, giue me the sworde with a ball of wildefire vpon it. Downe with him, downe with him. Goe to my child, away, away, away. Ah, saue that Infant, saue him, saue him. I, euen I speake to her, the Sun was downe. Streamers white. Red, Blacke, here here, here. Fling the meat in his face. <HI>Tamburlaine, tamburlaine,</HI> Let the souldiers be buried. Hel, death, <HI>tamburlain,</HI> Hell, make ready my Coch, my chaire, my iewels, I come, I come, I come.</P>
<STAGE>She runs against the Cage and braines her selfe</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<STAGE>Zenocrate wyth Anippe,</STAGE>
<L>Wretched <HI>Zenocrate,</HI> that liuest to see,</L>
<L><HI>Damascus</HI> walles di'd with Egytian blood.</L>
<L>Thy Fathers subiects and thy countrimen:</L>
<L>Thy streetes strowed with disseuered iointes of men,</L>
<L>And wounded bodies gasping yet for life.</L>
<L>But most accurst, to see the Sun-bright troope</L>
<L>Of heauenly vyrgins and vnspotted maides,</L>
<L>Whose lookes might make the angry God of armes,</L>
<L>To breake his sword, and mildly treat of loue,</L>
<L>On horsmens Lances to be hoisted vp,</L>
<L>And guiltlesly endure a cruell death.</L>
<L>For euery fell and stout Tartarian Stead,</L>
<PB REF="39"/><FW><MILESTONE N="E7r"/></FW>
<L>That stampt on others with their thundring hooues</L>
<L>When al their riders chardg'd their quiuering speares</L>
<L>Began to checke the ground, and rain themselues:</L>
<L>Gazing vpon the beautie of their lookes:</L>
<L>Ah <HI>Tamburlaine,</HI> wert thou the cause of this</L>
<L>That tearm'st <HI>Zenocrate</HI> thy dearest loue?</L>
<L>Whose liues were dearer to <HI>Zenocrate</HI></L>
<L>Than her owne life, or ought saue thine owne loue.</L>
<L>But see another bloody spectacle.</L>
<L>Ah wretched eies, the enemies of my hart,</L>
<L>How are ye glutted with these grieuous obiects,</L>
<L>And tell my soule mor tales of bleeding ruth?</L>
<L>See, se <HI>Anippe</HI> if they breathe or no.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anip.</SPEAKER>
<L>No breath nor sence, nor motion in them both</L>
<L>Ah Madam, this their slauery hath Enforc'd,</L>
<L>And ruthlesse cruelty of <HI>Tamburlaine.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Zen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Earth cast vp fountaines from thy entralles,</L>
<L>And wet thy cheeks for their vntimely deathes:</L>
<L>Shake with their waight in signe of feare &amp; griefe:</L>
<L>Blush heauen, that gaue them honor at their birth,</L>
<L>And let them die a death so barbarous.</L>
<L>Those that are proud of fickle Empery,</L>
<L>And place their chiefest good in earthly pompe:</L>
<L>Behold the Turke and his great Emperesse.</L>
<L>Ah <HI>tamburlaine,</HI> my loue, sweet <HI>tamburlaine,</HI></L>
<L>That fights for Scepters and for slippery crownes,</L>
<L>Behold the Turk and his great Emperesse,</L>
<L>Thou that in conduct of thy happy stars,</L>
<L>Sleep'st euery night with conquest on thy browes,</L>
<L>And yet wouldst shun the wauering turnes of war,</L>
<L>In feare and feeling of the like distresse,</L>
<L>Behold the Turke and his great Emperesse.</L>
<PB REF="40"/><FW><MILESTONE N="E7v"/></FW>
<L>Ah myghty <HI>Ioue</HI> and holy <HI>Mahomet,</HI></L>
<L>Pardon my Loue, oh pardon his contempt,</L>
<L>Of earthly fortune, and respect of pitie,</L>
<L>And let not conquest ruthlesly pursewde</L>
<L>Be equally against his life incenst,</L>
<L>In this great Turk and haplesse Emperesse.</L>
<L>And pardon me that was not moou'd with ruthe,</L>
<L>To see them liue so long in misery:</L>
<L>Ah what may chance to thee <HI>zenocrate?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anip,</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam content your self and be resolu'd,</L>
<L>Your Loue hath fortune so at his command,</L>
<L>That she shall stay and turne her wheele no more,</L>
<L>As long as life maintaines his mighty arme,</L>
<L>That fights for honor to adorne your head.</L>
<STAGE>Enter a Messenger.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Zen.</SPEAKER>
<L>What other heauie news now brings <HI>Philemus?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, your father and th' <HI>Arabian</HI> king,</L>
<L>The first affecter of your excellence,</L>
<L>Comes now as <HI>Turnus</HI> gainst <HI>Eneas</HI> did.</L>
<L>Armed with lance into the Egyptian fields,</L>
<L>Ready for battaile gainst my Lord the King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Zen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now shame and duty, loue and feare presents</L>
<L>A thousand sorrowes to my martyred soule:</L>
<L>Whom should I wish the fatall victory,</L>
<L>When my poore pleasures are deuided thus,</L>
<L>And rackt by dutie from my cursed heart:</L>
<L>My father and my first betrothed loue,</L>
<L>Must fight against my life and present loue:</L>
<L>Wherin the change I vse condemns my faith,</L>
<L>And makes my deeds infamous through the world.</L>
<L>But as the Gods to end the Troyans toile,</L>
<L>Preuent'd <HI>Turnus</HI> of <HI>Lauinia.</HI></L>
<PB REF="40"/><FW><MILESTONE N="E8r"/></FW>
<L>And fatally enricht <HI>Eneas</HI> loue.</L>
<L>So for a finall Issue to my griefes,</L>
<L>To pacifie my countrie and my loue,</L>
<L>Must <HI>Tamburlaine</HI> by their resistlesse powers,</L>
<L>With vertue of a gentle victorie,</L>
<L>Conclude a league of honor to my hope,</L>
<L>Then as the powers deuine haue preordainde,</L>
<L>With happy safty of my fathers life,</L>
<L>Send like defence of faire <HI>Arabia.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>They sound to the battaile. And Tamburlaine enioyes the victory, after Arabia enters wounded.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>What cursed power guides the murthering hands,</L>
<L>Of this infamous Tyrants souldiers.</L>
<L>That no escape may saue their enemies:</L>
<L>Nor fortune keep them selues from victory.</L>
<L>Lye down <HI>Arabia,</HI> wounded to the death,</L>
<L>And let <HI>Zenocrates</HI> faire eies beholde</L>
<L>That as for her thou bearst these wretched armes.</L>
<L>Euen so for her thou diest in these armes:</L>
<L>Leauing thy blood for witnesse of thy loue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>zen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Too deare a witnesse for such loue my Lord,</L>
<L>Behold <HI>Zenocrate,</HI> the cursed obiect</L>
<L>Whose Fortunes neuer mastered her griefs:</L>
<L>Behold her wounded in conceit for thee,</L>
<L>As much as thy faire body is for me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then shal I die with full contented heart,</L>
<L>Hauing beheld deuine <HI>Zenocrate,</HI></L>
<L>Whose sight with ioy would take away my life,</L>
<L>As now it bringeth sweetnesse to my wound,</L>
<L>If I had not bin wounded as I am.</L>
<PB REF="41"/><FW><MILESTONE N="E8v"/></FW>
<L>Ah that the deadly panges I suffer now,</L>
<L>Would lend an howers license to my tongue:</L>
<L>To make discourse of some sweet accidents</L>
<L>Haue chanc'd thy merits in this worthles bondage.</L>
<L>And that I might be priuy to the state,</L>
<L>Of thy deseru'd contentment and thy loue:</L>
<L>But making now a vertue of thy sight,</L>
<L>To driue all sorrow from my fainting soule:</L>
<L>Since Death denies me further cause of ioy.</L>
<L>Depriu'd of care, my heart with comfort dies.</L>
<L>Since thy desired hand shall close mine eies.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Tamburlain leading the Souldane, Techel∣les, Theridamas, Vsumeasane, with others.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come happy Father of <HI>Zenocrate,</HI></L>
<L>A title higher than thy Souldans name:</L>
<L>Though my right hand haue thus enthralled thee</L>
<L>Thy princely daughter here shall set thee free.</L>
<L>She that hath calmde the furie of my sword.</L>
<L>Which had ere this bin bathde in streames of blood,</L>
<L>As vast and deep as <HI>Euphrates</HI> or <HI>Nile.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Zen:</SPEAKER>
<L>O sight thrice welcome to my ioiful soule.</L>
<L>To see the king my Father issue safe,</L>
<L>From dangerous battel of my conguering Loue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wel met my only deare <HI>Zenocrate,</HI></L>
<L>Though with the losse of Egypt and my Crown.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Twas I my lord that gat the victory,</L>
<L>And therfore grieue not at your ouerthrow.</L>
<L>Since I shall render all into your hands.</L>
<L>And ad more strength to your dominions</L>
<L>Then euer yet confirm'd th'Egyptian Crown.</L>
<PB REF="41"/><FW><MILESTONE N="F1r"/></FW>
<L>The God of war resignes his roume to me,</L>
<L>Meaning to make me Generall of the world,</L>
<L><HI>Ioue</HI> viewing me in armes, lookes pale and wan,</L>
<L>Fearing my power should pull him from his throne,</L>
<L>Where ere I come the fatall sisters sweat,</L>
<L>And griesly death by running to and fro,</L>
<L>To doo their ceassles homag to my sword:</L>
<L>And here in Affrick where it seldom raines,</L>
<L>Since I arriu'd with my triumphat hoste,</L>
<L>Haue swelling cloudes drawen from wide gasping woundes.</L>
<L>Bene oft resolu'd in bloody purple showers,</L>
<L>A meteor that might terrify the earth,</L>
<L>And make it quake at euery drop it drinks:</L>
<L>Millions of soules sit on the bankes of <HI>Styx,</HI></L>
<L>Waiting the back returne of <HI>Charons</HI> boat,</L>
<L>Hell and <HI>Elisian</HI> swarme with ghosts of men,</L>
<L>That I haue sent from sundry foughten fields.</L>
<L>To spread my fame through hell and vp to heauen:</L>
<L>And see my Lord, a sight of strange import,</L>
<L>Emperours and kings lie breathlesse at my feet,</L>
<L>The Turk and his great Emperesse as it seems,</L>
<L>Left to themselues while we were at the fight.</L>
<L>Haue desperatly dispatcht their slauish liues:</L>
<L>With them <HI>Arabia</HI> too hath left his life,</L>
<L>Al sights of power to grace my victory:</L>
<L>And such are obiects fit for <HI>Tamburlaine.</HI></L>
<L>Wherein as in a mirrour may be seene,</L>
<L>His honor, that consists in sheading blood,</L>
<L>When men presume to manage armes with him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mighty hath God &amp; <HI>Mahomet</HI> made thy hand</L>
<L>(Renowmed <HI>tamburlain</HI>) to whom all kings</L>
<PB REF="42"/><FW><MILESTONE N="F1v"/></FW>
<L>Of force must yeeld their crownes and Emperies,</L>
<L>And I am pleasde with this my ouerthrow:</L>
<L>If as beseemes a person of thy state,</L>
<L>Thou hast with honor vsde <HI>Zenocrate.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Her state and person wants no pomp you see,</L>
<L>And for all blot of foule inchastity,</L>
<L>I record heauen, het heauenly selfe is cleare:</L>
<L>Then let me find no further time to grace</L>
<L>Her princely Temples with the Persean crowne:</L>
<L>But here these kings that on my fortunes wait:</L>
<L>And haue bene crown'd for prooued worthynesse,</L>
<L>Euen by this hand that shall establish them,</L>
<L>Shal now, adioining al their hands with mine,</L>
<L>Inuest her here my Queene of <HI>Persea,</HI></L>
<L>What saith the noble Souldane and <HI>Zenocrate:</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soul.</SPEAKER>
<L>I yeeld with thanks and protestations</L>
<L>Of endlesse honor to thee for her loue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then doubt I not but faire <HI>Zenocrate</HI></L>
<L>Will soone consent to satisfy vs both.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Zen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Els should I much forget my self, my Lord,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ther.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then let vs set the crowne vpon her head,</L>
<L>That long hath lingred for so high a seat.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tech.</SPEAKER>
<L>My hand is ready to performe the deed,</L>
<L>For now her mariage time shall worke vs rest:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vsum.</SPEAKER>
<L>And her's the crown my Lord, help set it on</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then sit thou downe diuine <HI>Zenocrate,</HI></L>
<L>And here we crowne thee Queene of <HI>Persea,</HI></L>
<L>And all the kingdomes and dominions</L>
<L>That late the power of <HI>Tamburlaine</HI> subdewed:</L>
<L>As Iuno, when the Giants were supprest,</L>
<L>That darted mount aines at her brother <HI>Ioue:</HI></L>
<L>So lookes my Loue, shadowing in her browes</L>
<PB REF="42"/><FW><MILESTONE N="F2r"/></FW>
<L>Triumphes and Trophees for my victories:</L>
<L>Or as <HI>Latonas</HI> daughter bent to armes,</L>
<L>Adding more courage to my conquering mind,</L>
<L>To gratify the sweet <HI>zenocrate,</HI></L>
<L>Egyptians, Moores and men of Asia,</L>
<L>From <HI>Barbary</HI> vnto the Westeme <HI>Indie,</HI></L>
<L>Shall pay a yearly tribute to thy Syre.</L>
<L>And from the boundes of <HI>Affrick</HI> to the banks</L>
<L>Of <HI>Ganges,</HI> shall his mighty arme extend.</L>
<L>And now my Lords and louing followers,</L>
<L>That purchac'd kingdomes by your matiall deeds,</L>
<L>Cast off your armor, put on scarlet roabes.</L>
<L>Mount vp your royall places of estate,</L>
<L>Enuironed with troopes of noble men,</L>
<L>And there make lawes to rule your prouinces:</L>
<L>Hang vp your weapons on <HI>Alcides</HI> poste,</L>
<L>For <HI>Tamburlaine</HI> takes truce with al the world,</L>
<L>Thy first betrothed, Loue <HI>Arabia,</HI></L>
<L>Shall we with honor (as beseemes) entombe,</L>
<L>With this great Turke and his faire Emperesse:</L>
<L>Then after all these solemne Exequies,</L>
<L>We wil our celebrated rites of mariage solemnize,</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<TRAILER>Finis Actus quinti &amp; vltimi huius primae partis.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="illustration">
<PB REF="43"/><FW><MILESTONE N="F2v"/></FW>
<P><FIGURE>
<HEAD>Tamburlaine, the great.</HEAD>
<FIGDESC>portrait of Tamburlaine</FIGDESC>
</FIGURE></P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="2" TYPE="part">
<PB REF="43"/><FW><MILESTONE N="F3r"/></FW>
<HEAD>THE SECOND PART OF The bloody Conquests of mighty Tamburlaine. With his impassionate fury, for the death of his Lady and loue, faire Zenocrate: his fourme of exhortation and discipline to his three sons, and the maner of his own death.</HEAD>
<DIV2 TYPE="prologue">
<HEAD>The Prologue.</HEAD>
<L>THe generall welcomes Tamburlain receiud,</L>
<L>When he arriued last vpon our stage,</L>
<L>Hath made our Poet pen his second part▪</L>
<L>Wher death cuts off the progres of his pomp.</L>
<L>And murdrous Fates throwes al his triumphs down,</L>
<L>But what became of faire Zenocrate,</L>
<L>And with how manie cities sacrifice</L>
<L>He celebrated her said funerall,</L>
<L>Himselfe in presence shal vnfold at large.</L>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus. 1.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scaena. 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Orcanes, king of Natolia, Gazellus, vice-roy of Byron, Vpibassa, and their traine, with drums and trumpets.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Orcanes-</SPEAKER>
<L>EGregious Viceroyes of these Eastern parts</L>
<L>Plac'd by the issue of great <HI>Baiazeth:</HI></L>
<L>And sacred Lord the mighty <HI>Calapine:</HI></L>
<L>Who liues in <HI>Egypt,</HI> prisoner to that slaue,</L>
<L>Which kept his father in an yron cage:</L>
<L>Now haue we martcht from faire <HI>Natolia</HI></L>
<PB REF="44"/><FW><MILESTONE N="F3v"/></FW>
<L>Two hundred leagues, and on <HI>Danubius</HI> banks,</L>
<L>Our warlike hoste in compleat armour rest,</L>
<L>Where <HI>Sigismond</HI> the king of <HI>Hungary</HI></L>
<L>Should meet our person to conclude a truce.</L>
<L>What? Shall we parle with the Christian?</L>
<L>Or crosse the streame, and meet him in the field.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Byr.</SPEAKER>
<L>King of <HI>Natolia,</HI> let vs treat of peace,</L>
<L>We all are glutted with the Christians blood,</L>
<L>And haue a greater foe to fight against,</L>
<L>Proud <HI>Tamburlaine,</HI> that now in <HI>Asia,</HI></L>
<L>Neere <HI>Guyrons</HI> head doth set his conquering feet,</L>
<L>And means to fire Turky as he goes:</L>
<L>Gainst him my Lord must you addresse your power.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vpibas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Besides, king <HI>Sigismond</HI> hath brought from Christendome,</L>
<L>More then his Camp of stout Hungarians,</L>
<L>Sclauonians, Almans, Rutters, Muffes, and Danes,</L>
<L>That with the Holbard, Lance, and murthering Axe,</L>
<L>Will hazard that we might with surety hold.</L>
<L>Though from the shortest Northren Paralell,</L>
<L>Vast <HI>Gruntland</HI> compast with the frozen sea,</L>
<L>Inhabited with tall and sturdy men,</L>
<L>Gyants as big as hugie <HI>Polypheme:</HI></L>
<L>Millions of Souldiers cut the Artick line,</L>
<L>Bringing the strength of <HI>Europe</HI> to these Armes.</L>
<L>Our Turky blades shal glide through al their throats,</L>
<L>And make this champion mead a bloody Fen,</L>
<L><HI>Danubius</HI> stream that runs to <HI>Trebizon,</HI></L>
<L>Shall carie wrapt within his scarlet waues,</L>
<L>As martiall presents to our friends at home.</L>
<L>The slaughtered bodies of these Christians.</L>
<L>The Terrene main wherin <HI>Danubius</HI> fals,</L>
<PB REF="44"/><FW><MILESTONE N="F4r"/></FW>
<L>Shall by this battell be the bloody Sea.</L>
<L>The wandring Sailers of proud Italy,</L>
<L>Shall meet those Christians fleeting with the tyde,</L>
<L>Be ating in heaps against their Argoses.</L>
<L>And make faire <HI>Europe</HI> mounted on her bull,</L>
<L>Trapt with the wealth and riches of the world,</L>
<L>Alight and weare a woful mourning weed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Byr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet stout <HI>Orcanes,</HI> Prorex of the world,</L>
<L>Since <HI>Tamburlaine</HI> hath mustred all his men,</L>
<L>Marching from <HI>Cairon</HI> northward with his camp,</L>
<L>To <HI>Alexandria,</HI> and the frontier townes,</L>
<L>Meanung to make a conquest of our land:</L>
<L>Tis requisit to parle for a peace</L>
<L>With <HI>Sigismond</HI> the king of <HI>Hungary:</HI></L>
<L>And saue our forces for the hot assaults</L>
<L>Proud <HI>Tamburlaine</HI> intends <HI>Natolia.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Orc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Viceroy of <HI>Byron,</HI> wisely hast thou said:</L>
<L>My realme, the Center of our Empery</L>
<L>Once lost, All Turkie would be ouerthrowne:</L>
<L>And for that cause the Christians shall haue peace.</L>
<L>Slauonians, Almains, Rutters, Muffes, and Danes</L>
<L>Feare not <HI>Orcanes,</HI> but great <HI>Tamburlaine.</HI></L>
<L>Nor he but Fortune that hath made him great.</L>
<L>We haue reuolted Grecians, Albanees,</L>
<L>Cicilians, Iewes, Arabians, Turks, and Moors,</L>
<L>Natolians, Sorians, blacke Egyptians,</L>
<L>Illicians, Thracians, and Bythimans,</L>
<L>Enough to swallow forcelesse <HI>Sigismond</HI></L>
<L>Yet scarse enough t'encounter <HI>Tamburlaine,</HI></L>
<L>He brings a world of people to the field,</L>
<L>From <HI>Scythia</HI> to the Orientall Plage</L>
<L>Of <HI>India,</HI> wher raging <HI>Lantchidol</HI></L>
<PB REF="45"/><FW><MILESTONE N="F4v"/></FW>
<L>Beates on the regions with his boysterous blowes,</L>
<L>That neuer sea-man yet discouered:</L>
<L>All <HI>Asia</HI> is in Armes with <HI>tamburlaine,</HI></L>
<L>Euen from the midst of fiery <HI>Cancers</HI> Tropick,</L>
<L>To <HI>Amazonia</HI> vnder <HI>Capricorne.</HI></L>
<L>And thence as far as <HI>Archipellago.</HI></L>
<L>All <HI>Affrike</HI> is in Armes with <HI>tamburlaine.</HI></L>
<L>Therefore Viceroies the Christians must haue peace.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="2 (?recte 1 cont.)" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Act. 1. Scaena. 2,</HEAD>
<STAGE>Sigismond, Fredericke, Baldwine, and their traine with drums and trumpets.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sigis.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>ORcanes</HI> (as our Legates promist thee)</L>
<L>Wee with our Peeres haue crost <HI>Danubius,</HI></L>
<L>to treat of friēdly peace or deadly war:</L>
<L>Take which thou wilt, for as the Romans vsde stream</L>
<L>I here present thee with a naked sword,</L>
<L>Wilt thou haue war, then shake this blade at me,</L>
<L>If peace, restore it to my hands againe:</L>
<L>And I wil sheath it to confirme the same.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Orc</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay <HI>Sigismond,</HI> forgetst thou I am he</L>
<L>That with the Cannon shooke <HI>Vienna</HI> walles.</L>
<L>And made it dance vpon the Continent:</L>
<L>As when the massy substance of the earth,</L>
<L>Quiuer about the Axeltree of heauen.</L>
<L>Forgetst thou that I sent a shower of dartes</L>
<L>Mingled with powdered shot and fethered steele</L>
<L>So thick vpon the blink-ei'd Burghers heads,</L>
<L>That thou thy self, then County-Pallatine,</L>
<L>The king of <HI>Boheme,</HI> and the <HI>Austrich</HI> Duke,</L>
<PB REF="45"/><FW><MILESTONE N="F5r"/></FW>
<L>Sent Herralds out, which basely on their knees</L>
<L>In all your names desirde a truce of me?</L>
<L>Forgetst thou, that to haue me raise my siege,</L>
<L>Wagons of gold were set before my tent:</L>
<L>Stampt with the princely Foule that in her wings</L>
<L>Caries the fearfull thunderbolts of <HI>Ioue,</HI></L>
<L>How canst thou think of this and offer war?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sig.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Vienna</HI> was besieg'd, and I was there,</L>
<L>Then County-Pallatine, but now a king:</L>
<L>And what we did, was in extremity:</L>
<L>But now <HI>Orcanes,</HI> view my royall hoste,</L>
<L>That hides these plaines, and seems as vast and wide,</L>
<L>As dooth the Desart of <HI>Arabia.</HI></L>
<L>To those that stand on <HI>Badgeths</HI> lofty Tower,</L>
<L>Or as the Ocean to the Traueiler</L>
<L>That restes vpon the snowy Appenines:</L>
<L>And tell me whether I should stoope so low,</L>
<L>Or treat of peace with the Natolian king?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Byr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Kings of <HI>Natolia</HI> and of <HI>Hungarie,</HI></L>
<L>We came from Turky to confirme a league,</L>
<L>And not to dare eeh other to the field:</L>
<L>A friendly parle might become ye both.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fred.</SPEAKER>
<L>And we from <HI>Europe</HI> to the same intent,</L>
<L>Which if your General refuse or scorne,</L>
<L>Our Tents are pitcht, our men stand in array.</L>
<L>Ready to charge you ere you stir your feet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nat.</SPEAKER>
<L>So prest are we, but yet if <HI>Sigismond</HI></L>
<L>Speake as a friend, and stand not vpon tearmes,</L>
<L>Here is his sword, let peace be ratified</L>
<L>On these conditions specified before,</L>
<L>Drawen with aduise of our Ambassadors.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sig.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then here I sheath it, and giue thee my hand,</L>
<PB REF="46"/><FW><MILESTONE N="F5v"/></FW>
<L>Neuer to draw it out, or manage armes</L>
<L>Against thy selfe or thy confederates:</L>
<L>But whilst I liue will be at truce with thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nat.</SPEAKER>
<L>But <HI>(Sigismond)</HI> confirme it with an oath,</L>
<L>And sweare in sight of heauen and by thy Christ.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sig.</SPEAKER>
<L>By him that made the world and sau'd my soule</L>
<L>The sonne of God and issue of a Mayd,</L>
<L>Sweet Iesus Christ, I sollemnly protest,</L>
<L>And vow to keepe this peace inuiolable.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nat.</SPEAKER>
<L>By sacred <HI>Mahomet,</HI> the friend of God,</L>
<L>Whose holy Alcaron remaines with vs,</L>
<L>Whose glorious body when he left the world,</L>
<L>Closde in a coffyn mounted vp the aire,</L>
<L>And hung on stately <HI>Mecas</HI> Temple roofe,</L>
<L>I sweare to keepe this truce imnolable:</L>
<L>Of whose conditions, and our solemne othes</L>
<L>Sign'd with our handes, each shal retaine a scrowle,</L>
<L>As memorable witnesse of our league.</L>
<L>Now <HI>Sigismond,</HI> if any Christian King</L>
<L>Encroche vpon the confines of thy realme,</L>
<L>Send woord, <HI>Orcanes</HI> of <HI>Natolia</HI></L>
<L>Confirm'd this league beyond <HI>Danubius</HI> streame,</L>
<L>And they will (trembling) sound a quicke retreat,</L>
<L>So am I fear'd among all Nations.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sig.</SPEAKER>
<L>If any heathen potentate or king</L>
<L>Inuade <HI>Natolia, Sigismond</HI> will send</L>
<L>A hundred thousand horse train'd to the war,</L>
<L>And backt by stout Lanceres of <HI>Germany.</HI></L>
<L>The strength and sinewes of the imperiall seat.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nat.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thank thee <HI>Sigismond,</HI> but when I war,</L>
<L>All <HI>Asia Minor, Affrica,</HI> and <HI>Greece</HI></L>
<PB REF="46"/><FW><MILESTONE N="F6r"/></FW>
<L>Follow my Standard and my thundring Drums:</L>
<L>Come let vs goe and banquet in our tents:</L>
<L>I will dispatch chiefe of my army hence</L>
<L>To faire <HI>Natolia,</HI> and to <HI>Trebizon,</HI></L>
<L>To stay my comming gainst proud <HI>Tamburlaine,</HI></L>
<L>Freend <HI>Sigismond,</HI> and peeres of <HI>Hungary,</HI></L>
<L>Come banquet and carouse with vs a while,</L>
<L>And then depart we to our territories.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="3 (?recte 2)" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Actus. 1. Scaena. 3.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Callapine with Almeda, his keeper.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Callap.</SPEAKER>
<L>SWeet <HI>Almeda,</HI> pity the ruthfull plight</L>
<L>Of <HI>Callapine,</HI> the sonne of <HI>Baiazeth,</HI></L>
<L>Born to be Monarch of the Western world:</L>
<L>Yet here detain'd by cruell <HI>Tamburlaine.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alm.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord I pitie it, and with my heart</L>
<L>With your release, but he whose wrath is death,</L>
<L>My soueraigue Lord, renowmed <HI>tamburlain.</HI></L>
<L>Forbids you further liberty than this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ah were I now but halfe so eloquent</L>
<L>To paint in woords, what Ile perfourme in deeds,</L>
<L>I know thou wouldst depart from hence with me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not for all <HI>Affrike,</HI> therefore mooue me not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet heare me speake my gentle <HI>Almeda.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>No speach to that end, by your fauour sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>By <HI>Cario</HI> runs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>No talke of running, I tell you sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>A litle further, gentle <HI>Almeda.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wel sir, what of this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>By <HI>Cario</HI> runs to <HI>Alexandria</HI> Bay,</L>
<PB REF="47"/><FW><MILESTONE N="F6v"/></FW>
<L><HI>Darotes</HI> streames, wherin at anchor lies</L>
<L>A Turkish Gally of my royall fleet,</L>
<L>Waiting my comming to the riuer side,</L>
<L>Hoping by some means I shall be releast,</L>
<L>Which when I come aboord will hoist vp saile,</L>
<L>And soon put foorth into the Terrene sea:</L>
<L>Where twirt the Ifles of <HI>Cyprus</HI> and of <HI>Creete,</HI></L>
<L>We quickly may in Turkish seas arriue.</L>
<L>Then shalt thou see a hundred kings and more</L>
<L>Vpon their knees, all bid me welcome home.</L>
<L>Amongst so mady crownes of burnisht gold,</L>
<L>Choose which thou wilt, all are at thy command,</L>
<L>A thousand Gallies mann'd with Christian slaues</L>
<L>I freely giue thee, which shall cut the straights,</L>
<L>And bring Armados from the coasts of Spaine,</L>
<L>Fraughted with golde of rich <HI>America:</HI></L>
<L>The Grecian virgins shall attend on thee,</L>
<L>Skilful in musicke and in amorous laies:</L>
<L>As faire as was <HI>Pigmalions</HI> Iuory gyrle,</L>
<L>Or louely <HI>Io</HI> metamorphosed.</L>
<L>With naked; Negros shall thy coach be drawen,</L>
<L>And as thou rid'st in triumph through the streets,</L>
<L>The pauement vnderneath thy chariot wheels</L>
<L>With Turky Carpets shall be couered:</L>
<L>And cloath of Arras hung about the walles,</L>
<L>Fit obiects for thy princely eie to pierce.</L>
<L>A hundred Bassoes cloath'd in crimson silk</L>
<L>Shall ride before the on Barbarian Steeds:</L>
<L>And when thou goest, a golden Canapie</L>
<L>Enchac'd with pretious stones, which shine as bright</L>
<L>As that faire vail that couers all the world:</L>
<L>When Phoebus leaning from his Hemi-Spheare,</L>
<PB REF="47"/><FW><MILESTONE N="F7r"/></FW>
<L>Discendeth downward to th'Antipodes.</L>
<L>And more than this, for all I cannot tell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alm.</SPEAKER>
<L>How far hence lies the Galley, say you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweet <HI>Almeda,</HI> scarse halfe a league from hence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alm.</SPEAKER>
<L>But need we not be spied going aboord?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Betwixt the hollow hanging of a hill</L>
<L>And crooked bending of a craggy rock,</L>
<L>The sailes wrapt vp, the mast and tacklings downe,</L>
<L>She lies so close that none can find her out,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alm.</SPEAKER>
<P>I like that well: but tel me my Lord, if I should let you goe, would you bee as good as your word? Shall I be made a king for my labour?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>As I am <HI>Callapine</HI> the Emperour,</L>
<L>And by the hand of <HI>Mahomet</HI> I sweare,</L>
<L>Thou shalt be crown'd a king and be my mate,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alm.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then here I sweare, as I am <HI>Almeda,</HI></L>
<L>Your Keeper vnder <HI>Tamburlaine</HI> the great,</L>
<L>(For that's the style and tytle I haue yet)</L>
<L>Although he sent a thousand armed men</L>
<L>To intercept this haughty enterprize,</L>
<L>Yet would I venture to conduct your Grace,</L>
<L>And die before I brought you backe again.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thanks gentle <HI>Almeda,</HI> then let vs haste,</L>
<L>Least time be past, and lingring let vs both.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>When you will my Lord, I am ready,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Euen straight: and farewell cursed <HI>Tambur∣laine.</HI></L>
<L>Now goe I to reuenge my fathers death.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="4 (?recte 3)" TYPE="scene">
<PB REF="48"/><FW><MILESTONE N="F7v"/></FW>
<HEAD>Actus. 1. Scaena. 4.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Tamburlaine with zenocrate, and his three sonnes, Calyphas, Amyras, and Celebinus, with drummes and trumpets.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>NOw bright <HI>zenocrate,</HI> the worlds faire eie,</L>
<L>Whose beames illuminate the lamps of heauē,</L>
<L>Whose chearful looks do cleare the clowdy aire</L>
<L>And cloath it in a christall liuerie,</L>
<L>Now rest thee here on faire <HI>Larissa</HI> Plaines,</L>
<L>Where Egypt and the Turkish Empire parts,</L>
<L>Betweene thy sons that shall be Emperours,</L>
<L>And euery one Commander of a world.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>zen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweet <HI>tamburlain,</HI> when wilt thou leaue these armes</L>
<L>And saue thy sacred person free from scathe:</L>
<L>And dangerous chances of the wrathfull war.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>When heauen shal cease to mooue on both the poles</L>
<L>&amp; when the ground wheron my souldiers march</L>
<L>Shal rise aloft and touch the horned Moon,</L>
<L>And not before my sweet <HI>zenocrate:</HI></L>
<L>Sit vp and rest thee like a louely Queene.</L>
<L>So, now she sits in pompe and maiestie:</L>
<L>When these my sonnes, more procious in mine eies</L>
<L>Than all the wealthy kingdomes I subdewed:</L>
<L>Plac'd by her side, looke on their mothers face,</L>
<L>But yet me thinks their looks are amorous,</L>
<L>Not martiall as the sons of <HI>Tamburlaine</HI></L>
<L>Water and ayre being simbolisde in one:</L>
<L>Argue their want of courage and of wit,</L>
<L>Their haire as white as milke and soft as Downe.</L>
<L>Which should be like the quilles of Porcupines.</L>
<PB REF="48"/><FW><MILESTONE N="F8r"/></FW>
<L>As blacke as Ieat, and hard as Iron or steel,</L>
<L>Bewraies they are too dainty for the wars.</L>
<L>Their fingers made to quauer on a Lute,</L>
<L>Their armes to hang about a Ladies necke:</L>
<L>Their legs to dance and caper in the aire:</L>
<L>Would make me thinke them Bastards, not my sons,</L>
<L>But that I know they issued from thy wombe,</L>
<L>That neuer look'd on man but <HI>Tamburlaine.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>zen</SPEAKER>
<L>My gratious Lord, they haue their mothers looks</L>
<L>But whē they list, their cōquering fathers hart:</L>
<L>This louely boy the yongest of the three,</L>
<L>Not long agoe bestrid a Scythian Sceed:</L>
<L>Trotting the ring, and tilting at a gloue:</L>
<L>Which when he tainted with his slender rod,</L>
<L>He raign'd him straight and made him so curuet,</L>
<L>As I cried out for feare he should haue falne,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wel done my boy, thou shalt haue shield and lance</L>
<L>Armour of proofe, horse, helme, &amp; Cuttle-axe</L>
<L>And I will teach thee how to charge thy foe,</L>
<L>And harmelesse run among the deadly pikes.</L>
<L>If thou wilt loue the warres and follow me,</L>
<L>Thou shalt be made a King and raigne with me.</L>
<L>Keeping in yron cages Emperours.</L>
<L>If thou exceed thy elder Brothers worth,</L>
<L>And shine in compleat vertue more than they,</L>
<L>Thou shalt be king before them, and thy seed</L>
<L>Shall issue crowned from their mothers wombe,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes father, you shal see me if I liue,</L>
<L>Haue vnder me as many kings as you,</L>
<L>And martch with such a multitude of men,</L>
<L>As all the world shall tremble at their view.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>These words assure me boy, thou art my sonne,</L>
<L>When I am old and cannot mannage armes,</L>
<PB REF="49"/><FW><MILESTONE N="F8v"/></FW>
<L>Be thou the scourge and terrour of the world,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why may not I my Lord, as wel as he,</L>
<L>Be tearm'd the scourge and terrour of the world?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be al a scourge and terror to the world,</L>
<L>Or els you are not sons of <HI>Tamburlaine.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>But while my brothers follow armes my lord</L>
<L>Let me accompany my gratious mother,</L>
<L>They are enough to conquer all the world</L>
<L>And you haue won enough for me to keep.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bastardly boy, sprong frō some cowards lions:</L>
<L>And not the issue of great <HI>Tamburlaine,</HI></L>
<L>Of all the prouinces I haue subdued</L>
<L>Thou shalt not haue a foot, vnlesse thou beare</L>
<L>A mind corragious and inuincible:</L>
<L>For he shall weare the crowne of <HI>Persea,</HI></L>
<L>Whose head hath deepest scarres, whose breast most woundes,</L>
<L>Which being wroth, sends lightning from his eies.</L>
<L>And in the furrowes of his frowning browes,</L>
<L>Harbors reuenge, war, death and cruelty:</L>
<L>For in a field whose superfluities</L>
<L>Is couered with a liquid purple veile,</L>
<L>And sprinkled with the braines of slaughtered men,</L>
<L>My royal chaire of state shall be aduanc'd:</L>
<L>And he that meanes to place himselfe therein</L>
<L>Must armed wade vp to the chin in blood.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>zen.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, such speeches to our princely sonnes,</L>
<L>Dismaies their mindes before they come to prooue</L>
<L>The wounding troubles angry war affoords.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>No Madam, these are speeches fit for vs,</L>
<L>For if his chaire were in a sea of blood,</L>
<L>I would prepare a ship and saile to it.</L>
<PB REF="49"/><FW><MILESTONE N="G1r"/></FW>
<L>Ere I would loose the tytle of a king,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amy.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I would striue to swim through pooles of blood,</L>
<L>Or make a bridge of murthered Carcases,</L>
<L>Whose arches should be fram'd with bones of Turks,</L>
<L>Ere I would loose the tytle of a king.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wel louely boies, you shal be Emperours both</L>
<L>Stretching your conquering armes from east to west:</L>
<L>And sirha, if you meane to weare a crowne,</L>
<L>When we shall meet the Turkish Deputie</L>
<L>And all his Viceroies, snatch it from his head,</L>
<L>And cleaue his Pericranion with thy sword.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>If any man will hold him, I will strike,</L>
<L>And cleaue him to the channell with my sword,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold him, and cleaue him too, or Ile cleaue thee</L>
<L>For we will martch against them presently.</L>
<L><HI>Theridamas, Techelles,</HI> and <HI>Casane</HI></L>
<L>Promist to meet me on <HI>Larissa</HI> plaines</L>
<L>With hostes apeece against this Turkish crue,</L>
<L>For I haue sworne by sacred <HI>Mahomet,</HI></L>
<L>To make it parcel of my Empery,</L>
<L>The trumpets sound <HI>Zenocrate,</HI> they come.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="5 (?recte 3 cont.)" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Actus: 1. Scaena. 5.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Theridamas, and his traine with Drums and Trumpets.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>WElcome <HI>Theridamas,</HI> king of <HI>Argier,</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ther,</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord the great and migh∣ty <HI>Tamburlain,</HI></L>
<L>Arch-Monarke of the world, I offer here,</L>
<PB REF="50"/><FW><MILESTONE N="G1v"/></FW>
<L>My crowne, my selfe, and all the power I haue,</L>
<L>In all affection at thy kingly feet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thanks good <HI>theridamas.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ther.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vnder my collors march ten thousand Greeks</L>
<L>And of <HI>Argier</HI> and <HI>Affriks</HI> frontier townes,</L>
<L>Twise twenty thousand valiant men at armes,</L>
<L>All which haue sworne to sacke <HI>Natolia:</HI></L>
<L>Fiue hundred Briggandines are vnder saile,</L>
<L>Meet for your seruice on the sea, my Lord,</L>
<L>That lanching from <HI>Argier</HI> to <HI>Tripoly,</HI></L>
<L>Will quickly ride before <HI>Natolia:</HI></L>
<L>And batter downe the castles on the shore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wel said <HI>Argier,</HI> receiue thy crowne againe.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="6 (?recte 3 cont.)" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Actus. 1. Scaena. 6.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Techelles and Vsumeasane together.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>KIngs of <HI>Morocus</HI> and of <HI>Fesse,</HI> welcome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vsu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Magnificent &amp; peerlesse <HI>Tamburlaine,</HI></L>
<L>I and my neighbor King of <HI>Fesse</HI> haue brought</L>
<L>To aide thee in this Turkish expedition,</L>
<L>A hundred thousand expert souldiers:</L>
<L>From <HI>Azamor</HI> to <HI>Tunys</HI> neare the sea,</L>
<L>Is <HI>Barbary</HI> vnpeopled for thy sake,</L>
<L>And all the men in armour vnder me,</L>
<L>Which with my crowne I gladly offer thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thanks king of <HI>Morocus,</HI> take your crown a∣gain.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tech.</SPEAKER>
<L>And mighty <HI>Tamburlaine,</HI> our earthly God,</L>
<L>Whose lookes make this inferiour world to quake,</L>
<L>I here present thee with the crowne of <HI>Fesse,</HI></L>
<L>And with an hoste of Moores trainde to the war,</L>
<L>Whose coleblacke faces make their foes retire,</L>
<L>And quake for feare, as if infernall <HI>Ioue</HI></L>
<PB REF="50"/><FW><MILESTONE N="G2r"/></FW>
<L>Meaning to aid them in this Turkish armes,</L>
<L>Should pierce the blacke circumference of hell,</L>
<L>With vgly Furies bearing fiery flags,</L>
<L>And millions of his strong tormenting spirits:</L>
<L>From strong <HI>Tesella</HI> vnto <HI>Biledull,</HI></L>
<L>All <HI>Barbary</HI> is vnpeopled for thy sake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thanks king of <HI>Fesse,</HI> take here thy crowne a∣gain</L>
<L>Your presence (louing friends and fellow kings)</L>
<L>Makes me to surfet in conceiuing ioy,</L>
<L>If all the christall gates of <HI>Ioues</HI> high court</L>
<L>Were opened wide, and I might enter in</L>
<L>To see the state and maiesty of heauen,</L>
<L>It could not more delight me than your sight.</L>
<L>Now will we banquet on these plaines a while,</L>
<L>And aster martch to Turky with our Campe,</L>
<L>In number more than are the drops that fall</L>
<L>When <HI>Boreas</HI> rents a thousand swelling cloudes,</L>
<L>And proud <HI>Orcanes</HI> of <HI>Natolia,</HI></L>
<L>With all his viceroies shall be so affraide,</L>
<L>That though the stones, as at <HI>Deucalions</HI> flood,</L>
<L>Were turnde to men, he should be ouercome:</L>
<L>Such lauish will I make of Turkish blood,</L>
<L>That <HI>Ioue</HI> shall send his winged Messenger</L>
<L>To bid me sheath my sword, and leaue the field:</L>
<L>The Sun vnable to sustaine the sight,</L>
<L>Shall hide his head in thetis watery lap,</L>
<L>And leaue his steeds to faire <HI>Boetes</HI> charge:</L>
<L>For halfe the world shall perish in this fight:</L>
<L>But now my friends, let me examine ye,</L>
<L>How haue ye spent your absent time from me:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vsum.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord our men of <HI>Barbary</HI> haue martcht</L>
<L>Foure hundred miles with armour on their backes,</L>
<PB REF="51"/><FW><MILESTONE N="G2v"/></FW>
<L>And laine in leagre fifteene moneths and more,</L>
<L>For since we left you at the Souldans court,</L>
<L>We haue subdude the Southerne <HI>Guallatia,</HI></L>
<L>And all the land vnto the coast of Spaine.</L>
<L>We kept the narrow straight of <HI>Gibralter,</HI></L>
<L>And made <HI>Canarea</HI> cal vs kings and Lords,</L>
<L>Yet neuer did they recreate themselues,</L>
<L>Or cease one day from war and hot alarms,</L>
<L>And therefore let them rest a while my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>They shal <HI>Casane,</HI> and tis time yfaith.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tech.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I haue martch'd along the riuer <HI>Nise</HI></L>
<L>To <HI>Machda,</HI> where the mighty Christian Priest</L>
<L>Cal'd <HI>Iohn</HI> the great, sits in a milk-white robe,</L>
<L>Whose triple Myter I did take by force,</L>
<L>And made him sweare obedience to my crowne.</L>
<L>From thence vnto <HI>Cazates</HI> did I martch,</L>
<L>Wher Amazonians met me in the field:</L>
<L>With whom (being women) I vouchsaft a league,</L>
<L>And with my power did march to <HI>zansibar</HI></L>
<L>The Westerne part of <HI>Affrike,</HI> where I view'd.</L>
<L>The Ethiopian sea, riuers and lakes:</L>
<L>But neither man nor child in al the land:</L>
<L>Therfore I tooke my course to <HI>Manico.</HI></L>
<L>Where vnresisted I remoou'd my campe:</L>
<L>And by the coast of Byather at last,</L>
<L>I came to <HI>Cubar,</HI> where the Negros dwell,</L>
<L>And conquering that, made haste to <HI>Nubia,</HI></L>
<L>There hauing sackt Borno the Kingly seat,</L>
<L>I took the king, and lead him bound in chaines</L>
<L>Vnto <HI>Damasco,</HI> where I staid before.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well done <HI>Techelles:</HI> what saith Theridamas:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="51"/><FW><MILESTONE N="G3r"/></FW>
<SPEAKER>ther.</SPEAKER>
<L>I left the confines and the bounds of Afrik</L>
<L>And made a voyage into <HI>Europe,</HI></L>
<L>Where by the riuer <HI>Tyros</HI> I subdew'd</L>
<L><HI>Stoka, Padalia,</HI> and <HI>Codemia.</HI></L>
<L>Then crost the sea and came to <HI>Oblia.</HI></L>
<L>And <HI>Nigra Silua,</HI> where the Deuils dance,</L>
<L>Which in despight of them I set on fires</L>
<L>From thence I crost the Gulfe, call by the name</L>
<L><HI>Mare magioré,</HI> of th'inhabitantes;</L>
<L>Yet shall my souldiers make no period</L>
<L>Vntill <HI>Natolia</HI> kneele before your feet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then wil we triumph, banquet and carouse,</L>
<L>Cookes shall haue pensions to prouide vs eates,</L>
<L>And glut vs with the dainties of the world,</L>
<L><HI>Lachrima Christi</HI> and Calabrian wines</L>
<L>Shall common Souldiers drink in quaffing boules,</L>
<L>I, liquid golde when we haue conquer'd him.</L>
<L>Mingled with corrall and with orientall pearles:</L>
<L>Come let vs banquet and carrouse the whiles.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV3>
<TRAILER>Finis Actus primi.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus. 2.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scaena. 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Sigismond, Fredericke, Baldwine, with their traine.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sigis.</SPEAKER>
<L>NOw say my Lords of <HI>Buda</HI> and <HI>Bohemia,</HI></L>
<L>What motiō is it that inflames your thoughts,</L>
<L>And stirs your valures to such soddaine armes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fred.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Maiesty remembers I am sure</L>
<L>What cruell slaughter of our Christian bloods,</L>
<L>These heathnish Turks and Pagans lately made,</L>
<PB REF="52"/><FW><MILESTONE N="G3v"/></FW>
<L>Betwixt the citie <HI>Zula</HI> and <HI>Danubius</HI></L>
<L>How through the midst of <HI>Verna</HI> and <HI>Bulgaria</HI></L>
<L>And almost to the very walles of <HI>Rome,</HI></L>
<L>They haue not long since massacred our Camp,</L>
<L>It resteth now then that your Maiesly</L>
<L>Take all aduantages of time and power,</L>
<L>And worke reuenge vpon these Infidels:</L>
<L>Your Highnesse knowes for <HI>Tamburlaines</HI> repaire,</L>
<L>That strikes a terrour to all Turkish hearts,</L>
<L><HI>Natolia</HI> hath dismist the greatest part</L>
<L>Of all his armie, pitcht against our power</L>
<L>Betwixt <HI>Cutheia</HI> and <HI>Orminius</HI> mount:</L>
<L>And sent them marching vp to <HI>Belgasar,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Acantha, Antioch,</HI> and <HI>Caesaria,</HI></L>
<L>To aid the kings of <HI>Soria</HI> and <HI>Ierusalem.</HI></L>
<L>Now thou my Lord, aduantage take hereof,</L>
<L>And issue sodainly vpon the rest:</L>
<L>That in the fortune of their ouerthrow,</L>
<L>We may discourage all the pagan troope,</L>
<L>That dare attempt to war with Christians.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sig.</SPEAKER>
<L>But cals not then your Grace to memorie</L>
<L>The league we lately made with king <HI>Orcanes,</HI></L>
<L>Confirm'd by oth and Articles of peace,</L>
<L>And calling Christ for record of our trueths?</L>
<L>This should be treacherie and violence,</L>
<L>Against the grace of our profession.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bald.</SPEAKER>
<L>No whit my Lord: for with such Infidels,</L>
<L>In whom no faith nor true religion rests,</L>
<L>We are not bound to those accomplishments,</L>
<L>The holy lawés of Christendome inioine:</L>
<L>But as the faith which they prophanely plight</L>
<L>Is not by necessary pollycy,</L>
<PB REF="52"/><FW><MILESTONE N="G4r"/></FW>
<L>To be esteem'd assurance for our selues,</L>
<L>So what we vow to them shauld not infringe</L>
<L>Our liberty of armes and victory.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sig.</SPEAKER>
<L>Though I confesse the othes they vndertake,</L>
<L>Breed litle strength to out securitie,</L>
<L>Yet those infirmities that thus defame</L>
<L>Their faiths, their honors, and their religion,</L>
<L>Should not giue vs presumption to the like,</L>
<L>Our faiths are sound, and must be consumate,</L>
<L>Religious, righteous, and inuiolate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fred.</SPEAKER>
<L>Assure your Grace tis superstition</L>
<L>To stand so strictly on dispensiue faith:</L>
<L>And should we lose the opportunity</L>
<L>That God hath giuen to venge our Christians death</L>
<L>And scourge their foule blasphemous Paganisme:</L>
<L>As fell to <HI>Saule,</HI> to <HI>Balaam</HI> and the rest,</L>
<L>That would not kill and curse at Gods command,</L>
<L>So surely will the vengeance of the highest</L>
<L>And iealous anger of his fearefull arme</L>
<L>Be pour'd with rigour on our sinfull heads,</L>
<L>If we neglect this offered victory.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sig.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then arme my Lords, and issue sodainly,</L>
<L>Giuing commandement to our generall hoste,</L>
<L>With expedition to assaile the Pagan,</L>
<L>And take the victorie our God hath giuen.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt,</STAGE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Actus, 2. Scaena, 2.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Orcanes, Gazellus, Vribassa with their traine.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Orcanes.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>GAzellus, Vribassa,</HI> and the rest,</L>
<L>Now will we march from proud <HI>Orminus</HI> mount</L>
<PB REF="53"/><FW><MILESTONE N="G4v"/></FW>
<L>To faire <HI>Natolia,</HI> where our neighbour kings</L>
<L>Expect our power and our royall presence,</L>
<L>T'incounter with the cruell <HI>tamburlain,</HI></L>
<L>That nigh <HI>Larissa</HI> swaies a mighty hoste,</L>
<L>And with the thunder of his martial tooles</L>
<L>Makes Earthquakes in the hearts of men and heauen,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gaz.</SPEAKER>
<L>And now come we to make his sinowes shake,</L>
<L>With greater power than erst his pride hath felt,</L>
<L>An hundred kings by scores wil bid him armes,</L>
<L>And hundred thousands subiects to each score:</L>
<L>Which if a shower of wounding thunderbolts</L>
<L>Should breake out off the bowels of the clowdes</L>
<L>And fall as thick as haile vpon our heads,</L>
<L>In partiall aid of that proud Scythian,</L>
<L>Yet should our courages and steeled crestes,</L>
<L>And numbers more than infinit of men,</L>
<L>Be able to withstand and conquer him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrib.</SPEAKER>
<L>Me thinks I see how glad the christian King</L>
<L>Is made, for ioy of your admitted truce:</L>
<L>That could not but before be terrified:</L>
<L>With vnacquainted power of our hoste.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter a messenger.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mess</SPEAKER>
<L>Arme dread Soueraign and my noble Lords</L>
<L>The treacherous army of the Christians,</L>
<L>Taking aduantage of your slender power,</L>
<L>Comes marching on vs, and determines straight,</L>
<L>To bid vs battaile for our dearest liues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Orc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Traitors, villaines, damned Christians,</L>
<L>Haue I not here the articles of peace,</L>
<L>And solemne couenants we haue both confirm'd,</L>
<PB REF="53"/><FW><MILESTONE N="G5r"/></FW>
<L>He by his Christ, and I by <HI>Mahomet:</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gaz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hel and confusion light vpon their heads,</L>
<L>That with such treason seek our ouerthrow,</L>
<L>And cares so litle for their prophet Christ.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Orc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can there be such deceit in Christians,</L>
<L>Or treason in the fleshly heart of man,</L>
<L>Whose shape is figure of the highest God?</L>
<L>Then if there be a Christ, as Christians say,</L>
<L>But in their deeds deny him for their Christ:</L>
<L>If he be son to euerliuing <HI>Ioue,</HI></L>
<L>And hath the power of his outstretched arme,</L>
<L>If he be iealous of his name and honor,</L>
<L>As is our holy prophet <HI>Mahomet,</HI></L>
<L>Take here these papers as our sacrifice</L>
<L>And witnesse of thy seruants periury.</L>
<L>Open thou shining vaile of <HI>Cynthia</HI></L>
<L>And make a passage from the imperiall heauen</L>
<L>That he that sits on high and neuer sleeps,</L>
<L>Nor in one place is circumscriptible,</L>
<L>But euery where fils euery Continent,</L>
<L>With strange infusion of his sacred vigor,</L>
<L>May in his endlesse power and puritie</L>
<L>Behold and venge this Traitors periury.</L>
<L>Thou Christ that art esteem'd omnipotent,</L>
<L>If thou wilt prooue thy selfe a perfect God,</L>
<L>Worthy the worship of all faithfull hearts,</L>
<L>Be now reueng'd vpon this Traitors soule,</L>
<L>And make the power I haue left behind</L>
<L>(Too litle to defend our guiltlesse liues)</L>
<L>Sufficient to discomfort and confound</L>
<L>The trustlesse force of those false Christians.</L>
<PB REF="54"/><FW><MILESTONE N="G5v"/></FW>
<L>To armes my Lords, on Christ still let vs crie,</L>
<L>If there be Christ, we shall haue victorie.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="scene" N="[3]">
<STAGE>Sound <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" RESP="keyers" DISP="•"/>o the battell, and Sigismond comes out wounded.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sig.</SPEAKER>
<L>Discomfited is all the Christian hoste,</L>
<L>And God hath thundered vengeance from on high,</L>
<L>For my accurst and hatefull periurie.</L>
<L>O iust and dreadfull punisher of sinne,</L>
<L>Let the dishonor of the paines I feele,</L>
<L>In this my mortall well deserued wound,</L>
<L>End all my penance in my sodaine death,</L>
<L>And let this death wherein to sinne I die,</L>
<L>Conceiue a second life in endlesse mercie.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Orcanes, Gazellus, Vribassa, with others.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Or.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now lie the Christians bathing in their bloods,</L>
<L>And Christ or <HI>Mahomet</HI> hath bene my friend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gaz.</SPEAKER>
<L>See here the periur'd traitor <HI>Hungary,</HI></L>
<L>Bloody and breathlesse for his villany.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Orc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now shall his barbarous body be a pray</L>
<L>To beasts and foules, and al the winds shall breath</L>
<L>Through shady leaues of euery sencelesse tree,</L>
<L>Murmures and hisses for his hainous sin.</L>
<L>Now scaldes his soule in the Tartarian streames,</L>
<L>And feeds vpon the banefull tree of hell,</L>
<L>That <HI>zoacum,</HI> that fruit of bytternesse,</L>
<L>That in the midst of fire is ingraft,</L>
<L>Yet flourisheth as <HI>Flora</HI> in her pride,</L>
<L>With apples like the heads of damned Feends,</L>
<PB REF="54"/><FW><MILESTONE N="G6r"/></FW>
<L>The Dyuils there in chaines of quencelesse flame,</L>
<L>Shall lead his soule through <HI>Orcus</HI> burning gulfes</L>
<L>From paine to paine, whose change shal neuer end:</L>
<L>What saiest thou yet <HI>Gazellus</HI> to his foile:</L>
<L>Which we referd to iustice of his Christ,</L>
<L>And to his power, which here appeares as full</L>
<L>As raies of <HI>Cynthia</HI> to the clearest sight?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gaz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis but the fortune of the wars my Lord,</L>
<L>Whose power is often proou'd a myracle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Orc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet in my thoughts shall Christ be honoured,</L>
<L>Not dooing <HI>Mahomet</HI> an iniurie,</L>
<L>Whose power had share in this our victory:</L>
<L>And since this miscreant hath disgrac'd his faith,</L>
<L>And died a traitor both to heauen and earth,</L>
<L>We wil both watch and ward shall keepe his trunke</L>
<L>Amidst these plaines, for Foules to pray vpon.</L>
<L>Go Vribassa, giue it straight in charge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vri.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Vrib.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Orc.</SPEAKER>
<L>And now <HI>Gazellus,</HI> let vs haste and meete</L>
<L>Our Army and our brother of <HI>Ierusalem,</HI></L>
<L>Of <HI>So<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" RESP="keyers" DISP="•"/>, Trebizon</HI> and <HI>Amasia,</HI></L>
<L>And happily with full Natolian bowles</L>
<L>Of Greekish wine now let vs celebrate</L>
<L>Our happy conquest, and his angry fate.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="[4]" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Actus. 2. Scaena vltima.</HEAD>
<STAGE>The Arras is drawen and Zenocrate lies in her bed of state, Tamburlaine sitting by her: three Phisi∣tians about her bed, tempering potions. Theri∣damas, Techelles, Vsumeasane, and the three sonnes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="55"/><FW><MILESTONE N="G6v"/></FW>
<SPEAKER>Tamburlaine,</SPEAKER>
<L>BLacke is the beauty of the brightest day,</L>
<L>The golden balle of heauens eternal fire,</L>
<L>That danc'd with glorie on the siluer waues:</L>
<L>Now wants the fewell that enflamde his beames</L>
<L>And all with faintnesse and for foule disgrace,</L>
<L>He bindes his temples with a frowning cloude,</L>
<L>Ready to darken earth with endlesse night:</L>
<L><HI>Zenocrate</HI> that gaue him light and life,</L>
<L>Whose eies shot fire from their Iuory bowers,</L>
<L>And tempered euery soule with liuely heat,</L>
<L>Now by the malice of the angry Skies,</L>
<L>Whose iealousie admits no second Mate,</L>
<L>Drawes in the comfort of her latest breath</L>
<L>All dassed with the hellish mists of death.</L>
<L>Now walk the angels on the walles of heauen,</L>
<L>As Centinels to warne th'immortall soules,</L>
<L>To entertaine deuine <HI>Zenocrate.</HI></L>
<L><HI>Apollo Cynthia,</HI> and the ceaslesse lamps</L>
<L>That gently look'd vpon this loathsome earth,</L>
<L>Shine downwards now no more, but deck the heauens</L>
<L>To entertaine diuine <HI>Zenocrate.</HI></L>
<L>The christall springs whose taste illuminates</L>
<L>Refined eies with an eternall sight,</L>
<L>Like tried siluer runs through Paradice</L>
<L>To entertaine diuine <HI>zenocrate.</HI></L>
<L>The Cherubins and holy Seraphins</L>
<L>That sing and play before the king of kings,</L>
<L>We all their voices and their instruments</L>
<L>To entertaine diuine <HI>Zenocrate.</HI></L>
<L>And in this sweet and currious harmony,</L>
<L>The God that tunes this musicke to our soules:</L>
<PB REF="55"/><FW><MILESTONE N="G7r"/></FW>
<L>Holds out his hand in highest maiesty</L>
<L>To entertaine diuine <HI>Zenocrate.</HI></L>
<L>Then let some holy trance conuay my thoughts,</L>
<L>Vp to the pallace of th'imperiall heauen:</L>
<L>That this my life may be as short to me</L>
<L>As are the daies of sweet <HI>Zenocrate:</HI></L>
<L>Phisitions, wil no phisicke do her good?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phis.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, your Maiesty shall soone perceiue▪</L>
<L>And if she passe this fit, the worst is past.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tell me, how fares my faire <HI>Zenocrate:</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>zen.</SPEAKER>
<L>I fare my Lord, as other Emperesses,</L>
<L>That when this fraile and transitory flesh,</L>
<L>Hath suckt the measure of that vitall aire</L>
<L>That feeds the body with his dated health,</L>
<L>Wanes with enforst and necessary change.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>May neuer such a change transfourme my loue</L>
<L>In whose sweet being I repose my life,</L>
<L>Whose heauenly presence beautified with health,</L>
<L>Giues light to <HI>Phoebus</HI> and the fixed stars,</L>
<L>Whose absence make the sun and Moone as darke</L>
<L>As when opposde in one Diamiter:</L>
<L>Their Spheares are mounted on the serpents head,</L>
<L>Or els discended to his winding traine:</L>
<L>Liue still my Loue and so conserue my life,</L>
<L>Or dieng, be the anchor of my death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>zen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Liue still my Lord, O let my soueraigne liue,</L>
<L>And sooner let the fiery Element</L>
<L>Dissolue, and make your kingdome in the Sky,</L>
<L>Than this base earth should shroud your maiesty:</L>
<L>For should I but suspect your death by mine,</L>
<L>The comfort of my future happinesse</L>
<L>And hope to meet your highnesse in the heauens,</L>
<PB REF="56"/><FW><MILESTONE N="G7v"/></FW>
<L>Turn'd to dispaire, would break my wretched breast,</L>
<L>And furie would confound my present rest.</L>
<L>But let me die my Loue, yet let me die,</L>
<L>With loue and patience let your true loue die:</L>
<L>Your griefe and furie hurtes my second life,</L>
<L>Yet let me kisse my Lord before I die,</L>
<L>And let me die with kissing of my Lord.</L>
<L>But since my life is lengthened yet a while,</L>
<L>Let me take leaue of these my louing sonnes,</L>
<L>And of my Lords whose true nobilitie</L>
<L>Haue merited my latest memorie:</L>
<L>Sweet sons farewell, in death resemble me,</L>
<L>And in your liues your fathers excellency.</L>
<L>Some musicke, and my fit wil cease my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>They call musicke.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Proud furie and intollorable fit,</L>
<L>That dares torment the body of my Loue,</L>
<L>And scourge the Scourge of the immortall God:</L>
<L>Now are those Spheares where <HI>Cupid</HI> vsde to sit,</L>
<L>Wounding the world with woonder and with loue,</L>
<L>Sadly supplied with pale and ghastly death:</L>
<L>Whose darts do pierce the Center of my soule,</L>
<L>Her sacred beauty hath enchaunted heauen,</L>
<L>And had she liu'd before the siege of <HI>Troy,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Hellen,</HI> whose beauty sommond Greece to armes,</L>
<L>And drew a thousand ships to <HI>Tenedos,</HI></L>
<L>Had not bene nam'd in <HI>Homers</HI> Iliads:</L>
<L>Her name had bene in euery line he wrote:</L>
<L>Or had those wanton Poets, for whose byrth</L>
<L>Olde Rome was proud, but gasde a while on her,</L>
<L>Nor <HI>Lesbia,</HI> nor <HI>Corrinna</HI> had bene nam'd,</L>
<L><HI>zenocrate</HI> had bene the argument</L>
<PB REF="56"/><FW><MILESTONE N="G8r"/></FW>
<L>Of euery Epigram or Eligie.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>The musicke sounds, and she dies.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>What, is she dead? <HI>Techelles,</HI> draw thy sword,</L>
<L>And wound the earth, that it may cleaue in twaine,</L>
<L>And we discend into th'infernall vaults,</L>
<L>To haile the fatall Sisters by the haire,</L>
<L>And throw them in the triple more of Hell,</L>
<L>For taking hence my faire <HI>zenocrate.</HI></L>
<L><HI>Casane</HI> and theridamas to armes,</L>
<L>Raise Caualieros higher than the cloudes:</L>
<L>And with the cannon breake the frame of heauen,</L>
<L>Batter the shining pallace of the Sun,</L>
<L>And shiuer all the starry strmament:</L>
<L>For amdrous <HI>Ioue</HI> hath snatcht my loue from hence,</L>
<L>Meaning to make her stately Queene of heauen,</L>
<L>What God so euer holds thee in his armes,</L>
<L>Giuing thee Nectar and Ambrosia,</L>
<L>Behold me here diuine <HI>zenocrate,</HI></L>
<L>Rauing, impatient, desperate and mad,</L>
<L>Breaking my steeled lance, with which I burst</L>
<L>The rusty beames of <HI>Ianus</HI> Temple doores,</L>
<L>Letting out death and tyrannising war:</L>
<L>To martch with me vnder this bloody flag,</L>
<L>And if thou pitiest <HI>Tamburlain</HI> the great,</L>
<L>Come downe from heauen and liue with me againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ther.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ah good my Lord be patient, she is dead,</L>
<L>And all this raging cannot make her liue,</L>
<L>If woords might serue, our voice hath rent the aire,</L>
<L>If teares, our eies haue watered all the earth:</L>
<L>If griefe, our murthered harts haue straind forth blood</L>
<L>Nothing preuailes, for she is dead my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>For she is dead: thy words doo pierce my soule</L>
<PB REF="57"/><FW><MILESTONE N="G8v"/></FW>
<L>Ah sweet theridamas, say so no more,</L>
<L>Though she be dead, yet let me think she liues,</L>
<L>And feed my mind that dies for want of her:</L>
<L>Where ere her soule be, thou shalt stay with me</L>
<L>Embalm'd with Cassia, Amber Greece and Myrre,</L>
<L>Not lapt in lead but in a sheet of gold,</L>
<L>And till I die thou shalt not be interrd.</L>
<L>Then in as rich a tombe as <HI>Mausolus,</HI></L>
<L>We both will rest and haue one Epitaph</L>
<L>Writ in as many seuerall languages,</L>
<L>As I haue conquered kingdomes with my sword,</L>
<L>This cursed towne will I consume with fire,</L>
<L>Because this place bereft me of my Loue:</L>
<L>The houses burnt, wil looke as if they mourn'd</L>
<L>And here will I set vp her stature,</L>
<L>And martch about it with my mourning campe,</L>
<L>Drooping and pining for <HI>zenocrate.</HI></L>
<STAGE>The Arras is drawen.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus. 3.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scaena. 1,</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter the kings of Trebisond and Soria, one brin∣ging a sword, &amp; another a scepter: Next Natolia and Ierusalem with the Emperiall crowne: After Calapine, and after him other Lordes: Orcanes and Ierusalem crowne him, and the other giue him the scepter.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Orca.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>CAlepinus Cyricelibes,</HI> otherwise <HI>Cybelius,</HI> son and successiue heire to the late mighty Empe∣rour <HI>Baiazeth,</HI> by the aid of God and his friend <HI>Mahomet,</HI> Emperour of <HI>Natolia, Ierusalem,</HI>
<PB REF="57"/><FW><MILESTONE N="H1r"/></FW>
<HI>Trebizon, Soria, Amasia, Thracia, Illyria, Carmo∣nia</HI> And al the hundred and thirty Kingdomes late con∣tributory to his mighty father. Long liue <HI>Callepinus,</HI> Emperour of Turky.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thrice worthy kings of <HI>Natolia,</HI> and the rest,</L>
<L>I will requite your royall gratitudes</L>
<L>With all the benefits my Empire yeelds:</L>
<L>And were the sinowes of th'imperiall seat</L>
<L>So knit and strengthned, as when <HI>Baiazeth</HI></L>
<L>My royall Lord and father fild the throne,</L>
<L>Whose cursed fate hath so dismembred it,</L>
<L>Then should you see this Thiefe of <HI>Scythia,</HI></L>
<L>This proud vsurping king of <HI>Persea,</HI></L>
<L>Do vs such honor and supremacie,</L>
<L>Bearing the vengeance of our fathers wrongs,</L>
<L>As all the world should blot our dignities</L>
<L>Out of the booke of base borne infamies.</L>
<L>And now I doubt not but your royall cares</L>
<L>Hath so prouided for this cursed foe,</L>
<L>That since the heire of mighty <HI>Baiazeth</HI></L>
<L>(An Emperour so honoured for his vertues)</L>
<L>Reuiues the spirits of true Turkish heartes,</L>
<L>In grieuous memorie of his fathers shame,</L>
<L>We shall not need to nourish any doubt,</L>
<L>But that proud Fortune, who hath followed long</L>
<L>The martiall sword of mighty <HI>Tamburlaine,</HI></L>
<L>Will now retaine her olde inconstancie,</L>
<L>And raise our honors to as high a pitch</L>
<L>In this our strong and fortunate encounter,</L>
<L>For so hath heauen prouided my escape,</L>
<L>From al the crueltie my soule sustaind,</L>
<L>By this my friendly keepers happy meanes,</L>
<PB REF="58"/><FW><MILESTONE N="H1v"/></FW>
<L>That <HI>Ioue</HI> sur char dg'd with pity of our wrongs,</L>
<L>Will poure it downe in showers on our heads:</L>
<L>Scourging the pride of cursed <HI>tamburlain.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Orc.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue a hundred thousad men in armes,</L>
<L>Some, that in conquest of the periur'd Christian.</L>
<L>Being a handfull to a mighty hoste,</L>
<L>Thinke them in number yet sufficient,</L>
<L>To drinke the riuer <HI>Nile</HI> or <HI>Euphrates,</HI></L>
<L>And for their power, ynow to win the world.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I as many from <HI>Ierusalem,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Iudaea, Gaza,</HI> and <HI>Scalonians</HI> bounds,</L>
<L>That on mount <HI>Sinay</HI> with their ensignes spread,</L>
<L>Looke like the parti-coloured cloudes of heauen,</L>
<L>That shew faire weather to the neighbor morne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Treb.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I as many bring from <HI>Trebizon,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Chio Famastro</HI> and <HI>Amasia,</HI></L>
<L>All bordring on the <HI>Mare-major sea:</HI></L>
<L><HI>Riso, Sancina,</HI> and the bordering townes,</L>
<L>That touch the end of famous <HI>Euphrates.</HI></L>
<L>Whose courages are kindled with the flames,</L>
<L>The cursed Scythian sets on all their townes,</L>
<L>And vow to burne the villaines cruell heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sor.</SPEAKER>
<L>From <HI>Soria</HI> with seuenty thousand strong,</L>
<L>Tane from <HI>Aleppo, Soldino, Tripoly,</HI></L>
<L>And so vnto my citie of <HI>Damasco,</HI></L>
<L>I march to meet and aide my neigbor kings,</L>
<L>All which will ioine against this <HI>Tamburlain,</HI></L>
<L>And bring him captiue to your highnesse feet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Orc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our battaile then in martiall maner pitcht,</L>
<L>According to our ancient vse, shall beare</L>
<L>The figure of the semi-circled Moone:</L>
<L>Whose hornes shall sprinkle through the tainted aire,</L>
<PB REF="58"/><FW><MILESTONE N="H2r"/></FW>
<L>The poisoned braines of this proud Scythian.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wel then my noble Lords, for this my friend,</L>
<L>That freed me from the bondage of my foe:</L>
<L>I thinke it requisite and honorable,</L>
<L>To keep my promise, and to make him king,</L>
<L>That is a Gentleman (I know) at least.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alm.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's no matter sir, for being a king,</L>
<L>For <HI>Tamburlain</HI> came vp of nothing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Maiesty may choose some pointed time,</L>
<L>Perfourming all your promise to the full:</L>
<L>Tis nought for your maiesty to giue a kingdome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then wil I shortly keep my promise <HI>Almeda</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alm.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, I thank your Maiesty.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Actus. 2. Scaena. 2.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Tamburlaine with Vsumeasane, and his three sons, foure bearing the hearse of Zenocrate, and the drums sounding a dolefull martch, the Towne burning.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>SO, burne the turrets of this cursed towne,</L>
<L>Flame to the highest region of the aire:</L>
<L>And kindle heaps of exhalations,</L>
<L>That being fiery meteors, may presage,</L>
<L>Death and destruction to th'inhabitants</L>
<L>Ouer my Zenith hang a blazing star,</L>
<L>That may endure till heauen be dissolud,</L>
<L>Fed with the fresh supply of earthly dregs,</L>
<L>Threatning a death and famine to this land,</L>
<L>Flieng Dragons, lightning, fearfull thunderclaps,</L>
<L>sindge these fair plaines, and make them seeme as black</L>
<PB REF="59"/><FW><MILESTONE N="H2v"/></FW>
<L>As is the Island where the Furies maske</L>
<L>Compast with <HI>Lethe, Styx and Phlegeton,</HI></L>
<L>Because my deare <HI>Zenocrate</HI> is dead.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>This Piller plac'd in memorie of her,</L>
<L>Where in Arabian, Hebrew, Greek, is writ</L>
<L><HI>This towne being burnt by Tamburlaine the great,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Forbids the world to build it vp againe.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amy.</SPEAKER>
<L>And here this mourful streamer shal be plac'd</L>
<L>Wrought with the Persean and Egyptian armes,</L>
<L>To signifie she was a princesse borne,</L>
<L>And wife vnto the Monarke of the East.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Celib.</SPEAKER>
<L>And here this table as a Register</L>
<L>Of all her vertues and perfections.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>And here the picture of <HI>zenocrate,</HI></L>
<L>To shew her beautie, which the world admyr'd,</L>
<L>Sweet picture of diuine <HI>Zenocrate,</HI></L>
<L>That hanging here, wil draw the Gods from heauen:</L>
<L>And cause the stars fixt in the Southern arke,</L>
<L>Whose louely faces neuer any viewed,</L>
<L>That haue not past the Centers latitude.</L>
<L>As Pilgrimes traueile to our Hemi-spheare.</L>
<L>Onely to gaze vpon <HI>Zenocrate.</HI></L>
<L>Thou shalt not beautifie <HI>Larissa</HI> plaines.</L>
<L>But keep within the circle of mine armes.</L>
<L>At euery towne and castle I besiege,</L>
<L>Thou shalt be set vpon my royall tent.</L>
<L>And when I meet an armie in the field,</L>
<L>Whose looks will shed such influence in my campe,</L>
<L>As if <HI>Bellona,</HI> Goddesse of the war</L>
<L>Threw naked swords and sulphur bals of fire,</L>
<L>Vpon the heads of all our enemies.</L>
<L>And now my Lords, aduance your speares againe,</L>
<PB REF="59"/><FW><MILESTONE N="H3r"/></FW>
<L>Sorrow no more my sweet <HI>Casane</HI> now:</L>
<L>Boyes leaue to mourne, this towne shall euer mourne,</L>
<L>Being burnt to cynders for your mothers death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>If I had wept a sea of teares for her,</L>
<L>It would not ease the sorrow I sustaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amy.</SPEAKER>
<L>As is that towne, so is my heart consum'd,</L>
<L>With griefe and sorrow for my mothers death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>My mothers death hath mortified my mind,</L>
<L>And sorrow stops the passage of my speech.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>But now my boies, leaue off, and <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" RESP="murp" DISP="•"/>ist to me,</L>
<L>That meane to teach you rudiments of war:</L>
<L>Ile haue you learne to sleepe vpon the ground,</L>
<L>March in your armour throwe watery Fens,</L>
<L>Sustaine the scortching heat and freezing cold,</L>
<L>Hunger and cold right adiuncts of the war.</L>
<L>And after this, to scale a castle wal,</L>
<L>Besiege a fort, to vndermine a towne,</L>
<L>And make whole cyties caper in the aire.</L>
<L>Then next, the way to fortifie your men,</L>
<L>In champion grounds, what figure serues you best,</L>
<L>For with the <HI>quinque-angle</HI> fourme is meet,</L>
<L>Because the corners there may fall more flat:</L>
<L>Whereas the Fort may fittest be assailde,</L>
<L>And sharpest where th'assault is desperate.</L>
<L>The ditches must be deepe, the Counterscarps</L>
<L>Narrow and steepe, the wals made high and broad,</L>
<L>The Bulwarks and the rampiers large and strong,</L>
<L>With Caualieros and thicke counterforts,</L>
<L>And roome within to lodge sixe thousand men.</L>
<L>It must haue priuy ditches, countermines,</L>
<L>And secret issuings to defend the ditch.</L>
<L>It must haue high Argins and couered waies</L>
<PB REF="60"/><FW><MILESTONE N="H3v"/></FW>
<L>To keep the bulwark fronts from battery,</L>
<L>And Parapets to hide the Muscatiers:</L>
<L>Casemates to place the great Artillery,</L>
<L>And store of ordinance that from euery flanke</L>
<L>May scoure the outward curtaines of the Fort,</L>
<L>Dismount the Cannon of the aduerse part,</L>
<L>Murther the Foe and saue their walles from breach.</L>
<L>When this is learn'd for seruice on the land,</L>
<L>By plaine and easie demonstration,</L>
<L>Ile teach you how to make the water mount,</L>
<L>That you may dryfoot martch through lakes &amp; pooles,</L>
<L>Deep riuers, hauens, creekes, and litle seas,</L>
<L>And make a Fortresse in the raging waues,</L>
<L>Fenc'd with the concaue of a monftrous rocke,</L>
<L>Inuincible by nature of the place.</L>
<L>When this is done, then are ye souldiers,</L>
<L>And worthy sounes of <HI>Tamburlain</HI> the great,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, but this is dangerous to be done,</L>
<L>We may be slaine or wounded ere we learne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Villain, art thou the sonne of <HI>Tamburlaine,</HI></L>
<L>And fear'st to die, or with a Curtle-axe</L>
<L>To hew thy flesh and make a gaping wound:</L>
<L>Hast thou beheld a peale of ordinance strike</L>
<L>A ring of pikes, mingled with shot and horse,</L>
<L>Whose shattered lims, being tost as high as heauen,</L>
<L>Hang in the aire as thicke as sunny motes,</L>
<L>And canst thou Coward stand in feare of death:</L>
<L>Hast thou not seene my horsmen charge the foe,</L>
<L>Shot through the armes, cut ouerthwart the hands,</L>
<L>Dieng their lances with their streaming blood,</L>
<L>And yet at night carrouse within my tent,</L>
<L>Filling their empty vaines with aiery wine,</L>
<PB REF="60"/><FW><MILESTONE N="H4r"/></FW>
<L>That being concocted, turnes to crimson blood,</L>
<L>And wilt thou shun the field for feare of woundes:</L>
<L>View me thy father that hath conquered kings,</L>
<L>And with his hoste martch round about the earth,</L>
<L>Quite voide of skars, and cleare from any wound,</L>
<L>That by the warres lost not a dram of blood,</L>
<L>And see him lance his flesh to teach you all.</L>
<STAGE>He cuts his arme.</STAGE>
<L>A wound is nothing be it nere so deepe,</L>
<L>Blood is the God of Wars rich liuery.</L>
<L>Now look I like a souldier, and this wound</L>
<L>As great a grace and maiesty to me,</L>
<L>As if a chaire of gold enamiled,</L>
<L>Enchac'd with Diamondes, Saphyres, Rubies</L>
<L>And fairest pearle of welthie <HI>India</HI></L>
<L>Were mounted here vnder a Canapie:</L>
<L>And I sat downe, cloth'd with the massie robe,</L>
<L>That late adorn'd the Affrike Potentate.</L>
<L>Whom I brought bound vnto <HI>Damascus</HI> walles.</L>
<L>Come boyes and with your fingers search my wound,</L>
<L>And in my blood wash all your hands at once,</L>
<L>While I sit smiling to behold the sight.</L>
<L>Now my boyes, what think you of a wound?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know not what I should think of it,</L>
<L>Me thinks tis a pitifull sight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis nothing: giue me a wound father.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amy.</SPEAKER>
<L>And me another my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come sirra, giue me your arme.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here father, cut it brauely as you did your own</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>It shall suffice thou darst abide a wound</L>
<L>My boy, Thou shalt not loose a drop of blood,</L>
<L>Before we meet the armie ef the Turke.</L>
<PB REF="61"/><FW><MILESTONE N="H4v"/></FW>
<L>But then run desperate through the thickest throngs,</L>
<L>Dreadlesse of blowes, of bloody wounds and death:</L>
<L>And let the burning of <HI>Larissa</HI> wals</L>
<L>My speech of war, and this my wound you see</L>
<L>Teach you my boyes to beare couragious minds,</L>
<L>Fit for the followers of great tamburlaine.</L>
<L><HI>Vsumeasane</HI> now come let vs martch</L>
<L>Towards <HI>Techelles</HI> and <HI>Theridamas,</HI></L>
<L>That we haue sent before to fire the townes,</L>
<L>The towers and cities of these hatefull Turks,</L>
<L>And hunt that Coward, faintheart, runaway,</L>
<L>With that accursed traitor <HI>Almeda,</HI></L>
<L>Til fire and sword haue found them at a bay.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vsu.</SPEAKER>
<L>I long to pierce his bowels with my sword,</L>
<L>That hath betraied my gracious Soueraigne,</L>
<L>That curst and damned Traitor <HI>Almeda.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then let vs see if coward <HI>Calapine</HI></L>
<L>Dare leuie armes against our puissance,</L>
<L>That we may tread vpon his captiue necke,</L>
<L>And treble all his fathers slaueries.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="1 (recte 3)" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Actus. 3. Scaena. 1,</HEAD>
<STAGE>Techelles, Theridamas and their traine.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Therid.</SPEAKER>
<L>THus haue wee martcht Northwarde from <HI>Tamburlaine,</HI></L>
<L>Vnto the frontier point of <HI>Soria:</HI></L>
<L>And this is <HI>Balsera</HI> their chiefest hold,</L>
<L>Wherein is all the treasure of the land.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tech.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then let vs bring our light Artilery,</L>
<L>Minions, Fauknets, and Sakars to the trench,</L>
<PB REF="61"/><FW><MILESTONE N="H5r"/></FW>
<L>Filling the ditches with the walles wide breach,</L>
<L>And enter in, to seaze vpon the gold:</L>
<L>How say ye Souldiers, Shal we not?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, my Lord, yes, come lets about it,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ther.</SPEAKER>
<L>But stay a while, summon a parle, Drum,</L>
<L>It may be they will yeeld it quietly,</L>
<L>Knowing two kings, the friend to tamburlain,</L>
<L>Stand at the walles, with such a mighty power.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Summon the battell.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Captaine with his wife and sonne.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>What requier you my maisters?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ther.</SPEAKER>
<L>Captaine, that thou yeeld vp thy hold to vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>To you. Why, do you thinke me weary of it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tech.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay Captain, thou art weary of thy life,</L>
<L>If thou withstand the friends of <HI>Tamburlain.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ther.</SPEAKER>
<L>These Pioners of Argier in Affrica,</L>
<L>Euen in the ca<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" RESP="keyers" DISP="•"/>ous face shall raise a hill</L>
<L>Of earth and fagots higher than thy Fort,</L>
<L>And ouer thy Argins and couered waies</L>
<L>Shal play vpon the bulwarks of thy hold</L>
<L>Volleies of ordinance til the breach be made,</L>
<L>That with his ruine fils vp all the trench.</L>
<L>And when we enter in, not heauen it selfe</L>
<L>Shall ransome thee, thy wife and family.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tech.</SPEAKER>
<L>Captaine, these Moores shall cut the leaden pipes,</L>
<L>That bring fresh water to thy men and thee,</L>
<L>And lie in trench before thy castle walles:</L>
<L>That no supply of victuall shall come in,</L>
<L>Nor issue foorth, but they shall die:</L>
<L>And therefore Captaine, yeeld it quietly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="62"/><FW><MILESTONE N="H5v"/></FW>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Were you that are the friends of Tamburlain</L>
<L>Brothers to holy Mahomet himselfe,</L>
<L>I would not yeeld it: therefore doo your worst.</L>
<L>Raise mounts, batter, intrench, and vndermine,</L>
<L>Cut off the water, all conuoies that can,</L>
<L>Yet I am resolute, and so farewell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ther.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pioners away, and where I stuck the stake,</L>
<L>Intrench with those dimensions I prescribed:</L>
<L>Cast vp the earth towards the castle wall,</L>
<L>Which til it may defend you, labour low:</L>
<L>And few or none shall perish by their shot.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pion.</SPEAKER>
<L>We will my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tech.</SPEAKER>
<L>A hundred horse shall scout about the plaines</L>
<L>To spie what force comes to relieue the holde.</L>
<L>Both we (theridamas) wil intrench our men,</L>
<L>And with the Iacobs staffe measure the height</L>
<L>And distance of the castle from the trench,</L>
<L>That we may know if our artillery</L>
<L>Will carie full point blancke vnto their wals.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ther.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then see the bringing of our ordinance</L>
<L>Along the trench into the battery,</L>
<L>Where we will haue Galions of sixe foot broad,</L>
<L>To saue our Cannoniers from musket shot,</L>
<L>Betwixt which, shall our ordinance thunder foorth,</L>
<L>And with the breaches fall, smoake, fire, and dust,</L>
<L>The cracke, the Ecchoe and the souldiers crie</L>
<L>Make deafe the aire, and dim the Christall Sky.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tech.</SPEAKER>
<L>Trumpets and drums, alarum presently,</L>
<L>And souldiers play the men, the holds is yours.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="scene" N="[4]">
<STAGE>Enter the Captaine with his wife and sonne.</STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="62"/><FW><MILESTONE N="H6r"/></FW>
<SPEAKER>Olym.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come good my Lord, &amp; let vs haste frō hence</L>
<L>Along the caue that leads beyond the foe,</L>
<L>No hope is left to saue this conquered hold.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>A deadly bullet gliding through my side,</L>
<L>Lies heauy on my heart, I cannot liue.</L>
<L>I feele my liuer pierc'd and all my vaines,</L>
<L>That there begin and nourish euery part,</L>
<L>Mangled and torne, and all my entrals bath'd</L>
<L>In blood that straineth from their orifex.</L>
<L>Farewell sweet wife, sweet son farewell, I die.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Olym.</SPEAKER>
<L>Death, whether art thou gone that both we liue:</L>
<L>Come back again (sweet death) &amp; strike vs both:</L>
<L>One minute end our daies, and one sepulcher</L>
<L>Containe our bodies: death, why comn'st thou not:</L>
<L>Wel, this must be the messenger for thee,</L>
<L>Now vgly death stretch out thy Sable wings,</L>
<L>And carie both our soules, where his remaines.</L>
<L>Tell me sweet boie, art thou content to die?</L>
<L>These barbarous Scythians full of cruelty,</L>
<L>And Moores, in whom was neuer pitie found,</L>
<L>Will hew vs peecemeale, put vs to the wheele,</L>
<L>Or els inuent some torture worse than that,</L>
<L>Therefore die by thy louing mothers hand,</L>
<L>Who gently now wil lance thy Iuory throat,</L>
<L>And quickly rid thee both of paine and life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Son.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mother dispatch me, or Ile kil my selfe,</L>
<L>For think ye I can liue, and see him dead:</L>
<L>Giue me your knife, good mother) or strike home:</L>
<L>The Scythiens shall not tyrannise on me.</L>
<L>Sweet mother strike, that I may meet my father.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>She stabs him.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Olym.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ah sacred Mahomet, if this be sin,</L>
<PB REF="63"/><FW><MILESTONE N="H6v"/></FW>
<L>Intreat a pardon of the God of heauen,</L>
<L>And purge my soule before it come to thee.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Entert Theridamas, Techelles and all their traine.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ther.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now Madam, what are you doing?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Olim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Killing my selfe, as I haue done my sonne,</L>
<L>Whose body with his fathers I haue burnt,</L>
<L>Least cruell Scythians should dismember him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tech.</SPEAKER>
<L>Twas brauely done, and like a souldiers wife,</L>
<L>Thou shalt with vs to <HI>Tamburlaine</HI> the great,</L>
<L>Who when he heares how resolute thou wert,</L>
<L>Wil match thee with a viceroy or a king.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Olym.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord deceast, was dearer vnto me,</L>
<L>Than any Viceroy, King or Emperour.</L>
<L>And for his sake here will I end my daies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ther.</SPEAKER>
<L>But Lady goe with vs to <HI>Tamburlaine,</HI></L>
<L>And thou shalt see a man greater <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="3 letters" RESP="murp" DISP="•••"/>n <HI>Mahomet.</HI></L>
<L>In whose high lookes is much more maiesty</L>
<L>Than from the Concaue superficies.</L>
<L>Of <HI>Ioues</HI> vast pallace the imperiall Orbe,</L>
<L>Vnto the shinining bower where <HI>Cynthia</HI> sits,</L>
<L>Like louely thetis in a Christall robe,</L>
<L>That treadeth Fortune vnderneath his feete,</L>
<L>And makes the mighty God of armes his slaue:</L>
<L>On whom death and the fatall sisters waite,</L>
<L>With naked swords and scarlet liueries:</L>
<L>Before whom (mounted on a Lions backe)</L>
<L><HI>Rhammusia</HI> beares a helmet ful of blood,</L>
<L>And strowes the way with braines of slaughtered men▪</L>
<L>By whose proud side the vgly furies run.</L>
<PB REF="63"/><FW><MILESTONE N="H7r"/></FW>
<L>Harkening when he shall bid them plague the world,</L>
<L>Ouer whose zenith cloth'd in windy aire,</L>
<L>And Eagles wings ioin'd to her feathered breast,</L>
<L>Fame houereth, sounding of her golden Trumpe:</L>
<L>That to the aduerse poles of that straight line,</L>
<L>Which measureth the glorious frame of heauen,</L>
<L>The name of mightie <HI>Tamburlain</HI> is spread:</L>
<L>And him faire Lady shall thy eies behold. Come.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Olim</SPEAKER>
<L>Take pitie of a Ladies ruthfull teares,</L>
<L>That humbly craues vpon her knees to stay,</L>
<L>And cast her bodie in the burning flame,</L>
<L>That feeds vpon her sonnes and husbands flesh.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tech.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, sooner shall fire consume vs both,</L>
<L>Then scortch a face so beautiful as this.</L>
<L>In frame of which, Nature hath shewed more skill,</L>
<L>Than when she ga<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" RESP="murp" DISP="•"/>e eternall <HI>Chaos</HI> forme,</L>
<L>Drawing from it the shining Lamps of heauen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ther.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, I am so far in loue with you,</L>
<L>That you must goe with vs, no remedy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Olim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then carie me I care not where you will,</L>
<L>And let the end of this my fatall iourney,</L>
<L>Be likewise end to my accursed life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tech.</SPEAKER>
<L>No Madam, but the beginning of your ioy,</L>
<L>Come willinglie, therfore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ther.</SPEAKER>
<L>Souldiers now let vs meet the Generall,</L>
<L>Who by this time is at <HI>Natolia,</HI></L>
<L>Ready to charge the army of the Turke.</L>
<L>The gold, the siluer, and the pearle ye got,</L>
<L>Rifling this Fort, deuide in equall shares:</L>
<L>This Lady shall haue twice so much againe,</L>
<L>Out of the coffers of our treasurie.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="5" TYPE="scene">
<PB REF="64"/><FW><MILESTONE N="H7v"/></FW>
<HEAD>Actus: 3. Scaena. 5.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Callepine, Orcanes, Ierusalem, Trebizon, Soria; Al∣meda; with their traine.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Messenger.</SPEAKER>
<L>REnowmed Emperour, mighty <HI>Callepine,</HI></L>
<L>Gods great lieftenant ouer all the world:</L>
<L>Here at <HI>Alepo</HI> with an hoste of men</L>
<L>Lies <HI>Tamburlaine,</HI> this king of <HI>Persea:</HI></L>
<L>In number more than are the quyuering leaues</L>
<L>Of <HI>Idas</HI> forrest, where your highnesse hounds,</L>
<L>With open crie pursues the wounded Stag:</L>
<L>Who meanes to gyrt <HI>Natolias</HI> walles with siege,</L>
<L>Fire the towne and ouerrun the land.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>My royal army is as great as his,</L>
<L>That from the bounds of <HI>Phrigia</HI> to the sea</L>
<L>Which washeth <HI>Cyprus</HI> with his brinish waues,</L>
<L>Couers the hils, the valleies and the plaines.</L>
<L>Viceroies and Peeres of Turky play the men,</L>
<L>Whet all your swords to mangle <HI>Tamburlain</HI></L>
<L>His sonnes, his Captaines and his followers,</L>
<L>By <HI>Mahomet</HI> not one of them shal liue.</L>
<L>The field wherin this battaile shall be fought,</L>
<L>For euer, terme, the Perseans sepulchre,</L>
<L>In memorie of this our victory.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Orc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now, he that cals himself the scourge of <HI>Ioue,</HI></L>
<L>The Emperour of the world, and earthly God,</L>
<L>Shal end the warlike progresse he intends,</L>
<L>And traueile hedlong to the lake of hell:</L>
<L>Where legions of deuils knowing he must die</L>
<PB REF="64"/><FW><MILESTONE N="H8r"/></FW>
<L>Here in <HI>Natolia,</HI> by your highnesse hands)</L>
<L>All brandishing their brands of quenchlesse fire,</L>
<L>Streching their monstrous pawes, grin with their teeth.</L>
<L>And guard the gates to entertaine his soule.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tel me Viceroies the number of your men,</L>
<L>And what our Army royall is esteem'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<L>From <HI>Palestina</HI> and <HI>Ierusalem,</HI></L>
<L>Of Hebrewes, three score thousand fighting men</L>
<L>Are come since last we shewed your maiesty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Orc.</SPEAKER>
<L>So from <HI>Arabia</HI> desart, and the bounds</L>
<L>Of that sweet land, whose braue Metropolis</L>
<L>Reedified the faire <HI>Semyramis,</HI></L>
<L>Came forty thousand warlike foot and horse,</L>
<L>Since last we numbred to your Maiesty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>treb.</SPEAKER>
<L>From <HI>trebizon</HI> in <HI>Asia</HI> the lesse,</L>
<L>Naturalized Turks and stout Bythinians</L>
<L>Came to my bands full fifty thousand more,</L>
<L>That fighting, knowes not what retreat doth meane,</L>
<L>Nor ere returne but with the victory,</L>
<L>Since last we numbred to your maiesty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Of Sorians from <HI>Halla</HI> is repair'd</L>
<L>And neighbor cities of your highnesse land,</L>
<L>Ten thousand horse, and thirty thousand foot,</L>
<L>Since last we numbred to your maiestie:</L>
<L>So that the Army royall is esteem'd</L>
<L>Six hundred thousand valiant fighting men.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Callep.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then welcome Tamburlaine vnto thy death.</L>
<L>Come puissant Viceroies, let vs to the field,</L>
<L>(The Perseans Sepulchre) and sacrifice</L>
<L>Mountaines of breathlesse men to <HI>Mahomet.</HI></L>
<PB REF="65"/><FW><MILESTONE N="H8v"/></FW>
<L>Who now with <HI>Ioue</HI> opens the firmament,</L>
<L>To see the slaughter of our enemies.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="2:1 (recte 3:5 cont.)" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Actus. 2. Scaena. 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Tamburlaine with his three sonnes, Vsumeasane with other.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>HOw now <HI>Casane?</HI> See a knot of kings,</L>
<L>Sitting as if they were a telling tidles.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vsu.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, your presence makes them pale and wan.</L>
<L>Poore soules they looke as if their deaths were neere.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, so he is <HI>Casane,</HI> I am here,</L>
<L>But yet Ile sane their liues and make them slaues.</L>
<L>Ye petty kings of Turkye I am come,</L>
<L>As <HI>Hector</HI> did into the Grecian campe.</L>
<L>To ouerdare the pride of <HI>Groecia.</HI></L>
<L>And set his warlike petson to the view</L>
<L>Of fierce <HI>Achilles,</HI> riuall of his fame,</L>
<L>I doe you honor in the <HI>simile.</HI></L>
<L>For if I should as <HI>Hector</HI> did <HI>Achilles,</HI></L>
<L>(The worthiest knight that euer brandishe sword)</L>
<L>Challenge in combat any of you all,</L>
<L>I see how fearfully ye would refuse,</L>
<L>And fly my gloue as from a Scorpion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Orc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now thou art fearfull of thy armies strength,</L>
<L>Thou wouldst with ouer match of person fight,</L>
<L>But Shepheards issue, base borne <HI>tamburlaine,</HI></L>
<L>Thinke of thy end, this sword shall lance thy throat.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Villain, the shepheards issue, at whose byrth</L>
<PB REF="65"/><FW><MILESTONE N="I1r"/></FW>
<L>Heauen did affoord a gratious aspect,</L>
<L>And ioin'd those stars that shall be opposite,</L>
<L>Euen till the dissolution of the world;</L>
<L>And neuer meant to make a Conquerour;</L>
<L>So famous as is mighty <HI>Tamburlain:</HI></L>
<L>Shall so torment thee and that <HI>Callapine,</HI></L>
<L>That like a roguish runnaway, suborn'd</L>
<L>That villaine there, that slaue, that Turkish dog,</L>
<L>To false his seruice to his Soueraigne,</L>
<L>As ye shal curse the byrth of <HI>Tamburlaine.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Raile not proud Scythian, I shall now reuenge</L>
<L>My fathers vile abuses and mine owne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<L>By <HI>Mahomet</HI> he shal be tied in chaines,</L>
<L>Rowing with Christians in a Brigandine,</L>
<L>About the Grecian Isses to rob and spoile:</L>
<L>And turne him to his ancient trade againe.</L>
<L>Me thinks the slaue should make a lusty theefe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, when the battaile ends, al we wil meet,</L>
<L>And sit in councell to inuent some paine,</L>
<L>That most may vex his body and his soule:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sirha, <HI>Callapine,</HI> Ile hang a clogge about
your necke for running away againe, you shall not trou∣ble me thus to come and fetch you.</P>
<L>But as for you (Viceroy) you shal haue bits,</L>
<L>And harnest like my horses, draw my coch:</L>
<L>And when ye stay, be lasht with whips of wier,</L>
<L>Ile haue you learne to feed on prouander,</L>
<L>And in a stable lie vpon the planks:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Orc.</SPEAKER>
<L>But <HI>Tamburlaine,</HI> first thou shalt kneele to vs</L>
<L>And humbly craue a pardon for thy life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>treb.</SPEAKER>
<L>The common souldiers of our mighty hoste</L>
<L>Shal bring thee bound vnto the Generals tent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="66"/><FW><MILESTONE N="I1v"/></FW>
<SPEAKER>Sor.</SPEAKER>
<L>And all haue iointly sworne thy cruell death,</L>
<L>Or bind thee in eternall torments wrath.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wel sirs, diet your selues, you knowe I shall haue occasion shortly to iourney you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<P>See father, how <HI>Almeda</HI> the Iaylor lookes vpon vs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Villaine, traitor, damned fugitiue,</L>
<L>Ile make thee wish the earth had swallowed thee:</L>
<L>Seest thou not death within my wrathfull looks.</L>
<L>Goe villaine, cast thee headlong from a rock,</L>
<L>Or rip thy bowels, and rend out thy heart,</L>
<L>T'appease my wrath, or els Ile torture thee,</L>
<L>Searing thy hatefull flesh with burning yrons,</L>
<L>And drops of scalding lead, while all thy ioints</L>
<L>Be rackt and beat asunder with the wheele,</L>
<L>For if thou liuest, not any Element</L>
<L>Shal shrowde thee from the wrath of <HI>tamburlaine</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wel, in despight of thee he shall be king:</L>
<L>Come <HI>Almeda,</HI> receiue this crowne of me,</L>
<L>I here inuest thee king of <HI>Ariadan,</HI></L>
<L>Bordering on <HI>Mare Roso</HI> neere to <HI>Meca.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Or.</SPEAKER>
<P>What, take it man.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good my Lord, let me take it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doost thou aske him leaue: Hēre, take it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Go too sirha, take your crown, and make vp the halfe dozen.</L>
<L>So sirha, now you are a king you must giue armes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Or.</SPEAKER>
<P>So he shal, and we are thy head in his Scutchion:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tamb.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, let him hang a bunch of keies on his stan∣derd, to put him in remembrance he was a Iailor, that when I take him, I may knocke out his braines with them, and lock you in the stable, when you shall come
<PB REF="66"/><FW><MILESTONE N="I2r"/></FW>
sweating from my chariot.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>treb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Away, let vs to the field, that the villaine may be slaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tamb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sirha, prepare whips, and bring my chariot to my Tent: For as soone as the battaile is done, Ile ride in triumph through the Camp.</P>
<STAGE>Enter Theridamas, Techelles and their traine.</STAGE>
<L>How now ye pety kings, loe, here are Bugges</L>
<L>Wil make the haire stand vpright on your heads,</L>
<L>And cast your crownes in slauery at their feet.</L>
<L>Welcome theridamas and techelles both,</L>
<L>See ye this rout, and know ye this same king:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ther.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, my Lord, he was <HI>Calapines</HI> keeper.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wel, now you see hee is a king, looke to him theridamas, when we are fighting, least hee hide his crowne as the foolish king of <HI>Persea</HI> did.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sor.</SPEAKER>
<P>No <HI>Tamburlaine,</HI> hee shall not be put to that Exigent, I warrant thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>You knowe not sir:</L>
<L>But now my followers and my louing friends,</L>
<L>Fight as you euer did, like Conquerours,</L>
<L>The glorie of this happy day is yours:</L>
<L>My sterne aspect shall make faire Victory,</L>
<L>Houering betwixt our armies, light on me,</L>
<L>Loden with Lawrell wreathes to crowne vs all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tech.</SPEAKER>
<L>I smile to think, how when this field is fought,</L>
<L>And rich <HI>Natolia</HI> ours, our men shall sweat</L>
<L>With carrieng pearle and treasure on their backes,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall be princes all immediatly:</L>
<L>Come fight ye Turks, or yeeld vs victory.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Or.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, we wil meet thee slauish <HI>tāburlain.</HI></L>
<STAGE>Exeunt</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="67"/><FW><MILESTONE N="I2v"/></FW>
<HEAD>Actus. 4.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scaena. 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Alarme: Amyras and Celebinus, issues from the tent where Caliphas sits a sleepe.</STAGE>
<L>NOw in their glories shine the golden crownes</L>
<L>Of these proud Turks, much like so many suns</L>
<L>That halfe dismay the maiesty of heauen:</L>
<L>Now brother follow we our fathers sword,</L>
<L>That flies with fury swifter than our thoughts,</L>
<L>And cuts down armies with his conquerings wings,</L>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Call foorth our laisie brother from the tent,</L>
<L>For if my father misse him in the field,</L>
<L>Wrath kindled in the furnace of his breast,</L>
<L>Wil send a deadly lightening to his heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Brother, ho, what, giuen so much to sleep</L>
<L>You cannot leaue it, when our enemies drums</L>
<L>And ratling cannons thunder in our eares</L>
<L>Our proper ruine, and our fathers foile:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away ye fools, my father needs not me,</L>
<L>Nor you in faith, but that you wil be thought</L>
<L>More childish valourous than manly wise:</L>
<L>If halfe our campe should sit and sleepe with me,</L>
<L>My father ware enough to scar the foe:</L>
<L>You doo dishonor to his maiesty,</L>
<L>To think our helps will doe him any good.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amy.</SPEAKER>
<L>What, dar'st thou then be absent frō the fight,</L>
<L>Knowing my father hates thy cowardise,</L>
<L>And oft hath warn'd thee to be stil in field,</L>
<L>When he himselfe amidst the thickest troopes</L>
<L>Beats downe our foes to flesh our taintlesse swords.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know sir, what it is to kil a man,</L>
<PB REF="67"/><FW><MILESTONE N="I3r"/></FW>
<L>It works remorse of conscience in me,</L>
<L>I take no pleasure to be murtherous,</L>
<L>Nor care for blood when wine wil quench my thirst.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>O cowardly boy, fie for shame, come foorth.</L>
<L>Thou doost dishonor manhood, and thy house.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe, goe tall stripling, fight you for vs both,</L>
<L>And take my other toward brother here,</L>
<L>For person like to prooue a second <HI>Mars,</HI></L>
<L>Twill please my mind as wel to heare both you</L>
<L>Haue won a heape of honor in the field,</L>
<L>And left your slender carkasses behind,</L>
<L>As if I lay with you for company.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amy.</SPEAKER>
<L>You wil not goe then:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal</SPEAKER>
<L>You say true.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Were all the lofty mounts of <HI>Zona mundi,</HI></L>
<L>That fill the midst of farthest <HI>Tartary,</HI></L>
<L>Turn'd into pearle and proffered for my stay,</L>
<L>I would not bide the furie of my father:</L>
<L>When made a victor in these hautie arms.</L>
<L>He comes and findes his sonnes haue had no shares</L>
<L>In all the honors he proposde for vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take you the honor, I will take my ease,</L>
<L>My wisedome shall excuse my cowardise:</L>
<L>I goe into the field before I need:</L>
<STAGE>Alarme, and Amy, and Celeb. run in.</STAGE>
<L>The bullets fly at random where they list.</L>
<L>And should I goe and kill a thousand men,</L>
<L>I were as soone rewarded with a shot,</L>
<L>And sooner far than he that neuer fights.</L>
<L>And should I goe and do nor harme nor good,</L>
<L>I might haue harme, which all the good I haue</L>
<L>Ioin'd with my fathers crowne would neuer cure.</L>
<PB REF="68"/><FW><MILESTONE N="I3v"/></FW>
<L>Ile to cardes: <HI>Perdicas.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perd.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come, thou and I wil goe to cardes to driue away the time.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<P>Content my Lord, but what shal we play for?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who shal kisse the fairest of the Turkes Con∣cubines first, when my father hath conquered them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<P>Agreed yfaith.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>They play.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<P>They say I am a coward, <HI>(Perdicas)</HI> and I feare as litle their <HI>tara, tantaras,</HI> their swordes or their cannons, as I doe a naked Lady in a net of golde, and for feare I should be affraid, would put it off and come to bed with me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<P>Such a feare (my Lord) would neuer make yee retire.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<P>I would my father would let me be put in the front of such a battaile once, to trie my valour.</P>
<STAGE>Alarme.</STAGE>
<P>What a coyle they keepe, I beleeue there will be some hurt done anon amongst them.</P>
<STAGE>Enter Tamburlain, Theridamas, Techelles, Vsu∣measane, Amyras, Celebinus, leading the Turkish kings.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>See now ye slaues, my childrē stoops your pride</L>
<L>And leads your glories sheep-like to the sword.</L>
<L>Bring them my boyes, and tel me if the warres</L>
<L>Be not a life that may illustrate Gods,</L>
<L>And tickle not your Spirits with desire</L>
<L>Stil to be train'd in armes and chiualry:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shal we let goe these kings again my Lord</L>
<L>To gather greater numbers gainst our power,</L>
<L>That they may say, it is not chance doth this,</L>
<PB REF="68"/><FW><MILESTONE N="I4r"/></FW>
<L>But matchlesse strength and magnanimity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, no <HI>Amyras,</HI> tempt not Fortune so,</L>
<L>Cherish thy valour stil with fresh supplies:</L>
<L>And glut it not with stale and daunted foes,</L>
<L>But wher's this coward, villaine, not my sonne,</L>
<L>But traitor to my name and maiesty.</L>
<STAGE>He goes in and brings him out.</STAGE>
<L>Image of sloth, and and picture of a slaue,</L>
<L>The obloquie and skorne of my renowne,</L>
<L>How may my hart, thus fired with mine eies,</L>
<L>Wounded with shame, and kill'd with discontent,</L>
<L>Shrowd any thought may holde my striuing hands</L>
<L>From martiall iustice on thy wretched soule.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ther.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet pardon him I pray your Maiesty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tech. &amp; Vsu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let al of vs intreat your highnesse par∣don</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stand vp, ye base vnworthy souldiers,</L>
<L>Know ye not yet the argument of Armes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good my Lord, let him be forgiuen for once,</L>
<L>And we wil force him to the field hereafter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stand vp my boyes, and I wil teach ye arms,</L>
<L>And what the iealousie of warres must doe.</L>
<L>O <HI>Samarcanda,</HI> where I breathed first,</L>
<L>And ioy'd the fire of this martiall flesh,</L>
<L>Blush, blush faire citie, at thine honors foile,</L>
<L>And shame of nature with <HI>Iaertis</HI> streame,</L>
<L>Embracing thee with deepest of his loue,</L>
<L>Can neuer wash from thy distained browes.</L>
<L>Here <HI>Ioue,</HI> receiue his fainting soule againe,</L>
<L>A Forme not meet to giue that subiect essence,</L>
<L>Whose matter is the flesh of <HI>Tamburlain,</HI></L>
<L>Wherein an incorporeall spirit mooues,</L>
<L>Made of the mould whereof of thy selfe consists.</L>
<PB REF="69"/><FW><MILESTONE N="I4v"/></FW>
<L>Which makes me valiant, proud, ambitious,</L>
<L>Ready to leuie power against thy throne,</L>
<L>That I might mooue the turning Spheares of heauē,</L>
<L>For earth and al this aery region</L>
<L>Cannot containe the state of <HI>Tamburlaine.</HI></L>
<L>By <HI>Mahomet,</HI> thy mighty friend I sweare,</L>
<L>In sending to my issue such a soule,</L>
<L>Created of the massy dregges of earth,</L>
<L>The scum and tartar of the Elements,</L>
<L>Wherein was neither corrage, strength or wit,</L>
<L>But follie, sloth, and damned idlenesse:</L>
<L>Thou hast procur'd a greater enemie,</L>
<L>Than he that darted mountaines at thy head.</L>
<L>Shaking the burthen mighty <HI>Atlas</HI> beares:</L>
<L>Whereat thou trembling hid'st thee in the aire.</L>
<L>Cloth'd with a pitchy cloud for being seene.</L>
<L>And now ye cankred curres of <HI>Asia,</HI></L>
<L>That will not see the strength of <HI>Tamburlaine,</HI></L>
<L>Although it shine as brightly as the Sun.</L>
<L>Now you shal feele the strength of <HI>Tamburlain,</HI></L>
<L>And by the state of his supremacie,</L>
<L>Approoue the difference twixt himself and you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Orc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou shewest the difference twixt our selues and thee.</L>
<L>In this thy barbarous damned tyranny.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy victories are growne so violent,</L>
<L>That shortly heauen, fild with the meteors</L>
<L>Of blood and fire thy tyrannies haue made,</L>
<L>Will poure down blood and fire on thy head:</L>
<L>Whose scalding drops wil pierce thy seething braines,</L>
<L>And with our bloods, reuenge our bloods on thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Villaines, these terrours and these tyrannies</L>
<PB REF="69"/><FW><MILESTONE N="I5r"/></FW>
<L>(If tyrannies wars iustice ye repute)</L>
<L>I execute, enioin'd me from aboue:</L>
<L>To scourge the pride of such as heauen abhors,</L>
<L>Nor am I made Arch-monark of the world,</L>
<L>Crown'd and inuested by the hand of <HI>Ioue,</HI></L>
<L>For deeds of bounty or nobility:</L>
<L>But since I exercise a greater name,</L>
<L>The Scourge of God and terrour of the world,</L>
<L>I must apply my selfe to fit those tearnies,</L>
<L>In war, in blood, in death, in crueltie,</L>
<L>And plague such Pesants as resisting me,</L>
<L>The power of heauens eternall maiesty.</L>
<L><HI>Theridamas, techelles,</HI> and <HI>Casane,</HI></L>
<L>Ransacke the tents and the pauilions</L>
<L>Of these proud Turks, and take their Concubines.</L>
<L>Making them burie this effeminate brat,</L>
<L>For not a common Souldier shall defile</L>
<L>His manly fingers with so faint a boy.</L>
<L>Then bring those Turkish harlots to my tent,</L>
<L>And Ile dispose them as it likes me best,</L>
<L>Meane while take him in.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soul.</SPEAKER>
<L>We will my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier</SPEAKER>
<L>O damned monster, nay a Feend of Hell,</L>
<L>Whose cruelties are not so harsh as thine,</L>
<L>Nor yet imposo, with such a bitter hate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Orc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Reuenge it <HI>Radamanth</HI> and Eacus,</L>
<L>And let your hates extended in his paines,</L>
<L>Expell the hate wherewith he paines our soules.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>treb.</SPEAKER>
<L>May neuer day giue vertue to his eies,</L>
<L>Whose sight composde of furie and of fire</L>
<L>Doth send such sterne affections to his heart,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sor.</SPEAKER>
<L>May neuer spirit, vaine or Artier feed</L>
<PB REF="70"/><FW><MILESTONE N="I5v"/></FW>
<L>The cursed substance of that cruel heart,</L>
<L>But (wanting moisture and remorsefull blood)</L>
<L>Drie vp with anger, and consume with heat.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wel, bark ye dogs, Ile bridle al your tongues</L>
<L>And bind them close with bits of burnisht steele,</L>
<L>Downe to the channels of your hatefull throats,</L>
<L>And with the paines my rigour shall inflict,</L>
<L>Ile make ye roare, that earth may eccho foorth</L>
<L>The far resounding torments ye sustaine,</L>
<L>As when an heard of lusty Cymbrian Buls,</L>
<L>Run mourning round about, the Femals misse,</L>
<L>And stung with furie of their following,</L>
<L>Fill all the aire with troublous bellowing:</L>
<L>I will with Engines, neuer exercisde,</L>
<L>Conquer, sacke, and vtterly consume</L>
<L>Your cities and your golden pallaces,</L>
<L>And with the flames that beat against the clowdes</L>
<L>Incense the heauens. and make the starres to melt,</L>
<L>As if they were the teares of <HI>Mahomet</HI></L>
<L>For hot consumption of his countries pride:</L>
<L>And til by viston, or by speach I heare</L>
<L>Immortall <HI>Ioue</HI> say, Cease my <HI>Tamburlaine,</HI></L>
<L>I will persist a terrour to the world,</L>
<L>Making the Meteors, that like armed men</L>
<L>Are seene to march vpon the towers of heauen,</L>
<L>Run tilting round about the firmament,</L>
<L>And breake their burming Lances in the aire,</L>
<L>For honor of my woondrous victories.</L>
<L>Come bring them in to our Pauilion.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="3 (recte 2)" TYPE="scene">
<PB REF="70"/><FW><MILESTONE N="I6r"/></FW>
<HEAD>Actus. 4. Scaena. 3,</HEAD>
<STAGE>Olympia alone.</STAGE>
<L>DIstrest <HI>Olympia,</HI> whose weeping eies</L>
<L>Since thy arriuall here beheld no Sun,</L>
<L>But closde within the compasse of a tent,</L>
<L>Hath stain'd thy cheekes, &amp; made thee look like death</L>
<L>Deuise some meanes to rid thee of thy life.</L>
<L>Rather than yeeld to his detested suit,</L>
<L>Whose drift is onely to dishonor thee.</L>
<L>And since this earth, dew'd with thy brinish teares,</L>
<L>Affoords no hearbs, whose taste may poison thee,</L>
<L>Nor yet this aier, beat often with thy sighes,</L>
<L>Contagious smels, and vapors to infect thee,</L>
<L>Nor thy close Caue a sword to murther thee,</L>
<L>Let this inuention be the instrument.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Theridamas.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>The.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wel met <HI>Olympia,</HI> I sought thee in my tent</L>
<L>But when I saw the place obscure and darke,</L>
<L>Which with thy beauty thou wast woont to light,</L>
<L>Enrag'd, I ran about the fields for thee,</L>
<L>Supposing, amorous <HI>Ioue</HI> had sent his sonne,</L>
<L>The winged <HI>Hermes,</HI> to conuay thee hence:</L>
<L>But now I finde thee, and that feare is past.</L>
<L>Tell me <HI>Olympia,</HI> wilt thou graunt my suit?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Olym.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord and husbandes death, with my sweete sons,</L>
<L>With whom I buried al affections,</L>
<L>Saue griefe and sorrow which torment my heart,</L>
<L>Forbids my mind to entertaine a thought</L>
<L>That tends to loue, but meditate on death,</L>
<PB REF="71"/><FW><MILESTONE N="I6v"/></FW>
<L>A fitter subiect for a pensiue soule.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ther.</SPEAKER>
<L>Olympia, pitie him, in whom thy looks</L>
<L>Haue greater operation and more force</L>
<L>Than Cynthias in the watery wildernes,</L>
<L>For with thy view my ioyes are at the full,</L>
<L>And eb againe, as thou departst from me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Olim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ah, pity me my Lord, and draw your sword,</L>
<L>Making a passage for my troubled soule,</L>
<L>Which beates against this prison to get out,</L>
<L>And meet my husband and my louing sonne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ther.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nothing, but stil thy husband and thy sonne?</L>
<L>Leaue this my Loue, and listen more to me,</L>
<L>Thou shalt be stately Queene of faire Argier,</L>
<L>And cloth'd in costly cloath of massy gold,</L>
<L>Vpon the marble turrets of my Court</L>
<L>Sit like to Venus in her chaire of state,</L>
<L>Commanding all thy princely eie desires,</L>
<L>And I will cast off armes and sit with thee,</L>
<L>Spending my life in sweet discourse of loue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Olym.</SPEAKER>
<L>No such discourse is pleasant in mine eaxes,</L>
<L>But that where euery period ends with death,</L>
<L>And euery line begins with death againe:</L>
<L>I cannot loue to be an Emperesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ther.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay Lady, then if nothing wil preuaile,</L>
<L>Ile vse some other means to make you yeeld,</L>
<L>Such is the sodaine fury of my loue,</L>
<L>I must and wil be pleasde, and you shall yeeld:</L>
<L>Come to the tent againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Olym.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay good my Lord, and wil you saue my honor,</L>
<L>Ile giue your Grace a present of such price,</L>
<L>As all the world cannot affoord the like.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ther.</SPEAKER>
<L>What is it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="71"/><FW><MILESTONE N="I7r"/></FW>
<SPEAKER>Olym.</SPEAKER>
<L>An ointment which a cunning Alcumist</L>
<L>Distilled from the purest Balsamum,</L>
<L>And simplest extracts of all Minerals,</L>
<L>In which the essentiall fourme of Marble stone,</L>
<L>Tempered by science metaphisicall,</L>
<L>And Spels of magicke from the mouthes of spirits,</L>
<L>With which if you but noint your tender Skin,</L>
<L>Nor Pistol, Sword, nor Lance can pierce your flesh.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ther.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why Madam, thinke ye to mocke me thus palpably?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Olim.</SPEAKER>
<L>To prooue it, I wil noint my naked throat,</L>
<L>Which when you stab, looke on your weapons point,</L>
<L>And you shall se't rebated with the blow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ther.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why gaue you not your husband some of it, if you loued him, and it so precious?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Olym.</SPEAKER>
<L>My purpose was (my Lord) to spend it so,</L>
<L>But was preuented by his sodaine end.</L>
<L>And for a present easie proofe hereof,</L>
<L>That I dissemble not, trie it on me,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ther.</SPEAKER>
<L>I wil <HI>Olympia,</HI> and will keep it for</L>
<L>The richest present of this Easterne world.</L>
<STAGE>She noints her throat.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Olym.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now stab my Lord, and mark your weapons point</L>
<L>That wil be blunted if the blow be great.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ther.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here then <HI>Olympia.</HI></L>
<L>What, haue I slaine her? Villaine, stab thy selfe:</L>
<L>Cut off this arme that murthered my Loue:</L>
<L>In whom the learned Rabies of this age,</L>
<L>Might find as many woondrous myracles,</L>
<L>As in the Theoria of the world.</L>
<L>Now Hell is fairer than <HI>Elisian,</HI></L>
<L>A greater Lamp than that bright eie of heauen,</L>
<PB REF="72"/><FW><MILESTONE N="I7v"/></FW>
<L>From whence the starres doo borrow all their light</L>
<L>Wanders about the black circumference,</L>
<L>And now the damned soules are free from paine,</L>
<L>For euery Fury gazeth on her lookes:</L>
<L>Infernall <HI>Dis</HI> is courting of my Loue,</L>
<L>Inuenting maskes and stately showes for her,</L>
<L>Opening the doores of his rich treasorie,</L>
<L>To entertaine this Queene of chastitie,</L>
<L>Whose body shall be comb'd with all the pompe</L>
<L>The treasure of my kingdome may affoord.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit, taking her away.</STAGE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="4 (recte 3)" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Actus. 4. Scaena. 4.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Tamburlaine drawen in his chariot by Trebizon and Soria with bittes in their mouthes, reines in his left hand, in his right hād a whip, with which he scourgeth them, Techelles, Theridamas, Vsu∣measane, Amyras, Celebinus: Natolia, and Ieru∣salem led by with fiue or six common souldiers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>HOlla, ye pampered Iades of <HI>Asia:</HI></L>
<L>What, can ye draw but twenty miles a day,</L>
<L>And haue so proud a chariot at your heeles,</L>
<L>And such a Coachman as great <HI>Tamburlaine?</HI></L>
<L>But from <HI>Asphaltis,</HI> where I conquer'd you,</L>
<L>To <HI>Byron</HI> here where thus I honor you:</L>
<L>The horse that guide the golden cie of heauen,</L>
<L>And blow the morning from their nosterils,</L>
<L>Making their fiery gate aboue the cloudes,</L>
<L>Are not so honoured in their Gouernour,</L>
<L>As you (ye slaues) in mighty <HI>Tamburlain.</HI></L>
<L>The headstrong Iades of <HI>Thrace, Alcides</HI> tam'd,</L>
<PB REF="72"/><FW><MILESTONE N="I8r"/></FW>
<L>That King <HI>Egeus</HI> fed with humaine flesh,</L>
<L>And made so wanton that they knew their strengths,</L>
<L>Were not subdew'd with valour more diuine,</L>
<L>Than you by this vnconquered arme of mine.</L>
<L>To make you fierce, and fit my appetite,</L>
<L>You shal be fed with flesh as raw as blood,</L>
<L>And drinke in pailes the strongest Muscadell:</L>
<L>If you can liue with it, then liue, and draw</L>
<L>My chariot swifter than the racking cloudes:</L>
<L>If not, then dy like beasts, and fit for nought</L>
<L>But perches for the black and fatall Rauens.</L>
<L>Thus am I right the Scourge of highest <HI>Ioue,</HI></L>
<L>And see the figure of my dignitie,</L>
<L>By which I hold my name and maiesty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ami.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me haue coach my Lord, that I may ride,</L>
<L>And thus be drawen with these two idle kings.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy youth for bids such ease my kingly boy,</L>
<L>They shall to morrow draw my chariot,</L>
<L>While these their fellow kings may be refresht,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Orc.</SPEAKER>
<L>O thou that swaiest the region vnder earth,</L>
<L>And art a king as absolute as <HI>Ioue,</HI></L>
<L>Come as thou didst in fruitfull Scicilie,</L>
<L>Suruaieng all the glories of the land:</L>
<L>And as thou took'st the faire <HI>Proserpina,</HI></L>
<L>Ioying the fruit of <HI>Ceres</HI> garden plot,</L>
<L>For loue, for honor, and to make het Queene,</L>
<L>So for iust hate, for shame, and to subdew</L>
<L>This proud contemner of thy dreadfull power,</L>
<L>Come once in furie and suruay his pride,</L>
<L>Haling him headlong to the lowest hell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ther.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Maiesty must get some byts for these,</L>
<L>To bridle their contemptuous cursing tongues,</L>
<PB REF="73"/><FW><MILESTONE N="I8v"/></FW>
<L>That like vnruly neuer broken Iades,</L>
<L>Breake through the hedges of their hateful mouthes,</L>
<L>And passe their fixed boundes exceedingly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tech.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, we wil break the hedges of their mouths</L>
<L>And pul their kicking colts out of their pastures,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vsu</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Maiesty already hath deuisde</L>
<L>A meane, as fit as may be to restraine</L>
<L>These coltish coach-horse tongues from blasphemy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>How like you that sir king? why speak you not?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ah cruel Brat, sprung from a tyrants loines,</L>
<L>How like his cursed father he begins,</L>
<L>To practize tauntes and bitter tyrannies?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>I Turke, I tel thee, this same Boy is he,</L>
<L>That must (aduaunst in higher pompe than this)</L>
<L>Rifle the kingdomes I shall leaue vnsackt.</L>
<L>If Ioue esteeming me too good for earth,</L>
<L>Raise me to match the faire Aldeboran,</L>
<L>Aboue the threefold Astracisme of heauen,</L>
<L>Before I conquere all the triple world.</L>
<L>New fetch me out the Turkish Concubines,</L>
<L>I will prefer them for the funerall</L>
<L>They haue bestowed on my abortiue sonne.</L>
<STAGE>The Cōncubines are brought in.</STAGE>
<L>Where are my common souldiers now that fought</L>
<L>So Lion-like vpon Asphaltis plaines?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold ye tal souldiers, take ye Queens apeece</L>
<L>(I meane such Queens as were kings Concubines)</L>
<L>Take them, deuide them and their iewels too,</L>
<L>And let them equally serue all your turnes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soul.</SPEAKER>
<L>We thank your maiesty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Brawle not (I warne yon for your lechery,</L>
<PB REF="73"/><FW><MILESTONE N="K1r"/></FW>
<L>For euery man that so offends shall die,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ore.</SPEAKER>
<L>Iniurious tyrant, wilt thou so defame</L>
<L>The hatefull fortunes of thy victory,</L>
<L>To exercise vpon such guiltlesse Dames,</L>
<L>The violence of thy common Souldiours lust.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Liue content then (ye slaues) and meet not me</L>
<L>With troopes of harlots at your sloothful heeles</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lad.</SPEAKER>
<L>O pity vs my Lord, and saue our honours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are ye not gone ye villaines with your spoiles?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>They run away with the Ladies.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<L>O mercilesse infernall cruelty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Saue your honours? twere but time indeed,</L>
<L>Lost long before you knew what honour meant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ther.</SPEAKER>
<L>It seemes they meant to conquer vs my Lord,</L>
<L>And make vs ieasting Pageants for their Trulles.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>And now themselues shal make our Pageant,</L>
<L>And common souldiers iest with all their Truls,</L>
<L>Let them take pleasure soundly in their spoiles,</L>
<L>Till we prepare our martch to <HI>Babylon,</HI></L>
<L>Whether we next make expedition.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tech.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let vs not be idle then my Lord,</L>
<L>But presently be prest to conquer it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>We wil <HI>techelles,</HI> forward then ye Iades:</L>
<L>Now crowch ye kings of greatest <HI>Asia,</HI></L>
<L>And tremble when ye heare this Scourge wil come,</L>
<L>That whips downe cities, and controwleth crownes,</L>
<L>Adding their wealth and treasure to my store,</L>
<L>The Euxine sea North to <HI>Natolia,</HI></L>
<L>The Terrene west, the Caspian north north-east,</L>
<L>And on the south <HI>Senus Arabicus.</HI></L>
<L>Shal al be loden with the martiall spoiles</L>
<L>We will conuay with vs to <HI>Persea.</HI></L>
<PB REF="74"/><FW><MILESTONE N="K1v"/></FW>
<L>Then shal my natiue city <HI>Samarcanda</HI></L>
<L>And christall waues of fresh <HI>Iaertis</HI> streame,</L>
<L>The pride and beautie of her princely seat,</L>
<L>Be famous through the furthest continents,</L>
<L>For there my Pallace royal shal be plac'd:</L>
<L>Whose shyning Turrets shal dismay the heauens,</L>
<L>And cast the fame of <HI>Ilions</HI> Tower to hell.</L>
<L>Thorow the streets with troops of conquered kings,</L>
<L>Ile ride in golden armour like the Sun,</L>
<L>And in my helme a triple plume shal spring,</L>
<L>Spangled with Diamonds dancing in the aire,</L>
<L>To note me Emperour of the threefold world.</L>
<L>Like to an almond tree ymounted high,</L>
<L>Vpon the lofty and celestiall mount,</L>
<L>Of euery greene <HI>Selinus</HI> queintly dect</L>
<L>With bloomes more white than <HI>Hericinas</HI> browes,</L>
<L>Whose tender blossoms tremble euery one,</L>
<L>At euery litle breath that thorow heauen is blowen:</L>
<L>Then in my coach like <HI>Saturnes</HI> royal son,</L>
<L>Mounted his shining chariots, gilt with fire.</L>
<L>And drawen with princely Eagles through the path,</L>
<L>Pau'd with bright Christall, and enchac'd with starres,</L>
<L>When all the Gods stand and gazing at his pomp.</L>
<L>So will I ride through <HI>Samarcanda</HI> streets,</L>
<L>Vntil my soule disseuered from this flesh,</L>
<L>Shall mount the milk-white way and meet him there.</L>
<L>To <HI>Babylon</HI> my Lords, to <HI>Babylon.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV3>
<TRAILER>Finis Actus quarti.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="74"/><FW><MILESTONE N="K2r"/></FW>
<HEAD>Actus. 5.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scaena. 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter the Gouernour of Babylon vpon the walles with others.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>WHat saith <HI>Maximus?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Max.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, the breach the enimie hath made</L>
<L>Giues such assurance of our ouerthrow,</L>
<L>That litle hope is left to saue our liues,</L>
<L>Or hold out citie from the Conquerours hands.</L>
<L>Then hang out flagges (my Lord of humble truce,</L>
<L>And satisfie the peoples generall praiers,</L>
<L>That <HI>Tamburlains</HI> intollorable wrath</L>
<L>May be supprest by our submission.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Villaine, respects thou more thy slauish life,</L>
<L>Than honor of thy countrie or thy name?</L>
<L>Is not my life and state as deere to me,</L>
<L>The citic and my natiue countries weale,</L>
<L>As any thing of price with thy conceit?</L>
<L>Haue we not hope, for all our battered walles,</L>
<L>To liue secure, and keep his forces out,</L>
<L>When this our famous lake of <HI>Limnasphaltis</HI></L>
<L>Makes walles a fresh with euery thing that falles</L>
<L>Into the liquid substance of his streame,</L>
<L>More strong than are the gates of death or hel,</L>
<L>What faintnesse should dismay our courages,</L>
<L>When we are thus defenc'd against our Foe,</L>
<L>And haue no terrour but his threatning lookes?</L>
<STAGE>Enter another, kneeling to the Gouernour.</STAGE>
<L>My Lord, if euer you did deed of tuth,</L>
<L>And now will work a refuge to our liues,</L>
<PB REF="75"/><FW><MILESTONE N="K2v"/></FW>
<L>Offer submission, hang vp flags of truce,</L>
<L>That <HI>Tambur laine</HI> may pitie our distresse,</L>
<L>And vse vs like a louing Conquerour,</L>
<L>Though this be held his last daies dreadfull siege,</L>
<L>Wherein he spareth neither man nor child,</L>
<L>Yet are there Christians of <HI>Georgia</HI> here,</L>
<L>Whose state he euer pitied and relieu'd:</L>
<L>Wil get his pardon if your grace would send.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>How is my soule enuironed,</L>
<L>And this eternisde citie <HI>Babylon,</HI></L>
<L>Fill'd with a packe of faintheart Fugitiues,</L>
<L>That thus intreat their shame and seruitude?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Another.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, if euer you wil win our hearts,</L>
<L>Yeeld vp the towne, saue our wiues and children:</L>
<L>For I wil cast my selfe from off these walles,</L>
<L>Or die some death of quickest violence,</L>
<L>Before I bide the wrath of <HI>Tamburlaine.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Villaines, cowards, Traitors to our state,</L>
<L>Fall to the earth, and pierce the pit of Hel,</L>
<L>That legions of tormenting spirits may ver</L>
<L>Your slauish bosomes with continuall pames,</L>
<L>I cate not, nor the towne will neuer yeeld</L>
<L>As long as any life is in my breast.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Theridamas and Techelles, with other souldiers.</STAGE>
<L>Thou desperate Gouernour of <HI>Babylon,</HI></L>
<L>To saue thy life, and vs a litle labour,</L>
<L>Yeeld speedily the citie to our hands,</L>
<L>Or els be sure thou shalt be forc'd with paines,</L>
<L>More exquisite than euer Traitor felt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tyrant, I turne the traitor in thy throat,</L>
<L>And wil defend it in despight of thee.</L>
<PB REF="75"/><FW><MILESTONE N="K3r"/></FW>
<L>Call vp the souldiers to defend these wals.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tech.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yeeld foolish Gouernour, we offer more</L>
<L>Than euer yet we did to such proud slaues,</L>
<L>As durst resist vs till our third daies siege:</L>
<L>Thou seest vs prest to giue the last assault,</L>
<L>And that shal bide no more regard of parlie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Assault and spare not, we wil neuer yeeld.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Alarme, and they scale the walles.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Tamburlain, with Vsumeasane. Amyras, and Celebinus, with others, the two spare kings.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>The stately buildings of faire <HI>Babylon,</HI></L>
<L>Whose lofty Pillers, higher than the cloudes,</L>
<L>Were woont to guide the seaman in the deepe.</L>
<L>Being caried thither by the cannons force,</L>
<L>Now fil the mouth of <HI>Limnasphaltes</HI> lake,</L>
<L>And make a bridge vnto the battered walles,</L>
<L>Where <HI>Belus, Ninus</HI> and great <HI>Alexander</HI></L>
<L>Haue rode in triumph, triumphs <HI>Tamburlaine,</HI></L>
<L>Whose chariot wheeles haue burst th' Assirians bones,</L>
<L>Drawen with these kings on heaps of carkasses,</L>
<L>Now in the place where faire <HI>Semiramis,</HI></L>
<L>Courted by kings and peeres of <HI>Asia,</HI></L>
<L>Hath trode the Meisures, do my souldiers martch,</L>
<L>And in the streets, where braue Assirian Dames</L>
<L>Haue rid in pompe like rich <HI>Saturnia,</HI></L>
<L>With furious words and frowning visages,</L>
<L>My horsmen brandish their vnruly blades.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Theridamas and Techelles bringing the Gouernor of Babylon.</STAGE>
<L>Who haue ye there my Lordes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="76"/><FW><MILESTONE N="K3v"/></FW>
<SPEAKER>Ther.</SPEAKER>
<L>The sturdy Gouernour of <HI>Babylon,</HI></L>
<L>That made vs all the labour for the towne,</L>
<L>And vsde such slender reckning of you maiesty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Go bind the villaine, he shall hang in chaines,</L>
<L>Vpon the ruines of this conquered towne,</L>
<L>Sirha, the view of our vermillion tents,</L>
<L>Which threatned more than if the region</L>
<L>Next vnderneath the Element of fire,</L>
<L>Were full of Commets and of blazing stars,</L>
<L>Whose flaming traines should reach down to the earth</L>
<L>Could not affright you, no, nor I my selfe,</L>
<L>The wrathfull messenger of mighty <HI>Iouc,</HI></L>
<L>That with his sword hath quail'd all earthly kings.</L>
<L>Could not perswadé you to submission,</L>
<L>But stil the ports were shut: villaine I say,</L>
<L>Should I but touch the rusty gates of hell,</L>
<L>The triple headed <HI>Cerberus</HI> would howle,</L>
<L>And wake blacke <HI>Ioue</HI> to crouch and kneele to me.</L>
<L>But I haue sent volleies of shot to you,</L>
<L>Yet could not enter till the breach was made,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor if my body could haue stopt the breach,</L>
<L>Shouldst thou haue entted, cruel <HI>tamburlaine:</HI></L>
<L>Tis not thy bloody tents can make me yeeld,</L>
<L>Nor yet thy selfe, thè anger of the highest,</L>
<L>For though thy cannon shooke the citie walles,</L>
<L>My heart did neuer quake, or corrage faint.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wel, now Ile make it quake, go draw him vp,</L>
<L>Hang him vp in chaines vpon the citie walles,</L>
<L>And let my souldiers shoot the slaue to death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gouern.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vile monster, borne of some infernal hag,</L>
<L>And sent from hell to tyrannise on earth,</L>
<L>Do all thy wurst, nor death, nor <HI>Tamburlaine,</HI></L>
<PB REF="76"/><FW><MILESTONE N="K4r"/></FW>
<L>Torture or paine can daunt my dreadlesse minde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vp with him then, his body shal be scard.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gou</SPEAKER>
<L>But <HI>Tamburlain,</HI> in <HI>Lymnasphaltis</HI> lake,</L>
<L>There lies more gold than <HI>Babylon</HI> is worth,</L>
<L>Which when the citie was besieg'd I hid,</L>
<L>Saue but my life and I wil giue it thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then for all your valour, you would saue your life,</L>
<L>Where about lies it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vnder a hollow bank, right opposite</L>
<L>Against the Westerne gate of <HI>Babylon.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam</SPEAKER>
<L>Go thither some of you and take his gold,</L>
<L>The rest forward with execution,</L>
<L>Away with him hence, let him speake no more:</L>
<L>I think I make your courage something quaile,</L>
<L>When this is done, we'll martch from <HI>Babylon,</HI></L>
<L>And make our greatest haste to <HI>Persea:</HI></L>
<L>These Iades are broken winded, and halfe tyr'd,</L>
<L>Vnharnesse them, and let me haue fresh horse:</L>
<L>So, now their best is done to honour me,</L>
<L>Take them, and hang them both vp presently.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tre.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vild Tyrant, barbarous bloody <HI>Tamburlain</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take them away <HI>Theridamas,</HI> see them dispatcht.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ther</SPEAKER>
<L>I will my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come Asian Viceroies, to your taskes a while</L>
<L>And take such fortune as your fellowes felt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Orc.</SPEAKER>
<L>First let thy Scythyan horse teare both our limmes</L>
<L>Rather then we should draw thy chariot.</L>
<L>And like base slaues abiect our princely mindes</L>
<L>To vile and ignominious seruitude.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rather lend me thy weapon <HI>Tamburlain,</HI></L>
<L>That I may sheath it in this breast of mine,</L>
<PB REF="77"/><FW><MILESTONE N="K4v"/></FW>
<L>A thousand deathes could not torment our hearts</L>
<L>More than the thought of this dooth vexe our soules.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amy.</SPEAKER>
<L>They will talk still my Lord, if you doe not bridle them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bridle them, and let me to my coach.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>They bridle them.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amy.</SPEAKER>
<L>See now my Lord how braue the Captaine hangs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis braue indeed my boy, wel done,</L>
<L>Shoot first my Lord, and then the rest shall follow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ther.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then haue at him to begin withall.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Theridamas shootes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gou</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet saue my life, and let this wound appease</L>
<L>The mortall furie of great <HI>Tamburlain.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, though <HI>Asphaltis</HI> lake were liquid gold,</L>
<L>And offer'd me as ransome for thy life,</L>
<L>Yet shouldst thou die, shoot at him all at once.</L>
<STAGE>They shoote.</STAGE>
<L>So now he hangs like <HI>Bagdets</HI> Gouernour,</L>
<L>Hauing as many bullets in his flesh,</L>
<L>As there be breaches in her battered wall.</L>
<L>Goe now and bind the Burghers hand and foot,</L>
<L>And cast them headlong in the cities lake:</L>
<L>Tartars and Perseans shall inhabit there,</L>
<L>And to command the citie, I will build</L>
<L>A Cytadell, that all Affrica</L>
<L>Which hath bene subiect to the Persean king,</L>
<L>Shall pay me tribute for, in <HI>Babylon.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tech.</SPEAKER>
<L>What shal be done with their wiues and chil∣dren my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam,</SPEAKER>
<L>Techelles, Drowne them all, man, woman, and child,</L>
<L>Leaue not a Babylonian in the towne.</L>
</SP>
<PB REF="77"/><FW><MILESTONE N="K5r"/></FW>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tech</SPEAKER>
<L>I will about it straight, come Souldiers.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now <HI>Casane,</HI> wher's the Turkish <HI>Alcaron,</HI></L>
<L>And all the heapes of supersticious bookes,</L>
<L>Found in the Temples of that <HI>Mahomet?</HI></L>
<L>Whom I haue thought a God, they shal be burnt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here they are my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wel said, let there be a fire presently,</L>
<L>In vaine I see men worship <HI>Mahomet,</HI></L>
<L>My sword hath sent millions of Turks to hell.</L>
<L>Slew all his Priests, his kinsmen, and his friends,</L>
<L>And yet I liue vntoucht by <HI>Mahomet:</HI></L>
<L>There is a God full of reuenging wrath,</L>
<L>From whom the thunder and the lightning breaks,</L>
<L>Whose Scourge I am, and him will I obey.</L>
<L>So <HI>Casane,</HI> fling them in the fire.</L>
<L>Now <HI>Mahomet,</HI> if thou haue any power,</L>
<L>Come downe thy selfe and worke a myracle,</L>
<L>Thou art not woorthy to be worshipped,</L>
<L>That suffers flames of fire to burne the writ</L>
<L>Wherein the sum of thy religion rests.</L>
<L>Why send 'st thou not a furious whyrlwind downe,</L>
<L>To blow thy Alcaron vp to thy throne,</L>
<L>Where men report, thou sitt'st by God himselfe,</L>
<L>Or vengeance on the head of <HI>Tamburlain,</HI></L>
<L>That shakes his sword against thy maiesty.</L>
<L>And spurns the Abstracts of thy foolish lawes.</L>
<L>Wel souldiers, <HI>Mahomet</HI> remaines in hell,</L>
<L>He cannot heare the voice of <HI>Tamburlain,</HI></L>
<L>Seeke out another Godhead to adore,</L>
<L>The God that sits in heauen, if any God,</L>
<L>For he is God alone, and none but he.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tech.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue fulfil'd your highnes wil, my Lord,</L>
<PB REF="78"/><FW><MILESTONE N="K5v"/></FW>
<L>Thousands of men drown'd in <HI>Asphal<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" RESP="murp" DISP="•"/>is</HI> Lake,</L>
<L>Haue made the water swell abore the bankes,</L>
<L>And fishes feed by humaine carkasses,</L>
<L>Amasde, swim vp and downe vpon the waues,</L>
<L>As when they swallow <HI>Assafitida,</HI></L>
<L>Which makes them fleet aloft and gaspe for aire,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wel then my friendly Lordes what now re∣maines</L>
<L>But that we leaue sufficient garrison</L>
<L>And presently depart to <HI>Persea,</HI></L>
<L>To triumph after all our victories.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ther.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, good my Lord, let vs in hast to <HI>Persea,</HI></L>
<L>And let this Captaine be remoou'd the walles,</L>
<L>To some high hill about the citie here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let it be so, about it souldiers:</L>
<L>But stay, I feele my selfe distempered sudainly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tech.</SPEAKER>
<L>What is it dares distemper <HI>Tamburlain</HI>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Something techelles but I know not what,</L>
<L>But foorth ye vassals, what so ere it be,</L>
<L>Sicknes or death can neuer conquer me.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt</STAGE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="4 (recte 2)" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Actus. 5. Scaena. 4.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Callapine, Amasia, with drums and trumpets.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Callap.</SPEAKER>
<L>KIng of <HI>Amasia,</HI> now our mighty hoste,</L>
<L>Marcheth in <HI>Asia maior</HI> where the streames,</L>
<L>Of Euphrates and <HI>Tigris</HI> swiftly runs,</L>
<L>And here may we behald great Babylon,</L>
<L>Circled about with <HI>Limnasphaltis</HI> Lake,</L>
<L>Where <HI>tamburlaine</HI> with all his armie lies,</L>
<L>Which being faint and weary with the siege,</L>
<L>Wee may lie ready to encounter him.</L>
<PB REF="78"/><FW><MILESTONE N="K6r"/></FW>
<L>Before his hoste be full from <HI>Babylon,</HI></L>
<L>And so reuenge our latest grieuous losse,</L>
<L>If God or <HI>Mahomet</HI> send any aide.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ama.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doubt not my lord, but we shal conquer him</L>
<L>The Monster that hath drinke a sea of blood,</L>
<L>And yet gapes stil for more to quench his thirst,</L>
<L>Our Turkish swords shal headlong send to hell,</L>
<L>And that vile Carkasse drawne by warlike kings,</L>
<L>The Foules shall eate, for neuer sepulchre</L>
<L>Shall grace that base-borne Tyrant <HI>tamburlaine.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>When I record my Parents slauish life,</L>
<L>Their cruel death, mine owne captiuity,</L>
<L>My Viceroies bondage vnder tamburlaine,</L>
<L>Me thinks I could sustaine a thousand deaths,</L>
<L>To be reueng'd of all his Villanie.</L>
<L>Ah sacred <HI>Mahomet,</HI> thou that hast seene,</L>
<L>Millions of Turkes perish by <HI>Tamburlaine,</HI></L>
<L>Kingdomes made waste, braue cities sackt &amp; burnt,</L>
<L>And but one hoste is left to honor thee.</L>
<L>And thy obedient seruant <HI>Callapine,</HI></L>
<L>And make him after all these ouerthrowes,</L>
<L>To triumph ouer cursed <HI>Tamburlaine.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ama</SPEAKER>
<L>Feare not my Lord, I see great <HI>Mahomet</HI></L>
<L>Clothed in purple clowdes, and on his head</L>
<L>A Chaplet brighter than <HI>Apollos</HI> crowne,</L>
<L>Marching about the ayer with armed men,</L>
<L>To ioine with you against this <HI>Tamburlaine.</HI></L>
<L>Renowmed Generall mighty <HI>Callapine,</HI></L>
<L>Though God himselfe and holy <HI>Mahomet,</HI></L>
<L>Should come in person to resist your power,</L>
<L>Yet might your mighty hoste incounter all,</L>
<L>And pull proud <HI>Tamburlaine</HI> vpon his knees,</L>
<PB REF="79"/><FW><MILESTONE N="K6v"/></FW>
<L>To sue for mercie at your highnesse feete,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Captaine the force of <HI>Tamburlaine</HI> is great,</L>
<L>His fortune greater, and the victories</L>
<L>Wherewith he hath so sore dismaide the world,</L>
<L>Are greatest to discourage all our drifts,</L>
<L>Yet when the pride of <HI>Cynthia</HI> is at full,</L>
<L>She waines againe, and so shall his I hope,</L>
<L>For we haue here the chiefe selected men</L>
<L>Of twenty seuerall kingdomes at the least:</L>
<L>Nor plowman, Priest, nor Merchant staies at home.</L>
<L>All Turkie is in armes with <HI>Callapine.</HI></L>
<L>And neuer wil we sunder camps and armes,</L>
<L>Before himselfe or his be conquered.</L>
<L>This is the time that must eternize me,</L>
<L>For conquering the Tyrant of the world.</L>
<L>Come Souldiers, let vs lie in wait for him</L>
<L>And if we find him absent from his campe,</L>
<L>Or that it be reioin'd again at full,</L>
<L>Assaile it and be sure of victorie.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="6 (recte 3)" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Actus. 5. Scaena. 6.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Theridamas, Techelles, Vsumeasane.</STAGE>
<L>WEepe heauens, and vanish into liquid teares</L>
<L>Fal starres that gouerne his natiuity,</L>
<L>And sommon al the shining lamps of heauen</L>
<L>To cast their bootlesse fires to the earth.</L>
<L>And shed their feble influence in the aire.</L>
<L>Muffle your beauties with eternall clowdes,</L>
<L>For hell and darknesse pitch their pitchy tentes,</L>
<L>And Death with armies of Cymerian spirits</L>
<PB REF="79"/><FW><MILESTONE N="K7r"/></FW>
<L>Giues battile gainst the heart of <HI>Tamburlaine.</HI></L>
<L>Now in defiance of that woonted loue,</L>
<L>Your sacred vertues pour'd vpon his throne,</L>
<L>And made his state an honor to the heauens,</L>
<L>These cowards inuisiblie assaile hys soule,</L>
<L>And threaten conquest on our Soueraigne:</L>
<L>But if he die, your glories are disgrac'd,</L>
<L>Earth droopes and saies, that hell in heauen is plac'd,</L>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tech.</SPEAKER>
<L>O then ye Powers that sway eternal seates,</L>
<L>And guide this massy substance of the earthe,</L>
<L>If you retaine desert of holinesse,</L>
<L>As your supreame estates instruct our thoughtes,</L>
<L>Be not iuconstant, carelesse of your fame,</L>
<L>Beare not the burthen of your enemies ioyes,</L>
<L>Triumphing in his fall whom you aduaimst,</L>
<L>But as his birth, life, health and maiesty</L>
<L>Were strangely blest and gouerned by heauen,</L>
<L>So honour heauen til heauen dissolued be,</L>
<L>His byrth, his life, his health and maiesty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cas..</SPEAKER>
<L>Blush heauen to loose the honor of thyname,</L>
<L>To see thy foot-stoole set vpon thy head,</L>
<L>And let no basenesse in thy haughty breast,</L>
<L>Sustaine a shame of such inexcellence:</L>
<L>To see the deuils mount in Angels throanes,</L>
<L>And Angels diue into the pooles of hell.</L>
<L>And though they think their painfull date is out,</L>
<L>And that their power is puissant as <HI>Ioues,</HI></L>
<L>Which makes them manage armes against thy state,</L>
<L>Yet make them feele the strength of <HI>Tamburlain,</HI></L>
<L>Thy instrument and note of Maisty.</L>
<L>Is greater far than they can thus subdue.</L>
<L>For if he die, thy glorie is disgrac'd,</L>
<PB REF="80"/><FW><MILESTONE N="K7v"/></FW>
<L>Earth droopes and saies that hel in heauen is plac'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>What daring God torments my body thus,</L>
<L>And seeks to conquet mighty <HI>Tamburlaine,</HI></L>
<L>Shall sicknesse prooue me now to be a man,</L>
<L>That haue bene tearm'd the terrour of the world?</L>
<L><HI>Techelles</HI> and the rest, come take your swords,</L>
<L>And threaten him whose hand afflicts my soul,</L>
<L>Come let vs march against the powers of heauen,</L>
<L>And set blacke streamers in the firmament,</L>
<L>To signifie the slaughter of the Gods,</L>
<L>Ah friends, what shal I doe I cannot stand,</L>
<L>Come carie me to war against the Gods,</L>
<L>That thus inuie the health of <HI>Tamburlaine,</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ther.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ah good my Lord, leaue these iinpatient words,</L>
<L>Which ad much danger to your malladie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why shal I sit and languish in this paine,</L>
<L>No, strike the drums, and in reuenge of this,</L>
<L>Come let vs chardge our speares and pierce his breast,</L>
<L>Whose shoulders beare the Axis of the world,</L>
<L>That if I perish, heauen and earth may fade,</L>
<L>theridamas, haste to the court of <HI>Ioue,</HI></L>
<L>Will him to send <HI>Apollo</HI> hether straight,</L>
<L>To cure me, or Ile fetch him downe my selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tech.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sit stil my gratious Lord, this griefe wil cease,</L>
<L>And cannot last, it is so violent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not last techelles, no, for I shall die,</L>
<L>See where my slaue, the vglie monster death</L>
<L>Shaking and quiuering, pale and wan for feare,</L>
<L>Stands aiming at me with his murthering dart,</L>
<L>Who flies away at euery glance I giue,</L>
<L>And when I look away, comes stealing on:</L>
<L>Villaine away, and hie thee to the field,</L>
<PB REF="80"/><FW><MILESTONE N="K8r"/></FW>
<L>I and myne armie come to lode thy barke</L>
<L>With soules of thousand mangled carkasses,</L>
<L>Looke where he goes, but see, he comes againe</L>
<L>Because I stay, <HI>techelles</HI> let vs march,</L>
<L>And weary Death with bearing soules to hell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pleaseth your Maiesty to drink this potion.</L>
<L>Which wil abate the furie of your fit,</L>
<L>And cause some milder spirits gouerne you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tel me, what think you of my sicknes now?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I view'd your vrine, and the Hipostates</L>
<L>Thick and obscure doth make your danger great,</L>
<L>Your vaines are full of accidentall heat,</L>
<L>Whereby the moisture of your blood is dried,</L>
<L>The <HI>Humidum</HI> and <HI>Calor,</HI> which some holde</L>
<L>Is not a parcell of the Elements,</L>
<L>But of a substance more diuine and pure,</L>
<L>Is almost cleane extinguished and spent.</L>
<L>Which being the cause of life, imports your death.</L>
<L>Besides my Lord, this day is Criticall,</L>
<L>Dangerous to those, whose Chrisis is as yours:</L>
<L>Your Artiers which alongst the vaines conuey</L>
<L>The liuely spirits which the heart ingenders</L>
<L>Are partcht and void of spirit that the soule</L>
<L>Wanting those Organnons by which it mooues,</L>
<L>Can not indure by argument of art.</L>
<L>Yet if your maiesty may escape this day,</L>
<L>No doubt, but you shal soone recouer all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then will I comfort all my vital parts,</L>
<L>And liue in spight of death aboue a day.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Alarme within.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mess.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord, yong <HI>Callapine</HI> that lately fled from your maiesty, hath nowe gathered a fresh Armie, and
<PB REF="81" MS="y"/><FW><MILESTONE N="K8v"/></FW>
hearing your absence in the field, offers to set vpon vs presently.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>See my Phisitions now, how <HI>Ioue</HI> hath sent,</L>
<L>A present medicince to recure my paine:</L>
<L>My looks shall make them flie, and might I follow,</L>
<L>There should not one of all the villaines power</L>
<L>Liue to giue offer of another fight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vsum.</SPEAKER>
<L>I ioy my Lord, your highnesse is so strong,</L>
<L>That can endure so well your royall presence,</L>
<L>Which onely will dismay the enemy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know it wil <HI>Casane:</HI> draw you slaues,</L>
<L>In spight of death I will goe show my face.</L>
<STAGE>Alarme, Tam. goes in, and comes out againe with al the rest.</STAGE>
<L>Thus are the villaines, cowards fled for feare,</L>
<L>Like Summers vapours, vanisht by the Sun.</L>
<L>And could I but a while pursue the field,</L>
<L>That <HI>Callapine</HI> should be my slaue againe.</L>
<L>But I perceiue my martial strength is spent,</L>
<L>In vaine I striue and raile against those powers,</L>
<L>That meane t'inuest me in a higher throne,</L>
<L>As much too high for this disdainfull earth.</L>
<L>Giue me a Map, then let me see how much</L>
<L>Is left for me to conquer all the world,</L>
<L>That these my boies may finish all my wantes,</L>
<STAGE>One brings a Map.</STAGE>
<L>Here I began to martch towards <HI>Persea,</HI></L>
<L>Along <HI>Armenia</HI> and the Caspian sea,</L>
<L>And thence vnto <HI>Bythinia,</HI> where I tooke</L>
<L>The Turke and his great Empresse priseners,</L>
<L>Then martcht I into <HI>Egypt</HI> and <HI>Arabia,</HI></L>
<L>And here not far from <HI>Alexandria,</HI></L>
<PB REF="81" MS="y"/><FW><MILESTONE N="L1r"/></FW>
<L>Whereas the Terren and the red sea meet,</L>
<L>Being distant lesse than stil a hundred leagues,</L>
<L>I meant to cut a channell to them both,</L>
<L>That men might quickly saile to India.</L>
<L>From thence to <HI>Nubia</HI> neere <HI>Borno</HI> Lake,</L>
<L>And so along the Ethiopian sea,</L>
<L>Cutting the Tropicke line of <HI>Capricorne,</HI></L>
<L>I conquered all as far as <HI>Zansibar,</HI></L>
<L>Then by the Northerne part of <HI>Affrica.</HI></L>
<L>I came at last to <HI>Graecia,</HI> and from thence</L>
<L>To <HI>Asia,</HI> where I stay against my will,</L>
<L>Which is from <HI>Scythia,</HI> where I first began,</L>
<L>Backeward and forwards nere fiue thousand leagues,</L>
<L>Looke here my boies, see what a world of ground,</L>
<L>Lies westward from the midst of <HI>Cancers</HI> line,</L>
<L>Vnto the rising of this earthly globe,</L>
<L>Whereas the Sun declining from our sight,</L>
<L>Begins the day with our Antypodes:</L>
<L>And shall I die, and this vnconquered?</L>
<L>Loe here my sonnes, are all the golden Mines,</L>
<L>Inestimable drugs and precious stones,</L>
<L>More worth than <HI>Asia,</HI> and the world beside,</L>
<L>And from th'Antartique Pole, Eastward behold</L>
<L>As much more land, which neuer was descried,</L>
<L>Wherein are rockes of Pearle, that shine as bright</L>
<L>As all the Lamps that beautifie the Sky,</L>
<L>And shal I die, and this vnconquered?</L>
<L>Here louely boies, what death forbids my life,</L>
<L>That let your liues commaund in spight of death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas my Lord, how should our bleeding harts</L>
<L>Wounded and broken with your Highnesse griefe,</L>
<L>Retaine a thought of ioy, or sparke of life?</L>
<PB REF="82"/><FW><MILESTONE N="K1v"/></FW>
<L>Your soul giues essence to our wretched subiects.</L>
<L>Whose matter is incorporoat in your flesh.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your paines do pierce our soules, no hope sur∣uiues,</L>
<L>For by your life we entertaine our liues,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>But sons, this subiect not of force enough,</L>
<L>To hold the fiery spirit it containes,</L>
<L>must part, imparting his impressions,</L>
<L>By equall portions into both your breasts:</L>
<L>My flesh deuided in your precious shapes,</L>
<L>Shal still retaine my spirit, though I die,</L>
<L>And liue in all your seedes immortally:</L>
<L>Then now remooue me, that I may resigne</L>
<L>My place and proper tytle to my sonne:</L>
<L>First take my Scourge and my imperiall Crowne,</L>
<L>And mount my royall chariot of estate,</L>
<L>That I may see thee crown'd before I die,</L>
<L>Help me (my Lords) to make my last remooue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ther.</SPEAKER>
<L>A woful change my Lord, that daunts our thoughts,</L>
<L>More than the ruine of our proper soules.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sit vp my sonne, let me see how well</L>
<L>Thou wilt become thy fathers maiestie.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>They crowne him.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ami</SPEAKER>
<L>With what a flinty bosome should I ioy.</L>
<L>The breath of life, and burthen of my soule,</L>
<L>If not resolu'd into resolued paines,</L>
<L>My bodies mortified lineaments</L>
<L>should exercise the motions of my heart,</L>
<L>Pierc'd with the ioy of any dignity?</L>
<L>O father, if the vnrelenting eares</L>
<L>Of death and hell be shut against my praiers,</L>
<L>And that the spightfull influence of heauen.</L>
<L>Denie my soule fruition of her ioy,</L>
<PB REF="82"/><FW><MILESTONE N="L2r"/></FW>
<L>How should I step or stir my hatefull feete,</L>
<L>Against the inward powers of my heart,</L>
<L>Leading a life that onely striues to die,</L>
<L>And plead in vaine, vnpleasing soueranity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let not thy loue exceed thyne honor sonne,</L>
<L>Nor bar thy mind that magnanimitie,</L>
<L>That nobly must admit necessity;</L>
<L>Sit vp my boy, and with those silken raines,</L>
<L>Bridle the steeled stomackes of those Iades.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ther.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, you must obey his maiesty,</L>
<L>Since Fate commands, and proud necessity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heauens witnes me, with what a broken hart</L>
<L>And damned spirit I ascend this seat,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" RESP="murp" DISP="•"/>nd send my soule before my father die,</L>
<L>His anguish and his burning agony.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now fetch the hearse of faire <HI>Zenocrate,</HI></L>
<L>Let it be plac'd by this my fatall chaire,</L>
<L>And serue as parcell of my funerall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then feeles your maiesty no soueraigne ease,</L>
<L>Nor may our hearts all drown'd in teares of blood,</L>
<L>Ioy any hope of your recouery?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tamb.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Casane</HI> no, the Monarke of the earth,</L>
<L>And eielesse Monster that torments my soule,</L>
<L>Cannot behold the teares ye shed for me,</L>
<L>And therefore stil augments his cruelty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tech.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then let some God oppose his holy power,</L>
<L>Against the wrath and tyranny of death,</L>
<L>That his teare-thyrsty and vnquenched hate,</L>
<L>May be vpon himselfe reuerberate.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>They bring in the hearse.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>tam</SPEAKER>
<L>Now eies, inioy your latest benefite,</L>
<L>And when my soule hath vertue of your sight,</L>
<PB REF="83"/><FW><MILESTONE N="L2v"/></FW>
<L>Pierce through the <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="3 letters" RESP="murp" DISP="•••"/>fin and the sheet of gold,</L>
<L>And glut your longings with a heauen of ioy.</L>
<L>So, raigne my sonne, scourge and controlle those slaues</L>
<L>Guiding thy chariot with thy Fathers hand.</L>
<L>As precious is the charge thou vndertak'st</L>
<L>As that which <HI>Clymens</HI> brainsicke sonne did guide,</L>
<L>When wandring <HI>Phoebes</HI> Iuory cheeks were scortcht</L>
<L>And all the earth like <HI>AEtna</HI> breathing fire:</L>
<L>Be warn'd by him, then learne with awfull eie</L>
<L>To sway a throane as dangerous as his:</L>
<L>For if thy body thriue not full of thoughtes</L>
<L>As pure and fiery as <HI>Phyteus</HI> beames,</L>
<L>The nature of these proud rebelling Iades</L>
<L>Wil take occasion by the slenderest haire,</L>
<L>And draw thee peecemeale like <HI>Hyppolitus,</HI></L>
<L>Through rocks more steepe and sharp than Caspian cliftes.</L>
<L>The nature of thy chariot wil not beare</L>
<L>A guide of baser temper than my selfe,</L>
<L>More then heauens coach, the pride of <HI>Phaeton.</HI></L>
<L>Fa<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="4 letters" RESP="murp" DISP="••••"/>l my boies, my dearest friends, farewel,</L>
<L>My body feeles, my soule dooth weepe to see</L>
<L>Your sweet desires depriu'd my company,</L>
<L>For <HI>Tamburlaine,</HI> the Scourge of God must die.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Meet heauen &amp; earth, &amp; here let al things end</L>
<L>For earth hath spent the pride of all her fruit,</L>
<L>And heauen consum'd his choisest liuing fire.</L>
<L>Let earth and heauen his timelesse death deplore,</L>
<L>For both their woorths wil equall him no more,</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

