<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2003-09-05</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Olivia Bottum</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Checked for N=""s. Checked for GROUP tags. Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, CLOSER, OPENER, ARGUMENT, EPIGRAPH, SIGNED, BYLINE, etc.). Checked for signatures. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, and UNCLEARs. Corrected 43 $-groups by inserting appropriate letters or GAPs. Checked spacing of foreign GAPs. Checked for LBs. Checked for startqs, endqs, oes, q;s, and Qs. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Checked for FIGUREs and decorated initials. Checked for missing-page GAPs. Revalidated. </ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A07064">
<STC T="S">17474</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99847512</BIBNO>
<VID>12549</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>ANTONIOS Reuenge.</P>
<P>The second part.</P>
<P>As it hath beene sundry times acted, by the children of <HI>Paules.</HI></P>
<P>Written by <HI>I. M.</HI></P>
<P>LONDON ¶ Printed for <HI>Thomas Fisher,</HI> and are to be soulde in Saint Dunstans Church-yarde. 1602.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="play">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>Antonios Reuenge. ¶ The second part of the Historie of Antonio and Mellida.</HEAD>
<DIV2 TYPE="prologue">
<HEAD>¶ The Prologue.</HEAD>
<L>THE rawish danke of clumzie winter ramps</L>
<L>The fluent summers vaine: and drizling sleete</L>
<L>Chilleth the wan bleak cheek of the numd earth,</L>
<L>Whilst snarling gusts nibble the iuyceles leaues,</L>
<L>From the nak't shuddring branch; and pils the skinne</L>
<L>From off the soft and delicate aspectes.</L>
<L>O, now, me thinks, a sullen tragick Sceane</L>
<L>Would suite the time, with pleasing congruence.</L>
<L>May we be happie in our weake deuoyer,</L>
<L>And all parte pleas'd in most wisht content:</L>
<L>But sweare of <HI>Hercules</HI> can nere beget</L>
<L>So blest an issue. Therefore we proclaime,</L>
<L>If any spirit breathes within this round,</L>
<L>Vncapable of waightie passion</L>
<L>(As from his birth, being hugged in the armes,</L>
<L>And nuzzled twixt the breastes of happinesse)</L>
<L><PB REF="3"/>Who winkes, and shuts his apprehension vp</L>
<L>From common sense of what men were, and are,</L>
<L>Who would not knowe what men must be; let such</L>
<L>Hurrie amaine from our black visag'd showes:</L>
<L>We shall affright their eyes. But if a breast,</L>
<L>Nail'd to the earth with griefe: if any heart</L>
<L>Pierc't through with anguish, pant within this ring:</L>
<L>If there be any blood, whose heate is choakt</L>
<L>And stifled with true sense of misery:</L>
<L>If ought of these straines fill this consort vp,</L>
<L>Th'arriue most welcome. O that our power</L>
<L>Could lackie, or keepe wing with our desires;</L>
<L>That with vnused paize of stile and sense,</L>
<L>We might waigh massy in iudicious scale.</L>
<L>Yet heere's the prop that doth support our hopes;</L>
<L>When our Sceanes falter, or inuention halts▪</L>
<L>Your fauour will giue crutches to our faults. <STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACT. I.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCEN▪ I▪</HEAD>
<STAGE>¶ <HI>Enter Piero, vnbrac't, his armes bare, smeer'd in blood, a poniard in one hand bloodie, and a torch in the other, Strotzo following him with a corde.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>HO, <HI>Gasper Strotzo,</HI> binde <HI>Feliches</HI> trunke</L>
<L>Vnto the panting side of <HI>Mellida.</HI> <STAGE>Exit Str.</STAGE></L>
<L>Tis yet dead night, yet al the earth is cloucht</L>
<L>In the dull leaden hand of snoring sleepe:</L>
<L>No breath disturbs the quiet of the ayre.</L>
<L>No spirit moues vpon the breast of earth,</L>
<L><PB REF="3" MS="y"/>Saue howling dogs, nightcrowes, &amp; screeching owls,</L>
<L>Saue meager ghosts, <HI>Piero,</HI> and black thoughts.</L>
<L>One, two▪ Lord, in two houres what a toplesse mount</L>
<L>Of vnpeer'd mischiefe, haue these hands cast vp!</L>
<STAGE>¶ <HI>Enter Strotzo.</HI></STAGE>
<L>I can scarce coope triumphing vengeance vp,</L>
<L>From bursting forth in bragart passion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Str.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, tis firmely saide that</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Andrugio</HI> sleepes in peace: this braine hath choakt</L>
<L>The organ of his breast. <HI>Feliche</HI> hangs,</L>
<L>But as a baite vpon the line of death,</L>
<L>To tice on mischiefe. I am great in blood,</L>
<L>Vnequald in reuenge. You horrid scouts,</L>
<L>That centinell swart night, giue lowde applause</L>
<L>From your large palms. First know, my hart was rais'd</L>
<L>Vnto <HI>Andrugios</HI> life, vpon this ground:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Str.</SPEAKER>
<L>Duke, tis reported</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>We both were riuals in our May of blood,</L>
<L>Vnto <HI>Maria, <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="obscured" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Ferraras</HI> heire.</L>
<L>He wan the Ladie, to my honours death:</L>
<L>And from her sweetes, cropt this <HI>Antonio</HI>:</L>
<L>For which, I burnt in inward sweltring hate,</L>
<L>And festred rankling malice in my breast,</L>
<L>Till I might belke reuenge vpon his eyes:</L>
<L>And now (ô blessed now) tis done. Hell, night,</L>
<L>Giue lowde applause to my hypocrisie.</L>
<L>When his bright valour euen dazled sense,</L>
<L>In offring his owne heade, publick reproach</L>
<L>Had blurd my name. Speake <HI>Strotzo,</HI> had it not?</L>
<L>If then I had</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Str.</SPEAKER>
<L>It had, so please</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="4"/>
<SPEAKER>Pier.</SPEAKER>
<L>What had so please? Vnseasoned Sycophant,</L>
<L><HI>Piero Sforza</HI> is no nummed Lord,</L>
<L>Senselesse of all true touch; stroake not the head</L>
<L>Of infant speach, till it be fully borne▪</L>
<L>Goe to.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Strot.</SPEAKER>
<P>How now? Fut, Ile not smother your speach.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, right thine eyes: twas but a little splene:</L>
<L>(Huge plunge!</L>
<L>Sinn's growne a slaue, and must obserue slight euils.</L>
<L>Huge villaines are inforc't to clawe all diuels.)</L>
<L>Pish, sweete thy thoughts, and giue me</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Str.</SPEAKER>
<P>Stroake not the heade of infant speach? Goe to?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, calme this storme. I euer held thy breast</L>
<L>More secret, and more firme in league of blood,</L>
<L>Then to be struck in heate with each-slight puffe.</L>
<L>Giue me thy eares; Huge infamie</L>
<L>Presse downe my honour; if euen then, when</L>
<L>His fresh act of prowesse bloom'd out full,</L>
<L>I had tane vengeance on his hated head</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Str.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why it had</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pier.</SPEAKER>
<L>Could I auoyde to giue a seeming graunt</L>
<L>Vnto fruition of <HI>Antonios</HI> loue?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Str.</SPEAKER>
<P>No.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>And didst thou euer see, a <HI>Iudas</HI> kisse,</L>
<L>With a more couert touch of fleering hate?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<P>No.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>And hauing clipt them with pretence of loue,</L>
<L>Haue I not crusht them with a cruell wring?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Strot.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Piero.</SPEAKER>
<L>Say, faith, didst thou ere heare, or reade, or see</L>
<L><PB REF="4"/>Such happie vengeance, vnsuspected death?</L>
<L>That I should drop strong poyson in the boawle,</L>
<L>Which I my selfe carous't vnto his health,</L>
<L>And future fortune of our vnitie,</L>
<L>That it should worke even in the husht of night,</L>
<L>And strangle him on sodaine; that faire showe</L>
<L>Of death, for the excessiue ioy of his fate,</L>
<L>Might choake the murder? Ha <HI>Strotzo,</HI> is't not rare?</L>
<L>Nay, but waigh it. Then <HI>Feliche</HI> stabd</L>
<L>(Whose sinking thought frighted my conscious hart)</L>
<L>And laid by <HI>Mellida,</HI> to stop the match,</L>
<L>And hale on mischiefe. This all in one night?</L>
<L>Is't to be equall'd thinkst thou? O, I could eate</L>
<L>Thy fumbling throat, for thy lagd censure. Fut,</L>
<L>Is't not rare?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Str.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>No? yes? nothing but no, and yes, dull lumpe?</L>
<L>Canst thou not hony me with fluent speach,</L>
<L>And euen adore my toplesse villany?</L>
<L>Will I not blast my owne blood for reuenge?</L>
<L>Must not thou straight be periur'd for reuenge▪</L>
<L>And yet no creature dreame tis my reuenge.</L>
<L>Will I not turne a glorious bridall morne</L>
<L>Vnto a <HI>Stygian</HI> night? Yet naught but no, and yes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Str.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would haue told you, if the <HI>incubus,</HI></L>
<L>That rides your bosome, would haue patience:</L>
<L>It is reported, that in priuate state,</L>
<L><HI>Maria, Genous</HI> Dutchesse, makes to Court,</L>
<L>Longing to see him, whom she nere shall see,</L>
<L>Her Lord <HI>Andrugio.</HI> Belike she hath receiu'd</L>
<L><PB REF="5"/>The newes of reconciliation:</L>
<L>Reconciliation with a death?</L>
<L>Poore Ladie shall but finde poore comfort in't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, let me swoone for ioy. By heauen, I thinke</L>
<L>I ha said my prayers, within this month at least;</L>
<L>I am so boundlesse happie. Doth she come?</L>
<L>By this warme reeking goare, Ile marrie her.</L>
<L>Looke I not now like an inamorate?</L>
<L>Poyson the father, butcher the son, &amp; marry the mo∣ther; ha!</L>
<L><HI>Strotzo,</HI> to bed: snort in securest sleepe:</L>
<L>For see, the dapple gray coursers of the morne</L>
<L>Beat vp the light with their bright siluer hooues,</L>
<L>And chase it through the skye. To bed, to bed.</L>
<L>This morne my vengeance shall be amply fed. <STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA SECVNDA.</HEAD>
<STAGE>¶ <HI>Enter Luceo, Maria, and Nutriche.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>STAY gentle <HI>Luceo,</HI> and vouchsafe thy hand.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lu.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, Madam</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, pree thee giue me leaue to say, vouchsafe,</L>
<L>Submisse intreats beseeme my humble fate.</L>
<L>Here let vs sit. O <HI>Luceo,</HI> fortunes gilt</L>
<L>Is rubd quite off from my slight tin-foild state,</L>
<L>And poore <HI>Maria</HI> must appeare vngrac't</L>
<L>Of the bright fulgor of gloss'd maiestie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cheer vp your spirits Madam; fairer chance</L>
<L>Then that which courts your presence instantly,</L>
<L>Can not be formd by the quick mould of thought.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="5"/>
<SPEAKER>Mari.</SPEAKER>
<L>Art thou assur'd the dukes are reconcil'd▪</L>
<L>Shall my wombes honour wed faire <HI>Mellida?</HI></L>
<L>Will heauen at length grant harbour to my head?</L>
<L>Shall I once more clip my <HI>Andrugio?</HI></L>
<L>And wreath my armes about <HI>Antonio's</HI> necke?</L>
<L>Or is glib rumor growne a parasite,</L>
<L>Holding a false glasse to my sorrowes eyes,</L>
<L>Making the wrinkl'd front of griefe seeme faire,</L>
<L>Though tis much riueld with abortiue care.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most virtuous Princesse, banish straggling feare;</L>
<L>Keepe league with comfort. For these eyes beheld</L>
<L>Tke Dukes vnited; you faint glimmering light</L>
<L>Nere peeped through the crannies of the east,</L>
<L>Since I beheld them drinke a sound carouse,</L>
<L>In sparkling <HI>Bacchus,</HI></L>
<L>Vnto eache others health;</L>
<L>Your sonne assur'd to beautious <HI>Mellida</HI>:</L>
<L>And all clouds clear'd of threatning discontent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<P>What age is morning of?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lu.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thinke 'bout fiue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Nutriche, Nutriche.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Beshrow your fingers marry, you haue disturb'd the pleasure of the finest dreame. O God, I was euen comming to it lawe▪ O Iesu, twas comming of the swe∣test. Ile tell you now, me thought I was maried, and mee thought I spent (O Lord why did you wake mee) and mee thought I spent three spur Roials on the Fid∣lers for striking vp a fresh hornepipe. Saint <HI>Vrsula,</HI> I was euen going to bed, &amp; you, mee thought, my hus∣band was euen putting out the tapers, when you, Lord
<PB REF="6"/>
I shall neuer haue such a dreame come vpon mee, as long as</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace idle creature, peace.</L>
<L>When will the Court rise?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, twere best you tooke some lodging vp,</L>
<L>And lay in priuate till the soile of griefe</L>
<L>Were cleard your cheeke, and new burnisht lustre</L>
<L>Cloath'd your presence, 'fore you sawe the Dukes,</L>
<L>And enterd, 'mong the proud <HI>Venetian</HI> States.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>No <HI>Lucio,</HI> my deare Lord's wise, and knowes</L>
<L>That tinsill glitter, or rich purfled robes,</L>
<L>Curled haires, hung full of sparkling Carcanets,</L>
<L>Are not the true adornements of a wife.</L>
<L>So long as wiues are faithfull, modest, chaste,</L>
<L>Wise Lords affect them. Vertue doth not waste,</L>
<L>With each slight flame of crackling vanitie.</L>
<L>A modest eye forceth affection,</L>
<L>Whilest outward gainesse light lookes but entice.</L>
<L>Fairer then Natures faire is fowlest vice.</L>
<L>She that loues Art, to get her cheeke more louers,</L>
<L>Much outward gaudes slight inward grace discouers.</L>
<L>I care not to seeme faire, but to my Lord.</L>
<L>Those that striue most to please most strangers sight,</L>
<L>Follie may iudge most faire, wisdome most light.</L>
<STAGE>¶ <HI>Musique sounds a short straine.</HI></STAGE>
<L>But harke, soft musique gently mooues the ayre:</L>
<L>I thinke the bridegroom's vp. <HI>Lucio,</HI> stand close.</L>
<L>O, now <HI>Marya,</HI> chalenge griefe to stay</L>
<L>Thy ioyes encounter. Looke <HI>Lucio,</HI> tis cleare day.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<PB REF="6"/>
<HEAD>SCENA TERTIA.</HEAD>
<STAGE>¶ <HI>Enter Antonio, Galeatzo, Matzagente, Balurdo, Pandulpho Feliche, Alberto, Forobosco, Ca∣stilio, and a Page.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>DARKNESSE is fled: looke, infant morn hath drawne</L>
<L>Bright siluer curtains, 'bout the couch of night:</L>
<L>And now <HI>Auroras</HI> horse trots azure rings,</L>
<L>Breathing faire light about the firmament,</L>
<L>Stand, what's that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>And if a horned diuell should burst forth,</L>
<L>I would passe on him with a mortall stocke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, a horned diuell would prooue ominous,</L>
<L>Vnto a bridegroomes eyes,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<P>A horned diuel? good, good: ha ha ha, very good.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good tand prince laugh not. By the ioyes of loue,</L>
<L>When thou dost girne, thy rusty face doth looke</L>
<L>Like the head of a rosted rabbit: fie vpont.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>By my troth, me thinks his nose is iust colour <HI>de Roy</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<P>I tel thee foole, my nose will abide no iest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<P>No in truth, I doe not ieast, I speake truth. Truth is the touchstone of all things: and if your nose will not abide the truth, your nose will not abide the touch: and if your nose will not abide the touch, your nose is a copper nose, and must be nail'd vp for a slip.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<P>I scorne to retort the obtuse ieast of a foole.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Balurdo drawes out his writing tables, and writes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Retort and obtuse, good words, very good words.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="7"/>
<SPEAKER>Gal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Young Prince, looke sprightly; fie, a bridegroom sadde!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<P>In truth, if he were retort, and obtuse, no questi∣on, hee would bee merrie: but and please my <HI>Genius,</HI> I will be most retort and obtuse ere night. Ile tell you, what Ile beare soone at night in my shielde, for my deuice.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gal.</SPEAKER>
<P>What, good <HI>Balurdo?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<P>O, doe me right: sir <HI>Gefferey Balurdo</HI>: sir, sir, as long as yee liue, sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gal.</SPEAKER>
<P>What, good sir <HI>Gefferey Balurdo?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<P>Marry forsooth, Ile carrie for my deuice, my grand fathers great stone-hors, flinging vp his head, &amp; ierking out his left legge. The word; <HI>Wighy Purt.</HI> As I am a true knight, wil't not bee most retort and obtuse, ha?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Blowe hence these faplesse iestes. I tell you bloods</L>
<L>My spirit's heauie, and the iuyce of life</L>
<L>Creepes slowly through my stifned arteries.</L>
<L>Last sleep, my sense was steep't in horrid dreames:</L>
<L>Three parrs of night were swallow'd in the gulfe</L>
<L>Of rauenous time, when to my slumbring powers,</L>
<L>Two meager ghosts made apparition.</L>
<L>The on's breast seem'd fresh pauncht with bleeding wounds:</L>
<L>Whose bubling gore sprang in frighted eyes.</L>
<L>The other ghost assum'd my fathers shape:</L>
<L>Both cride <HI>Reuenge.</HI> At which my trembling ioynts</L>
<L>(Iced quite ouer with a froz'd cold sweate)</L>
<L>Leap't forth the sheets. Three times I gasp't at shades:</L>
<L>And thrice, deluded by erroneous sense,</L>
<L>I forc't my thoughts make stand; when loe, I op't</L>
<L><PB REF="7"/>A large bay window, through which the night</L>
<L>Struck terror to my soule. The verge of heauen</L>
<L>Was ringd with flames, and all the vpper vault</L>
<L>Thick lac't with flakes of fire; in midst whereof</L>
<L>A blazing Comet shot his threatning traine</L>
<L>Iust on my face. Viewing these prodigies,</L>
<L>I bow'd my naked knee, and pierc't the starre,</L>
<L>With an outfacing eye; pronouncing thus;</L>
<L><HI>Deus imperat astris.</HI> At which, my nose straight bled:</L>
<L>Then doubl'd I my word, so slunke to bed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<P>Verely, sir <HI>Gefferey</HI> had a monstrous strange dream the last night. For mee thought I dreamt I was asleepe, and me thought the ground yaun'd and belkt vp the abhominable ghost of a misshapen <HI>Simile,</HI> with two vgly Pages; the one called master, euen as going be∣fore; and the other <HI>Mounser,</HI> euen so following after; whil'st <HI>Signior Simile</HI> stalked most prodigiously in the midst. At which I bewrayed the fearefulnesse of my nature: and being readie to forsake the fortresse of my wit, start vp, called for a cleane shirt, eate a messe of broth, and with that I awakt.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>I pree thee peace. I tell you gentlemen,</L>
<L>The frightfull shades of night yet shake my braine:</L>
<L>My gellied blood's not thaw'd: the sulphur damps,</L>
<L>That flowe in winged lightning 'bout my couch,</L>
<L>Yet stick within my sense, my soule is great,</L>
<L>In expectation of dire prodigies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tut, my young Prince, let not thy fortunes see</L>
<L>Their Lord a coward. He, thats nobly borne,</L>
<L>Abhorres to feare. Base feare's the brand of slaues.</L>
<L><PB REF="8"/>Hee that obserues, pursues, slinks back for fright,</L>
<L>Was neuer cast in mould of noble spright.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ga.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tush, there's a fun will straight exhale these damps</L>
<L>Of chilling feare. Come, shal's salute the bride?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant, Castilio,</SPEAKER>
<L>I pree the mixe thy breath with his:</L>
<L>Sing one of <HI>Signior Renaldo's</HI> ayres,</L>
<L>To rouse the slumbring bride from gluttoning,</L>
<L>In surfet of superfluous sleepe. Good Signior, sing.</L>
<STAGE>CANTANT.</STAGE>
<L>What meanes this silence and vnmooued calme!</L>
<L>Boy, winde thy Cornet: force the leaden gates</L>
<L>Of lasie sleepe fly open, with thy breath,</L>
<L>My <HI>Mellida</HI> not vp? not stirring yet? vmh.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<P>That voice, should be my sonnes <HI>Antonio's. Antonio?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here, who cals? here stands <HI>Antonio.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mari.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sweete sonne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Deare mother.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faire honour of a chast and loyall bed,</L>
<L>Thy fathers beautie, thy sad mothers loue,</L>
<L>Were I as powrefull as the voice of fate,</L>
<L>Felicitie compleat should sweete thy state:</L>
<L>But all the blessings, that a poore banisht wretch,</L>
<L>Can powre vpon thy heade, take gentle sonne:</L>
<L>Liue, gratious youth, to close thy mothers eyes,</L>
<L>Lou'd of thy parents, till their latest hower:</L>
<L>How cheares my Lord, thy father? O sweet boy,</L>
<L>Part of him thus I clip, my deare, deare ioy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="8"/>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, last night I kist his princely hand,</L>
<L>And tooke a treasur'd blessing from his lips:</L>
<L>O mother, you arriue in <HI>Iubile,</HI></L>
<L>And firme attonement of all boystrous rage:</L>
<L>Pleasure, vnited loue, protested faith,</L>
<L>Guard my lou'd father, as sworne Pensioners:</L>
<L>The Dukes are leagu'd in firmest bond of loue,</L>
<L>And you arriue euen in the <HI>Solsticie,</HI></L>
<L>And highest point of sun-shine happinesse.</L>
<STAGE>¶ <HI>One windes a Cornet within.</HI></STAGE>
<L>Harke Madam, how you Cornet ierketh vp</L>
<L>His straind shrill accents, in the capering ayre;</L>
<L>As proud to summon vp my bright cheek't loue.</L>
<L>Now, mother, ope wide expectation:</L>
<L>Let loose your amplest sense, to entertaine</L>
<L>Th'impression of an obiect of such worth,</L>
<L>That life's too poore to▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay leaue <HI>Hyperboles.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>I tel thee prince, that presence straight appears,</L>
<L>Of which thou canst not forme <HI>Hyperboles,</HI></L>
<L>The trophy of tryumphing excellence:</L>
<L>The heart of beautie, <HI>Mellida</HI> appeares.</L>
<L>See, looke, the curtaine stirs, shine natures pride,</L>
<L>Loues vitall spirit, deare <HI>Antonio's</HI> bride.</L>
<STAGE>¶ <HI>The Curtain's drawne, and the bodie of Feliche, stabd thick with wounds, appeares hung vp.</HI></STAGE>
<L>What villaine bloods the window of my loue?</L>
<L>What slaue hath hung you gorie ensigne vp,</L>
<L>In flat defiance of humanitie?</L>
<L>Awake thou faire vnspotted puritie.</L>
<L><PB REF="9"/>Death's at thy windowe, awake bright <HI>Mellida</HI>:</L>
<L><HI>Antonio</HI> cals.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="4" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA QVARTA.</HEAD>
<STAGE>¶ <HI>Enter Piero as at first, with Forobosco.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVHO giues these il-befitting attributes</L>
<L>Of chast, vnspotted, bright, to <HI>Mellida,</HI></L>
<L>He lies as lowde as thunder, shee's vnchast,</L>
<L>Tainted, impure, blacke as the soule of hell.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>¶ <HI>He drawes his rapier, offers to runne at Piero: but Maria holds his arme &amp; staies him.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dog, I will make the eate thy vomit vp,</L>
<L>Which thou hast belk't gainst taintlesse <HI>Mellida.</HI></L>
<L>Ramm't quicklie downe, that it may not rise vp</L>
<L>To imbraid my thoughts. Behold my stomack's:</L>
<L>Strike me quite through with the relentlesse edge</L>
<L>Of raging furie. Boy, Ile kill thy loue</L>
<L><HI>Pandulfe Feliche,</HI> I haue stabd thy sonne:</L>
<L>Looke, yet his lifeblood reekes vpon this steele.</L>
<L><HI>Albert,</HI> you hangs thy friend▪ Haue none of you</L>
<L>Courage of vengeance? Forget I am your Duke.</L>
<L>Thinke <HI>Mellida</HI> is not <HI>Pieros</HI> bloode.</L>
<L>Imagine on slight ground, Ile blast his honour.</L>
<L>Suppose I sawe not that incestuous slaue,</L>
<L>Clipping the strumpet, with luxurious twines:</L>
<L>O, numme my sense of anguish, cast my life</L>
<L>In a dead sleepe, whilst lawe cuts off yon maine,</L>
<L>Yon putred vlcer of my roiall bloode.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Foro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Keepe league with reason, gratious Soueraigne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="9"/>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>There glowe no sparkes of reason in the world;</L>
<L>All are rak't vp in ashie beastlinesse.</L>
<L>The bulke of man's as darke as <HI>Erebus,</HI></L>
<L>No branch of Reasons light hangs in his trunke:</L>
<L>There liues no reason to keepe league withall.</L>
<L>I ha no reason to be reasonable.</L>
<L>Her wedding eue, linkt to the noble blood</L>
<L>Of my most firmely reconciled friend,</L>
<L>And found euen clingd in sensualitie!</L>
<L>O heauen! O heauen! Were she as neare my heart</L>
<L>As is my liuer, I would rend her off.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="5" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA QVINTA.</HEAD>
<STAGE>¶ <HI>Enter Strozzo.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Str.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVHITHER, O whither shal I hurle vast griefe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pier.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here, into my breast: tis a place built wide</L>
<L>By fate, to giue receipt to boundlesse woes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Str.</SPEAKER>
<L>O no; here throb those hearts, which I must cleaue</L>
<L>With my keene pearcing newes. <HI>Andrugio's</HI> dead.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pier.</SPEAKER>
<P>Dead?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<P>O me most miserable.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dead, alas, how dead? <STAGE>Giue seeming passion.</STAGE></L>
<L>Fut weepe, act, faine. Dead, alas, how dead?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Str.</SPEAKER>
<L>The vast delights of his large sodaine ioyes</L>
<L>Opned his powers so wide, that's natiue heate</L>
<L>So prodigally flow'd, t'exterior parts,</L>
<L>That thinner Citadell was left vnmand,</L>
<L>And so surpriz'd onsodaine by colde death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="10"/>
<SPEAKER>Mari▪</SPEAKER>
<L>O fatal, disastrous, cursed, dismall!</L>
<L>Choake breath and life▪ I breath, I liue too long.</L>
<L><HI>Andrugio</HI> my Lord, I come, I come.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be cheerefull Princesse, help <HI>Castilio,</HI></L>
<L>The Ladie's swouned, helpe to beare her in.</L>
<L>Slow comfort to huge cares, is swiftest sin.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Courage, courage sweet Ladie, tis sir <HI>Gefferey Ba∣lurdo</HI>
bids you courage. Truly I am as nimble as an E∣lephant about a Ladie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Dead?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Dead.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Dead?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>An.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why now the womb of mischiefe is deliuer'd,</L>
<L>Of the prodigious issue of the night.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha, ha, ha.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>My father dead, my loue attaint of lust:</L>
<L>Thats a large lye, as vast as spatious hell:</L>
<L>Poore guiltlesse Ladie. O accursed lye.</L>
<L>What, whome, whether, which shall I first lament?</L>
<L>A deade father, a dishonour'd wife. Stand.</L>
<L>Me thinkes I feele the frame of nature shake.</L>
<L>Cracks not the ioynts of earth to beare my woes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sweet Prince, be patient.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>S'lid sir, I will not in despight of thee.</L>
<L>Patience is slaue to fooles: a chaine that's fixt</L>
<L>Onely to postes, and senslesse log-like dolts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis reasons glorie to commaund affects.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>An.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lies thy cold father dead, his glossed eyes</L>
<L>New closed vp by thy sad mothers hands?</L>
<L>Hast thou a loue as spotlesse as the browe</L>
<L>Of clearest heauen, blurd with false defames?</L>
<L>Are thy moyst entrals crumpled vp with griefe</L>
<L><PB REF="10"/>Of parching mischiefs? Tel me, does thy hart</L>
<L>With punching anguish spur thy galled ribs?</L>
<L>Then come and let's sit and weep &amp; wreath our arms:</L>
<L>Ile heare thy counsell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take comfort</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Confusion to all comfort: I defie it.</L>
<L>Comfort's a Parasite, a flattring Iack:</L>
<L>And melts resolu'd despaire. O boundlesse woe,</L>
<L>If there be any black yet vnknowen griefe:</L>
<L>If there be any horror yet vnfelt,</L>
<L>Vnthought of mischiefe in thy fiendlike power,</L>
<L>Dash it vpon my miserable heade.</L>
<L>Make me more wretch, more cursed if thou canst.</L>
<L>O, now my fate is more than I could feare:</L>
<L>My woes more waightie than my soule can beare. <STAGE>Exit</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, ha, ha,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why laugh you vncle? Thats my cuz, your son,</L>
<L>Whose brest hangs cased in his cluttered gore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pa.</SPEAKER>
<L>True man, true: why, wherfore should I weepe?</L>
<L>Come sit, kinde Nephew: come on: thou and I</L>
<L>Will talke as <HI>Chorus</HI> to this tragedie▪</L>
<L>Intreat the musick straine their instruments,</L>
<L>With a slight touch whilst we. Say on fair cuz.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<L>He was the very hope of Italy, <STAGE>Musick sounds softly.</STAGE></L>
<L>The blooming honour of your drooping age.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P.</SPEAKER>
<L>True cuz, true. They say that men of hope are crusht:</L>
<L>Good are supprest by base desertlesse clods,</L>
<L>That stifle gasping vertue. Look sweet youth,</L>
<L>How prouident our quick <HI>Venetians</HI> are,</L>
<L>Least houes of iades should trample on my boy:</L>
<L>Looke how they lift him vp to eminence,</L>
<L>Heaue him, boue reach of flesh. Ha, ha, ha.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="11"/>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Vncle, this laughter ill becomes your griefe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would'st haue me cry, run rauing vp &amp; down,</L>
<L>For my sons losse? would'st haue me turn rank mad,</L>
<L>Or wring my face with mimick action;</L>
<L>Stampe, curse, weepe, rage, &amp; then my bosome strike?</L>
<L>Away tis apish action, player-like.</L>
<L>If hee is guiltlesse, why should teares be spent?</L>
<L>Thrice blessed soule that dyeth innocent.</L>
<L>If he is leapred with so foule a guilt,</L>
<L>Why should a sigh be lent, a teare be spilt?</L>
<L>The gripe of chaunce is weake, to wring a teare,</L>
<L>From him that knowes what fortitude should beare.</L>
<L>Listen young blood. Tis not true valors pride,</L>
<L>To swagger, quarrell, sweare, stampe, raue, and chide,</L>
<L>To stab in fume of blood, to keepe lowde coyle,</L>
<L>To bandie factions in domestick broyles,</L>
<L>To dare the act of Sins, whose filth excels.</L>
<L>The blackest customes of blinde Infidels.</L>
<L>No, my lou'd youth: he may of valour vaunt;</L>
<L>Whom fortunes lowdest thunder can not daunt,</L>
<L>Whom fretful gaules of chance, sterne fortunes siege;</L>
<L>Makes not his reason slinke, the soules faire liege,</L>
<L>Whose well pais'd action euer rests vpon</L>
<L>Not giddie humours, but discretion.</L>
<L>This heart in valour euen <HI>Ioue</HI> out-goes:</L>
<L><HI>Ioue</HI> is without, but this 'boue sense of woes:</L>
<L>And such a one eternitie: Behold,</L>
<L>Good morrow sonne: thou bidst a fig for colde.</L>
<L>Sound lowder musick: let my breath exact,</L>
<L>You strike sad Tones vnto this dismall act.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="11"/>
<HEAD>ACT. II.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCEN. I.</HEAD>
<STAGE>The Cornets sound a cynet.</STAGE>
<STAGE>¶ <HI>Enter two mourners with torches, two with streamers: Castilio &amp; Forobosco, with torches: a Heralde bearing Andrugio's helme &amp; sword, the coffin: Maria supported by Lucio and Alberto, Antonio by himselfe: Piero, and Strozzo talking: Galeatzo and Matzagente, Balurdo &amp; Pandulfo: the coffin set downe: helme, sworde, and strea∣mers hung vp, placed by the Herald: whil'st Antonio and Maria wet their handkerchers with their teares, kisse them, and lay them on the hearse, kneeling: all goe out but Piero. Cornets cease, and he speakes.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>ROT ther thou cearcloth that infolds the flesh</L>
<L>Of my loath'd foe; moulder to crūbling dust:</L>
<L>Obliuion choake the passage of thy fame.</L>
<L>Trophees of honor'd birth droppe quickly downe:</L>
<L>Let naught of him, but what was vitious, liue.</L>
<L>Though thou art deade, thinke not my hate is dead:</L>
<L>I haue but newly twone my arme in the curld locks</L>
<L>Of snakie vengeance. Pale beetle-brow'd hate</L>
<L>But newly bustles vp. Sweet wrong, I clap thy thoughts.</L>
<L>O let me hug my bosome, rub my breast,</L>
<L>In hope of what may happe. <HI>Andrugio</HI> rots:</L>
<L><HI>Antonio</HI> liues: vmh: how long? ha, ha; how long?</L>
<L><PB REF="12"/><HI>Antonio</HI> packt hence, Ile his mother wed,</L>
<L>Then cleare my daughter of supposed lust,</L>
<L>Wed her to <HI>Florence</HI> heire. O excellent.</L>
<L><HI>Venice, Genoa, Florence,</HI> at my becke,</L>
<L>At <HI>Piero's</HI> nod, <HI>Balurdo,</HI> ô ho.</L>
<L>O, twill be rare, all vnsuspected donne.</L>
<L>I haue bin nurst in blood, and still haue suckt</L>
<L>The steeme of reeking gore. <HI>Balurdo,</HI> ho?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>¶ <HI>Enter Balurdo with a beard, halfe of, halfe on.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<P>When my beard is on, most noble prince, when my beard is on.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pier.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, what dost thou with a beard?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<P>In truth, one tolde me that my wit was balde, &amp; that a Meremaide was halfe fish, and halfe fish: and therefore to speake wisely, like one of your counsell, as indeede it hath pleased you to make me, not onely being a foole, of your counsell, but also to make me of your counsell, being a foole; If my wit be bald, and a Mermaid be halfe fish and halfe cunger, then I must be forced to conclude the tyring man hath not glewd on my beard halfe fast, enough. Gods bores, it wil not stick to fal off.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>Dost thou know what thou hast spoken all this while?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<P>O Lord Duke, I would be sorie of that. Many men can vtter that which, no man, but themselues can conceiue: but I thanke a good wit, I haue the gift to speake that which neither any man els, nor my selfe vnderstands.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou art wise. He that speaks he knows not what, shal neuer sin against his own conscience: go to, thou
<PB REF="12"/>
art wise.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wise? O no. I haue a little naturall discretion, or so: but for wise, I am somewhat prudent: but for wise, ô Lord▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie▪</SPEAKER>
<P>Hold, take those keyes, open the Castle vault, &amp; put in <HI>Mellida.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>And put in <HI>Mellida?</HI> well, let me alone,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bid <HI>Forobosco,</HI> and <HI>Castilio</HI> guard,</L>
<L>Indeere thy selfe <HI>Piero's</HI> intimate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeere, and intimate: good, I assure you. I will indeere and intimate <HI>Mellida</HI> into the dūgeon presētly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>Will <HI>Pandulfo Feliche</HI> waite on me?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will make him come, most retort and obtuse, to you presently. I thinke, sir <HI>Ieffrey</HI> talks like a counseller. Go to, gods neaks, I thinke I tickle it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile seeme to winde you foole with kindest arme.</L>
<L>He that's ambitious minded, and but man,</L>
<L>Must haue his followers beasts, dubd slauish sots:</L>
<L>Whose seruice is obedience, and whose wit</L>
<L>Reacheth no further then to admire their Lord,</L>
<L>And stare in adoration of his worth.</L>
<L>I loue, a slaue rak't out of common mud</L>
<L>Should seeme to sit in counsell with my heart.</L>
<L>High honour'd blood's too squemish to assent,</L>
<L>And lend a hand to an ignoble act▪</L>
<L>Poyson from roses who could ere abstract?</L>
<L>How now <HI>Pandulfo,</HI> weeping for thy sonne?</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<PB REF="13"/>
<HEAD>SCENA SECVNDA.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Pandulfo.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>NO no, <HI>Piero,</HI> weeping for my sinnes:</L>
<L>Had I bin a good father, he had bin a gratious sonne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pollution must be purg'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why taintst thou then the ayre with stench of flesh,</L>
<L>And humane putrifactions noysome sent?</L>
<L>I pray his bodie. Who lesse boone can craue,</L>
<L>Than to bestowe vpon the deade, his graue?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Graue? why? think'st thou he deserues a graue,</L>
<L>That hath defil'd the temple of</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace, peace:</L>
<L>Me thinks I heare a humming murmur creepe</L>
<L>From out his gelli'd wounds. Looke on those lips,</L>
<L>Those now lawne pillowes, on whose tender softnesse,</L>
<L>Chaste modest speach, stealing from out his breast,</L>
<L>Had wont to rest it selfe, as loath to poast</L>
<L>From out so faire an Inne: look, look, they seeme to stir,</L>
<L>And breath defyance to black obloquie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>Think'st thou thy sonne could suffer wrongfully?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>A wise man wrongfully, but neuer wrong</L>
<L>Can take: his breast's of such well tempered proofe,</L>
<L>It may be rac'd, not pearc't by sauage tooth</L>
<L>Of foaming malice: showers of dartes may darke</L>
<L>Heauens ample browe: but not strike out a sparke;</L>
<L>Much lesse pearce the Suns cheek. Such songs as these,</L>
<L><PB REF="13"/>I often dittied till my boy did sleepe:</L>
<L>But now I turne plaine foole (alas) I weepe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fore heauen he makes me shrug: wold a were deade:</L>
<L>He is a vertuous man. What has our court to doe</L>
<L>With vertue, in the diuels name! <HI>Pandulpho,</HI> harke.</L>
<L>My lustfull daughter dies: start not, she dies.</L>
<L>I pursue iustice, I loue sanctitie,</L>
<L>And an vndefiled temple of pure thoughts.</L>
<L>Shall I speake freely? Good <HI>Andrugio's</HI> dead:</L>
<L>And I doe feare a fetch; but (vmh) would I durst speake.</L>
<L>I doe mistrust; but (vmh) death: is he all, all man:</L>
<L>Hath he no part of mother in him, ha?</L>
<L>No licorish womanish inquisitiuenesse?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Andrugio's</HI> deade!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, and I feare, his owne vnnaturall blood,</L>
<L>To whome he gaue life, hath giuen death for life.</L>
<L>How could he come on, I see false suspect</L>
<L>Is vicde; wrung hardly in a vertuous heart.</L>
<L>Well, I could giue you reason for my doubts.</L>
<L>You are of honour'd birth, my very friende.</L>
<L>You know how god-like tis to roote out sin.</L>
<L><HI>Antonio</HI> is a villaine. Will you ioyne</L>
<L>In oath with me, against the traitors life,</L>
<L>And sweare, you knewe, he sought his fathers death?</L>
<L>I lou'd him well, yet I loue iustice more:</L>
<L>Our friends we should affect, iustice adore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, the clapper of my mouth's not glibd</L>
<L>With court oyle, twill not strike on both sides yet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis iust that subiectes acte commaunds of kings.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Commaund then iust and honorable things.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="14"/>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>Euen so my selfe then will traduce his guilt.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Beware, take heed least guiltlesse blood be spilt.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where onely honest deeds to kings are free,</L>
<L>It is no empire, but a beggery.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where more than noble deeds to kings are free,</L>
<L>It is no empire, but a tyranny.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tush iuicelesse graybeard, tis immunity,</L>
<L>Proper to princes, that our state exactes,</L>
<L>Our subiects not alone to beare, but praise our acts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, but that prince that worthfull praise aspires,</L>
<L>From hearts, and not from lips, applause desires.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pish, true praise, the brow of common men doth ring,</L>
<L>False, only girts the temple of a king,</L>
<L>He that hath strength, and's ignorant of power,</L>
<L>He was not made to rule, but to be rul'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis praise to doe, not what we can, but should.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hence doting Stoick: by my hope of blisse,</L>
<L>Ile make thee wretched.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Defyance to thy power, thou rifted Iawne.</L>
<L>Now, by the lou'd heauen, sooner thou shalt</L>
<L>Rince thy soule ribs from the black filth of sinne,</L>
<L>That soots thy heart, then make me wretched. Pish,</L>
<L>Thou canst not coupe me vp. Hadst thou a Iaile</L>
<L>With trebble walles, like antick <HI>Babilon,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Pandulpho</HI> can get out. I tell thee Duke,</L>
<L>I haue ould <HI>Fortunatus</HI> wishing cappe:</L>
<L>And can be where I list, euen in a trice.</L>
<L>Ile skippe from earth into the armes of heauen:</L>
<L>And from tryumphall arch of blessednesse,</L>
<L>Spit on thy froathy breast. Thou canst not slaue</L>
<L><PB REF="14"/>Or banish me; I will be free at home,</L>
<L>Maugre the bearde of greatnesse. The port holes</L>
<L>Of sheathed spirit are nere corb'd vp:</L>
<L>But still stand open readie to discharge</L>
<L>Their pretious shot into the shrowds of heauen▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>O torture! slaue, I banish thee the towne,</L>
<L>Thy natiue seate of birth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pa.</SPEAKER>
<L>How proud thou speak'st! I tell thee Duke, the blasts</L>
<L>Of the swolne cheekt winds, nor all the breath of kings</L>
<L>Can puffe me out my natiue seat of birth.</L>
<L>The earth's my bodies, and the heauen's my soules</L>
<L>Most natiue place of birth, which they will keepe:</L>
<L>Despite the menace of mortalitie.</L>
<L>Why Duke:</L>
<L>That's not my natiue place, where I was rockt.</L>
<L>A wise mans home is wheresoere he is wise.</L>
<L>Now that, from man, not from the place doth rise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wold I were deafe (ô plague) hence dotard wretch:</L>
<L>Tread not in court. All that thou hast, I seize.</L>
<L>His quiet's firmer then I can disease.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe, boast vnto thy flattring Sycophants;</L>
<L><HI>Pandulpho's</HI> slaue, <HI>Piero</HI> hath orethrowne.</L>
<L>Loose Fortunes rags are lost; my owne's my owne.</L>
<STAGE>¶ <HI>Piero's going out, lookes backe, Exeunt at seuerall doores.</HI></STAGE>
<L>Tis true <HI>Piero,</HI> thy vext heart shall see,</L>
<L>Thou hast but tript my slaue, not conquerd mee.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<PB REF="15"/>
<HEAD>SCENA TERTIA.</HEAD>
<STAGE>¶ <HI>Enter Antonio with a booke, Lucio, Alberto, Antonio in blacke.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<L>NAY sweet be comforted, take counsell and</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Alberto,</HI> peace: that griefe is wanton sick,</L>
<L>Whose stomacke can digest and brooke the dyet</L>
<L>Of stale ill relisht counsell. Pigmie cares</L>
<L>Can shelter vnder patience shield: but gyant griefes</L>
<L>Will burst all couert.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lu.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord, tis supper time.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Drinke deepe <HI>Alberto</HI>: eate, good <HI>Lucio</HI>:</L>
<L>But my pin'd heart shall eat on naught but woe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord, we dare not leaue you thus alone.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>You cannot leaue <HI>Antonio</HI> alone.</L>
<L>The chamber of my breast is euen throngd,</L>
<L>With firme attendance, that forsweares to flinch.</L>
<L>I haue a thing sits here; it is not griefe,</L>
<L>Tis not despaire, nor the most plague</L>
<L>That the most wretched are infected with:</L>
<L>But the most greefull, despairing, wretched,</L>
<L>Accursed, miserable. O, for heauens sake</L>
<L>Forsake me now; you see how light I am,</L>
<L>And yet you force me to defame my patience.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faire gentle prince</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away, thy voice is hatefull: thou dost buzze,</L>
<L><PB REF="15"/>And beat my eares with intimations</L>
<L>That <HI>Mellida,</HI> that <HI>Mellida</HI> is light,</L>
<L>And stained with adulterous luxury:</L>
<L>I cannot brook't. I tell the <HI>Lucio,</HI></L>
<L>Sooner will I giue faith, that vertue's scant</L>
<L>In princes courts, will be adorn'd with wreath</L>
<L>Of choyce respect, and indeerd intimate.</L>
<L>Sooner will I beleeue that friendships raine.</L>
<L>Will curbe ambition from vtilitie,</L>
<L>Then <HI>Mellida</HI> is light. Alas poore soule,</L>
<L>Didst ere see her (good heart) hast heard her speake?</L>
<L>Kinde, kinde soule▪ Incredulitie it selfe</L>
<L>Would not be so brasse hearted, as suspect so modest cheeks</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lu.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away, a selfe-one guilt doth onely hatch distrust:</L>
<L>But a chaste thought's as farre from doubt, as lust.</L>
<L>I intreat you leaue me,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Will you endeauour to forget your griefe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>I faith I will, good friend, I faith I will.</L>
<L>Ile come and eate with you. <HI>Alberto,</HI> see,</L>
<L>I am taking Physicke, heer's Philosophie.</L>
<L>Good honest leaue me, Ile drinke wine anone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Since you enforce vs, faire prince, we are gone.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Alberto and Lucio.</STAGE>
<STAGE>¶ <HI>Antonio reades.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>A.</SPEAKER>
<P><LETTER>
<P>Ferte fortiter: hoc est quo deum antecedatis. Ille enim ex∣tra patientiam malorum; vos supra. Contemnite dolorem: aut soluetur, aut soluet. Contemnite fortunā: nullū telū, quo feriret animum habet.</P>
</LETTER></P>
<LG>
<L>Pish, thy mother was not lately widdowed,</L>
<L><PB REF="16"/>Thy deare affied loue, lately defam'd,</L>
<L>With blemish of foule lust, when thou wrot'st thus.</L>
<L>Thou wrapt in furres, beaking thy lymbs 'fore fiers,</L>
<L>Forbidst the frozē Zone to shudder. Ha, ha: tis naught,</L>
<L>But fomie bubling of a fleamie braine,</L>
<L>Naught els but smoake. O what danke marrish spirit,</L>
<L>But would be fyred with impatience,</L>
<L>At my No more, no more: he that was neuer blest,</L>
<L>With height of birth, faire expectation</L>
<L>Of mounted fortunes, knowes not what it is</L>
<L>To be the pittied obiect of the worlde.</L>
<L>O, poore <HI>Antonio,</HI> thou maist sigh.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mell.</SPEAKER>
<P>Aye me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant▪</SPEAKER>
<P>And curse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Black powers.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>And cry.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<P>O heauen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>And close laments with</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<P>O me most miserable.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Woe for my deare deare sonne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Woe for my deare, deare husband.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Woe for my deare deare loue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Woe for me all, close all your woes in me:</L>
<L>In me <HI>Antonio,</HI> ha? Where liue these sounds?</L>
<L>I can see nothing; griefe's inuisible,</L>
<L>And lurkes in secret angles of the heart▪</L>
<L>Come sigh againe, <HI>Antonio</HI> beares his part.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mell.</SPEAKER>
<L>O here, here is a vent to passe my sighes.</L>
<L>I haue surcharg'd the dungeon with my plaints.</L>
<L>Prison, and heart will burst, if void of vent▪</L>
<L><PB REF="16"/>I, that is <HI>Phoebe,</HI> empresse of the night,</L>
<L>That gins to mount; ô chastest deitie:</L>
<L>If I be false to my <HI>Antonio,</HI></L>
<L>If the least soyle of lust smeers my pure loue,</L>
<L>Make me more wretched, make me more accurst</L>
<L>Then infamie, torture, death, hell and heauen</L>
<L>Can bound with amplest power of thought: if not,</L>
<L>Purge my poore heart, with defamations blot.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Purge my poore heart from defamations blot!</L>
<L>Poore heart, how like her vertuous selfe▪ she speakes.</L>
<L><HI>Mellida,</HI> deare <HI>Mellida,</HI> it is <HI>Antonio</HI>:</L>
<L>Slinke not away, tis thy <HI>Antonio.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>How found you out, my Lord (alas) I knowe</L>
<L>Tis easie in this age, to finde out woe.</L>
<L>I haue a sute to you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>What is't, deare soule?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mell.</SPEAKER>
<L>Kill me, I faith Ile winke, not stir a iot.</L>
<L>For God sake kill mee: insooth, lou'd youth,</L>
<L>I am much iniur'd; looke, see how I creepe.</L>
<L>I cannot wreake my wrong, but sigh and weepe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>An.</SPEAKER>
<P>May I be cursed, but I credit thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mell.</SPEAKER>
<P>To morrowe I must die▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>An.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas, for what?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mell.</SPEAKER>
<L>For louing thee; tis true my sweetest breast▪</L>
<L>I must die falsely: so must thou, deare heart.</L>
<L>Nets are a knitting to intrappe thy life.</L>
<L>Thy fathers death must make a Paradice</L>
<L>To my (I shame to call him) father. Tell me sweet,</L>
<L>Shall I die thine? dost loue mee still, and still?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="17"/>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>I doe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mell.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then welcome heauens will.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Madam, I will not swell like a Tragedian, in for∣ced passion of affected straines.</P>
<P>If I had present power of ought but pittying you, I would be as readie to redresse your wrongs, as to pur∣sue your loue. Throngs of thoughts crowde for their passage, somewhat I will doe.</P>
<LG>
<L>Reach me thy hand: thinke this is honors bent,</L>
<L>To liue vnslau'd, to die innocent.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me entreat a fauour, gratious loue.</L>
<L>Be patient, see me die, good doe not weepe:</L>
<L>Goe sup, sweete chuck, drinke, and securely sleepe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>I faith I cannot, but Ile force my face</L>
<L>To palliate my sicknesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mell.</SPEAKER>
<L>Giue me thy hand. Peace on thy bosome dwel:</L>
<L>Thats all my woe can breath: kisse. Thus farewell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Farewell: my heart is great of thoughts,</L>
<L>Stay doue:</L>
<L>And therefore I must speake: but what? ô Loue!</L>
<L>By this white hand: eno more: reade in these teares,</L>
<L>What crushing anguish thy <HI>Antonio</HI> beares.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Antonio kisseth Mellida's hand: then Mellida goes from the grate.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>God night good harte,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thus heate from blood, thus soules from bodies part.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>¶ <HI>Enter Piero and Strozzo.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie▪</SPEAKER>
<L>He greeues, laughe <HI>Strozzo</HI>: laugh, he weepes.</L>
<L>Hath he teares? ô pleasure! hath he teares?</L>
<L>Now doe I scourge <HI>Andrugio</HI> with steele whips</L>
<L><PB REF="17"/>Of knottie vengeance. <HI>Strozzo,</HI> cause me straight</L>
<L>Some plaining dittie to augment despaire.</L>
<L>Tryumph <HI>Piero</HI>: harke, he groanes, ô rare!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beholde a prostrate wretch laid on his toumbe.</L>
<L>His Epitaph, thus; <HI>Ne plus vltra.</HI> Ho.</L>
<L>Let none out▪ woe me: mine's <HI>Herculean</HI> woe.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>CANTANT.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Exit Piero at the end of the song.</STAGE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="4" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA QVARTA.</HEAD>
<STAGE>¶ <HI>Enter Maria.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>MAY I be more cursed then heauen can make me;</L>
<L>If I am not more wretched</L>
<L>Then man can conceiue me. Sore forlorne</L>
<L>Orphant, what omnipotence can make thee happie?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>How now sweete sonne? good youth, what dost thou?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Weepe, weepe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Dost naught but weepe, weepe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes mother, I do sigh, and wring my hands,</L>
<L>Beat my poore breast, and wreath my tender armes.</L>
<L>Harke yee; Ile tel you wondrous strange, strāge news.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<P>What my good boy, starke mad?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas, is that strange newes?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="18"/>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Strange news? why mother, is't not wondrous strange</L>
<L>I am not mad? I run not frantick, ha?</L>
<L>Knowing my fathers trunke scarce colde, your loue</L>
<L>Is sought by him that doth pursue my life?</L>
<L>Seeing the beautie of creation,</L>
<L><HI>Antonio's</HI> bride, pure heart, defam'd, and stoad</L>
<L>Vnder the hatches of obscuring earth.</L>
<L>Heu quo labor, quo vota ceciderunt mea!</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>¶ <HI>Enter Piero.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good euening to the faire <HI>Antonio,</HI></L>
<L>Most happie fortune, sweete succeeding time,</L>
<L>Rich hope: think not thy fate a bankrout though</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Vmh, the diuell in his good time and tide for∣sake thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>How now? harke yee Prince.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>An.</SPEAKER>
<P>God be with you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, noble blood, I hope yee not suspect</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>An.</SPEAKER>
<L>Suspect, I scorn't. Here's cap &amp; leg; good night:</L>
<L>Thou that wants power, with dissemblance fight.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Antonio.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pier.</SPEAKER>
<P>Madam, O that you could remēber to forget</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<P>I had a husband and a happie sonne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Most powreful beautie, that inchanting grace</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Talke not of beautie, nor inchanting grace.</L>
<L>My husband's deade, my son's distraught, accurst.</L>
<L>Come, I must vent my griefes, or heart will burst.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Maria.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee's gone (&amp; yet she's here) she hath left a print</L>
<L>Of her sweete graces fixt within my heart,</L>
<L>As fresh as is her face. Ile marrie her.</L>
<L><PB REF="18"/>Shee's most fair, true, most chaste, most false: because</L>
<L>Most faire, tis firme Ile marrie her.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="5" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA QVINTA.</HEAD>
<STAGE>¶ <HI>Enter Strotzo.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Str.</SPEAKER>
<L>MY Lord,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Piero.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, <HI>Strotzo,</HI> my other soule; my life,</L>
<L>Deare, hast thou steel'd the point of thy resolue?</L>
<L>Wilt not turne edge in execution?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Str.</SPEAKER>
<P>No.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe it with rare passion, and present thy guilt,</L>
<L>As if twere wrung out with thy conscience gripe.</L>
<L>Sweare that my daughter's innocent of lust,</L>
<L>And that <HI>Antonio</HI> brib'd thee to defame</L>
<L>Her maiden honour, on inueterate hate</L>
<L>Vnto my bloode; and that thy hand was feed</L>
<L>By his large bountie, for his fathers death.</L>
<L>Sweare plainly that thou chok'tst <HI>Andrugio,</HI></L>
<L>By his sons onely egging. Rush me in</L>
<L>Whil'st <HI>Mellida</HI> prepares her selfe to die:</L>
<L>Halter about thy necke, and with such sighs,</L>
<L>Laments and acclamations lyfen it,</L>
<L>As if impulsiue power of remorse</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Str.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile weepe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, I, fall on thy face and cry; why suffer you</L>
<L>So lewde a slaue as <HI>Strotzo</HI> is to breath?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Str.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile beg a strangling, growe importunate</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>As if thy life were loathsome to thee: then I</L>
<L>Catch straight the cords end; and, as much incens'd</L>
<L>With thy damn'd mischiefes, offer a rude hand,</L>
<L><PB REF="19"/>As readie to girde in thy pipe of breath:</L>
<L>But on the sodaine straight Ile stand amaz'd,</L>
<L>And fall in exclamations of thy vertues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Str.</SPEAKER>
<P>Applaud my agonies, and penitence.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy honest stomack, that could not disgest</L>
<L>The crudities of murder: but surcharg'd,</L>
<L>Vomited'st them vp in Christian pietie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Str.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then clip me in your armes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>And call thee brother, mount thee straight to state,</L>
<L>Make thee of counsell; tut, tut, what not, what not?</L>
<L>Thinke ont, be confident, pursue the plot.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Str.</SPEAKER>
<L>Looke here's a troop, a true rogues lips are mute▪</L>
<L>I doe not vse to speake, but execute.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>He layes finger on his mouth, and drawes his dagger.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>So, so; run headlong to confusion:</L>
<L>Thou slight brain'd mischiefe, thou art made as durt,</L>
<L>To plaster vp the bracks of my defects.</L>
<L>Ile wring what may be squeas'd from out his vse:</L>
<L>And good night <HI>Strozzo.</HI> Swell plump bold heart.</L>
<L>For now thy tide of vengeance rowleth in:</L>
<L>O now <HI>Tragoedia Cothurnata</HI> mounts▪</L>
<L><HI>Piero's</HI> thoughts are fixt on dire exploites.</L>
<L><HI>Pell mell</HI>: confusion, and black murder guides</L>
<L>The organs of my spirit: shrinke not heart.</L>
<L>Capienda rebus in malis praeceps via est.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<TRAILER><HI>FINIS</HI> ACTVS SECVNDI.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="19"/>
<HEAD>ACT. III.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCEN. I.</HEAD>
<STAGE>¶ <HI>A dumbe showe. The cornets sounding for the Acte.</HI></STAGE>
<STAGE>¶ <HI>Enter Castilio and Forobosco, Alberto and Balurdo, with polaxes: Strozzo talking with Piero, seemeth to send out Strotzo. Exit Strotzo. Enter Strotzo, Maria, Nutriche, and Luceo. Piero passeth through his guard, and talkes with her with seeming amorousnesse: she seemeth to reiect his suite, flyes to the toumbe, kneeles, and kisseth it. Piero bribes Nutriche and Lucio: they goe to her, seeming to solicite his suite. She riseth, offers to goe out, Piero stay∣eth her, teares open his breast, imbraceth and kisseth her, and so they goe all out in State.</HI></STAGE>
<STAGE>¶ <HI>Enter two pages, the one with two tapers, the other with a chafing dish: a perfume in it. Antonio, in his night gowne, and a night cap, vnbrac't, following after.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>An.</SPEAKER>
<P>THE black iades of swart night trot foggy rings Bout heauens browe. (12) Tis now starke deade night.</P>
<LG>
<L>Is this Saint <HI>Markes</HI> Church?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Pa.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>It is, my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Where stands my fathers hearse?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Pa.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Those streamers beare his armes. I, that is it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Set tapers to the toumbe, &amp; lampe the Church.</L>
<L>Giue me the fire, Now depart and sleepe. <STAGE>Exeunt pages.</STAGE></L>
<L><PB REF="20"/>I purifie the ayre with odorous fume.</L>
<L>Graues, valts, and toumbes, groane not to beare my weight,</L>
<L>Colde flesh, bleake trunkes, wrapt in your half-rot shrowdes,</L>
<L>I presse you softly, with a tender foote.</L>
<L>Most honour'd sepulchre, vouchsafe a wretch,</L>
<L>Leaue to weepe ore thee, Toumb, Ile not be long</L>
<L>Ere I creepe in thee, and with bloodlesse lips</L>
<L>Kisse my cold fathers cheeke. I pree thee, graue,</L>
<L>Prouide soft mould to wrap my carcasse in.</L>
<L>Thou royal spirit of <HI>Andrugio,</HI> where ere thou houerst</L>
<L>(Ayrie intellectt) I heaue vp tapers to thee (viewe thy son)</L>
<L>In celebration of dewe obsequies.</L>
<L>Once euery night, Ile dewe thy funerall hearse</L>
<L>With my religious teares,</L>
<L>O blessed father of a cursed son,</L>
<L>Thou diedst most happie, since thou liuedst not</L>
<L>To see thy sonne most wretched, and thy wife</L>
<L>Pursu'd by him that seekes my guiltlesse blood.</L>
<L>O, in what orbe thy mightie spirit soares,</L>
<L>Stoop and beat downe this rising fog of shame,</L>
<L>That striues to blur thy blood, and girt defame</L>
<L>About my innocent and spotlesse browes.</L>
<L>Non est mori miserum, sed miserè mori.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy pangs of anguish rip my cerecloth vp:</L>
<L>And loe the ghoast of ould <HI>Andrugio</HI></L>
<L>Forsakes his coffin. <HI>Antonio,</HI> reuenge.</L>
<L>I was impoyson'd by <HI>Piero's</HI> hand:</L>
<L>Reuenge my bloode; take spirit gentle boy:</L>
<L>Reuenge my bloode. Thy <HI>Mellida,</HI> is chaste:</L>
<L><PB REF="20"/>Onely to frustrate thy pursuite in loue,</L>
<L>Is blaz'd vnchaste. Thy mother yeelds consent</L>
<L>To be his wife, &amp; giue his bloode a sonne,</L>
<L>That made her husbandlesse, and doth complot</L>
<L>To make her sonlesse: but before I touch</L>
<L>The banks of rest, my ghost shall visite her.</L>
<L>Thou vigor of my youth, iuyce of my loue,</L>
<L>Seize on reuenge, graspe the sterne bended front</L>
<L>Of frowning vengeance, with vnpaized clutch.</L>
<L>Alarum <HI>Nemesis,</HI> rouze vp thy blood,</L>
<L>Inuent some stratageme of vengeance:</L>
<L>Which but to thinke on, may like lightning glide,</L>
<L>With horor through thy breast; remember this.</L>
<L>Scelera non vlcisceris, nisi vincis. <STAGE>Exit Andrugio's ghost.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA SECVNDA.</HEAD>
<STAGE>¶ <HI>Enter Maria, her haire about her eares: Nutriche, and Lucio, with Pages, and torches.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVHERE left you him? shewe mee good boyes, away.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nut.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gods mee, your haire.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nurse, tis not yet prowde day:</L>
<L>The neat gay mistes of the light's not vp,</L>
<L>Her cheekes not yet flurd ouer with the paint</L>
<L>Of borrowed crimsone; the vnpranked world</L>
<L><PB REF="21"/>Wears yet the night-cloathes: let flare my loosed hair.</L>
<L>I scorne the presence of the night.</L>
<L>Where's my boy? Run: Ile range about the Church,</L>
<L>Like frantick <HI>Bachanell,</HI> or <HI>Iasons</HI> wife,</L>
<L>Inuoking all the spirits of the graues,</L>
<L>To tell me where. Hah? O my poore wretched blood,</L>
<L>What dost thou vp at midnight, my kinde boy?</L>
<L>Deare soule, to bed: ô thou hast struck a fright</L>
<L>Vnto thy mothers panting</L>
<L>O quisquis noua</L>
<L>Supplicia functis dirus vmbrarum arbiter</L>
<L>Disponis, quisquis exeso iaces</L>
<L>Pauidus sub antri, quisquis venturi times</L>
<L>Montis ruinam, quisquis auidorum feres,</L>
<L>Rictus leonum, &amp; dira furiarum agmina</L>
<L>Implicitus horres, Antonii vocem excipe</L>
<L>Properantis ad vos Vlciscar.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas my son's distraught. Sweete boy appease▪</L>
<L>Thy mutining affections.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>By the astonning terror of swart night,</L>
<L>By the infectious damps of clammie graues,</L>
<L>And by the mould that presseth downe</L>
<L>My deade fathers sculle: Ile be reueng'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wherefore? on whom? for what? go, go to bed</L>
<L>Good dutious sonne. Ho, but thy idle</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>An.</SPEAKER>
<L>So I may sleepe toumb'd in an honour'd hearse,</L>
<L>So may my bones rest in that Sepulcher,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<P>Forget not dutie sonne: to bed, to bed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>An.</SPEAKER>
<L>May I be cursed by my fathers ghost,</L>
<L>And blasted with incensed breath of heauen,</L>
<L><PB REF="21"/>If my heart beat on ought but vengeance,</L>
<L>May I be numd with horror, and my vaines</L>
<L>Pucker with sing'ing torture, if my braine</L>
<L>Disgest a thought, but of dire vengeance:</L>
<L>May I be fetter'd slaue to coward Chaunce,</L>
<L>If blood, heart, braine, plot ought saue vengeance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wilt thou to bed▪ I wonder when thou sleepst▪</L>
<L>Ifaith thou look'st sunk-ey'd▪ go couch thy head:</L>
<L>Now faith tis idle: sweet, sweet sonne to bed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue a prayer or two, to offer vp,</L>
<L>For the good, good Prince, my most deare, dear Lord,</L>
<L>The Duke <HI>Piero,</HI> and your vertuous selfe:</L>
<L>And then when those prayers haue obtain'd successe,</L>
<L>In sooth Ile come (beleeue it now) and couch</L>
<L>My heade in downie moulde: but first Ile see</L>
<L>You safely laide. Ile bring yee all to bed.</L>
<L>Piero, Maria, Strotzo, Lucio,</L>
<L>Ile see you all laid: Ile bringe you all to bed,</L>
<L>And then, ifaith, Ile come and couch my head,</L>
<L>And sleepe in peace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<P>Looke then, wee goe before.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt all but Antonio.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, so you must, before we touch the shore</L>
<L>Of wisht reuenge. O you departed soules,</L>
<L>That lodge in coffin'd <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="over-inked" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, which my feet presse</L>
<L>(If <HI>Pythagorian Axiomes</HI> be true,</L>
<L>Of spirits transmigration) floote no more</L>
<L>To humane bodies, rather liue in swine,</L>
<L>Inhabit wolues flesh, scorpions, dogs, and toads,</L>
<L>Rather then man, The curse of heauen raines</L>
<L><PB REF="22"/>In plagues vnlimitted through all his daies,</L>
<L>His mature age growes onely mature vice,</L>
<L>And ripens onely to corrupt and rot</L>
<L>The budding hopes of infant modestie.</L>
<L>Still striuing to be more then man, he prooues</L>
<L>More then a diuell, diuelish suspect, diuelish crueltie:</L>
<L>All hell-straid iuyce is powred to his vaines,</L>
<L>Making him drunke with fuming surquedries,</L>
<L>Contempt of heauen, vntam'd arrogance,</L>
<L>Lust, state, pride, murder.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<P>Murder.
<STAGE>From aboue and beneath.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Murder.
<STAGE>From aboue and beneath.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Murder.
<STAGE>From aboue and beneath.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, I will murder: graues and ghosts</L>
<L>Fright me no more, Ile suck red vengeance</L>
<L>Out of <HI>Pieros</HI> wounds <HI>Piero's</HI> wounds.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter two boyes, with Piero in his night gown &amp; night cap.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Maria,</HI> loue <HI>Maria:</HI> she tooke this Ile.</L>
<L>Left you her here? On lights away:</L>
<L>I thinke we shall not warme our beds to day.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>¶ <HI>Enter Iulio, Forobosco, and Castilio▪</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ho, father? father?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now <HI>Iulio,</HI> my little prettie sonne?</L>
<L>Why suffer you the childe to walke so late.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Foro.</SPEAKER>
<L>He will not sleepe, but cals to followe you,</L>
<L>Crying that bug-beares &amp; spirits haunted him.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Antonio offers to come, nere and stab, Piero presently withdrawes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, not so.</L>
<L>This shall be sought for; Ile force him feede on life</L>
<L>Till he shall loath it. This shall be the close.</L>
<L><PB REF="22"/>Of vengeance straine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away there: Pages, leade on fast with light.</L>
<L>The Church is full of damps: tis yet deade night.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit all, sauing Iulio.</STAGE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA TERTIA.</HEAD>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>BROTHER <HI>Antonio,</HI> are you here ifaith?</L>
<L>Why doe you frowne? Indeed my sister said,</L>
<L>That I should call you brother, that she did,</L>
<L>When you were married to her. Busse me; good</L>
<L>Truth, I loue you better then my father, deede.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy father? Gratious, ô bounteous heauen!</L>
<L>I doe adore thy Iustice; <HI>Venit in nostras manus</HI></L>
<L>Tandem vindicta, venit &amp; tota quidem.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Truth, since my mother dyed, I lou'd you best.</L>
<L>Something hath angred you; pray you look merily.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will laugh, and dimple my thinne cheeke,</L>
<L>With capring ioy; chuck, my heart doth leape</L>
<L>To graspe thy bosome. Time, place, and blood,</L>
<L>How fit you close togither! <HI>Heauens tones</HI></L>
<L>Strike not such musick to immortall soules,</L>
<L>As your accordance sweetes my breast withall.</L>
<L>Me thinks I pase vpon the front of <HI>Ioue,</HI></L>
<L>And kick corruption with a scornefull heele,</L>
<L>Griping this flesh, disdaine mortalitie.</L>
<L><HI>O</HI> that I knewe which ioynt, which side, which lim</L>
<L>Were father all, and had no mother in't:</L>
<L>That I might rip it vaine by vaine; and carue reuenge</L>
<L>In bleeding races: but since 'tis mixt together,</L>
<L>Haue at aduenture, pel mell, no reuerse.</L>
<L><PB REF="23"/>Come hither boy. This is <HI>Andrugio's</HI> hearse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>O God, youle hurt me. For my sisters sake,</L>
<L>Pray you doe not hurt me. And you kill me, deede,</L>
<L>Ile tell my father</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>An.</SPEAKER>
<P>O, for thy sisters sake, I flagge reuenge.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Andr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Reuenge.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay, stay, deare father, fright mine eyes no more.</L>
<L>Reuenge as swift as lightning bursteth forth,</L>
<L>And cleares his heart. Come, prettie tender childe,</L>
<L>It is not thee I hate, not thee I kill.</L>
<L>Thy fathers blood that flowes within thy veines,</L>
<L>Is it I loath; is that, Reuenge must sucke.</L>
<L>I loue thy soule: and were thy heart lapt vp</L>
<L>In any flesh, but in <HI>Piero's</HI> bloode,</L>
<L>I would thus kisse it: but being his: thus, thus,</L>
<L>And thus Ile punch it. Abandon feares.</L>
<L>Whil'st thy wounds bleede, my browes shall gush out teares.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuli.</SPEAKER>
<P>So you will loue me, doe euen what you will.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now barkes the Wolfe against the full cheekt Moone.</L>
<L>Now Lyons halfe-clamd entrals roare for food.</L>
<L>Now croakes the toad, &amp; night-crowes screech aloud,</L>
<L>Fluttering 'bout casements of departing soules.</L>
<L>Now gapes the graues, and through their yawnes let loose</L>
<L>Imprison'd spirits to reuisit earth:</L>
<L>And now swarte night, to swell thy hower out,</L>
<L>Behold I spurt warme bloode in thy blacke eyes.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>From vnder the stage a groane.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Howle not thou pury mould, groan not ye graues.</L>
<L><PB REF="23"/>Be dumbe all breath. Here stands <HI>Andrugio's</HI> sonne,</L>
<L>Worthie his father. So: I feele no breath.</L>
<L>His iawes are falne, his dislodg'd soule is fled:</L>
<L>And now there's nothing, but <HI>Piero,</HI> left.</L>
<L>He is all <HI>Piero,</HI> father all. This blood,</L>
<L>This breast, this heart, <HI>Piero</HI> all:</L>
<L>Whome thus I mangle. Spright of <HI>Iulyo,</HI></L>
<L>Forget this was thy trunke. I liue thy friend.</L>
<L>Maist thou be twined with the sofest imbrace</L>
<L>Of cleare eternitie: but thy fathers blood,</L>
<L>I thus make incense of, to vengeance.</L>
<L>Ghost of my poysoned Syre, sucke this fume:</L>
<L>To sweete reuenge perfume thy circling ayre,</L>
<L>With smoake of bloode. I sprinkle round his goare,</L>
<L>And dewe thy hearse, with these fresh reeking drops.</L>
<L>Loe thus I heaue my blood-died handes to heauen:</L>
<L>Euen like insatiate hell, still crying; More.</L>
<L>My heart hath thirsting Dropsies after goare.</L>
<L>Sound peace, and rest, to Church, night ghosts, and graues.</L>
<L>Blood cries for bloode; and murder murder craues.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="4" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA QVARTA.</HEAD>
<STAGE>¶<HI>Enter two Pages with torches. Marya, her hayre loose, and Nutriche.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nut.</SPEAKER>
<P>FY, fie; to morrowe your wedding day, and weepe! Gods my comfort. <HI>Andrugio</HI> could do well: <HI>Piero</HI> may doe better. I haue had foure husbands
<PB REF="24"/>
my selfe. The first I called, <HI>Sweete Duck</HI>; the second, <HI>Deare Heart</HI>; the third, <HI>Prettie Pugge</HI>: But the fourth most sweete, deare, prettie, all in all: he was the verie cockeall of a husband. What, Ladie? your skinne is smooth, your bloode warme, your cheeke fresh, your eye quick: change of pasture makes fat calues: choice of linnen, cleane bodies; and (no question) variety of husbands perfect wiues▪ I would you should knowe it, as fewe teeth as I haue in my heade, I haue red <HI>A∣ristotles Problemes,</HI> which saith; that woman receiueth perfection by the man. What then be the men? Goe to, to bed, lye on your backe, dream not on <HI>Piero.</HI> I say no more: to morrowe is your wedding: doe, dreame not of <HI>Piero.</HI></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>¶<HI>Enter Balurdo with abase Vyole.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>What an idle prate thou keep'st? good nurse goe sleepe.</L>
<L>I haue a mightie taske of teares to weepe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ladie, with a most retort and obtuse legge I kisse the curled locks of your loose haire. The Duke hath sent you the most musicall sir <HI>Gefferey,</HI> with his not base, but most innobled Viole, to rock your baby thoughts in the Cradle of sleepe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<P>I giue the noble Duke respectiue thanks.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Respectiue; truely a verie prettie word. Indeed Madam, I haue the most respectiue fiddle▪ Did you e∣uer smell a more sweete sounde. My dittie must goe thus; verie wittie, I assure you: I my selfe in an humo∣rous passion made it, to the tune of my mistresse <HI>Nu∣triches</HI> beautie. Indeede, verie prettie, verie retort, and
<PB REF="24"/>
obtuse; Ile assure you tis thus.</P>
<LG>
<L>My mistresse eye doth oyle my ioynts,</L>
<L>And makes my fingers nimble:</L>
<L>O loue, come on, vntrusse your points,</L>
<L>My fiddlestick wants Rozzen.</L>
<L>My Ladies dugges are all so smooth,</L>
<L>That no flesh must them handle▪</L>
<L>Her eyes doe shine, for to say sooth,</L>
<L>Like a newe snuffed candle.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Truelie, verie patheticall, and vnuulgar.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<P>Patheticall, and vnuulgar; words of worth, ex∣cellent words. In sooth, Madam, I haue taken a murre, which makes my nose run most patheticallie, and vn∣vulgarlie. Haue you anie Tobacco?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good Signior, your song.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<L>Instantlie, most vnvulgarlie, at your seruice.</L>
<L>Truelie, here's the most patheticall rozzen. Vmh.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>CANTANT.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<P>In sooth, most knightlie sung, &amp; like sir <HI>Gefferey.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, looke you Ladie, I was wade a knight on∣ly for my voice; &amp; a counseller, only for my wit.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<P>I beleeue it. God night, gentle sir, god night.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<P>You will giue me leaue to take my leaue of my mistresse, and I will do it most famously in rime.</P>
<LG>
<L>Farewell, adieu: Saith thy loue true,</L>
<L>As to part loath.</L>
<L>Time bids vs parte, Mine owne sweete heart,</L>
<L>God blesse vs both. <STAGE>Exit Balurdo.</STAGE></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>God night <HI>Nutriche.</HI> Pages, leaue the roome.</L>
<L>The life of night growes short, tis almost dead.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt Pages and Nutriche.</STAGE>
<L><PB REF="25"/>O thou cold widdowe bed, sometime thrice blest,</L>
<L>By the warme pressure of my sleeping Lord:</L>
<L>Open thy leaues, and whilst on thee I treade,</L>
<L>Groane out. Alas, my deare <HI>Andrugio's</HI> deade.</L>
<STAGE>Maria draweth the courtaine: and the ghost of Andrugio is displayed, sitting on the bed.</STAGE>
<L>Amazing terror, what portent is this?</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="5" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA QVINTA.</HEAD>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>DISLOYAL to our Hymniall rites,</L>
<L>What raging heat rains in thy strūpet blood?</L>
<L>Hast thou so soone forgot <HI>Andrugio?</HI></L>
<L>Are our loue-bands so quickly cancelled?</L>
<L>Where liues thy plighted faith vnto this breast?</L>
<L>O weake <HI>Marya</HI>! Go to, calme thy feares.</L>
<L>I pardon thee, poore soule. O shed no teares.</L>
<L>Thy sexe is weake. That black incarnate fiende</L>
<L>May trippe thy faith, that hath orethrowne my life:</L>
<L>I was impoyson'd by <HI>Piero's</HI> hand.</L>
<L>Ioyne with my sonne, to bend vp straind reuenge.</L>
<L>Maintaine a seeming fauour to his suite,</L>
<L>Till time may forme our vengeance absolute.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>¶ <HI>Enter Antonio, his armes bloody: a torch and a poniard.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>An.</SPEAKER>
<L>See, vnamaz'd, I will beholde thy face,</L>
<L>Outstare the terror of thy grimme aspect,</L>
<L>Daring the horred'st obiect of the night.</L>
<L>Looke how I smoake in blood, reeking the steame▪</L>
<L><PB REF="25"/>Of foming vengeance. O my soule's inthroan'd</L>
<L>In the tryumphant chariot of reuenge.</L>
<L>Me thinks I am all ayre, and feele no waight</L>
<L>Of humane dirt clogge. This is <HI>Iulios</HI> bloode.</L>
<L>Rich musique, father; this is <HI>Iulio's</HI> blood.</L>
<L>Why liues that mother?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pardon ignorance. Fly deare <HI>Antonio</HI>:</L>
<L>Once more assume disguise, and dog the Court</L>
<L>In fained habit, till <HI>Piero's</HI> blood</L>
<L>May euen ore-flowe the brimme of full reuenge.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Antonio.</STAGE>
<L>Peace, and all blessed fortunes to you both.</L>
<L>Fly thou from Court, be pearelesse in reuenge:</L>
<L>Sleepe thou in rest, loe here I close thy couch.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Maria to her bed, Andrugio drawing the Curtaines.</STAGE>
<L>And now yee sootie coursers of the night,</L>
<L>Hurrie your chariot into hels black wombe.</L>
<L>Darkenesse, make flight; Graues, eat your dead again:</L>
<L>Let's repossesse our shrowdes. Why lags delay?</L>
<L>Mount sparkling brightnesse, giue the world his day.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Andrugio.</STAGE>
</DIV3>
<TRAILER>Explicit Actus tertius.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="26"/>
<HEAD>ACT. IIII.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCEN. I.</HEAD>
<STAGE>¶ <HI>Enter Antonio in a fooles habit, with a little toy of a walnut shell, and sope, to make bubbles: Maria, and Alberto.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<P>AWAY with this disguise in any hand.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fie, tis vnsuting to your elate spirite:</L>
<L>Rather put on some transshap't caualier,</L>
<L>Some habit of a spitting Critick, whose mouth</L>
<L>Voids nothing but gentile and vnuulgar</L>
<L>Rheume of censure: rather assume▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why then should I put on the verie flesh</L>
<L>Of solid folly. No, this cockscombe is a crowne</L>
<L>Which I affect, euen with vnbounded zeale.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<P>Twil twhart your plot, disgrace your high resolue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>An.</SPEAKER>
<L>By wisdomes heart there is no essence mortal,</L>
<L>That I can enuie, but a plumpe cheekt foole:</L>
<L>O, he hath a patent of immunities</L>
<L>Confirm'd by custome, seald by pollicie,</L>
<L>As large as spatious thought.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<L>You can not presse among the courtiers,</L>
<L>And haue accesse to</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>An.</SPEAKER>
<L>What? not a foole? Why friend, a golden asse,</L>
<L>A babl'd foole are sole canonicall,</L>
<L>Whil'st pale cheekt wisdome, and leane ribd arte</L>
<L><PB REF="26"/>Are kept in distance at the halberts point:</L>
<L>All held <HI>Apocrypha,</HI> not worth suruey.</L>
<L>Why, by the <HI>Genius</HI> of that <HI>Florentine,</HI></L>
<L>Deepe, deepe obseruing, sound brain'd Macheueil,</L>
<L>He is is not wise that striues not to seeme foole.</L>
<L>When will the Duke holde feed Intelligence,</L>
<L>Keepe warie obseruation in large pay,</L>
<L>To dogge a fooles act?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, but such faining, known, disgraceth much.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>An.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pish, most things that morally adhere to soules,</L>
<L>VVholly exist in drunke opinion:</L>
<L>VVhose reeling censure, if I valew not,</L>
<L>It valewes naught.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are transported with too slight a thought,</L>
<L>If you but meditate of what is past,</L>
<L>And what you plot to passe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Euen in that, note a fooles beatitude:</L>
<L>He is not capeable of passion,</L>
<L>VVanting the power of distinction,</L>
<L>He beares an vnturnd sayle with euery winde:</L>
<L>Blowe East, blowe West, he stirs his course alike.</L>
<L>I neuer sawe a foole leane: the chub-fac'tfop</L>
<L>Shines sleeke with full cramm'd fat of happinesse,</L>
<L>Whil'st studious contemplation sucks the iuyce</L>
<L>From wisards cheekes: who making curious search</L>
<L>For Natures secrets, the first innating cause</L>
<L>Laughes them to scorne, as man doth busie Apes</L>
<L>When they will zanie men. Had heauen bin kinde,</L>
<L>Creating me an honest senselesse dolt,</L>
<L>A good poore foole, I should want sense to feele</L>
<L><PB REF="27"/>The stings of anguish shoot through euery vaine,</L>
<L>I should not know what twere to loose a father:</L>
<L>I should be deade of sense, to viewe defame</L>
<L>Blur my bright loue; I could not thus run mad,</L>
<L>As one confounded in a maze of mischiefe,</L>
<L>Staggerd, starke feld with brusing stroke of chance.</L>
<L>I should not shoote mine eyes into the earth,</L>
<L>Poring for mischiefe, that might counterpoise <STAGE>¶ <HI>Enter Luceo.</HI></STAGE>
mischiefe, murder and How now <HI>Lucio?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lu.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, the Duke, with the <HI>Venetian</HI> States,</L>
<L>Approach the great hall to iudge <HI>Mellida.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Askt he for <HI>Iulio</HI> yet?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lu.</SPEAKER>
<P>No motion of him: dare you trust this habit?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>An.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Alberto,</HI> see you streight rumour me dead:</L>
<L>Leaue me, good mother, leaue me <HI>Luceo,</HI></L>
<L>Forsake me all. Now patience hoope my sides,</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt omnes, sauing Antonio.</STAGE>
<L>With steeled ribs, least I doe burst my breast</L>
<L>With struggling passions. Now disguise stand bolde.</L>
<L>Poore scorned habits, oft choyce soules infould.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>¶ <HI>The Cornets sound a Cynet.</HI></STAGE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA SECVNDA.</HEAD>
<STAGE>¶ <HI>Enter Castilio, Forobosco, Balurdo &amp; Alberto, with pol∣axes: Luceo bare. Piero &amp; Maria talking together: two Senators, Galeatzo, and Matzagente, Nutriche.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="27"/>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>INTREAT me not: ther's not a beauty liues,</L>
<L>Hath that imperiall predominance</L>
<L>Ore my affectes, as your inchanting graces:</L>
<L>Yet giue me leaue to be my selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>A villaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pier.</SPEAKER>
<P>Iust.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Most iust.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most iust and vpright in our iudgement seat.</L>
<L>Were <HI>Mellida</HI> mine eye, with such a blemish</L>
<L>Of most loath'd loosenesse, I would scratch it out.</L>
<L>Produce the strumpet in her bridall robes,</L>
<L>That she may blush t'appeare so white in showe,</L>
<L>And blacke in inward substance. Bring her in.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt Forobosco and Castilio.</STAGE>
<L>I holde <HI>Antonio,</HI> for his fathers sake,</L>
<L>So verie dearely, so entirely choyce,</L>
<L>That knewe I but a thought of preiudice,</L>
<L>Imaigin'd 'gainst his high innobled blood,</L>
<L>I would maintaine a mortall feude, vndying hate</L>
<L>Gainst the conceiuers life. And shall Iustice sleepe</L>
<L>In fleshly Lethargie, for myne owne bloods fauour,</L>
<L>When the sweete prince hath so apparant scorne</L>
<L>By my (I wil not call her) daughter. Goe,</L>
<L>Conduct in the loued youth <HI>Antonio</HI>:</L>
<STAGE>Exit Alberto to fetch Antonio.</STAGE>
<L>He shall beholde me spurne my priuate good.</L>
<L><HI>Piero</HI> loues his honour more then's blood.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>The diuell he does more then both.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<P>Stand backe there, foole; I do hate a foole most most pathetically. O these that haue no sappe of of re∣tort
<PB REF="28"/>
and obtuse wit in them: faugh.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Puffe; holde world: puffe, hold bubble; Puffe, holde world: puffe, breake not behinde: puffe, thou art full of winde; puffe, keepe vp by winde: puffe, 'tis broake: &amp; now I laugh like a good foole at the breath of mine owne lips, he, he, he, he, he.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<P>You foole.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>You foole, puffe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<P>I cannot disgest thee, the vnuulgar foole. Goe foole.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pier.</SPEAKER>
<L>Forbeare, <HI>Balurdo,</HI> let the foole alone,</L>
<L>Come hither (<HI>ficto</HI>) Is he your foole?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, my lou'd Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would all the States in <HI>Venice</HI> were like thee.</L>
<L>O then I were secur'd.</L>
<L>He that's a villaine, or but meanely sowl'd,</L>
<L>Must stil conuerse, and cling to routes of fooles,</L>
<L>That can not search the leakes of his defectes.</L>
<L>O, your vnsalted fresh foole is your onely man:</L>
<L>These vinegar tart spirits are too pearcing,</L>
<L>Too searching in the vnglewd ioynts of shaken wits.</L>
<L>Finde they a chinke, they'l wriggle in and in,</L>
<L>And eat like salt sea in his siddowe ribs,</L>
<L>Till they haue opened all his rotten parts,</L>
<L>Vnto the vaunting surge of base contempt,</L>
<L>And sunke the tossed galleasse in depth</L>
<L>Of whirlepoole Scorne. Giue me an honest fopp:</L>
<L>Dud a dud a? why loe sir, this takes he</L>
<L>As grateful now, as a Monopolie.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<PB REF="28"/>
<HEAD>SCENA TERTIA.</HEAD>
<STAGE>¶ <HI>The still flutes sound softly.</HI></STAGE>
<STAGE>¶<HI>Enter Forobosco, and Castilio: Mellida supported by two waiting women.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mell.</SPEAKER>
<P>ALL honour to this royall confluence.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Forbeare (impure) to blot bright honours name,</L>
<L>With thy defiled lips. The fluxe of sinne</L>
<L>Flowes from thy tainted bodie: thou so foule,</L>
<L>So all dishonour'd, canst no honour giue,</L>
<L>No wish of good, that can haue good effect</L>
<L>To this graue senate, and illustrate bloodes.</L>
<L>Why staies the doome of death?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Sen.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Who riseth vp to manifest her guilt?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Sen.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>You must produce apparant proofe, my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, where is <HI>Strotzo?</HI> he that swore he saw</L>
<L>The verie acte: and vow'd that <HI>Feliche</HI> fled</L>
<L>Vpon his sight: on which, I brake the breast</L>
<L>Of the adulterous letcher, with fiue stabbes.</L>
<L>Goe fetch in <HI>Strotzo.</HI> Now thou impudent,</L>
<L>If thou hast any droppe of modest bloode</L>
<L>Shrowded within thy cheeks; blush, blush for shame,</L>
<L>That rumor yet may say, thou felt'st defame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mell.</SPEAKER>
<L>Produce the diuel,; let your <HI>Strotzo</HI> come:</L>
<L>I can defeat his strongest argument,</L>
<L>VVhich</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="29"/>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>With what?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mell.</SPEAKER>
<L>With teares, with blushes, sighes, &amp; clasped hands,</L>
<L>With innocent vpreared armes to heauen:</L>
<L>With my vnnookt simplicitie. These, these</L>
<L>Must, will, can only quit my heart of guilt.</L>
<L>Heauen permits not taintlesse blood be spilt.</L>
<L>If no remorse liue in your sauage breast</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Piero.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then thou must die</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mell.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yet dying, Ile be blest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Piero.</SPEAKER>
<P>Accurst by me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mell.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet blest, in that I stroue</L>
<L>To liue, and die</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>My hate.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mell.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Antonyo's</HI> loue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Antonio's</HI> loue!</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>¶ <HI>Enter Strotzo, a corde about his necke.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<L>O what vast ocean of repentant teares</L>
<L>Can cleanse my breast from the polluting filth</L>
<L>Of vlcerous sinne! <HI>Supreame Efficient,</HI></L>
<L>Why cleau'st thou not my breast with thunderbolts</L>
<L>Of wingd reuenge?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>What meanes this passion?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>An.</SPEAKER>
<P>What villanie are they decocting now? Vmh.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Str.</SPEAKER>
<L>In me conuertite ferrum, O proceres.</L>
<L>Nihil iste, nec ista.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>Lay holde on him. What strange portent is this?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Str.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will not flinch. Death, hel more grimly stare</L>
<L>Within my heart, then in your threatning browes.</L>
<L>Record, thou threefolde garde of dreadest power,</L>
<L>What I here speake, is forced from my lips,</L>
<L><PB REF="29"/>By the pulsiue straine of conscience,</L>
<L>I haue a mount of mischiefe clogs my soule,</L>
<L>As waightie as the high-nol'd <HI>Appenine</HI>:</L>
<L>Which I must straight disgorge, or breast will burst.</L>
<L>I haue defam'd this Ladie wrongfully,</L>
<L>By instigation of <HI>Antonio:</HI></L>
<L>Whose reeling loue, tost on each fancies surge,</L>
<L>Began to loath before it fully ioyed.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Forobosco.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>Goe, seize <HI>Antonio,</HI> guard him strongly in.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Str.</SPEAKER>
<L>By his ambition, being only brib'd,</L>
<L>Feed by his impious hand, I poysoned</L>
<L>His aged father: that his thirstie hope</L>
<L>Might quench their dropsie of aspiring drought,</L>
<L>With full vnbounded quaffe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>Seize me <HI>Antonio.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Str.</SPEAKER>
<L>O why permit you now such scum of filth</L>
<L>As <HI>Strotzo</HI> is, to liue, and taint the ayre,</L>
<L>With his infectious breath!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>My selfe will be thy strangler, vnmatcht slaue.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>¶ <HI>Piero comes from his chaire, snatcheth the cords end, &amp; Castilio aydeth him; both strangle Strotzo.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Str.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now change your</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, pluck <HI>Castilio</HI>: I change my humour? plucke Castilio.</L>
<L>Dye, with thy deathes intreats euen in thy iawes.</L>
<L>Now, now, now, now, now, my plot begins to worke.</L>
<L>Why, thus should States-men doe,</L>
<L>That cleaue through knots of craggie pollicies,</L>
<L>Vse men like wedges, one strike out another;</L>
<L><PB REF="30"/>Till by degrees the tough and knurly trunke</L>
<L>Be riu'd in sunder. Where's <HI>Antonio</HI>?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>¶ <HI>Enter Alberto, running.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<P>O black accursed fate. <HI>Antonyo's</HI> drown'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>Speake, on thy faith, on thy allegeance, speake.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<P>As I doe loue <HI>Piero,</HI> he is drownde.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>In an inundation of amazement.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mell.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, is this the clofe of all my straines in loue?</L>
<L>O me most wretched maide.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Antonio</HI> drownde? how? how? <HI>Antonio</HI> drownd?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Distraught and rauing, from a turrets top</L>
<L>He threwe his bodie in the high swolne sea,</L>
<L>And as he headlong topsie turuie dingd downe,</L>
<P>He still cri'd <HI>Mellida.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>My loues bright crowne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mell.</SPEAKER>
<P>He still cry'd <HI>Mellida?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pier.</SPEAKER>
<L>Daughter, me thinks your eyes should sparkle ioy,</L>
<L>Your bosome rise on tiptoe at this news.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mell.</SPEAKER>
<P>Aye me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now? Ay me? why, art not great of thanks</L>
<L>To gratious heauen, for the iust reuenge</L>
<L>Vpon the author of thy obloquies!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweete beautie, I could sigh as fast as you,</L>
<L>But that I knowe that, which I weepe to knowe,</L>
<L>His fortunes should be such he dare not showe</L>
<L>His open presence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mell.</SPEAKER>
<L>I knowe he lou'd me dearely, dearely, I:</L>
<L>And since I cannot liue with him, I dye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fore heauen, her speach falters, look she swouns.</L>
<L>Conuey her vp into her priuate bed.</L>
<STAGE><PB REF="30"/>¶ <HI>Maria, Nutriche, and the Ladies beare out Mellida, as being swouned.</HI></STAGE>
<L>I hope sheele liue. If not</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>An.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Antonio's</HI> dead, the foole wil follow too, he, he, he,</L>
<L>Now workes the sceane; quick obseruation scud</L>
<L>To coate the plot, or els the path is lost:</L>
<L>My verie selfe am gone, my way is fled:</L>
<L>I, all is lost, if <HI>Mellida</HI> is deade. <STAGE>Exit Antonio.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Alberto,</HI> I am kinde, <HI>Alberto,</HI> kinde.</L>
<L>I am sorie for thy couz, ifaith I am.</L>
<L>Goe, take him downe, and beare him to his father:</L>
<L>Let him be buried, looke yee, Ile pay the priest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Please you to admit his father to the Court?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Piero.</SPEAKER>
<P>No.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<P>Please you to restore his lands &amp; goods againe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Piero.</SPEAKER>
<P>No.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Please you vouchsafe him lodging in the city?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gods fut, no, thou odde vnciuill fellow:</L>
<L>I thinke you doe forget sir, where you are.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<P>I know you doe forget sir, where you must be.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Foro.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are too malepert, ifaith you are.</L>
<L>Your honour might doe well to</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace Parasite, thou bur, that only sticks</L>
<L>Vnto the nappe of greatnesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>Away with that same yelping cur, away.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, I am gone: but marke, <HI>Piero,</HI> this.</L>
<L>There is a thing cald scourging <HI>Nemesis.</HI> <STAGE>Exit Alb.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gods neakes he has wrong, that he has: and</L>
<L>S'fut, and I were as he, I would beare no coles, lawe I,</L>
<L>I begin to swell, puffe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="31"/>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>How now foole, fop, foole?</P>
<P>Foole, fop, foole? Marry muffe. I pray you, how ma∣nie fooles haue you seene goe in a suite of Sattin? I hope yet, I doe not look a foole ifaith: a foole? Gods bores, I scorn't with my heele. S'neaks, and I were worth but three hundred pound a yeare more, I could sweare richly: nay, but as poore as I am, I will sweare the fellowe hath wrong.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Piero.</SPEAKER>
<L>Young <HI>Galeatzo?</HI> I, a proper man.</L>
<L><HI>Florence,</HI> a goodly citie: it shall be so.</L>
<L>Ile marrie her to him instantly.</L>
<L>Then <HI>Genoa</HI> mine, by my <HI>Mariaes</HI> match,</L>
<L>Which Ile solemnize ere next setting Sun.</L>
<L>Thus <HI>Venice, Florence, Genoa,</HI> strongly leagu'd.</L>
<L>Excellent, excellent. Ile conquer <HI>Rome,</HI></L>
<L>Pop out the light of bright religion:</L>
<L>And then, helter skelter, all cock sure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<P>Goe to, tis iust, the man hath wrong: go to.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe to, thou shalt haue right. Go to <HI>Castilio,</HI></L>
<L>Clap him into the Palace dungeon:</L>
<L>Lappe him in rags, and let him feede on slime</L>
<L>That smeares the dungeon cheeke. Away with him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<P>In verie good truth now, Ile nere do so more; this one time and</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>Away with him, obserue it strictly, goe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why then, ô wight, alas poore knight.</L>
<L>O, welladay, sir <HI>Gefferey.</HI> Let Poets roare,</L>
<L>And all deplore: for now I bid you god night.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Balurdo with Castilio.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>O pittious end of loue: ô too too rude hand</L>
<L><PB REF="31"/>Of vnrespectiue death! Alas, sweete maide.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Forbear me heauen. What intend these plaints?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>The beautie of admir'd creation,</L>
<L>The life of modest vnmixt puritie,</L>
<L>Our sexes glorie, <HI>Mellida</HI> is</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>What? ô heauen, what?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<P>Deade.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>May it not sad your thoughts, how?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Being laid vpon her bed, she graspt my hād,</L>
<L>And kissing it, spake thus; Thou very pore,</L>
<L>Why dost not weepe? The Iewell of thy browe,</L>
<L>The rich adornement, that inchac't thy breast,</L>
<L>Is lost: thy son, my loue is lost, is deade.</L>
<L>And doe I liue to say <HI>Antonio's</HI> deade?</L>
<L>And haue I liu'd to see his vertues blurd,</L>
<L>With guiltlesse blots! O world thou art too subtile,</L>
<L>For honest natures to conuerse withall.</L>
<L>Therefore Ile leaue thee; farewell mart of woe,</L>
<L>I fly to clip my loue, <HI>Antonio.</HI></L>
<L>With that her head sunk down vpon her brest:</L>
<L>Her cheeke chang'd earth, her senses slept in rest:</L>
<L>Vntill my foole, that press'd vnto the bed,</L>
<L>Screch't out so lowd, that he brought back her soule,</L>
<L>Calde her againe, that her bright eyes gan ope,</L>
<L>And starde vpon him: he audatious foole,</L>
<L>Dar'd kisse her hand, wisht her soft rest, lou'd bride;</L>
<L>She fumbled out, thanks good, and so she dide.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Piero.</SPEAKER>
<L>And so she dide: I doe not vse to weepe:</L>
<L>But by thy loue (out of whose fertile sweete,</L>
<L>I hope for as faire fruite) I am deepe sad:</L>
<L><PB REF="32"/>I will not stay my mariage for all this.</L>
<L><HI>Castilio Forobosco,</HI> all</L>
<L>Straine all your wits, winde vp inuention</L>
<L>Vnto his highest bent: to sweete this night,</L>
<L>Make vs drinke <HI>Lethe</HI> by your queint conceipts;</L>
<L>That for two daies, obliuion smother griefe:</L>
<L>But when my daughters exequies approach,</L>
<L>Let's all turne sighers. Come, despight of fate,</L>
<L>Sound lowdest musick, lets pase out in state.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>¶ <HI>The Cornets sound. Exeunt.</HI></STAGE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="4" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA QVARTA.</HEAD>
<STAGE>¶ <HI>Enter Antonio solus, in fooles habit.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>I Heauen, thou maist, thou maist omnipotence.</L>
<L>What vermine bred of putrifacted slime,</L>
<L>Shall dare to expostulate with thy decrees!</L>
<L>O heauen, thou maist indeede: she was all thine,</L>
<L>All heauenly, I did but humbly beg</L>
<L>To borrowe her of thee a little time.</L>
<L>Thou gau'st her me, as some weake breasted dame</L>
<L>Giueth her infant, puts it out to nurse;</L>
<L>And when it once goes high-lone, takes it back.</L>
<L>She was my vitall blood, and yet, and yet,</L>
<L>Ile not blaspheame. Looke here, beholde,</L>
<STAGE>Antonio puts off his cap, and lyeth iust vpon his back.</STAGE>
<L>I turne my prostrate breast vpon thy face,</L>
<L>And vent a heauing sigh. O heare but this;</L>
<L><PB REF="32"/>I am a poore poore Orphant; a weake, weak childe,</L>
<L>The wrack of splitted fortune, the very Ouze,</L>
<L>The quick sand that deuours all miserie.</L>
<L>Beholde the valiant'st creature that doth breath.</L>
<L>For all this, I dare liue, and I will liue,</L>
<L>Onely to numme some others cursed bloode,</L>
<L>With the dead palsie of like misery.</L>
<L>Then death, like to a stifling <HI>Incubus,</HI></L>
<L>Lie on my bosome. Loe sir, I am sped.</L>
<L>My breast is <HI>Golgotha,</HI> graue for the deade.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="5" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA QVINTA.</HEAD>
<STAGE>¶ <HI>Enter Pandulpho, Alberto, and a Page, carrying Fe∣liches trunke in a winding sheete, and lay it twhart Antonios breast.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>ANTONIO, kisse my foote: I honour thee,</L>
<L>In laying thwart my blood vpon thy breast.</L>
<L>I tell thee boy, he was <HI>Pandulphos</HI> sonne:</L>
<L>And I doe grace thee with supporting him,</L>
<L>Young man.</L>
<L>The dominering Monarch of the earth,</L>
<L>He who hath naught that fortunes gripe can seize,</L>
<L>He who is all impregnably his owne,</L>
<L>Hee whose great heart heauen can not force with force,</L>
<L>Vouchsafes his loue. <HI>Non seruio Deo, sed assentio.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="33"/>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>I ha lost a good wife.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Didst finde her good, or didst thou make her good?</L>
<L>If found, thou maist refinde, because thou hadst her.</L>
<L>If made, the worke is lost: but thou that mad'st her</L>
<L>Liu'st yet as cunning. Hast lost a good wife?</L>
<L>Thrice blessed man that lost her whilst she was good,</L>
<L>Faire, young, vnblemisht, constant, louing, chaste.</L>
<L>I tell thee youth, age knows, yong loues seeme grac't,</L>
<L>VVhich with gray cares, rude iarres, are oft defac't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>An.</SPEAKER>
<P>But shee was full of hope.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>May be, may be: but that, which may be, stood,</L>
<L>Stands now without all may; she died good,</L>
<L>And dost thou grieue?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alberto.</SPEAKER>
<P>I ha lost a true friend.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>I liue incompast with two blessed soules.</L>
<L>Thou lost a good wife, thou lost a trew friend, ha?</L>
<L>Two of the rarest lendings of the heauens:</L>
<L>But lendings: which at the fixed day of pay</L>
<L>Set downe by fate, thou must restore againe.</L>
<L>O what vnconscionable soules are here?</L>
<L>Are you all like the spoke-shaues of the Church?</L>
<L>Haue you no mawe to restitution?</L>
<L>Hast lost a true friend, cuz? then thou hadst one.</L>
<L>I tell thee youth, tis all as difficult</L>
<L>To finde true friend in this apostate age</L>
<L>(That balkes all right affiance twixt two hearts)</L>
<L>As tis to finde a fixed modest heart,</L>
<L>Vnder a painted breast. Lost a true friend?</L>
<L>O happie soule that lost him whilst he was true.</L>
<L><PB REF="33"/>Beleeue it cuz, I to my teares haue found,</L>
<L>Oft durts respect makes firmer friends vnsounde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<P>You haue lost a good sonne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why there's the cōfort ont, that he was good:</L>
<L>Alas, poore innocent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why weepes mine vncle?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, dost aske me why? ha? ha?</L>
<L>Good cuz, looke here.</L>
<STAGE>He showes him his sonnes breast.</STAGE>
<L>Man will breake out, despight Philosophie.</L>
<L>Why, all this while I ha but plaid a part,</L>
<L>Like to some boy, that actes a Tragedie,</L>
<L>Speakes burly words, and raues out passion:</L>
<L>But, when he thinks vpon his infant weaknesse,</L>
<L>He droopes his eye. I spake more then a god;</L>
<L>Yet am lesse then a man.</L>
<L>I am the miserablest sowle that breathes.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Antonio starts vp.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>S'lid, sir ye lye: by th'heart of griefe, thou lyest.</L>
<L>I scorn't that any wretched should suruiue,</L>
<L>Outmounting me in that Superlatiue,</L>
<L>Most miserable, most vnmatcht in woe:</L>
<L>Who dare assume that, but <HI>Antonio?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wilt still be so? and shall you blood-hound liue?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>An.</SPEAKER>
<P>Haue I an arme, a heart, a sword, a sowle?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Were you but priuate vnto what we know</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile knowe it all; first let's interre the dead:</L>
<L>Let's dig his graue, with that shall dig the heart,</L>
<L>Liuer, and intrals of the murderer.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>They strike the stage with their daggers, and the graue openeth.</STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="34"/>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wilt sing a Dirge boy?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, no song: twill be vile out of tune.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeede he's hoarce: the poore boyes voice is crackt.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why cuz? why shold it not be hoarce &amp; crackt,</L>
<L>When all the strings of natures symphony</L>
<L>Are crackt, &amp; iar? why should his voice keepe tune,</L>
<L>When ther's no musick in the breast of man?</L>
<L>Ile say an honest antick rime I haue;</L>
<L>(Helpe me good sorrow-mates to giue him graue.)</L>
<STAGE>They all helpe to carie Feliche to his graue.</STAGE>
<L>Death, exile, plaints, and woe,</L>
<L>Are but mans lackies, not his foe.</L>
<L>No mortall scapes from fortunes warre,</L>
<L>Without a wound, at least a scarre.</L>
<L>Many haue led these to the graue:</L>
<L>But all shall followe, none shall saue.</L>
<L>Bloode of my youth, rot and consume,</L>
<L>Virtue, in dirt, doth life assume:</L>
<L>With this ould sawe, close vp this dust;</L>
<L>Thrice blessed man that dyeth iust.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>An.</SPEAKER>
<L>The gloomie wing of night begins to stretch</L>
<L>His lasie pinion ouer all the ayre:</L>
<L>We must be stiffe and steddie in resolue.</L>
<L>Let's thus our hands, our hearts, our armes inuolue.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>They wreath their armes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now sweare we by this Gordian knot of loue,</L>
<L>By the fresh turnd vp mould that wraps my sonne;</L>
<L>By the deade browe of triple <HI>Hecate</HI>:</L>
<L>Ere night shall close the lids of you bright stars,</L>
<L><PB REF="34"/>Weele sit as heauie on <HI>Pieros</HI> heart,</L>
<L>As <HI>Aetna</HI> doth on groning <HI>Pelorus.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thanks good old man.</L>
<L>Weele cast at royall chaunce.</L>
<L>Let's thinke a plot; then pell mell vengeance.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt, their armes wreathed.</STAGE>
<STAGE>¶<HI>The Cornets sounde for the Acte.</HI></STAGE>
<STAGE>¶<HI>The dumbe showe.</HI></STAGE>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACT. V.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCEN. I.</HEAD>
<STAGE>¶<HI>Enter at one dore, Castilio and Forobosco, with halberts: foure Pages with torches: Luceo bare: Piero, Maria and Alberto, talking: Alberto drawes out his dagger, Maria her knife, ayming to menace the Duke. Then Ga∣leatzo betwixt two Senators, reading a paper to them: at which, they all make semblance of loathing Piero, and knit their fists at him; two Ladies and Nutriche: all these goe softly ouer the Stage, whilst at the other doore enters the ghost of Andrugio, who passeth by them, tos∣sing his torch about his heade in triumph. All forsake the Stage, sauing Andrugio, who speaking, begins the Acte.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>Venit dies, tempúsque, quo reddat suis</L>
<L>Animam squallentem sceleribus.</L>
<L>The fist of strenuous vengeance is clutcht,</L>
<L>And sterne <HI>Vindicta</HI> towreth vp aloft,</L>
<L>That she may fal with a more waightie paise,</L>
<L>And crush liues sap from out <HI>Pieros</HI> vaines.</L>
<L><PB REF="35"/>Now gins the leprous cores of vlcered sins</L>
<L>Wheale to a heade: now is his fate growne mellow,</L>
<L>Instant to fall into the rotten iawes</L>
<L>Of chap-falne death. Now downe lookes prouidēce,</L>
<L>T'attend the last act of my sons reuenge.</L>
<L>Be gratious, Obseruation, to our sceane:</L>
<L>For now the plot vnites his scattred limbes</L>
<L>Close in contracted bands. The <HI>Florence</HI> Prince</L>
<L>(Drawne by firme notice of the Dukes black deeds)</L>
<L>Is made a partner in conspiracie.</L>
<L>The States of <HI>Venice</HI> are so swolne in hate</L>
<L>Against the Duke, for his accursed deeds</L>
<L>(Of which they are confirm'd by some odde letters</L>
<L>Found in dead <HI>Strotzos</HI> studie, which had past</L>
<L>Betwixt <HI>Piero</HI> and the murdring slaue)</L>
<L>That they can scarce retaine from bursting foorth</L>
<L>In plaine reuolt. O, now tryumphes my ghost;</L>
<L>Exclaiming, heauen's iust; for I shal see,</L>
<L>The scourge of murder and impietie.
<STAGE>Exit</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA SECVNDA.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Balurdo from vnder the Stage.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<P>HOE, who's aboue there, hoe? A murren on all Prouerbes. They say, hunger breakes tho∣rough stone walles; but I am as gant, as leane ribd fa∣mine: yet I can burst through no stone walles. O, now sir <HI>Gefferey,</HI> shewe thy valour, breake prison, and be
<PB REF="35"/>
hangd. Nor shall the darkest nooke of hell containe the discontented sir <HI>Balurdos</HI> ghost. Well, I am out well, I haue put off the prison to put on the rope. O poore shotten herring, what a pickle art thou in! <HI>O</HI> hunger, how thou dominer'st in my guts! O, for a fat leg of Ewe mutton in stewde broth; or drunken song to feede on. I could belch rarely, for I am all winde. O colde, colde, colde, colde, colde. O poore knight, ô poore sir <HI>Gefferey</HI>; sing like an Vnicorne, before thou dost dip thy horne in the water of death; ô cold, ô sing, ô colde, ô poore sir <HI>Geffrey,</HI> sing, sing.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>CANTAT.</STAGE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA TERTIA.</HEAD>
<STAGE>¶ <HI>Enter Antonio and Alberto, at seuerall doores, their rapi∣ers drawne, in their masking attyre.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>VINDICTA.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Mellida.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Alberto.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Antonio.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hath the Duke supt?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, and tryumphant reuels mount aloft.</L>
<L>The Duke drinkes deepe to ouerdowe his griefe.</L>
<L>The court is rackt to pleasure, each man straines</L>
<L>To faine a iocund eye. The <HI>Florentine</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="36"/>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Young <HI>Galeatzo?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Euen he is mightie on our part. The States of <HI>Venice</HI></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>¶ <HI>Enter Pandulpho running, in masking attyre.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Like high-swoln floods, driue down the mud∣die dammes</L>
<L>Of pent allegeance. O, my lustie bloods,</L>
<L>Heauen sits clapping of our enterprise.</L>
<L>I haue beene labouring generall fauour firme,</L>
<L>And I doe finde the citizens growne sick</L>
<L>With swallowing the bloodie crudities</L>
<L>Of black <HI>Pieros</HI> acts; they faine would cast</L>
<L>And vomit him from off their gouernement.</L>
<L>Now is the plot of mischiefe ript wide ope:</L>
<L>Letters are found twixt <HI>Strotzo</HI> and the Duke,</L>
<L>So cleare apparent: yet more firmely strong</L>
<L>By suiting circumstance; that as I walkt</L>
<L>Muffled, to eues-drop speech, I might obserue</L>
<L>The grauer States-men whispering fearefully.</L>
<L>Here one giues nods &amp; hums, what he would speake:</L>
<L>The rumour's got 'mong troope of citizens,</L>
<L>Making lowde murmur, with confused dinne:</L>
<L>One shakes his head, and sighes; O ill vs'd powre:</L>
<L>Another frets, and sets his grinding teeth,</L>
<L>Foaming with rage; and sweares this must not be.</L>
<L>Here one complots, and on a sodaine starts,</L>
<L>And cries; ô monstrous, ô deepe villanie!</L>
<L>All knit there nerues, and from beneath swoln brows</L>
<L>Appeares a gloting eye of much mislike:</L>
<L>Whilst swart <HI>Pieros</HI> lips reake steame of wine,</L>
<L><PB REF="36"/>Swallowes lust-thoughts, deuours all pleasing hopes,</L>
<L>With strong imagination of, what not?</L>
<L>O, now <HI>Vindicta</HI>; that's the word we haue:</L>
<L>A royall vengeance, or a royall graue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Vindicta.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am acolde.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who's there? sir <HI>Geffrey?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<P>A poor knight, god wot: the nose of thy knight∣hoode is bitten off with cold. O poore sir <HI>Geffrey,</HI> cold, cold.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>What chance of fortune hath tript vp his heels,</L>
<L>And laid him in the kennell? ha?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will discourse it all. Poore honest soule,</L>
<L>Hadst thou a beuer to clasp vp thy face,</L>
<L>Thou shouldst associate vs in masquery,</L>
<L>And see reuenge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, and you talke of reuenge, my stomack's vp,</L>
<P>For I am most tyrannically hungry. A beuer? I haue a headpeece, a skull, a braine of proofe, I warrant yee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Slinke to my chamber then, and tyre thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is there a fire?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Yes.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is there a fat leg of Ewe mutton?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<P>And a cleane shirt?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then am I for you, most pathetically, &amp; vnvul∣garly, law.
<STAGE>Exit</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Resolued hearts, time curtals night, opportunity shakes vs his foretop. Steel your thoughts, sharp your resolue, imboldē your spirit, grasp your swords; alarum mischief, &amp; with an vndāted brow, out scout the grim opposition
<PB REF="37"/>Of most menacing perill.</P>
<L>Harke here, proud pomp shoots mounting tryumph vp,</L>
<L>Borne in lowde accents to the front of <HI>Ioue.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>O now, he that wants sowle to kill a slaue,</L>
<L>Let him die slaue, and rot in pesants graue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Giue me thy hand, and thine, most noble heart,</L>
<L>Thus will wee liue, and, but thus, neuer part.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt twin'd together.</STAGE>
<STAGE>¶ <HI>Cornets sound a Cynet.</HI></STAGE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="4" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA QVARTA.</HEAD>
<STAGE>¶ <HI>Enter Castilio and Forobosco, two Pages with torches, Lucio bare, Piero and Maria, Galeatzo, two Senators and Nutriche.</HI></STAGE>
<STAGE>¶ <HI>Piero to Maria.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>SIt close vnto my breast, heart of my loue,</L>
<L>Aduance thy drooping eyes,</L>
<L>Thy sonne is drownde,</L>
<L>Rich happinesse that such a sonne is drownde.</L>
<L>Thy husband's deade, life of my ioyes most blest,</L>
<L>In that the saplesse logge, that prest thy bed</L>
<L>With an vnpleasing waight, being lifted hence,</L>
<L>Euen I <HI>Piero,</HI> liue to warme his place.</L>
<L>I tell you, Ladie, had you view'd vs both,</L>
<L>With an vnprtiall eye, when first we woo'd</L>
<L>Your maiden beauties, I had borne the prize,</L>
<L><PB REF="37"/>Tis firme I had: for, faire, I ha done that</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<P>Murder.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Which he would quake to haue aduentur'd;</L>
<L>Thou know'st I haue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mari.</SPEAKER>
<P>Murdred my husband.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pier.</SPEAKER>
<L>Borne out the shock of war, &amp; done, what not,</L>
<L>That valour durst. Do'st loue me fairest? say.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<P>As I doe hate my son, I loue thy soule.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why then <HI>Io</HI> to <HI>Hymen,</HI> mount a loftie note:</L>
<L>Fill red cheekt <HI>Bacchus,</HI> let <HI>Lyeus</HI> flote</L>
<L>In burnisht gobblets. Force the plump lipt god,</L>
<L>Skip light lauoltaes in your full sapt vaines.</L>
<L>Tis well brim full. Euen I haue glut of blood:</L>
<L>Let quaffe carouse; I drinke this <HI>Burdeaux</HI> wine</L>
<L>Vnto the health of deade <HI>Andrugio,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Feliche, Strotzo</HI>▪ and <HI>Antonios</HI> ghosts.</L>
<L>Would I had some poyson to infuse it with;</L>
<L>That hauing done this honour to the dead,</L>
<L>I might send one to giue them notice ont.</L>
<L>I would indeere my fauour to the full.</L>
<L>Boy, sing alowd, make heauens vault to ring</L>
<L>With thy breaths strength. I drink. Now lowdly sing.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>CANTAT.</STAGE>
<STAGE>¶ <HI>The song ended, the Cornets sound a Cynet.</HI></STAGE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="5" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA QVINTA.</HEAD>
<STAGE><PB REF="38"/>¶ <HI>Enter Antonio, Pandulfo, and Alberto, in maskery, Balurdo, and a torchbearer.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>CALL <HI>Iulio</HI> hither; where's the little fowle?</L>
<L>I sawe him not to day. Here's sport alone</L>
<L>For him, ifaith; for babes and fooles, I know,</L>
<L>Relish not substance, but applaud the showe.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>To the conspirators as they stand in ranke for the measure.</STAGE>
<STAGE>To Antonio.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gal.</SPEAKER>
<L>All blessed fortune crown your braue attempt.</L>
<STAGE>To Pandulpho.</STAGE>
<L>I haue a troope to second your attempt.</L>
<STAGE>To Alberto.</STAGE>
<L>The <HI>Venice</HI> States ioyne hearts vnto your hands.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>By the delights in contemplation</L>
<L>Of comming ioyes, 'tis magnificent.</L>
<L>You grace my mariage eue with sumptuous pompe.</L>
<L>Sound still, lowde musick. O, your breath giues grace</L>
<L>To curious feete, that in proud measure pase.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mother, is <HI>Iulios</HI> bodie</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speake not, doubt not; all is aboue all hope.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then wil I daunce and whirle about the ayre.</L>
<L>Me thinks I am all sowle, all heart, all spirit.</L>
<L>Now murder shall receiue his ample merite.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>¶ <HI>The measure.</HI></STAGE>
<STAGE>¶ <HI>While the measure is dauncing, Andrugios ghost is pla∣ced betwixt the musick houses.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="38"/>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bring hither suckets, canded delicates.</L>
<L>Weele taste some sweet meats, gallants, ere we sleep.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Weele cooke your sweete meats, gallants, with tart sower sawce.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here will I sit, spectator of reuenge,</L>
<L>And glad my ghost in anguish of my foe.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>The maskers whisper with Piero.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Piero.</SPEAKER>
<L>Marry and shall; ifaith I were too rude,</L>
<L>If I gainesaide so ciuill fashion.</L>
<L>The maskers pray you to forbeare the roome,</L>
<L>Till they haue banqueted. Let it be so:</L>
<L>No man presume to visite them, on death.</L>
<STAGE>The maskers whisper againe.</STAGE>
<L>Onely my selfe? O, why with all my heart▪</L>
<L>Ile fill your consort; here <HI>Piero</HI> sits:</L>
<L>Come on, vnmaske, lets fall to</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>The conspirators binde Piero, pluck out his tongue, and tryumph ouer him.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Murder and torture: no prayers, no entreats.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Weele spoyle your oratory. Out with his tong.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue't <HI>Pandulpho</HI>: the vaines panting bleede,</L>
<L>Trickling fresh goare about my fist. Bind fast; so, so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>Blest be thy hand. I taste the ioyes of heauen,</L>
<L>Viewing my sonne tryumph in his blacke bloode.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Downe to the dungeon with him, Ile dungeon with him; Ile foole you: sir <HI>Gefferey</HI> will be sir <HI>Geffrey.</HI> Ile tickle you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Beholde, black dogge.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Grinst thou, thou snurling curre?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Eate thy black liuer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>To thine anguish see</L>
<L><PB REF="39"/>A foole tryumphant in thy misery.</L>
<L>Vex him <HI>Balurdo.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>He weepes: now doe I glorifie my hands,</L>
<L>I had no vengeance, if I had no teares.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fal to, good Duke. ô these are worthlesse cares,</L>
<L>You haue no stomack to them; looke, looke here:</L>
<L>Here lies a dish to feast thy fathers gorge.</L>
<L>Here's flesh and blood, which I am sure thou lou'st.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>¶ <HI>Piero seemes to condole his sonne</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Was he thy flesh, thy son, thy dearest sonne?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>So was <HI>Andrugio</HI> my dearest father.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<P>So was <HI>Feliche</HI> my dearest sonne.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>¶ <HI>Enter Maria.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<P>So was <HI>Andrugio</HI> my dearest husband.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>My father found no pittie in thy blood.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Remorse was banisht, when thou slew'st my son.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>When thou impoysoned'st my louing Lord,</L>
<L>Exilde was pietie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>An.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now, therefore, pittie, piety, remorse,</L>
<L>Be aliens to our thoughts: grim fier-ey'd rage</L>
<L>Possesse vs wholly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy son? true: and which is my most ioy,</L>
<L>I hope no bastard, but thy very blood</L>
<L>Thy true begotten, most legitimate</L>
<L>And loued issue: there's the comfort ont.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Scum of the mud of hell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Slime of all filth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou most detested road.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou most retort and obtuse rascall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thus charge we death at thee: remember hel,</L>
<L>And let the howling murmurs of black spirits,</L>
<L><PB REF="39"/>The horrid torments of the damned Ghosts</L>
<L>Affright thy sowle, as it descendeth downe</L>
<L>Into the intrals of the vgly deepe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sa, sa; no, let him die, and die, and stil be dying,</L>
<STAGE>¶<HI>They offer to runne all at Piero, and on a sodain stop.</HI></STAGE>
<L>And yet not die, till he hath di'd and di'd</L>
<L>Ten thousand deathes in agonie of heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>An.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now pel mell; thus the hand of heauen chokes</L>
<L>The throate of murder. This for my fathers blood.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>He stabs Piero.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<P>This for my sonne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<L>This for them all.</L>
<L>And this, and this; sinke to the heart of hell.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>They run all at Piero with their Rapiers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Murder for murder, blood for blood doth yell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Andr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis done, and now my sowle shal sleep in rest.</L>
<L>Sons that reuenge their fathers blood, are blest.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>The curtaines being drawne, Exit Andrugio.</STAGE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="6" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA SEXTA.</HEAD>
<STAGE>¶ <HI>Enter Galeatzo, two Senators, Luceo, Forobosco, Castilio, and Ladies.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Sen.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>WHOSE hand presents this gory spe∣ctacle?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<P>No: mine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<P>No: mine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="40"/>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will not loose the glorie of the deede,</L>
<L>Were all the tortures of the deepest hell</L>
<L>Fixt to my limbs. I pearc't the monsters heart,</L>
<L>With an vndaunted hand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>By yon bright spangled front of heauen twas I:</L>
<L>Twas I sluc't out his life bloode.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tush, to say truth, twas all.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Sen.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Blest be you all, and may your honours liue</L>
<L>Religiously helde sacred, euen for euer and euer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gal.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>To Antonio.</HI> Thou art another <HI>Hercules</HI> to vs,</L>
<L>In ridding huge pollution from our State.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Sen.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Antonio,</HI> beliefe is fortified,</L>
<L>With most inuincible approuemēts of much wrong,</L>
<L>By this <HI>Piero</HI> to thee. We haue found</L>
<L>Beadroles of mischiefe, plots of villany,</L>
<L>Laide twixt the Duke and <HI>Strotzo</HI>: which we found</L>
<L>Too firmely acted.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Sen.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Alas poore Orphant.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>An.</SPEAKER>
<L>Poore? standing tryumphant ouer <HI>Belzebub</HI>?</L>
<L>Hauing large interest for blood; &amp; yet deem'd poor?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Sen.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>What satisfaction outward pomp can yield,</L>
<L>Or cheefest fortunes of the <HI>Venice</HI> state,</L>
<L>Claime freely. You are well seasond props,</L>
<L>And will not warpe, or leane to either part▪</L>
<L>Calamity giues man a steddy heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are amaz'd at your benignitie:</L>
<L>But other vowes constraine another course.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>We know the world, and did we know no more,</L>
<L>Wee would not liue to know: but since constraint</L>
<L>Of holy bands forceth vs keepe this lodge</L>
<L><PB REF="40"/>Of durts corruption, till dread power cals</L>
<L>Our soules appearance, we will liue inclos'd</L>
<L>In holy verge of some religious order,</L>
<L>Most constant votaries.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>The curtaines are drawne, Piero departeth.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>First let's cleanse our hands,</L>
<L>Purge hearts of hatred, and intoumbe my loue:</L>
<L>Ouer whose hearse, Ile weepe away my braine</L>
<L>In true affections teares,</L>
<L>For her sake, here I vowe a virgine bed.</L>
<L>She liues in me, with her my loue is deade.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Sen.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>We will attend her mournfull exequies,</L>
<L>Conduct you to your calme sequestred life,</L>
<L>And then</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Maria.</SPEAKER>
<L>Leaue vs, to meditate on misery;</L>
<L>To sad our thought with contemplation</L>
<L>Of past calamities. If any aske</L>
<L>Where liues the widdowe of the poisoned Lord?</L>
<L>Where lies the Orphant of a murdred father?</L>
<L>Where lies the father of a butchered son?</L>
<L>Where liues all woe? conduct him to vs three;</L>
<L>The downe-cast ruines of calamitie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sound dolefull tunes, a solemne hymn aduance,</L>
<L>To close the last act of my vengeance:</L>
<L>And when the subiect of your passion's spent,</L>
<L>Sing <HI>Mellida</HI> is deade, all hearts will relent,</L>
<L>In sad condolement, at that heauie sound,</L>
<L>Neuer more woe in lesser plot was found.</L>
<L>And, ô, if euer time create a Muse,</L>
<L><PB REF="41" MS="y"/>That to th'immortall fame of virgine faith,</L>
<L>Dares once engage his pen to write her death,</L>
<L>Presenting it in some black Tragedie.</L>
<L>May it proue gratious, may his stile be deckt</L>
<L>With freshest bloomes of purest elegance;</L>
<L>May it haue gentle presence, and the Sceans suckt vp</L>
<L>By calme attention of choyce audience:</L>
<L>And when the closing Epilogue appeares,</L>
<L>In stead of claps, may it obtaine but teares.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>CANTANT.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Exeunt omnes.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Antonij vindictae.</STAGE>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
<PB REF="41"/>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

