<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2002-02-13</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Judith Siefring</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Checked for TYPE="book". Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, etc.). Checked for signatures. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, and UNCLEARs. Corrected 21 $s of 614. Converted 593 $s to GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc". Checked for EPIGRAPHs and ARGUMENTs. Checked for startqs, endqs, oes, q;s, and Qs. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Checked for CLOSERs, TRAILERs, and BYLINEs. Sample: 15 minutes. Proofing: 25 minutes. Tag review and corrections: 70 minutes. DONE.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="A07240">
<STC T="S">17638.5</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99847675</BIBNO>
<VID>12729</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT>
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>THE MAID OF HONOVR. AS IT HATH BEENE OFTEN PRESENTED with good allowance at the <HI>Phoenix</HI> in DRVRIE-LANE, by the Queenes Majesties SERVANTS.</P>
<P>Written by PHILIP MASSINGER.</P>
<P><HI>LONDON,</HI> Printed by <HI>I. B.</HI> for <HI>Robert Allot,</HI> and are to be sold at his Shop at the signe of the blacke Beare in <HI>Pauls</HI> Church-yard, 1632.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dramatis personae">
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>The Actors names.</HEAD>
<LIST>
<LABEL>Roberto,</LABEL>
<ITEM>King of <HI>Sicilie.</HI></ITEM>
<LABEL>Ferdinand,</LABEL>
<ITEM>Duke of <HI>Vrbin.</HI></ITEM>
<LABEL>Bertoldo,</LABEL>
<ITEM>The Kings naturall brother, a knight of <HI>Malta.</HI></ITEM>
<LABEL>Gonzaga,</LABEL>
<ITEM>A knight of <HI>Malta,</HI> General to the Duchesse of <HI>Siena.</HI></ITEM>
<LABEL>Astutio,</LABEL>
<ITEM>A counsellor of state</ITEM>
<LABEL>Fulgentio,</LABEL>
<ITEM>The mignion of <HI>Roberto.</HI></ITEM>
<LABEL>Adorni,</LABEL>
<ITEM>A follower of <HI>Camiolas</HI> father.</ITEM>
<LABEL>Embassador,</LABEL>
<ITEM>From the Duke of <HI>Vrbin.</HI></ITEM>
<LABEL>Signior Sylli,</LABEL>
<ITEM>A foolish selfe-lover.</ITEM>
<LABEL>Anthonio, Gasparo,</LABEL>
<ITEM>Two rich heyres, Citty-bred.</ITEM>
<LABEL>Pierio,</LABEL>
<ITEM>A Colonel to <HI>Gonzaga.</HI></ITEM>
<LABEL>Roderigo, Iacomo,</LABEL>
<ITEM>Captaines to <HI>Gonzaga.</HI></ITEM>
<LABEL><HI>D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uso, Livio,</HI></LABEL>
<ITEM>Captaines to Duke <HI>Ferdinand.</HI></ITEM>
<LABEL>Paulo,</LABEL>
<ITEM>A priest, <HI>Camiolas</HI> confessor.</ITEM>
<LABEL>Scout,</LABEL>
<ITEM></ITEM>
<LABEL>Souldiers,</LABEL>
<ITEM></ITEM>
<LABEL>Servants,</LABEL>
<ITEM></ITEM>
<LABEL>Iaylor,</LABEL>
<ITEM></ITEM>
<LABEL>Dwarfe,</LABEL>
<ITEM></ITEM>
<LABEL>Mutes,</LABEL>
<ITEM></ITEM>
<LABEL><HI>A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>elia,</HI></LABEL>
<ITEM>Duchesse of <HI>Siena.</HI></ITEM>
<LABEL>Camiola.</LABEL>
<ITEM>The Maid of Honou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</ITEM>
<LABEL>Clarinda,</LABEL>
<ITEM>Her Woman.</ITEM>
</LIST>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>To my most honour'd friends, Sir FRANCIS FOLIAMBE, Knight, and Baronet, and to Sir THOMAS BLAND Knight.</HEAD>
<P>THat you have beene, and continued so for many yeeres (since you vouchsafed to owne me) Patrons to me and my de∣spised studies, I cannot but with all humble thankefulnesse acknowledge: And living, as you have done, inseparable in your friendship (notwithstanding all differences, and suites in Law arising betweene you) I held it as im∣pertinent, as absurd, in the presentment of my service in this kinde, to divide you. A free confession of a debt in a meaner man, is the amplest satisfaction to his superiours, and I heartily wish, that the world may take notice, and from my selfe, that I had not to this time subsisted, but that I was supported by your frequent courtesies, and favours, when your more serious occasions will give you leave, you may please to peruse this trifle, and peradventure find somthing in it that may appeare worthy of your protection. Receive it, I beseech you, as a testimony of his duty, who, while he lives, resolves to be</P>
<CLOSER>

<SIGNED>Truly, and sincerely devoted to your service, <HI>Philip Massinger.</HI></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="poem">
<PB REF="3"/>
<HEAD>TO MY WORTHY FRIEND THE AVTHOR VPON HIS TRAGAE<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>COMAEDY, THE MAID OF HONOVR.</HEAD>
<L>WAs not thy <HI>Emperor</HI> enough before</L>
<L>For thee to give, that thou dost give vs more?</L>
<L>I would be just, but cannot: that I know</L>
<L>I did not slander, this I feare I doe.</L>
<L>But pardon mee, if I offend: Thy fire</L>
<L>Let equall Poets praise, while I admire.</L>
<L>If any say that I enough have writ,</L>
<L>They are thy foes, and envy at thy wit.</L>
<L>Believe not them, nor mee, they know thy lines</L>
<L>Deserve applause, but speake against their mindes.</L>
<L>I, out of iustice, would commend thy Play,</L>
<L>But (friend forgive mee) 'tis above my way.</L>
<L>One word, and I have done (and from my heart</L>
<L>Would I could speake the whole truth, not the part)</L>
<L>Because 'tis thine; it henceforth will be said,</L>
<L>Not the Maid of Honour, but the Honour'd Maid.</L>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>ASTON COKAYNE.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 N="1" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="3"/>
<HEAD>THE MAIDE OF HONOVR. A Tragae-Comedy.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. 1. SCENE. 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Astutio. Adorni.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ADORNI.</SPEAKER>
<L>GOod day to your Lordship:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Astutio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thanks <HI>Adorni.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ador</SPEAKER>
<L>May I presume to aske if the Em∣bassador</L>
<L>Imploy'd by <HI>Ferdinand,</HI> the Duke of <HI>Vr∣bin</HI></L>
<L>Hath audience this morning?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Fulgent.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Astu.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis uncertaine,</L>
<L>For though a counsaylor of state, I am not</L>
<L>Of the Cabinet counsaile. But ther's one if he please</L>
<L>That may resolve you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="4"/>
<SPEAKER>Ador.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will move him S<SUP>r</SUP>.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aulgen.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you have a suite, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hew water, I am blinde else.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ador.</SPEAKER>
<L>A suite, y<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t of a nature, not to prove</L>
<L>The quarrie that you hawke for: If your words</L>
<L>Are not like Indian wares<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> and every scruple</L>
<L>To be waigh'd and rated, one poore sillable</L>
<L>Vouchsaf'd in answer of a faire demand,</L>
<L>Cannot deserve a fee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fulgen.</SPEAKER>
<L>It seemes you are ignorant,</L>
<L>I neiher speake, nor hold my peace for nothing:</L>
<L>And yet for once, I care not if I answer</L>
<L>One single question, <HI>grati<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ador.</SPEAKER>
<L>I much thanke you.</L>
<L>Hath the Embassador audience Sir to day?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fulgen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ador.</SPEAKER>
<L>At what houre?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fulgen.</SPEAKER>
<L>I promis'd not so much.</L>
<L>A sillable you begg'd, my Charity gaue it.</L>
<L>Move me no further.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Exit Fulgenti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Astu.</SPEAKER>
<L>This you wonder at?</L>
<L>With me 'tis usuall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ador.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray you S<SUP>r</SUP>. what is he?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Astu.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Gentlemaan, yet no lord. He hath some drop<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Of the Kings blood running in his veines, deriu'd</L>
<L>Some ten degrees off. His revenue lyes</L>
<L>In a narrow compasse, the Kings eare, and yeelds him</L>
<L>Every houre a fruitfull harvest. Men may talk<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Of three croppes in a yeare in the fortunate Islands.</L>
<L>Or profit made by wooll. But while there are sutors<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>His sheepe sheering, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ay <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>having to the quicke</L>
<L>Is in every quarter of the Moone, and constant,</L>
<L>In the time of trussing a point, he can undoe</L>
<L>Or make a man. His play or recreation</L>
<L>Is to raise <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ihs up, o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> pu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l downe that, and though</L>
<L>He neve yet tooke orders, makes more Bishops</L>
<L><PB REF="4"/>In Sicilie, then the Pope himselfe.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Bertoldo. Gasparo. Anthonio. a servant.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ador.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most strange!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Astu.</SPEAKER>
<L>The presence fils. He in the Malta hab<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t</L>
<L>Is the naturall brother of the King, a by blow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ador.</SPEAKER>
<L>I understand you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>asp.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Morrow to my Vncle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Antho.</SPEAKER>
<L>And my late Guardian. But at length I have</L>
<L>The reignes in my owne hands.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Astu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray you use 'em well,</L>
<L>Or you'll too late repent it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>With this Iewell</L>
<L>Presented to <HI>Camiola,</HI> prepare</L>
<L>This night a uisit for me. I shall have</L>
<STAGE>Exit servant.</STAGE>
<L>Your company Gallants I perceive, if that</L>
<L>The King will heare of war.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Antho.</SPEAKER>
<L>S<SUP>r</SUP>. I have horses</L>
<L>Of the best breed in Naples, fitter far</L>
<L>To breake a ranke, then cracke a lance, and are</L>
<L>In their carere of such incredible swiftnes</L>
<L>They out-strip swallowes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>And such may bee usefull</L>
<L>To run away with, should we be defeated.</L>
<L>You are well provided Signior</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tho.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>S<SUP>r</SUP>. excuse me.</L>
<L>All of their race by instinct know a Coward.</L>
<L>And scorne the burthen. They come on like lightning,</L>
<L>Founder'd in a retreat.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>By no meanes backe 'em.</L>
<L>Vnlesse you know your courage sympathize</L>
<L>With the daring of your horse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Antho.</SPEAKER>
<L>My lord, this is <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>itter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will rayse me a company of foote,</L>
<L>And when at push of pike I am to enter</L>
<L>A brea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h, to shew my valour, I have bought mee</L>
<L><PB REF="5"/>An armor cannon proofe</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>You will not leape then</L>
<L>Ore an out-worke in your shirt<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<L>I do not like</L>
<L>Activity that way.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>You had rather stand</L>
<L>A marke to try their muskets on?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<L>If I doe</L>
<L>No good, I'll doe no hurt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis in you Sign<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>or</L>
<L>A Christian resolution, and becomes you,</L>
<L>But I will not discourage you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Antho.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are S<SUP>r</SUP>.</L>
<L>A knight of Malta, and as I have heard<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Have serv'd aga<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nst the Turke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Ber<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI></SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis true.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Antho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray you shew vs</L>
<L>The difference betweene the city valour.</L>
<L>And service in the field.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis somewhat more</L>
<L>Then roaring in a t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>verne, or a brothell,</L>
<L>Or to steale a Constable from a sleeping watch;</L>
<L>Then burne their halberds; or safe guarded by</L>
<L>Your tenants sonnes, to carry away a Maypole</L>
<L>From a neighbour village; you will not finde there</L>
<L>Your Masters of Dependencies to take up</L>
<L>A drunken brawle, or to get you the names</L>
<L>Of valiant Cheivaleirs, fellowes that will bee</L>
<L>For a clo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ke with thrice died veluet, and a cast suite</L>
<L>Kick'd down the stairs. A knave with halfe a britch there,</L>
<L>And no shirt (being a thing superfluous,</L>
<L>And worne ou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> of his memorie) if you beare not</L>
<L>Your selves both in, and upright with a provant sword</L>
<L>Will slash your skarlets, and your plush a new way;</L>
<L>Or with the hilts thunder about your eares</L>
<L>Such musicke as will make your worships dance</L>
<L><PB REF="5"/>To the dolefull tune of <HI>La<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>yr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ma,</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must tell you,</L>
<L>In priuate, as you are my princely friend,</L>
<L>I doe not like such Fidlers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Bert<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>No? they are usefull</L>
<L>For your imitation; I remember you</L>
<L>When you came first to the Court, and talkt of nothing</L>
<L>But you rents, and your entradas; ever chiming</L>
<L>The golden bells in your pockets, you belieu'd</L>
<L>The taking of the wall, as a tribute due to</L>
<L>Your gaudy clothes; and could not walke at m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d-night</L>
<L>Without a causelesse quarrell, as if men</L>
<L>Of courser outsides were in duty bound</L>
<L>To suffer your affronts: but when you had beene</L>
<L>Cud<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ell'd well, twice or thrice, and from the doctrine</L>
<L>Made profitable uses, you concluded</L>
<L>The soveraigne meanes to teach irregular heyres</L>
<L>Civility, with conformity of manners,</L>
<L>VVere two or three sound beatings.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Antho.</SPEAKER>
<L>I confesse</L>
<L>They did much good upon mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<L>And on mee—the principles that they read were sound.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bertol.</SPEAKER>
<L>You'll finde</L>
<L>The like instructions in the Campe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Ast<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>The King.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>A Florish.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Roberto. Fulgentio. Embassador. Attendants.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rober.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVee sit prepar'd to heare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Embas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Majesty</L>
<L>Hath beene long since familiar, I doubt not,</L>
<L>VVith the desperate fortunes of my Lord, and pitty</L>
<L>Of the much that your confederate hath suffer'd</L>
<L>(You being his last refuge) may perswade you</L>
<L>Not alone to compassionate, but to lend</L>
<L><PB REF="6"/>Your royall aydes to stay him in his fall</L>
<L>To certaine ruine. Hee too late is conscious,</L>
<L>That his ambition to incroach upon</L>
<L>His neighbours territories, with the danger of</L>
<L>His liberty, nay his life, hath brough in question</L>
<L>Hi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> owne inheritance: but youth and heat</L>
<L>Of blood<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> in your interpretation, may</L>
<L>Both plead, and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ediate for him. I must grant it</L>
<L>An error in him, being deni'd the favours though</L>
<L>Of the faire Princesse of <HI>Siena</HI></L>
<L>He sought her in a noble way) t'andeavou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>To for<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> affection, by surprisall of</L>
<L>Her principall seat <HI>Siena.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rober.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhich now proves</L>
<L>The seat of his captivity<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> not triumph.</L>
<L>Heaven is still just.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Embas.</SPEAKER>
<L>And yet that justice is</L>
<L>To be with mercy temper'd, which heau'<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s Deputies</L>
<L>Stand bound to minister. The injur'd Duche<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>se</L>
<L>By reason taught, as nature, could not with</L>
<L>The reparation of her wrongs, but aime at</L>
<L>A brave revenge, and my Lord feeles too late</L>
<L>That innocence will finde friends. The great Gonzaga,</L>
<L>The honor of his Order, I must praise</L>
<L>Vertue, though in an enemy. Hee whose fights</L>
<L>And conquests hold one number, rallying up</L>
<L>Her scatter'd troopes, before wee could get time</L>
<L>To victuall, or to man the conquer'd City,</L>
<L>Sate downe before it, and presuming that</L>
<L>'Tis not to be releev'd, admits no parley,</L>
<L>Our s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ags of truce hung out in vaine, nor will hee</L>
<L>Lend an eare to composition, but exacts</L>
<L>With the rendring up the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>owne, the goods, and lines</L>
<L>Of all within the walls, and of all Sexes</L>
<L>To be at his discretion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Roberto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Since injustice</L>
<L><PB REF="6"/>In your Duke, meets this correction, can you presse us</L>
<L>With any seeming argument of reason,</L>
<L>In foolish pitty to decline his dangers,</L>
<L>To draw 'em on our selfe? Shall we not be,</L>
<L>Warn'd by his harmes? The league proclaim'd between us.</L>
<L>Bound neither of us farther then to ayde</L>
<L>Each other, if by forraigne force invaded,</L>
<L>And so farre in my honour I was tied.</L>
<L>But <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ince without our counsell, or allowance,</L>
<L>He hath tooke armes, with his good leave, he must</L>
<L>Excuse us, if wee steere not on a rocke</L>
<L>We see, and may avoyd. Let other Monarchs</L>
<L>Contend to be made glorious by proud warre,</L>
<L>And with the blood of their poore subjects purchase</L>
<L>Increase of Empire, and augment their cares</L>
<L>In keeping that which was by wrongs extorted;</L>
<L>Guilding unjust invasions with the trimne</L>
<L>Of glorious conquests; wee that would be knowne</L>
<L>The father of our people in our study,</L>
<L>And vigilance for their safety, must not change</L>
<L>Their plough-shares into swords, or force them from</L>
<L>The secure shade of their owne vines to be</L>
<L>Scorch'd with the flames of warre, or for our sport</L>
<L>Expose their liues to ruine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Embas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you then</L>
<L>In his extremity forsake your friend?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Roberto.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, but preserue our selfe:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bertol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cannot the beames</L>
<L>Of honour thaw your icie feares?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Roberto.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVho's that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rertol.</SPEAKER>
<L>A kinde of brother, Sir, how e'er your subject,</L>
<L>Your father's Sonne, and one who blushes that</L>
<L>You are not heire to his brave spirit, and vigour,</L>
<L>As to his Kingdome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Roberto.</SPEAKER>
<L>How's this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bertol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, to be</L>
<L><PB REF="7"/>His living Chronicle, and to speake his praise</L>
<L>Cannot deserve your anger.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rober.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhere's your warrant</L>
<L>For this presumption?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bertol.</SPEAKER>
<L>He<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e, Sir, in my heart.</L>
<L>Let Sycopha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ts, that feed upon your favours,</L>
<L>Stile coldnesse in you caution, and preferre</L>
<L>Your ease before your honour; and conclude</L>
<L>To eate and s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eepe supinely, is the end</L>
<L>Of humane blessings: I must tell you Sir,</L>
<L>Vertue, if not in action, is a vice,</L>
<L>And when wee move not forward, we goe backeward;</L>
<L>Nor is this peace (the nurse of drones, and cowards)</L>
<L>Our health, but a disease.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVel urg'd my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Antho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Perfit what is so well begunne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Embas.</SPEAKER>
<L>And binde,</L>
<L>My Lord, your servant:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rober.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hare-braind foole! what reason</L>
<L>Canst thou inferre to make this good?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Bert<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>A thousand</L>
<L>Not to be contradicted. But consider</L>
<L>VVhere your command lies? 'Tis not, Sir, in <HI>France,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Spaine, Germany, Portugall,</HI> but in <HI>Sicilie,</HI></L>
<L>An Island, Sir. Here are no mines of gold,</L>
<L>Or silver to enrich you, no worme spinnes</L>
<L>Silke in her wombe to make distinction</L>
<L>Betweene you, and a Peasant, in your habits.</L>
<L>No fish liues neere our shores, who's blood can dy</L>
<L>Scarlet, or purple; all that wee possesse</L>
<L>VVith beasts, wee have in common: Nature did</L>
<L>Designe us robe warriours, and to breake through</L>
<L>Our ring the sea, by which we are inviron'd;</L>
<L>And we by force must fetch in what is wanting,</L>
<L>Or precious to us. Adde to this, wee are</L>
<L>A populous nation, and increase so fast,</L>
<L><PB REF="7"/>That if we by our providence, are not sent</L>
<L>Abroad in colonies, or fall by the sword,</L>
<L>Not <HI>Sicilie</HI> (though now, it were more fruitfull,</L>
<L>Then when 'twas stil'd the granary of great <HI>Rom<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI>)</L>
<L>Can yeeld our numerous frie bread, we must starve,</L>
<L>Or eat vp one another.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adorn.</SPEAKER>
<L>The King heares</L>
<L>With much atten<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Astut.</SPEAKER>
<L>And seemes mou'd with what</L>
<L><HI>Bertoldo</HI> hath deliver'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bertol.</SPEAKER>
<L>May you live long, Sir,</L>
<L>The King of peace, so you deny not us</L>
<L>The glory of the warre; let not our nerves</L>
<L>Shrincke up with <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>loth, nor for want of imployment</L>
<L>Make younger brothers theves; 'tis their swordes, Sir,</L>
<L>Must sow and re<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pe their harvest; if examples</L>
<L>May move you more then arguments, looke on <HI>England,</HI></L>
<L>The Empresse of the European Isles,</L>
<L>And unto whom alone ours yeelds procedence,</L>
<L>When did she flourish so, as when she was</L>
<L>The Mistresse of the Ocean. Her navies</L>
<L>Putting a girdle round about the world,</L>
<L>When the <HI>Iberian</HI> quak'd, her worthies nam'd;</L>
<L>And the faire flowre Deluc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> grew pale, set by</L>
<L>The red Rose and the white: let not our armour</L>
<L>Hung up, or our unrig'd <HI>Armada</HI> make us</L>
<L>Ridiculous to the late poore snakes our neighbours</L>
<L>VVarm'd in our bosomes, and to whom againe</L>
<L>VVe may be terrible: while wee spend our houres</L>
<L>Without variety, confinde to drinke,</L>
<L>Dice, Cards, or whores. Rowze us, Sir, from the sleepe</L>
<L>Of idlenesse, and redeeme our morgag'd honour<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</L>
<L>Your birth, and justly, claimes my fathers Kingdome;</L>
<L>But his Heroique minde descends to mee,</L>
<L>I will confirme so much.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adorn.</SPEAKER>
<L>In his lookes he seemes</L>
<L><PB REF="8"/>To breake ope <HI>Ianu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> Temple.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Astut.</SPEAKER>
<L>How these younglings</L>
<L>Take fire from him!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ador.</SPEAKER>
<L>It works an alteration</L>
<L>Vpon the King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Antho.</SPEAKER>
<L>I can forbeare no longer:</L>
<L>Warre, warre, my Soveraigne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fulg.</SPEAKER>
<L>The King appeares</L>
<L>Resolv'd, and do<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s prepare to speake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Robert.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thinke not</L>
<L>Our counsel's built upon so weake a base,</L>
<L>As to be overturn'd, or shaken with</L>
<L>Tempestuous windes of words. As I, my Lord,</L>
<L>Before resolv'd you, I will not ingage</L>
<L>My person in this quarrell; neyther presse</L>
<L>My Subjects to maintaine it: yet to shew</L>
<L>My rule is gentle, and that I have feeling</L>
<L>Of your Masters sufferings, since these Gallants weary</L>
<L>Of the happinesse of peace, desire to taste</L>
<L>The bitter sweets of warre, wee doe consent</L>
<L>That as Adventures, and Voluntiers</L>
<L>(No way compell'd by us) they may make tryall</L>
<L>Of their boasted valours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bertol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee desire no more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Robert.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis well, and but my grant in this, expect not</L>
<L>Assistance from mee. Governe as you please</L>
<L>The Province you make choice of, for I vow.</L>
<L>By all things sacred, if that thou miscarry</L>
<L>In this rash undertaking, I will heare it</L>
<L>No otherwise then as a sad disaster,</L>
<L>Falne on a stranger: nor will I esteeme</L>
<L>That man my Subject, who in thy extremes</L>
<L>In purse or person ayds thee. Take your fortune:</L>
<L>You know mee, I haue said it. So my Lord</L>
<L>You have my absolute answer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Embas.</SPEAKER>
<L>My<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Prince payes</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n me his duty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="8"/>
<SPEAKER>Robert.</SPEAKER>
<L>Follow me, <HI>Fulgentio,</HI></L>
<L>And you, <HI>Astutio.</HI>
<STAGE>Exeunt <HI>Roberto, Fulgentio, Astutio</HI> attendants.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhat a frowne he threw</L>
<L>At his departure, on you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bertol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let him keepe</L>
<L>His smiles for his state Catamite, I care not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Antho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall wee aboord to night?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Embas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your speed, my Lord,</L>
<L>Doubles the benefit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bertol.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have a businesse</L>
<L>Requires dispatch, some two houres hence I'll meet you.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. I. SCENE. II.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Signior Sylli.</HI> walking fantastically before, followed by <HI>Camiola</HI> and <HI>Clarinda:</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAmiola.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay <HI>Signior</HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> this is too much ceremony in my owne house.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sylli.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhat's gratious abroad, must be in private practis'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clar.</SPEAKER>
<L>For your mirth-sake</L>
<L>Let him alone, he has beene all this morning</L>
<L>In practice with a perugd Gentleman vsher,</L>
<L>To teach him his true amble and his postures,
<STAGE><HI>Sylli</HI> wal∣king by, and pra∣ctising his postures.</STAGE></L>
<L>VVhen he walkes before a Lady</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syll.</SPEAKER>
<L>You may, Madame,</L>
<L>Perhaps, beleeve that I in this use art,</L>
<L>To make you dote upon mee by exposing</L>
<L>My more then most rare features to your view.</L>
<L>But I as I have ever done, deale simply,</L>
<L>A marke of sweet simplicity ever noted</L>
<L>I'the family of the <HI>Syllies.</HI> Therefore Lady,</L>
<L>Looke not with too much contemplation on mee,</L>
<L>If you doe, you are i'the suds.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Camil.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are no Barber?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sylli.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fie no, not I, but my good parts have drawne</L>
<L>More loving hearts out of faire Ladies bellies,</L>
<L><PB REF="9"/>Then the whole trade haue done teeth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Cam<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Is't possible?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sylli.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, and they live too, marry much condoling</L>
<L>The scorne of their <HI>Narcissus,</HI> as they call mee,</L>
<L>Because I love my selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVithout a rivall;</L>
<L>What philtres or love-powders doe you use</L>
<L>To force affection? I see nothing in</L>
<L>Your person, but I dare looke on, yet keepe</L>
<L>My owne poore heart still.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sylli.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are warn'd, be arm'd,</L>
<L>And doe not lose the hope of such a husband</L>
<L>In being too soone enamour'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold in yo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r head,</L>
<L>Or you must haue a martingale.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sylli:</SPEAKER>
<L>I have sworne</L>
<L>Neuer to take a wife, but such a one</L>
<L>(O may your Ladiship prove so strong) as can</L>
<L>Hold out a moneth against mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam</SPEAKER>
<L>Never feare it,</L>
<L>Though your best taking part, your wealth were trebl'd</L>
<L>I would not wooe you. But since in your pitty</L>
<L>You please to give me caution, tell me what</L>
<L>Temp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ations I must flye from?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sylli.</SPEAKER>
<L>The first is</L>
<L>That you n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ver heare mee sing, for I am a <HI>Syri.</HI></L>
<L>If you observe, when I warble, the dogs howle</L>
<L>As ravish'd with my D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tties, and you will</L>
<L>runne m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d to heare mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will stop my eares,</L>
<L>And <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pe me little wits.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sylli.</SPEAKER>
<L>Next when I dance</L>
<L>And come alo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t thus, cast not a sheepes eye</L>
<L>Vpon the quivering of my calfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Proceed, Sir,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sylli.</SPEAKER>
<L>But on no ter<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es, for 'tis a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aine point, drea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e not</L>
<L><PB REF="9"/>Of the strength of my back, though it will beare a burthen</L>
<L>With any porter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cami.</SPEAKER>
<L>I meane not to ride you,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor I your little Ladiship, 'till you have</L>
<L>Perform'd the Covenants. Be not taken with</L>
<L>My prettie spider fingers, nor my eyes,</L>
<L>That twinckle on both sides.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cami.</SPEAKER>
<L>Was there ever such
<STAGE>One knocks.</STAGE></L>
<L>A piece of motlie heard of! who's that? you may spare</L>
<L>The Catalogue of my dangers.
<STAGE><HI>Exit Clarin<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>.</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syl.</SPEAKER>
<L>No good Madam,</L>
<L>I have not told you halfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cami.</SPEAKER>
<L>Enough good Signior,</L>
<L>If I <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>te more of such sweete meats, I shall surfet.</L>
<L>Who is't?
<STAGE>Enter Clarinda.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clar.</SPEAKER>
<L>The brother of the King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay start not,</L>
<L>The brother of the King! is he no more?</L>
<L>Were it the King himselfe, I'll give him leave</L>
<L>To speake his mind to you, for I am not jealo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s,</L>
<L>And to assure your Ladyship of so much,</L>
<L>I'll usher him in, and that done, hide my selfe.
<STAGE>Exit Syl.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cami.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Camiola</HI> if ever, now be constant</L>
<L>This is indeed a sutor, whose sweet presence,</L>
<L>Cou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tship and loving language would have stagger'd</L>
<L>The chast <HI>Penelope.</HI> And to increase</L>
<L>The wonder, did not modestie forbid it</L>
<L>I should aske that from him, he sues to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e for;</L>
<L>And yet my reason like a tyran, tells <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e</L>
<L>I must nor give, nor take it.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Sylli, and Bertoldo.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syl.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must tell you

</L>
<L>You loose your labour. 'Tis enough to prove i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</L>
<L><HI>Signior Sylli</HI> came before you, and you know</L>
<L>First come first seru'd yet you <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>all have my countenance</L>
<L>To parley with her and I'<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> take speciall care</L>
<L>That none shal interru<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t you</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="10"/>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are courteous.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come wench wilt thou heare wisedome?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ar.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Yes from you S<SUP>r</SUP>.
<STAGE>Steps aside kisseth her.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>If forcing this sweet favour from your lips</L>
<L>Faire Madam, argue me of too much boldnesse</L>
<L>When you are pleas'd to understand, I take</L>
<L>A parting kisse, if not excuse, at least</L>
<L>'Twill qualifie the offence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cami.</SPEAKER>
<L>A parting kisse S<SUP>r</SUP>.?</L>
<L>What Nation envious of the happinesse</L>
<L>Which Sicilie enjoyes in your sweet presence,</L>
<L>Can buy you from her? or what Climate yeeld</L>
<L>Pleasures transcending those which you injoy here,</L>
<L>Being both belou'd and honor'd. The North-star</L>
<L>And guider of all hearts, and to summe up</L>
<L>Your full accompt of happinesse, in a word,</L>
<L>The brother of the King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe you alone,</L>
<L>And with an unexampl'd cruelty,</L>
<L>Inforce my absence, and deprive me of</L>
<L>Those blessings, which you with a polish'd phrase</L>
<L>Seeme to insinuate, that I doe possesse,</L>
<L>And yet tax me as being guilty of</L>
<L>My wilfull exile? what are Titles to me?</L>
<L>Or popular suffrage? or my neerenesse to</L>
<L>The King in blood? or fruitfull Sicilie,</L>
<L>Though it confess'd no Soveraigne but my selfe,</L>
<L>When you that are the essence of my being,</L>
<L>The anchor of my hopes; the reall substance</L>
<L>Of my felicity, in your disdaine</L>
<L>Turne all to fading and deceiving shaddowes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cami.</SPEAKER>
<L>You tax me without cause.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>You must confesse it.</L>
<L>But answer love with love, and seale the contract</L>
<L>In the vniting of our soules, how gladly</L>
<L>(though now I were in action, and assur'd,</L>
<L><PB REF="10"/>Following my fortune; that plum'd victory</L>
<L>Would make her glorious stand upon my tent)</L>
<L>Would I put off my armour, in my heate</L>
<L>Of conquest, and like <HI>Anthonie</HI> pursue</L>
<L>My <HI>Cleopatra!</HI> will you yet looke on me</L>
<L>With an eye of Favour?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cami.</SPEAKER>
<L>Truth beare witnesse for me,</L>
<L>That in the Iudgement of my Soule, you are</L>
<L>A man so absolute, and circular</L>
<L>In all those wish'd-for rarities, that may take</L>
<L>A Virgin captive, that though at this instant</L>
<L>All sceptr'd Monarches of our Westerne world</L>
<L>Were rivalls with you, and <HI>Camiola</HI> worthy</L>
<L>Of such a competition, you alone</L>
<L>Should weare the ghirlond.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>If so, what diverts</L>
<L>Your Favour from me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Cami<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI></SPEAKER>
<L>No mulct in your selfe,</L>
<L>Or in your person, mind or fortune.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>What then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cami.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Consciousnesse of mine owne wants. Alas S<SUP>r</SUP>.</L>
<L>We are not parallells, but like lines divided</L>
<L>Can nere meete in one Centre, your Birth Sir</L>
<L>(Without addition) were an ample Dowrie</L>
<L>For one of fairer Fortunes, and this shape,</L>
<L>Were you ignoble, far above all value;</L>
<L>To this, so cleare a mind, so furnish'd with</L>
<L>Harmonious faculties, moulded from heaven,</L>
<L>That though you were <HI>Thersites</HI> in your features</L>
<L>Of no descent, and <HI>Irus</HI> in your fortunes,</L>
<L><HI>Vlisses</HI> like you would force all eyes, and eares</L>
<L>To love, but seene, and when heard, wonder at</L>
<L>Your matchlesse story. But all these bound up</L>
<L>Together in one Volume, give me leave</L>
<L>With admiration to looke upon 'em,</L>
<L>But not presume in my owne flattering hopes,</L>
<L>I may or can injoy 'em.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>How you ruine</L>
<L>What you would seeme to build up. I know no</L>
<L>Disparitie betweene vs, you are an heyre</L>
<L><PB REF="11"/>Sprung from a noble familie, faire, rich, young.</L>
<L>And every way my equall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cami.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir excuse me<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>One aerie with proportion, nere discloses</L>
<L>The eagle and the wren tissue, and freese</L>
<L>In the same garment monstrous: But suppose</L>
<L>That what's in you excessive, were diminish'd<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>And my desert supply'd, the strongest bar,</L>
<L>Religion stops our Entrance, you are Sir</L>
<L>A Knight of Malta, by your order bound</L>
<L>To a single life, you cannot marrie me,</L>
<L>And I assure my selfe you are too noble</L>
<L>To seek me (though my frailtie should consent)</L>
<L>In a base path.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>A dispensation Lady</L>
<L>Will easiely absolve me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cami.</SPEAKER>
<L>O take heed S<SUP>r</SUP>.</L>
<L>When, what is vow'd to heaven, is dispens'd with,</L>
<L>To serve our ends on earth, a curse must follow,</L>
<L>And not a blessing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is there no hope left me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor to my selfe, but is a neighbour to</L>
<L>Impossibility: true love should walke</L>
<L>On equall feete, in vs it does not Sir.</L>
<L>But rest assur'd, excepting this, I shall be</L>
<L>Devoted to your service.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>And this is your</L>
<L>Determinate sentence?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cami.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not to be revok'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>Far<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>well then fairest cruell. All thoughts in me</L>
<L>Of Women perish. Let the glorious light</L>
<L>Of noble war extinguish loves dimne taper</L>
<L>That onely lends me light to see my follie;</L>
<L>Honor, be thou my everliving Mistresse,</L>
<L>And sond affection as thy bond-slave serve thee.
<STAGE>Exit Ber:</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>How soone my Sun is set: He being absent,</L>
<L>Never to rise againe! what a fierce battaile</L>
<L>Is fought betweene my passions! me thinkes</L>
<L>We should haue kiss'd at parting.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syl.</SPEAKER>
<L>I perceive<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>He has his answer, now must I step in</L>
<L>To comfort her, you have found, I hope, sweet Lady,</L>
<L>Some diff<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rence betweene a youth of my pitch<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L><PB REF="11"/>And this bug-beare <HI>Bertoldo,</HI> men are men,</L>
<L>The Kings brother is no more: good parts will doe it,</L>
<L>When Titles faile, despaire not, I may be</L>
<L>In time intreated.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be so now to leave mee,</L>
<L>Lights for my chamber, O my heart!
<STAGE>Exeunt <HI>Cami∣ola,</HI> &amp; <HI>Clarinda.</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sylli.</SPEAKER>
<L>She now</L>
<L>I know is going to bed to ruminate</L>
<L>Which way to glut her selfe upon my person,</L>
<L>But for my o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>th-sake I will keepe her hungry,</L>
<L>And to grow full my selfe, I'll straight to supper.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<TRAILER>The end of the first Act.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="2" TYPE="act">
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. II. SCENE. I.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Roberto, Fulgentio, Astutio.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Roberto.</SPEAKER>
<L>EMbarqu'd to night doe you say?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fulgentio.</SPEAKER>
<L>I saw him aboord, Sir,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Rob<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rto.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>And withou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> taking of his leave?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Astut<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>'Twas strange!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Roberto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are we growne so contemptible?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fulgentio.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis far from me Sir, to adde fuell to your anger,</L>
<L>That in your ill opinion of him, burnes</L>
<L>Too hot already, else I should affirme</L>
<L>It was a gros<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e neglect.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Roberto.</SPEAKER>
<L>A wilfull scorne</L>
<L>Of duty and alleageance, you giue it</L>
<L>Too faire a name. But we shall think on't: can you</L>
<L>Guesse what the numbers were that follow'd him</L>
<L>In his desperate action?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Roberto.</SPEAKER>
<L>More then you thinke, Sir.</L>
<L><PB REF="12"/>All ill affected spirits in Palermo,</L>
<L>Or to your government, or person, with</L>
<L>The turbulent sword-men, such whose poverty forc'd 'em</L>
<L>To wish a change, are gone along with him;</L>
<L>Crea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ures devoted to his undertakings</L>
<L>In right or wrong, and to expresse their zeale,</L>
<L>And readinesse to serve him, ere they went</L>
<L>Prophanely tooke the sacrament on their knees,</L>
<L>To live and dye with him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Roberto.</SPEAKER>
<L>O most impious! their loyalty to us forgot?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>F<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lg<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nt.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>I feare so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Astut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vnthankfull as they are.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fulgen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet this deserves not</L>
<L>One troubled thought in you, Sir, with your pardon</L>
<L>I hold that their remove from hence makes more</L>
<L>For your security, then danger.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Rob<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rt.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>True; and as I'll fashion it, they shall feele it too<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L><HI>Astutio,</HI> you shall presently be dispatch'd</L>
<L>With letters writ, and sign'd with our owne hand,</L>
<L>To the Duchesse of <HI>Sie<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>a,</HI> in excuse</L>
<L>Of th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>se <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>orces sent against her. If you spare</L>
<L>An oath to give it credit, that, wee never</L>
<L>Con<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ented to it, swearing for the King,</L>
<L>Though false, it is no perjury.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Astut.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know it.</L>
<L>They are not fit to be state agents, Sir,</L>
<L>That without scruple of their conscience, cannot</L>
<L>Be prodigall in such trifles.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fulgentio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Right, <HI>Astutio.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Roberto.</SPEAKER>
<L>You must beside from us take some instructions</L>
<L>To be imparted, as you judge 'em usefull,</L>
<L>To the Generall Gonzaga. Instantly</L>
<L>Pr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pare you for your journey.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Astut.</SPEAKER>
<L>With the wings</L>
<L>Of loyalty and duty.
<STAGE>Exit <HI>Astutio.</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fulg.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am bold to put your Majesty in mind.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="12"/>
<SPEAKER>Roberto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Of my promise,</L>
<L>And ayds, to further you in your amorous project</L>
<L>To the faire, and rich <HI>Camiola</HI>: there's my ring</L>
<L>Whatever you shall say that I intreat</L>
<L>Or can command by power, I will make good.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fulg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ever your Majesties creature.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Venus</HI> prove propitious to you.
<STAGE>Exit <HI>Robert.</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fulg.</SPEAKER>
<L>All sorts to my wishes:</L>
<L><HI>B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rtoldo</HI> was my hindrance. Hee remov'd,</L>
<L>I now will court her in the conquerous stile,</L>
<L>Come, see, and overcome. Boy.
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Page.</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Page.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, your pleasure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fulg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Haste to <HI>Camiola,</HI> bid her prepare</L>
<L>An entertainment sutable to a fortune,</L>
<L>She could not hope for. Tell her, I vouchsafe</L>
<L>To honour her with a visit</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Page.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis a favour</L>
<L>VVill make her proud.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fulg.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know it</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Page.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am gone, Sir.
<STAGE>Exit <HI>Page.</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fulg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Intreaties fit not me, a man in grace,</L>
<L>May challenge awe, and priviledge by his place,
<STAGE>Exit <HI>Fulgentio.</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. II. SCENE. II.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Sylli, Adorni, Clari<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>da.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ador.</SPEAKER>
<L>SO melancholy say you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Never given</L>
<L>To such retirement.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adorn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can you guesse the ca<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>se?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clar</SPEAKER>
<L>If it hath not it's birth, and being from</L>
<L>The brave <HI>Bertoldo's</HI> absence, I confesse</L>
<L>It is pass'd my apprehension.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="13"/>
<SPEAKER>Sylli.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are wide,</L>
<L>The whole field wide. I in my understanding</L>
<L>Pitty your ignorance: yet if you will</L>
<L>Sweare to conceale it, I will let you know</L>
<L>VVhere her shooe ringes her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I vow, <HI>Signior,</HI></L>
<L>By my virginity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sylli.</SPEAKER>
<L>A perillous oath</L>
<L>In a waiting-woman of fifteene, and is indeed</L>
<L>A Kinde of nothing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adorn.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'll take one of something</L>
<L>If you please to minister it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sylli.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, you shall not sweare,</L>
<L>I had rather take your word, for should you vow:</L>
<L>Damne mee, I'll doe this, you are sure to breake<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adorn.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thanke you <HI>Signior,</HI> but resolve us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sylli.</SPEAKER>
<L>Know then,</L>
<L>Here walkes the cause. She dar<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s not looke upon me,</L>
<L>My beauties are so terrible, and inchaunting,</L>
<L>Shee cannot endure my sight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adorn.</SPEAKER>
<L>There I believe you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sylli.</SPEAKER>
<L>But the time will come, be comforted, when I will</L>
<L>Put off this vizor of unkindnesse to her,</L>
<L>And shew an amorous, and yeelding face:</L>
<L>And vntill then, though <HI>Hercules</HI> himselfe</L>
<L>Desire to see her, hee had better eate</L>
<L>His clubbe then passe her threshold, for I'll be</L>
<L>Her <HI>Cerberus</HI> to guard her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adorn.</SPEAKER>
<L>A good dogge.
<STAGE>enter <HI>Page.</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clar.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVorth twenty porters.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Page.</SPEAKER>
<L>Keepe you open house here?</L>
<L>No groome to attend a Gentleman? O, I spie one.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sylli.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee meanes not mee, I am sure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Page.</SPEAKER>
<L>You sirrha; Sheepes-head,</L>
<L>With a face cut on a cat-sticke, Doe you heare?</L>
<L>You yeoman phewterer, conduct mee to</L>
<L><PB REF="13"/>The Lady of the mansion, or my poniard</L>
<L>Shall disemboge thy soule.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syl.</SPEAKER>
<L>O terrible!</L>
<L>Disemboge! I talke of <HI>Hercules,</HI> and here is one</L>
<L>Bound up in <HI>decimo sext<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pag.</SPEAKER>
<L>Answer wretch.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray you little gentleman, be not so furious,</L>
<L>The Lady keepes her chamber.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pag.</SPEAKER>
<L>And we present?</L>
<L>Sent in an Embassie to her? But here is</L>
<L>Her gentlewoman, Sirrah hold my cloake,</L>
<L>While I take a leape at her lips, do it and neatly;</L>
<L>Or having first tripp'd up thy heeles, I'll make</L>
<L>Thy backe my footstoole.
<STAGE>Page kisses Clar.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syl.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Tamberlaine</HI> in little!</L>
<L>Am I turn'd Turke! what an office am I put to!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lady, gentle youth is indispos'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pag.</SPEAKER>
<L>Though she were dead and buried, only tell her,</L>
<L>The great man in the Court, the brave <HI>Fulgentio</HI></L>
<L>Descends to v<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>it her, and it will raise her</L>
<L>Out of the grave for joy.
<STAGE>Enter Fulgen.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here comes another!</L>
<L>The divell I feare in his holi-day clothes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pag.</SPEAKER>
<L>So soone,</L>
<L>My part is at an end then, cover my shoulders,</L>
<L>When I grow great, thou shalt serve me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fulgen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you Sirrah</L>
<L>An <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mplement of the house?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Su<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e he will make</L>
<L>A joynes-stoole of me!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fulgen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or if you belong</L>
<L>To the Lady of the place, command her hither.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adorn.</SPEAKER>
<L>I do not weare her livery, yet acknowledge</L>
<L>A duty to her. And as little bound</L>
<L>To serve your peremptorie will, as she is</L>
<L>To obey your summons. 'Twill become you Sir,</L>
<L><PB REF="14"/>To waite her leisurue, then her pleasure knowne</L>
<L>You may present your duty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fulgen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Duty? Slave,</L>
<L>I'll teach you manners.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ador.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am past learning, make not</L>
<L>A tumult in the house.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fulgen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall I be brau'd thu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syl.</SPEAKER>
<L>O I am dead! and now I sowne.
<STAGE><HI>They dr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/> fals on his face.</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clarin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Helpe, murther!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pag.</SPEAKER>
<L>Recover Sirrah, the Ladies here.
<STAGE>Enter Cam.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay then</L>
<L>I am alive againe, and I'll be valiant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>What insolence is this? <HI>Adorni,</HI> hold,</L>
<L>Hold I command you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fulgen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sawcy groome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cami.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not so Sir,</L>
<L>However in his life, he had dependance</L>
<L>Vpon my Father, He is a gentleman</L>
<L>As well borne as your selfe. Put on your hat.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fulgen.</SPEAKER>
<L>In my presence, without leaue?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syl.</SPEAKER>
<L>He has mine Madam?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I must tell you Sir, and in plaine language,</L>
<L>How e'r your glittring out-side promise gentry,</L>
<L>The rudenesse of your carriage and behaviour</L>
<L>Speakes you a couser thing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syl.</SPEAKER>
<L>She meanes a clowne S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</L>
<L>I am her interpreter for want of a better.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am a Queene in mine owne house, nor must you</L>
<L>Expect an Empire here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sure I must love her</L>
<L>Before the day, the prettie Soule's so valiant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cami.</SPEAKER>
<L>What are you? and what would you with me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fulgen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Proud one,</L>
<L>When you know what I am, and what I came for,</L>
<L>And may on your submission proceed <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o,</L>
<L>You in your reason must repent the coursenesse</L>
<L>Of my entertain<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ment.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cami.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why fine man? what are you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fulgen.</SPEAKER>
<L>A kinsman of the Kings.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>I cry you mercy,</L>
<L>For his sake, not your owne. But grant you are so,</L>
<L>'Tis not impossible, but a king may have</L>
<L>A foole to his kinsman, no way meaning you Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="14"/>
<SPEAKER>Fulgen.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have heard of <HI>Fulgen.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Long since Sir,</L>
<L>A suit-broker in Court. He has the worst</L>
<L>Report among good men I ever heard of,</L>
<L>For briberie and extortion. In their prayers</L>
<L>Widdowes and Orphans curse him for a canker,</L>
<L>And caterpill<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r in the state. I hope Sir,</L>
<L>You are not the man, much lesse imploy'd by him</L>
<L>As a smocke-agent to me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fulgen.</SPEAKER>
<L>I reply not</L>
<L>As you deserve, being assur'd you know me,</L>
<L>Pretending ignorance of my person, onely</L>
<L>To give me a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ast of your wit; 'Tis well and courtly,</L>
<L>I like a sharpe wit well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syl.</SPEAKER>
<L>I cannot indure it,</L>
<L>Nor any of the <HI>Sylli<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fulgen.</SPEAKER>
<L>More I know too,</L>
<L>This harsh induction must serve as a foyle</L>
<L>To the well tun'd observance and respect,</L>
<L>You will hereafter pay me, being made</L>
<L>Familiar with my credit with the King,</L>
<L>And that, containe your joy, I daine to love you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Love me? I am not rap'd with't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ful.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hear't againe.</L>
<L>I love you honestly, now you admire me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe indeed, it being a word so seldome</L>
<L>Heard from a courtiers mouth. But pray you deale plainly,</L>
<L>Since you finde me simple. what might be the motives</L>
<L>Inducing you to leave the freedome of</L>
<L>A batchelers life, on your so<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t necke to weare</L>
<L>The stubborne yoake of marriage? And of all</L>
<L>The beauties in <HI>Palerm<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</HI> to choose me,</L>
<L>Poore me? that is the maine point you must treate of.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ful.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why I will tell you. Of a little thing</L>
<L>You are a prettle peate, indifferenly faire too;</L>
<L>And like a new-rigg'd shippe both tite, and y'are</L>
<L>Well truss'd to beare. Virgins of Gyant size</L>
<L>Are <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>luggards at the sport: but for my pleasure,</L>
<L>Give me a near well <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>imbred gamster like you,</L>
<L>S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ch neede no sp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rres, the quickenes of your eye</L>
<L>Assures an active spirit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are pleasant Sir,</L>
<L><PB REF="15"/>Yet I presume, that there was one thing in me</L>
<L>Vnmention'd yet, that tooke you more then all</L>
<L>Those parts you have remembred.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fulgen.</SPEAKER>
<L>What?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>My wealth Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fulgen.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are i'the right, without that beautie is</L>
<L>A flower worne in the morning, at night trod on<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>But beautie, youth, and fortune meeting in you,</L>
<L>I will vouchsafe to marrie you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>You speake well,</L>
<L>And in returne excuse me Sir, if I</L>
<L>Deliver reasons why upon no tearmes</L>
<L>I'll marrie you, I fable not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syl.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am glad</L>
<L>To heare this, I began to have an ague.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fulgen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> your wise reasons.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Such as they are, pray you take them.</L>
<L>First I am doubtfull whether you are a man,</L>
<L>Since for your shape trimmd up in a Ladies dressing</L>
<L>You might passe for a woman: now I love</L>
<L>To deale on certainties. And for the fairenes</L>
<L>Of your complexion, which you thinke will take me,</L>
<L>The colour I must tell you in a man</L>
<L>Is weake and fa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nt, and never will hold out</L>
<L>If put to labour, giue me the lovely browne.</L>
<L>A thicke curl'd hayre of the same dye; broad shoulders,</L>
<L>A brawnie arme full of veines, a legge without</L>
<L>An artificiall calfe, I suspect yours,</L>
<L>But let that passe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syl.</SPEAKER>
<L>She meanes me all this while,</L>
<L>For I have every one of those good parts,</L>
<L>O <HI>Sylli,</HI> fortunate <HI>Sylli</HI>!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cami.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are mov'd Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fulgen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fie no, go on.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cami.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then as you are a courtier;</L>
<L>A gr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>c'd one too, I feare you have beene too forward,</L>
<L>And so much for your person. Rich you are,</L>
<L>Divelish rich, as 'tis reported, and sur<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> have</L>
<L>The aides of Satans little fiends to get it,</L>
<L>And what is got upon his backe, must be</L>
<L>Spent you know where, the proverb's sta'e, one word more</L>
<L>And I have done.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fulgen.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'll <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ase you of the trouble,</L>
<L><PB REF="15"/>Coy, and disdainefull.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Save me, or else he'll beat me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fulg.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, your owne folly shall, and since you put mee</L>
<L>To my last charme, look upon this, and tremble.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>At the sight of a faire ring? the Kings, I take it.</L>
<L>I have seene him weare the like; if he hath sent it
<STAGE>Shewes the Kings ring.</STAGE></L>
<L>as a favour to mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fulg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, 'tis verie likely,</L>
<L>His dying mothers gift, priz'd at his crowne,</L>
<L>By this hee does command you to be mine,</L>
<L>By his gift you are so: you may yet redeme all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are in a wrong account still. Though the King may</L>
<L>Dispose of my life and goods, my mind's mine owne,</L>
<L>And shall be never yours. The King (Heaven blesse him)</L>
<L>Is good and gracious, and being in himselfe</L>
<L>Abstemious from base and goatish loosenesse,</L>
<L>Will not compell against their wills, cha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>te Madiens,</L>
<L>To dance in his magnious circles. I believe</L>
<L>Forgetting it, when he washed his hands, you stole it</L>
<L>With an intent to awe me. But you are coozin'd,</L>
<L>I am still my selfe, and will be.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fulg.</SPEAKER>
<L>A proud haggard,</L>
<L>And not to be reclaim'd, which of your groomes,</L>
<L>Your coach-man, foole, or foot-man, ministers</L>
<L>Night phisicque to you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are soule-mouth'd,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fulg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Much fairer</L>
<L>Then thy blacke soule, and so I will proclaime thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Were I a man, thou durst not speake this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fulg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heav'n</L>
<L>So prosper mee, as I resolve to doe it</L>
<L>To a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l men, and in every place, scorn'd by</L>
<L>A tit of pen-pence?
<STAGE>Exit <HI>Fulge<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tio</HI> and his <HI>Page.</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sylli.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now I begin to be valiant</L>
<L>Nay, I will draw my sword. O for a butche<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>!</L>
<L>Doe a friends part, pray you carry him the length of't.</L>
<L>I give him three yeeres, and a day to match my <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oledo,</L>
<L><PB REF="16"/>And then wee'll fight like Dragons.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adorn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray have patience.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>I may live to have vengeance; My <HI>Bertoldo</HI></L>
<L>Would not have heard this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adorn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Pray you spare</L>
<L>Your language; Pre'thee foole, and make me merry:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sylli.</SPEAKER>
<L>That is my Office ever.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adorn.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must doe,</L>
<L>Not talke, this glorious gallant shall heare from me.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. II. SCENE. III.</HEAD>
<STAGE>The chambers discharg'd: A flourish, as to an as∣sault. <HI>Gonzaga, Pierio, Roderigo, Iacomo,</HI> Souldiers<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gonzaga.</SPEAKER>
<L>IS the breach made assaultable?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pierio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, and the moate</L>
<L>Fill'd up, the Canonier hath don his parts,</L>
<L>We may enter six a brest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Roderig.</SPEAKER>
<L>There's not a man</L>
<L>Dares <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hew himselfe upon the wall<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Facom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Deseate not</L>
<L>The souldiers hop'd-for spoile.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pier.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you, Sir,</L>
<L>Delay the assault, and the Citie be given up</L>
<L>To your discretion, you in honour cannot</L>
<L>Vse the extremitie of warre, but in</L>
<L>Compassion to 'em, you to us prove cruell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iacom.</SPEAKER>
<L>And an enemy to your selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Roder.</SPEAKER>
<L>A hindrance to</L>
<L>The brave revenge you have vow'd</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Gonz<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Temper your heat,</L>
<L>And loose not by too sudden rashnesse, tha</L>
<L>Which be but patient, will be offer'd to you</L>
<L><PB REF="16"/>Security ushers ruine; proud contempt</L>
<L>Of an enemy three parts vanquish'd with desire</L>
<L>And greedinesse of spoyle, have often wrested</L>
<L>A certaine victory from the Conquerours gripe.</L>
<L>Discretion is the tutor of the warre,</L>
<L>Valour the pupill, and when we command</L>
<L>With lenity and your directions follow'd</L>
<L>With cheerefulnesse, a prosperous end must crowne</L>
<L>Our workes well undertaken.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Roderig.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ours are finish'd</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pier.</SPEAKER>
<L>If we make use of fortune.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gonz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Her false smiles</L>
<L>Deprive you of your judgements. The condition</L>
<L>Of our affaires exacts a double care,</L>
<L>And like bifronted <HI>Ianus,</HI> wee must looke</L>
<L>Backward, as forwards: though a flattering calme</L>
<L>Bids us urge on, a sudden tempest rais'd,</L>
<L>Not fear'd, much lesse expected, in our reere</L>
<L>May foully fall upon us, and distract us</L>
<L>To our confusion. Our scout! what brings
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Scout.</HI></STAGE></L>
<L>Thy ghastly lookes, and sudden speede?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scout.</SPEAKER>
<L>Th'assurance</L>
<L>Of a new enemy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gonz.</SPEAKER>
<L>This I fore-saw<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> and fear'd.</L>
<L>What are they, know it thou?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scout.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are by their colours</L>
<L>Sicilians, brav<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ly mounted, and the brightne<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/></L>
<L>Of their rich armours doubly guilded with</L>
<L>Reflection of the Sunne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gonz.</SPEAKER>
<L>From Sicilie?</L>
<L>The King in leagu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>! no warr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> proclaimed <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> 'tis foule<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>But this must be prevented, not disputed</L>
<L>Ha, how is this? your Estridge plumes, that but</L>
<L>E'n now like quills of Porcupines seem'd to threaten</L>
<L>The sta<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>es, drop at the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>umor of a sh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>wer?</L>
<L>And like to captive colours sweep the earth?</L>
<L><PB REF="17"/>Beare up, but in great dangers, greater mindes</L>
<L>Are neuer proud. Shall a few loose troopes untrain'd</L>
<L>But in a customary oftentatiou,</L>
<L>P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>sented as a sacrifice to your valours</L>
<L>Cause a dejection in you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pier.</SPEAKER>
<L>No dejection.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L>However startl'd, where you lead, we'll follow</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gon.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis bravely said. We will not stay their charge,</L>
<L>But meet'<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m man to man, and horse to horse.</L>
<L><HI>Pierio</HI> in our absence hold our place,</L>
<L>And with our foot-men, and those sickely troupes,</L>
<L>Prevent a sally. I in mine owne person,</L>
<L>With part of the cavallery, will bid,</L>
<L>These hunters welcome to a bloody breakefast,</L>
<L>But I lose time.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pier.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'll to my charge.
<STAGE>Exit <HI>Pierio.</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gonz.</SPEAKER>
<L>And wee</L>
<L>To ours. I'll bring you on.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iacom.</SPEAKER>
<L>If we come off</L>
<L>It is not amisse, if not, my state is settl'd
<STAGE>Exeunt, alarme.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. II. SCENE. IIII.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Ferdinand. Druso. Livio.</HI> above.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Far.</SPEAKER>
<L>NO aydes from <HI>Sicilie?</HI> Hath hope forsooke us?</L>
<L>And that vaine comfort to affliction, pitty</L>
<L>By our vow'd friend deni'd us? we can nor live,</L>
<L>Nor die with honor: like beasts in a toyle</L>
<L>Wee waite the leasure of the bloody hunter,</L>
<L>Who is not so farre reconcil'd u<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>to us,</L>
<L>As in one death to give a period</L>
<L>To our calamities, but in delaying</L>
<L>The fate wee cannot flie from, starv'd with wants,</L>
<L>Wee die this night to live againe to morrow,</L>
<L><PB REF="17"/>And suffer greater torments.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Druso.</SPEAKER>
<L>There is not</L>
<L>Three dayes provision for every soldiour,</L>
<L>At an ounce of bread a day left in the Citty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Liv.</SPEAKER>
<L>To dye the beggers death with hunger, made</L>
<L>Anatom es while we live, cannot but cracke</L>
<L>Our heart-strings with vexation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would they would breake,</L>
<L>Breake altogether, how willingly like <HI>Cato</HI></L>
<L>Could I teare out my bowells, rather then</L>
<L>Looke on the conquerors insulting face,</L>
<L>But that religion, and the horrid dreame</L>
<L>To be suffer'd in the other world denyes it. <STAGE>Enter <HI>Souldier.</HI></STAGE></L>
<L>What newes with thee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soul.</SPEAKER>
<L>From the turret of the fort</L>
<L>By the rising clouds of dust, through which, like lightning</L>
<L>The spendor of bright armes sometimes brake through,</L>
<L>I did descry some forces making towards us,</L>
<L>And from the campe, as emulous of their glory,</L>
<L>The Generall, (for I know him by his horse)</L>
<L>Tnd bravely seconded. encounter'd 'em.</L>
<L>Their greetings were to rough for friends, their swords</L>
<L>And not their tongues exchanging courtesies.</L>
<L>By this the maine Battalias are joyn'd,</L>
<L>And if you please to be spectators of</L>
<L>The horrid issue, I will bring you where</L>
<L>As in a Theater you may see their fates</L>
<L>In purple gore presented.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heaven. If yet</L>
<L>Thou art appeas'd for my wrong done to <HI>Aurelia,</HI></L>
<L>Take pitty of my miseries. Lead the way, friend.</L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="scene">
<PB REF="18"/>
<HEAD>ACT. II. SCENE. V. A long charge after a Flourish for Victory.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Gonzaga. Iacomo. Roderigo wounded. Bertoldo. Gasparo. Anthonio Prisoners.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gonz.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVE have 'em yet, though they cost vs deer. This was</L>
<L>Charg'd home, and bravely follow'd. Be to your¦selves</L>
<L>True mirrors to each others worth, and looking</L>
<L>W<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>th noble Emulation on his wounds,</L>
<L>(<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he glorious Livery of t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>iumphant war)
<STAGE>To Iacomo and Roderigo.</STAGE></L>
<L>Imagine these with equall grace appeare</L>
<L>Vpon your selfe. The bloody <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>wsat you have suffer'd</L>
<L>In this laborious, nay toylesome harvest,</L>
<L>Yeelds a rich crop of conquest, and the spoyle</L>
<L>Most precious balsum to a souldies hu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>s</L>
<L>Will <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ase and cure 'em. Let me looke up<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n
<STAGE>To Gasparo and Anthon.</STAGE></L>
<L>T<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e prisones faces. O how much transform'd</L>
<L>From what they were. O <HI>Mars</HI>! were the<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e toyes fashion'd</L>
<L>To undergoe the burthen of thy service?</L>
<L>The weight of their defe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sive armor bruiz'd</L>
<L>Their weak, effe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>inate limbes, and would have forc'd'em</L>
<L>In a hot day without a blow to yeeld.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Antho.</SPEAKER>
<L>This insultation shewes not manly in you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Go<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>z.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>To men I had for<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>orne it, you are women,</L>
<L>Or at the best loose carpet knights, what fury</L>
<L>Seduc'd you to exchange your <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ase in Court</L>
<L>For labour in the field? Perhaps you thought.</L>
<L>To charge through dust, and blood, an armed foe,</L>
<L>Was but like gracefull running at the ring</L>
<L>For a want on mistrisse glove, and the encounter</L>
<L>A soft impression on her lips. But you</L>
<L>A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e gawdi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> butterflies, and I wrong my selfe</L>
<L><PB REF="18"/>In parling with you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gaspa.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Vae victis.</HI> Now we prove it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L>But here's one fashion'd in another mould,</L>
<L>And made of tougher mettall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gonz.</SPEAKER>
<L>True, I owe him</L>
<L>For this wound bravely given.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>O that mountaines</L>
<L>Were heap'd upon me, that I might expire</L>
<L>A wretch no more remembred.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gonz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Look up S<SUP>r</SUP>.</L>
<L>To be orecome deserves no shame. If you</L>
<L>Had falne ingloriously, or could accuse</L>
<L>Your want of courage in resistance, 'twere</L>
<L>To be lamented: But since you perform'd</L>
<L>As much as could be hop'd for from a man,</L>
<L>(Fortune his enemy) you wrong your selfe</L>
<L>In this direction<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> I am honor'd in</L>
<L>My victory ore you: but to have these</L>
<L>My prisoners, is in my true judgement rather,</L>
<L>Captivitie then a triumph; you shall finde</L>
<L>Faire quarter from me, and your many wounds</L>
<L>(Which I hope are not mortall) with such care</L>
<L>Lookt to, aud cur'd, as if your nearest friend</L>
<L>Attended on you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>When you know me better,</L>
<L>You will make void this promise: Can you call me</L>
<L>Into your memory.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Go<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>z.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>The brave <HI>Bertoldo!</HI></L>
<L>A brother of our order! By Saint <HI>Iohn,</HI></L>
<L>(our holy patron) I am more amaz'd,</L>
<L>Nay thunderstrooke, with thy Apostacy,</L>
<L>And praecipice from the most solemne vowes</L>
<L>Made vnto heaven, when this, the glorious badge</L>
<L>Of our redeemer was conferr'd upon thee,</L>
<L>By the great master, then if I had seene</L>
<L>A reprobate Iew, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n Atheist, Turke, or Tartar</L>
<L>Bap<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>z'd in our religion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>This I look'd for,</L>
<L>And am resolv'd to suffer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fellow Souldiers<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L><PB REF="19"/>Behold this man, and taught by his example</L>
<L>Know that 'tis safer far to play with lightning,</L>
<L>Then trifle in things sacred. In my rag
<STAGE><HI>weepes<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI></STAGE></L>
<L>I shed these at the funerall of his vertue,</L>
<L>Faith and r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ligion; why I will tell you</L>
<L>He was a gentleman, so trayn'd up, and fashion'd</L>
<L>For noble uses, and his youth did promise</L>
<L>Such c<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rt<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>inties, more then hopes, of great atchievments,</L>
<L>As if the Christian world had stood oppos'd</L>
<L>Against the Ottoman race to trie the fortune</L>
<L>Of one encounter, this <HI>Bertoldo</HI> had beene</L>
<L>For his knoweldge to direct, and matchles courage</L>
<L>To execute, without a rivall, by</L>
<L>The votes of good men chosen generall,</L>
<L>As the prime souldier, and most deserving,</L>
<L>Of all that weare the crosse, which now in justice</L>
<L>I thus teare from him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me dye with it,</L>
<L>Vpon my breast.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gouz.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, by this thou wer't sworne</L>
<L>On all occasions, as a knight to guard</L>
<L>Weake Ladies from oppression, and never</L>
<L>To draw thy sword against 'em, where as thou</L>
<L>In hope of gaine or glory, when a Princesse</L>
<L>And such a Princesse as <HI>Aurelia</HI> is,</L>
<L>Was dispossess'd by violence, of what was</L>
<L>Her true inheritance, against thine oth,</L>
<L>Hast to thy uttermost labour'd to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>phold</L>
<L>Her falling enemie. But thou shalt pay</L>
<L>A heavy forfeiture, and learne too la<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e,</L>
<L>Valour, imploy'd in an ill quarrell, turnes</L>
<L>To cowardice, and vertve then puts on</L>
<L>Foule vices vizard. This is that which cancells</L>
<L>All friendsh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ps bands between vs Beare 'em off</L>
<L>I will heare no replie. And let the ransome</L>
<L><PB REF="19"/>Of these, for they are yours, be highly rated.</L>
<L>In this I doe but right, and let it be</L>
<L>Stil'd justice, and not wilfull cruelty.
<STAGE><HI>Ex<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/>.</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<TRAILER>The end of the second Act.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="3" TYPE="act">
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. III. SCENE. I.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Gonzaga, Astutio, Roderigo, Iacomo.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gonzága.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVHat I have done S<SUP>r</SUP> by the law of arme<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>I can, and will make good.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Ast<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>I have no commission</L>
<L>To expostulate the act. These letters speake</L>
<L>The King my Masters love to you, and his</L>
<L>vow'd service to the Duchesse, on who<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e person</L>
<L>I am to giue attendance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gonz.</SPEAKER>
<L>At this instant.</L>
<L>Shee's at <HI>Pienza</HI>; you may sp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re the trouble</L>
<L>Of riding thither: I have advertized her</L>
<L>Of our successe, and on what humble termes</L>
<L><HI>Siena</HI> stands: though presently I can</L>
<L>Possesse it I deferre it, that shee may</L>
<L>Enter her owne, and as she please dispose of</L>
<L>The prisoners and the spoyle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Astut.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thanke you, Sir.</L>
<L>I'the meane time, if I may have your licence,</L>
<L>I have a Nephew, and one once my ward</L>
<L>For whose liberties and ransomes, I would gladly</L>
<L>Make composition.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Go<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>z.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>They are, as I take it,</L>
<L>Call'd <HI>Gasparo,</HI> and <HI>Anthonio,</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Astut.</SPEAKER>
<L>The same, Sir,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="20"/>
<SPEAKER>Gonz.</SPEAKER>
<L>For them you must treat with these, but for <HI>Bertoldo,</HI></L>
<L>He is mine owne, if the King will ransom him,</L>
<L>He payes downe fifty thousand crownes, if not</L>
<L>He liues, and dies my slave,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>As<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ut.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Pray you a word.</L>
<L>The King will rather thanke you <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>taine him,</L>
<L>Then give one crowne to free him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gonz.</SPEAKER>
<L>At his pleasure.</L>
<L>I'll send the p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>oners under guard<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> my businesse</L>
<L>Ca<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> me another way.
<STAGE>Exit <HI>Gonzaga.</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Astut.</SPEAKER>
<L>My service waits you,</L>
<L>Now Gentlemen do not deale like Merchants with me,</L>
<L>But noble Captaines, you know in great mindes</L>
<L><HI>Posse, &amp; nolle no<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>le.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray you speake</L>
<L>Our language.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iacom.</SPEAKER>
<L>I finde not in my commission</L>
<L>An officers bound to speake or understand</L>
<L>More then his Mother tongue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Roder.</SPEAKER>
<L>If hee speake that</L>
<L>After midnight 'tis remarkable.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Astu.</SPEAKER>
<L>In plaine termes then,</L>
<L><HI>Anthonio</HI> is your prisoner. <HI>Gasparo</HI> yours</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iacom.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are i'the right.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Astu.</SPEAKER>
<L>At what summe doe you rate</L>
<L>Their severall ransomes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must make my market</L>
<L>As the commodity cost me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Astut.</SPEAKER>
<L>As it cost you?</L>
<L>You did not buy your Captainship? your desert</L>
<L>I hope advanc'd you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L>How? it well appeares</L>
<L>You are no souldier. Desert in these daies?</L>
<L>Desert may make a Serieant to a Colonel,</L>
<L>And it may hinder him from rising higher,</L>
<L>But if it ever get a company,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> company, pray you marke mee, without money</L>
<L><PB REF="20"/>Or private seruice done for the Generalls Mistresse,</L>
<L>With a commendatory Epistle from her,</L>
<L>I will turne Lansprizadoe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iacom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray you observe, Sir:</L>
<L>I serv'd two prenticeships, just foureteene yeere,</L>
<L>Trayling the puissant pike; and halfe so long</L>
<L>Had the right hand file, and I fought well, 'twas said too:</L>
<L>But I might have serv'd, and fought, and serv'd ti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>doomsday</L>
<L>And never have carryed a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lagge, but for the legacy</L>
<L>A buxsome widdow of threescore, bequeath'd mee,</L>
<L>And that too, my backe knowes, I labour hard for,</L>
<L>But was better paid.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Astut.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are merry with your selves</L>
<L>But this is from the purpose.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Roder.</SPEAKER>
<L>To the point then.</L>
<L>Prisoners are not tane every day, and when</L>
<L>We have 'em we must make the best use of 'em.</L>
<L>Our pay is little to the part we should beare,</L>
<L>And that so long a comming, that 'tis spent</L>
<L>Before we have it, and hardly wipes off scores</L>
<L>At the Taverne, and the Ordinary.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iacom.</SPEAKER>
<L>You may adde to</L>
<L>Our sport tooke up on trust.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oder.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Peace, thou smo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ke vermin.</L>
<L>Discover commanders, secrets! In a word, Sir,</L>
<L>We have requir'd, and find our prisoners rich:</L>
<L>Two thousand crownes a piece, our companies cost vs,</L>
<L>And so much each of us will have, and that</L>
<L>In present pay.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iacom.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is too little; yet</L>
<L>Since you haue said the word, I am content,</L>
<L>But will not goe a gazet lesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Astut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Since you are not</L>
<L>To be brought lower, there is no evading<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>I'll be your pay-master.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Roder.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee desire no better.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="21"/>
<SPEAKER>Astnt.</SPEAKER>
<L>But not a word of what's agreed between us,</L>
<L>'Till I have schoold my gallants.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iacom.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am dumb, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter a guard: <HI>Bertoldo, Anthonio, Gaspero,</HI> in yrons.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bert.</SPEAKER>
<L>And where remov'd now? hath the Tyrant found out</L>
<L>Worse usage for us?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Antho.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVorse it cannot be.</L>
<L>My grewhound has fresh straw, and scraps in his kennell,</L>
<L>But wee have neyther.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did I ever thinke</L>
<L>To weare such garters on silke stockings? or</L>
<L>That my too curious appetite, that turn'd</L>
<L>At the sight of godwits, pheasant, partidge, quases</L>
<L>Larkes, wood-cocks, caluerd sammon, as course diet,</L>
<L>Would leape at a mouldy crust?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Antho.</SPEAKER>
<L>And goe without it;</L>
<L>So of<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> as I doe, O how haue I jeer'd</L>
<L>The City entertainment. A huge shoulder</L>
<L>Of glorious fat Ramme Mutton, seconded</L>
<L>With a paire of taine cats, or conies, a crabbe tart</L>
<L>With a worthy loyne of veale, and valiant Capon,</L>
<L>Mortifi'd to grow tender. These I scorn'd</L>
<L>From their plentifull horne of abu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>dance, though invited:</L>
<L>But now I could carry my owne stoole to a tripe,</L>
<L>And call their chitterlings charity, and blesse the founder.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bertol.</SPEAKER>
<L>O that I were no farther sensible</L>
<L>Of my miseries then you are! you like beasts</L>
<L>F<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ele onely stings of hunge<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, and complaine not</L>
<L>But when you are empty: but your narrow soules</L>
<L>(If you have any) cannot comprehend</L>
<L>How insupportable the torments are,</L>
<L>Which a free and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oble soule made capti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e, suffers:</L>
<L>Most miserable men! and what am I then,</L>
<L>That enuy you? Fetters though made of gold,</L>
<L><PB REF="21"/>Expresse base thraldome and all delicates</L>
<L>Prepar'd by Median cookes for Epicures,</L>
<L>When not our owne, are bitter quilts fill'd high</L>
<L>With gossamire and roses, cannot yeeld</L>
<L>The body soft repose, the mind kep't waking</L>
<L>With anguish and affliction.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Astut.</SPEAKER>
<L>My good Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is no time, nor place for flaterry Sir,</L>
<L>Pray you stile me as I am, a wretch forsaken</L>
<L>Of the world, as my selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Astut.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would it were</L>
<L>In me to helpe you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>I if that you want power Sir,</L>
<L>Lip comfort cannot cure me, pray you leave mee</L>
<L>To mine owne private thoughts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Astu.</SPEAKER>
<L>My valiant Nephew!
<STAGE>walkes by.</STAGE></L>
<L>And my more then warlike-ward! I am glad to see you</L>
<L>After your glorious conquests. Are these chaines</L>
<L>Rewardee for your good service? If they are</L>
<L>You should weare 'em on your ne<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ks (since they are massie)</L>
<L>Like Aldermen of the war.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Antho.</SPEAKER>
<L>You jeere us to!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good uncle name not (as you are a man of honor)</L>
<L>That fatall word of war, the very sounde of't</L>
<L>Is more dreadfull then a Cannon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Antho.</SPEAKER>
<L>But redeeme us</L>
<L>From this Captivitie, and I'll vow hereafter</L>
<L>Never to weare a sword, or cut my meate</L>
<L>With a knife, that has an edge or point. I'll starve first</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will crie broome or cats meate in <HI>Pal<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rm<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI>;</L>
<L>Turne porter, carrie burthens; any thing,</L>
<L>Rather then live a souldier.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Astut.</SPEAKER>
<L>This should have</L>
<L>Beene thought upon before. At what price thinke you</L>
<L>Your two wise heads are rated?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Antho.</SPEAKER>
<L>A calves head is</L>
<L>More worth then mine, I am sure it had more braines in't</L>
<L><PB REF="22"/>Or I had never come here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Roder.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I will eate it</L>
<L>With bacon, if I have not speedy ransome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>And a little garlick too, for your own sake Sir</L>
<L>I will boyle in your stomacke else.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beware of mine</L>
<L>Or the hornes may choake you. I am married Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Antho.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall have my row of houses neare the pallace</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<L>And my vil<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>a all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Antho.</SPEAKER>
<L>All that we have.
<STAGE>To Astutio.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Astut<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Well, have more wit hereafter</L>
<L>For this time you are ransom'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iacom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Off with their irons.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do do<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> If you are ours again, you know your price.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Antho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray you dispatch us: I shall nere beleeve</L>
<L>I am a freeman, till I set my foote</L>
<L>In Sicilie agen, and drinke <HI>Palermo,</HI></L>
<L>And in <HI>Palermo</HI> too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Astut.</SPEAKER>
<L>The wind fits faire,</L>
<L>You shall aboord to night with the rising Sun</L>
<L>You may touch upon the coast. But take your leaves</L>
<L>Of the late Generall first.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will be briefe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Antho.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I, my lord heaven keepe you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yours to use</L>
<L>In the way of peace, but as your souldiers never.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Antho.</SPEAKER>
<L>A pox of war no more of war.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>Have you
<STAGE><HI>Excun<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Roderig. Iaco. Anthon<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>. Gaspar<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</HI></STAGE></L>
<L>Authority to loose their bonds, yet leave</L>
<L>The brother of your King, whose worth disdaines</L>
<L>Comparison with such as these, in irons?</L>
<L>If ransome may redeeme them, I have landes,</L>
<L>A patrimony of mine owne assign'd me,</L>
<L>By my deceased sire to satisfie</L>
<L>What ere can be demanded for my freedome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Astut.</SPEAKER>
<L>I wish you had Sir, but the king who yeelds<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L><PB REF="22"/>No reason for his will, in his displeasure</L>
<L>Hath seas'd on all you had; nor will <HI>Gonzaga,</HI></L>
<L>Whose prisoner now you are, accept of lesse</L>
<L>Then fiftie thousand crownes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>I finde it now</L>
<L>That misery nere comes alone. But grant</L>
<L>The King is yet inexorable, time</L>
<L>May worke him to a feeling of my sufferings.</L>
<L>I have friends, that swore their lives and fortunes were</L>
<L>At my devotion, and among the rest</L>
<L>Your selfe my lord, when forfeited to the Law</L>
<L>For a foule murther, and in cold blood done,</L>
<L>I made your life my gift, and reconcil'd you</L>
<L>To this incensed king, and got your pardon.</L>
<L>Beware ingratitude. I know you are rich</L>
<L>And may pay downe the Sum.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Astut.</SPEAKER>
<L>I might my lord,</L>
<L>But pardon me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>And will <HI>Astutio</HI> prove then</L>
<L>To please a passionate man, the kings no more,</L>
<L>False to his maker and his reason? which</L>
<L>Commandes more then I aske? ô summer friendship,</L>
<L>Whose flattering leaves that shaddowed us in</L>
<L>Our prosperity, with the least gust drop off</L>
<L>In th'Autumne of adversity! How like</L>
<L>A prison is to a grave! when dead we are</L>
<L>With solemne Pompe brought thither, and our heires,</L>
<L>(Masking their joy in false dissembled teares)</L>
<L>Weepe ore the hearse, but earth no sooner covers</L>
<L>The earth brought thither, but they turne away</L>
<L>With inward smiles, the dead no more remembred.</L>
<L>So enter'd in a prison.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Astut.</SPEAKER>
<L>My occasions</L>
<L>Command me hence my lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray you leave me, doe;</L>
<L>And tell the cruell king, that I will weare</L>
<L>The<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>etters 'till my flesh, and they are one</L>
<L><PB REF="23"/>Incorporated substance. In my selfe,</L>
<L>As in a glasse, I'll looke on humane frailty,</L>
<L>And curse the height of Royall blood: since I</L>
<L>In being borne neare to <HI>Iove,</HI> am neare his thunder.</L>
<L>Cedars once shaken with a storme, their owne
<STAGE>Exit Astutio.</STAGE></L>
<L>Waight gr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> their rootes out. Le<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d me where you please;</L>
<L>I am his, not fortunes martyr, and will dye</L>
<L>The great example of his cruelty.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit cum suis.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. III. SCENE. II.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Adorni.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adorn.</SPEAKER>
<L>HE undergoes my challenge, and contemnes it,</L>
<L>And threatens me with the late Edict made</L>
<L>'Gainst duellists, then altar cowards flie to.</L>
<L>But I that am ingag'd, and nourish in me</L>
<L>A higher aime then faire <HI>Camiola</HI> dreames of,</L>
<L>Must not sit down thus. In the court I dare not</L>
<L>Attempt him; and in publike, hee's so guarded</L>
<L>With a heard of Parasites, Clients, fooles and sutors,</L>
<L>That a musket cannot reach him, my designes</L>
<L>Admit of no delay. This is her birth-day,</L>
<L>Which with a fit and due solemnitie</L>
<L><HI>C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>miola</HI> celebrates; and on it, all such</L>
<L>As love or serve her, usually present</L>
<L>A tributary duty. I'll have something</L>
<L>To give, if my intelligence prove true,</L>
<L>Shall find acceptance. I am told, neare this grove</L>
<L><HI>Fulgentio</HI> very morning makes his makets</L>
<L>With his petitioners. I may present him</L>
<L>With a sharpe petition. H<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, 'tis he<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> my sate</L>
<L>Be ever bless'd for't.
<STAGE>Exit Fulgen.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fulgen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Command such as waite me</L>
<L><PB REF="23"/>Not to presume at the least for halfe an houre</L>
<L>To pre<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>e on my rettirements.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Page.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will say, Sir, you are at your prayers<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fulg.</SPEAKER>
<L>That will not finde beliefe,</L>
<L>Courtiers have something else to do, be gon, Sir,</L>
<L>Ghalleng'd <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> 'tis well I and by a grome! still better <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Was this shape made to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ight? I have a tongue yet,</L>
<L>How e'r no sword to kill him, and what way</L>
<L>This morning, I'll resolve of.
<STAGE>Exit <HI>Fulgenti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adorn.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall crosse</L>
<L>Your resolution, or suffer for you.
<STAGE>Exit <HI>Adorn<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. III. SCENE. III.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Camiola</HI>: divers servants with presents: <HI>Sylli, Clarinda.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sylli.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVHat are all these?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sevants with serverall presents,</L>
<L>And rich ones too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Serv.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>With her best wishes, Madam,</L>
<L>Of many such daies to you, the Lady <HI>Petula</HI></L>
<L>Presents you with this fanne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Serv.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>This Diamond</L>
<L>From your Aunt <HI>Honoria.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3. <HI>Serv.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>This piece of plate</L>
<L>From your Vncle, old <HI>Vincentio,</HI> with your armes</L>
<L>Graven upon it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good friends they are too.</L>
<L>Munificent in their love, and favour to me.</L>
<L>Out of my cabinet returne such jewells</L>
<L>As this directs you, for your paines; and yours;</L>
<L>Nor must you be forgotten. Honour mee</L>
<L>With the drinking of a health.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Serv.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Gold on my life!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="24"/>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Serv.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>She scornes to give base silver.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3. <HI>Serv.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>VVould she had beene</L>
<L>Borne every moneth in the yeere!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Serv.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Moneth? every day.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Serv.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Shew such another maid.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<L>All happinesse wait you.
<STAGE>Exeunt <HI>Sylli, Clarinda, Servants.</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sylli.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'll fee your will done.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>How, <HI>Adorny</HI> wounded?
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Adorni wounded</HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ador.</SPEAKER>
<L>A scratch got in your service, else not worth</L>
<L>Your observation; I bring not Madame</L>
<L>In honour of your birth-day, anticque plate,</L>
<L>Or pearle, for which the savage Indian dives</L>
<L>Into the bottome of the Sea; nor Diamonds</L>
<L>Hewne from steepe rockes with danger: Such as give</L>
<L>To those that have what they themselves want, aime at</L>
<L>A glad returne with profit: yet despise not</L>
<L>My offering at the altar of your favour;</L>
<L>Nor let the lownesse of the giver lessen</L>
<L>T<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e height of whats presented. Since it is</L>
<L>A pretious jewell, almost forfeyted,</L>
<L>And dimn'd with clouds of infamy redeem'd</L>
<L>And in in its naturall splendor, with addition,</L>
<L>Restor'd to the true owner.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>How is this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ador.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not to hold you in suspence, I bring you, Madame,</L>
<L>Your wounded reputation cur'd, the sting</L>
<L>Of virulent malice, festring your faire name,</L>
<L>Pluck'd out and trode on. That proud man, that was</L>
<L>Deny'd the honour of your bed, yet durst</L>
<L>With his untrue reports, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>trumpet your <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ame,</L>
<L>Compell'd by mee, hath given himselfe the lye,</L>
<L>And in his owne blood wrote it, you may r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>d</L>
<L><HI>Fulgentio</HI> subscrib'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am amaz'd!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adorn.</SPEAKER>
<L>It does deserve it, Madam. Common service</L>
<L>Is fit for hindes, and the reward proportion'd</L>
<L><PB REF="24"/>To their conditions. Therefore looke not on mee</L>
<L>As a follower of your fathers fortunes, or</L>
<L>One that subsists on yours, you frowne I my service</L>
<L>Merits not this aspect.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Which of my savo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rs,</L>
<L>I might say bounties, hath begot, and nourish'd</L>
<L>This more then rude presumption? since you had</L>
<L>An itch to try your desperate valour, wherefore</L>
<L>Went you not to the warre? couldst thou suppose</L>
<L>My innocence could ever fall so low,</L>
<L>As to have need of thy rash sword to guard it</L>
<L>Against malicious slander? O how much</L>
<L>Those Ladies are deceiv'd and cheated, when</L>
<L>The clearnesse and integrity of their actions</L>
<L>Doe not defend themselves, and stand secure</L>
<L>On their owne bases? Such as in a colour</L>
<L>Of seeming service give protection to 'em,</L>
<L>Betray their owne strengrhes. Malice scorn'd, puts out</L>
<L>It selfe, but argu'd, gives a kinde of credit</L>
<L>To a false accusation. In this</L>
<L>This your most memorable service, you beleev'd</L>
<L>You did me right, but you have wrong'd mee more</L>
<L>In your defence of my undoubted honour,</L>
<L>Then false <HI>Fulgentio</HI> could.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adorn.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am sorry, What</L>
<L>Was so well intended, is so ill receiv'd,</L>
<L>Yet under your correction you wish'd
<STAGE>Ente <HI>Clarinda</HI></STAGE></L>
<L><HI>Bertoldo</HI> had beene present.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>True I did:</L>
<L>But he and you, Sir, are not parallells,</L>
<L>Nor must you thinke your selfe so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adorn.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am what</L>
<L>You'll please to have mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>If <HI>Bertoldo</HI> had</L>
<L>Punish'd <HI>Fugentio's</HI> insolence, it had showne</L>
<L>His love to her, whom in his judgement hee</L>
<L><PB REF="25"/>Vouchsafe to make his wife. A height I hope</L>
<L>Which you dare not aspire to. The same actions</L>
<L>Sute not all men alike: but I perceive</L>
<L>Repentance in your lookes. For this time leave me</L>
<L>I may forgive, perhaps forget your folly,</L>
<L>Conceale yourselfe till this storme be blowne over.</L>
<L>You will be sought for, yet for my estate
<STAGE>Gives him her hand to kisse.</STAGE></L>
<L>Can hinder it, shall not suffer in my sevice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ador.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is something yet, tho I mist the mark I shot at.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>This Gentleman is of a noble temper.
<STAGE>Exit <HI>Adorni,</HI></STAGE></L>
<L>And I too harsh, perhaps in my reproofe,</L>
<L>Was I not <HI>Clarinda?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clarind.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am not to censure</L>
<L>Your actions Madame: but there are a thousand</L>
<L>Ladies, and of good fame, in such a cause.</L>
<L>Would be proud of such a servant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>It may be;
<STAGE>Enter a <HI>Servant</HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></STAGE></L>
<L>Let me offend in this kinde. Why uncall'd for?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Serv.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Signiors, Madame, <HI>Gasparo</HI> and <HI>Anthonio,</HI></L>
<L>(Selected friends of the renowned <HI>Bertoldo</HI>)</L>
<L>Pu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> a shore this morning.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Without him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Serv.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thinke so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Never thinke more then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Serv.</SPEAKER>
<L>They have beene at Court.</L>
<L>Kiss'd the Kings hand; and there first duties done</L>
<L>To him, appeare ambitions to tender</L>
<L>To you their second service.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Waite 'em hither.
<STAGE>Eexeunt <HI>Servant.</HI></STAGE></L>
<L>Feare doe not racke me, reason, now if ever,</L>
<L>Haste with thy ayde, and tell me such a wonder,</L>
<L>As my <HI>Bertoldo</HI> is, with such care fashion'd,
<STAGE>Enter An∣thonio. Gas∣paro. Serv.</STAGE></L>
<L>Must not, nay cannot, in hev'ns providence,</L>
<L>So soone miscarry; pray you forbeare, ere you</L>
<L>Take the priveledge, as strangers to salute mee,</L>
<L>(Excuse my manners) make me first und<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rstaud,</L>
<L><PB REF="25"/>How it is with <HI>Bertoldo</HI>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>The relation</L>
<L>Will not I feare deserve your thankes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Antho.</SPEAKER>
<L>I wish</L>
<L>Some other should informe you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cami,</SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he dead?</L>
<L>You see, though with some feare, I dare enquire it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dead! Would that were the worst, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> debt were pay'd then,</L>
<L>Kings in their birth owe nature.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cami.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is there ought</L>
<L>More terrible then death?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Antho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes to a spirit</L>
<L>Like his. Cruell imprisonment, and that</L>
<L>Without the hope of freedome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cami.</SPEAKER>
<L>You abuse me,</L>
<L>The royall King cannot in love to vertue,</L>
<L>(Though all springs of affection were dri'd up)</L>
<L>But pay his ran<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<L>When you know what 'tis</L>
<L>You will thinke otherwise; No lesse will do it</L>
<L>Then fifty thousand crownes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>A prettie sum,</L>
<L>The price waigh'd, with the purchase, 50. thousand?</L>
<L>To the King 'tis nothing. He that can spare more</L>
<L>To his minion for a masque, cannot but ransome</L>
<L>Such a brother at a million, you wrong</L>
<L>The Kings magnificence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Antho.</SPEAKER>
<L>In your opinion,</L>
<L>But 'tis most certaine. He does not alone</L>
<L>In himselfe refuse to pay it, but forbids</L>
<L>All other men.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Cam<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Are you sure of this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<L>You may reade</L>
<L>The edict to that purpose, publish'd by him,</L>
<L>That will resolve you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cami.</SPEAKER>
<L>Possible! pray you stand off,</L>
<L><PB REF="26"/>I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> I doe not mutter treason to my selfe</L>
<L>My heart will breake; yet I will not curse him,</L>
<L>He is my king. The newes you have delivered,</L>
<L>Makes me wearie of your company, wee'll salu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e</L>
<L>When we meete next. I'll bring you to the dore.</L>
<L>Nay pray yo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> no more <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>complements.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<L>One thing more</L>
<L>And that's substantiall. Let your <HI>Adorni.</HI></L>
<L>Looke to himselfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Antho.</SPEAKER>
<L>The king is much incens'd</L>
<L>Against him for <HI>Fulgentio.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Camio.</SPEAKER>
<L>As I am</L>
<L>For yuor slownesse to depart</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Both.</SPEAKER>
<L>Farewell swoet Lady.
<STAGE><HI>Exeunt Gaspa. Antho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>O more then impious times! when not alone</L>
<L>Subordinate Ministers of justice are</L>
<L>Corrupted, and seduc'd, but kings themselves,</L>
<L>(The greater wheeles by which the le<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ser move)</L>
<L>Are broken or disjonted; could it be else</L>
<L>A king, to sooth his politique ends, should so far</L>
<L>Fo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sake his honor, as at once to breake</L>
<L>Th'Adamant chaines of nature and religion,</L>
<L>To binde up Atheisme, as a defence</L>
<L>To his darke counsailes? will it ever be</L>
<L>That to deserve too much is dangerous,</L>
<L>And vertue, when too eminent a crime?</L>
<L>Must she serve fortune still? or when stripp'd of</L>
<L>Her gay, and glorious favours, loose the beauties</L>
<L>Of her owne naturall shape? O my <HI>Bertoldo!</HI></L>
<L>Thou onely Sun in honors Spheare, how soone</L>
<L>Art thou eclipsed and darkened! not the nearnesse</L>
<L>Of blood prevailing on the king; nor all</L>
<L>The benefits to the generall good dispens'd</L>
<L>Gayning a retribution! But that</L>
<L>To owe a courtesie to a simple Virgin</L>
<L>Would take from the deserving, I finde in me</L>
<L><PB REF="26"/>Som sparks of fire, which fann'd with honors breath</L>
<L>Might rise into a flame, and in men darken</L>
<L>Their usurp'd splendor. H<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>! my aime is high,</L>
<L>And for the honor of my sex to fall so,</L>
<L>Can never prove inglorious. 'Tis resolv'd:</L>
<L>Call in <HI>Adorni.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am happy in</L>
<L>Such imployment, Madam.
<STAGE>Exit Clarin.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee's a man,</L>
<L>I know that at a reverend distance loves me,</L>
<L>A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d such are ever faithfull: What a Sea</L>
<L>Of melting ice I walke on! what strange censures</L>
<L>Am I to undergoe! but good intent<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Deride all future rumors.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ador.</SPEAKER>
<L>I obey
<STAGE>Exit Clarin. &amp; Adorn.</STAGE></L>
<L>Your summons, Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Leave the place <HI>Clarinda,</HI></L>
<L>One woman, in a secret of such waight,</L>
<L>Wisemen may thinke too much, nearer <HI>Adorni.</HI></L>
<L>I warrant it with a smile.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adorn.</SPEAKER>
<L>I cannot aske</L>
<L>Safer protection, what's your will?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cami.</SPEAKER>
<L>To doubt</L>
<L>Your ready desire to serve me, or prepare you</L>
<L>With the repetition of former merits,</L>
<L>Would in my diffidence wrong you. But I will</L>
<L>And without circumstance, in the trust that I</L>
<L>Impose upon you, free you from suspition.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adorn.</SPEAKER>
<L>I foster none of you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cami.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know you do not.</L>
<L>You are <HI>Adorni</HI> by the love you owe me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adorn.</SPEAKER>
<L>The surest conjuration.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cami.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take me with you,</L>
<L>Love borne of duty, but advance noe further,</L>
<L>You are Sir as I layd to do me service,</L>
<L>To undertake a taske, in which your faith,</L>
<L><PB REF="27"/><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>udgement, discretion, in a word, your all</L>
<L>That's good, must be ingag'd, nor must you studie</L>
<L>In <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he execution, but what may make</L>
<L>For the ends I aime at.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adorn.</SPEAKER>
<L>They admit no rivalls.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>You answer well, you have heard of <HI>Bertoldo's</HI></L>
<L>Cap<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ivity? and the kings neglect? the greatnesse</L>
<L>Of his ransome, fiftie thousand crownes, <HI>Adorni,</HI></L>
<L>Two parts of my estate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ador.</SPEAKER>
<L>To what tends this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet I so love the gentleman (for to you</L>
<L>I will confesse my weaknesses) that I purpose</L>
<L>Now, when he is forsaken by the king,</L>
<L>And his owne hopes to ransome him, and receive him</L>
<L>Into my bosome as my lawfull husband,
<STAGE><HI>Adorni star<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s and seems troubl'd</HI></STAGE></L>
<L>Why change you colour</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ador.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis in wonder of</L>
<L>Your vertue, Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cami</SPEAKER>
<L>You must therefore to</L>
<L><HI>Si<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>na</HI> for mee, and pay to <HI>Gonzaga</HI></L>
<L>This ransome for his liberty, you shall</L>
<L>Have bills of exchange along with you. Let him sweare</L>
<L>A solemne contract to me, for you must be</L>
<L>My principall witnesse, if he should. But why</L>
<L>Do I entertaine these jealousies? you will do this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adorn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faithfully, Madam. But not live long after
<STAGE>aside</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>One thing I had forgot. Besides his freedome</L>
<L>He may want accomodations, furnish him</L>
<L>According to his birth. And from <HI>Camiola</HI></L>
<L>Deliver this kisse, printed on your lips
<STAGE>kisses him</STAGE></L>
<L>Seal'd on his hand! you shall not see my blushe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</L>
<L>I'll instantly dispatch you.
<STAGE>Exit Camiola.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adorni.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am halfe</L>
<L>Hang'd out of the way already, was there ever</L>
<L>Poore lover so imploy'd against himselfe</L>
<L>To make way for his rivall? I must doe it,</L>
<L><PB REF="27"/>Nay more, I will. If loyalty can finde</L>
<L>Recompence beyond hope, or imagination</L>
<L>Let it fall on mee in the other world,</L>
<L>As a reward, for in this I dare not hope it.
<STAGE>Exit</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<TRAILER>The end of the third Act.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="4" TYPE="act">
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. IIII. SCENE. I.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Gonzaga, Piero Roderigo, Iacomo.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gonzaga.</SPEAKER>
<L>YOu haue seaz'd upon the Citadell, and dis∣arm'd</L>
<L>All that could make resistance</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pierio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hunger had</L>
<L>Done that before wee came; nor was the souldiour</L>
<L>Compel<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'d to seeke for prey the famish'd wretches,</L>
<L>In hope of mercy, as a sacrifice offer'd</L>
<L>All that was worth the taking.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gonzag.</SPEAKER>
<L>You proclaim'd,</L>
<L>On paine of death, no violence should be offe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'d</L>
<L>To any woman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L>But it needed not,</L>
<L>For famine had so humbl'd 'em and tooke off</L>
<L>The care of their sexes honour, that there was not</L>
<L>So coy a bea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>y in the towne, but would</L>
<L>For halfe a mouldy bisket sell her selfe</L>
<L>To a poore besognion, and without shrieking</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gonz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where is the Duke of <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rbin.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iacom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vnder guard,</L>
<L>As you directed</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gonzag.</SPEAKER>
<L>See the Souldiers set.</L>
<L>In ranke, and file, and as the Du<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>chesse passes</L>
<L>Bid 'em vaile their ensignes, and charge 'em on their lives</L>
<L>Not to cry whores.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="28"/>
<SPEAKER>Iacom.</SPEAKER>
<L>The divell cannot fright 'em</L>
<L>From their military licence, though they know</L>
<L>They are her subjects, and will part with being,</L>
<L>To do her service; yet since she is a woman,</L>
<L>They will touch at her britch with their tongues, and that is all</L>
<L>That they can hope for.
<STAGE>A shout, and a generall cry within, whores, whores.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<L>O the divell! they are at it.</L>
<L>Hell, stoppe, their bawling throats; againe! make up</L>
<L>And cudgell them into jelly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Roder.</SPEAKER>
<L>To no purpose,</L>
<L>Though their mouthes were there,</L>
<L>They would have the same name for 'em.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. IIII. SCENE. II.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Roderigo, Iacomo, Pierio, Gonzga, Aurelia</HI> (under a Canopie) <HI>Astutio</HI> presents her with letters, lowd, musicke, shee reads the letters.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gonzaga.</SPEAKER>
<L>I Doe beseech your high<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>esse not to ascribe</L>
<L>To the want of disciplin, the barbarous rudenes</L>
<L>Of the souldie<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> in his prophanation of</L>
<L>Your sacred name, and vertues</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurelia.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, Lord Generall,</L>
<L>I have heard my father say oft, 'twas a custome,</L>
<L>Vsuall in the campe, nor are they to be punish'd</L>
<L>For words, that have in fact deserv'd so well.</L>
<L>Let the one excuse the other.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<L>Excellent Princesse!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>But for these aids from Sicily sent against us</L>
<L>To blast our <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pring of conquest in the bud:</L>
<L>I cannot find, my Lord Embassadour,</L>
<L>How we should entertaine't but as a wrong.</L>
<L>With purpose to detaine us from our owne.</L>
<L>How e'r the King endeavours in his letters</L>
<L>To mitigate the affront.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="28"/>
<SPEAKER>Astut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your grace hereafter</L>
<L>May heare from me such strong assurances</L>
<L>Of his unlimitted desires to serve you,</L>
<L>As will, I hope, drowne in forgetfulnesse</L>
<L>The memory of what's past.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Au<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>el.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Wee shall take time</L>
<L>To search the depth of't further, and proceed</L>
<L>As our counsell shall direct vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gonza.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee present you</L>
<L>With the keyes of the Citty, all lets are remov'd,</L>
<L>Your way is smooth and easie, at your feet</L>
<L>Your proudest enemy falls.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee thanke your valoures</L>
<L>A victory without blood is twice atchiev'd,</L>
<L>And the disposure of it to us tender'd,
<STAGE><HI>A Guard made<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Aurelia. passe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> thorow<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> em. lowd musick<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</HI></STAGE></L>
<L>The greatest honor, worthy captains thanks.</L>
<L>My love extends it selfe to all</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gonz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Make way there.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. IIII. SCENE. III.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Bertoldo</HI> with a small booke in fetters, <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aylor.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rtoldo.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Tis here determin'd (great examples arm'd</L>
<L>Winh arguments produc'd to make it good)</L>
<L>That neither tyrants, nor the wrested lawes;</L>
<L>The peoples <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ranticke rage, sad ex<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>le, want,</L>
<L>Nor that which I endure, captivity,</L>
<L>Can doe a wise man any injury:</L>
<L>Thus <HI>Seneca,</HI> when he wrot it, thought. But then</L>
<L>Fecliity courted him; his wealth exceeding</L>
<L>A private man's happy in the em<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>races</L>
<L>Of his chaste wife <HI>Paulina,</HI>; his house <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ull</L>
<L>Of childr, enclyents, servants, flattering friends</L>
<L>Soothing his lip-positions, and created</L>
<L>Prince of the Senate, by the generall voyce,</L>
<L><PB REF="29"/>As his pupill newes suffrage: then no doubt</L>
<L>H<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> held, and did believe this<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> But no sooner</L>
<L>The Princes frownes, and iealosies had throw'n him</L>
<L>Out of securities lappe, and a centurion</L>
<L>Had off<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r'd him what choyce of death he pleas'd,</L>
<L>But told him dye he must: when straight the armour</L>
<L>Of his so boasted fortitude, fel off
<STAGE><HI>Throwes away the book<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</HI></STAGE></L>
<L>Complaining of his frailtie. Can it then</L>
<L>Be censur'd womanish weaknesse in mee, if</L>
<L>Thus clog'd with yrons, and the period</L>
<L>To close up all calamities, deni'd mee,</L>
<L>(Which was presented <HI>Senica</HI>) I wish</L>
<L>I ne'r had being, at least, never knew</L>
<L>What happines was, or argue with heavens justice?</L>
<L>Tea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ing my locks, and in defiance throwing</L>
<L>Dust in the ayre? or falling on the ground, thus</L>
<L>With my nayles, and teeth to digge a grave or rend</L>
<L>The bowells of the earth, my stepmother,</L>
<L>And not a naturall parent? or thus practise</L>
<L>To dye, and as I were insensible,</L>
<L>Believe I had no motion
<STAGE><HI>lies on his face</HI> Enter <HI>Gonzaga A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>orn. Iaylor.</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gonz.</SPEAKER>
<L>There he is:</L>
<L>Ile not enquire by whom his ransome's pai'd</L>
<L>I am satisfi'd that I have it: nor alleage</L>
<L>One reason to excuse his cruell usage,</L>
<L>As you may interpret it, let it su<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>fice</L>
<L>It was my will to have it so, he is yours now,</L>
<L>Dispose of him as you please
<STAGE>Exit <HI>Gonzaga.</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adorn.</SPEAKER>
<L>How e'r I hate him,</L>
<L>As one preferr'd before me, being a man,</L>
<L>He does deserve my pitty. Sir, he sl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>epes:</L>
<L>Or is he dead? would hee were a Saint in heaven;</L>
<L>'Tis is all the hurt I wish him. But was not
<STAGE>Kneeles by him.</STAGE></L>
<L>Borne o such happinesse. No he breaths, come neer,</L>
<L>A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d if '<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> be possi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>le, without his f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eling</L>
<L>T<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ke off his yrons<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> so, now leave <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s privat
<STAGE>His yrons taken off.</STAGE></L>
<L>He does begin to stir, and as transported
<STAGE>Exit <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aylor.</HI></STAGE></L>
<L><PB REF="29"/>With a joyfull dreame, how he stares! and feeles his legg<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s,</L>
<L>As yet uncertaine, whether it can be</L>
<L>True or phantasticall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ministers of mercy</L>
<L>Mocke not calamitie. Ha! 'tis no vision!</L>
<L>Or if it be, the happiest that ever</L>
<L>Appear'd to sinfull flesh! who's here! His face</L>
<L>Speakes him <HI>Adorni</HI>! but some glorious Angell</L>
<L>Concealing its divinity in his shape,</L>
<L>Hath done this miracle, it being not an act</L>
<L>For wolvish man. Resolve me, if thou look'st for</L>
<L>Bent knees in adoration?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adorn.</SPEAKER>
<L>O forbeare Sir,</L>
<L>I am <HI>Adorni,</HI> and the instrument</L>
<L>Of your deliverance; but the benefit</L>
<L>You owe another.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>If he has a name,</L>
<L>Assoone as spoken, 'tis writ on my heart,</L>
<L>I am his bond<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ador.</SPEAKER>
<L>To the shame of men,</L>
<L>This great act is a womans.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>The whole sex</L>
<L>For her s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ke must be deifi'd. How I wander</L>
<L>In my imagination, yet cannot</L>
<L>Ghesse who this <HI>Phoenix</HI> should be!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ador.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis <HI>Camiola.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray you sp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ake't againe, there's musicke in her name</L>
<L>Once more I pray you Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ador.</SPEAKER>
<L>Camiola,</L>
<L>The Maid of honor,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>Curs'd Atheist that I was,</L>
<L>Onely to doubt it could be any other,</L>
<L>Since she alone in the abstract of her selfe,</L>
<L>Tha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> small, but ravishing substance comprehends</L>
<L>What ever <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, or can be wished, in the</L>
<L>I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>dea of a woman. O what service,</L>
<L>Or sacrifice of duty can I pay her!</L>
<L><PB REF="30"/>I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> not to live, and dye her charities slave,</L>
<L>Which is resolv'd already.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adorn.</SPEAKER>
<L>She expects not</L>
<L>Such a dominion ore you: yet ere I</L>
<L>Deliver her demands, give me your hand:</L>
<L>On this, as she enjoyn'd me, with my lips</L>
<L>I print her love and service by me sent you,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bert.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am orewhelm'd with wonder!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ador.</SPEAKER>
<L>You must now</L>
<L>(Which is the sum of all that she desires)</L>
<L>By a solemne contract bind your selfe, when she</L>
<L>Requires it as a debt, due for your fredome</L>
<L>To marrie her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>This does ingage me further,</L>
<L>A payment! an increase of obligation!</L>
<L>To marry her! 'twas my <HI>uil ultra</HI> ever!</L>
<L>The end of my ambition! O that now</L>
<L>The holy man, she present, were prepar'd</L>
<L>To joyne our hands, but with that speed, my heart</L>
<L>Wishes, mine eyes might see her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adorn.</SPEAKER>
<L>You must sweare this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>Swear it? Collect all oaths, and imprecations</L>
<L>Whose least breach is damnation, and those</L>
<L>Ministred to me in a forme more dreadfull,</L>
<L>Set heaven, and hell before me, I will take 'em:</L>
<L>False to <HI>Camiola</HI>? Never. Shall I now</L>
<L>Begin my vowes to you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ador.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am no Church-man,</L>
<L>Such a one must file it on record, you are free,</L>
<L>And that you may appeare like to your selfe</L>
<L>(For so she wish'd) her's gold with which you may</L>
<L>Redeeme your truncks and servants, and what ever</L>
<L>Of late you lost. I have found out the Captaine</L>
<L>Whose spoyle they were. His name is <HI>Roderigo.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ador.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have done my parts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>So much Sir</L>
<L><PB REF="30"/>As I am ever your's for't, now me thinkes</L>
<L>I walke in ayre! divine <HI>Camiola,</HI></L>
<L>But words cannot expresse thee. I'll build to thee</L>
<L>An altar in my soule, on which I'll offer</L>
<L>A still increasing sacrifice of duty.
<STAGE><HI>Exit Ber<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ador.</SPEAKER>
<L>What will become of me now is apparant!</L>
<L>Whether a poniard, or a halter be</L>
<L>The nearest way to hell (for I must thither,</L>
<L>After I have kill'd my selfe) is somewhat doubtfull?</L>
<L>This Roman resolution of selfe-murther,</L>
<L>Will not hold water, at the high Tribunall,</L>
<L>When it comes to be argu'd; my good Genius</L>
<L>Prompts me to this consideration. He</L>
<L>That kills himselfe, to avoid mis<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ry, feares it,</L>
<L>And at the best shewes but a bastard valour,</L>
<L>This lifes a fort co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mitted to my trust,</L>
<L>Which I must not yeeld up, till it be forc'd,</L>
<L>Nor will I: Hee's not valiant that dares dy,</L>
<L>But he that boldly beares calamitie.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. IV. SCENE. IV. A Flourish.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Pierio. Roderigo. Iacomo. Gonzaga. Aurelia. Ferdinand. Astutio. Attendants.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurelia.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Seat here for the Duke. It is our glory</L>
<L>To overcom with courtesies, not rigor;</L>
<L>To Lordly Roman, who held it the height</L>
<L>Of humane happinesse, to have kings and Queenes</L>
<L>To wait by his triumphant chariot wheeles</L>
<L>In his insulting pride, depriv'd himselfe</L>
<L>Of drawing neare the nature of the gods,</L>
<L>Best known for such, in being mercifull,</L>
<L><PB REF="31"/>Yet give me leave, but still with gentle language,</L>
<L>And with the freedome of a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>riend to tell you,</L>
<L>To seeke by force, what courtship could not win,</L>
<L>was not harsh, and never taught in loves milde schoole.</L>
<L>Wise Poets faine that Venus coach is draw'n</L>
<L>By doues, and sparrowes, not by beares, and tygres.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>I spare the application.</L>
<L>In my fortune,</L>
<L>Heav'ns justice hath confirm'd it, yet great Lady,</L>
<L>Since my offence grew from excesse of love,</L>
<L>And not to be resisted, having paid too,</L>
<L>With the losse of liberty, the forfeyture</L>
<L>Of my presumption, in your clemency</L>
<L>It may finde pardon</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurel.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall have just cause</L>
<L>To say it hath. The charge of the long siege</L>
<L>Defraid, and the losse my subjects have sustain'd</L>
<L>Made good, since so farre I must deale with caution,</L>
<L>You have your liberty</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>I could not hope for gentler conditions.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurel.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord <HI>Gonzaga.</HI></L>
<L>Since my comming to <HI>Siena,</HI> I haue heard much</L>
<L>Of your prisoner; brave <HI>Bert<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ldo.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gonza.</SPEAKER>
<L>Such <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n one, Madam, I had.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Astut.</SPEAKER>
<L>And have still, Sir, I hope.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gonz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your hopes deceive you. He is ransom'd<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Madame,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Astut.</SPEAKER>
<L>By whom, I pray you, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gonzag.</SPEAKER>
<L>You had best enquire</L>
<L>Of your intelligencer. I am no informer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Astut.</SPEAKER>
<L>I like not this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurel.</SPEAKER>
<L>He is, as 'tis reported,</L>
<L>A goodly gentleman, and of noble parts,</L>
<L>A brother of your order.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gonzaga.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee was, Madam,</L>
<L>Till he against his oath wrong'd you, a princesse,</L>
<L>Which his religion bound him from.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Great mindes</L>
<L><PB REF="31"/>For tryall of their valours oft maintaine</L>
<L>Quarrells that are unjust, yet without malice,</L>
<L>And such a faire construction I make of him.</L>
<L>I would see that brave enemy;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gonzaga.</SPEAKER>
<L>My duty</L>
<L>Commands me to seeke for him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray you doe:</L>
<L>And bring him to our presence.
<STAGE>Exit <HI>Gonzaga.</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Ast<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>I must blast</L>
<L>His entertainment; may it please your excellency,</L>
<L>He is a man debauch'd, and for his riots</L>
<L>Cast off by the King my Master, and that, I hope, is</L>
<L>A crime sufficient</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>To you his subjects,</L>
<L>That like as your king likes
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Gonzaga, Bert<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ldo, richly habi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ed: Adorni.</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurel.</SPEAKER>
<L>But not to us;</L>
<L>We must waigh with our owne scale. This is he, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>are!</L>
<L>How soone mine eye had found him! what a port</L>
<L>He beares! how well his bravery becomes him!</L>
<L>A prisoner! nay, a princly sutor rather!</L>
<L>But I am too sudden.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madame, 'twas his suite,</L>
<L>Vnsent for, to present his service to you,</L>
<L>Ere his departure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurel.</SPEAKER>
<L>With what Majesty</L>
<L>He beares himselfe!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Astut.</SPEAKER>
<L>The divell I thinke supplies him,</L>
<L>Ransom'd, and thus rich too!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurel.</SPEAKER>
<L>You ill deserve
<STAGE><HI>Ferdinand kn<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eling, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>isses her hand.</HI></STAGE></L>
<L>The favour of our hand; we are no<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> well,</L>
<L>Give us more ayre.
<STAGE><HI>S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> descends suddenly<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gonz.</SPEAKER>
<L>What sudden qualme is this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurel.</SPEAKER>
<L>That lifted yours against mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rtol.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Thus once more,</L>
<L>I sue for pardon</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sure his lips are poyson'd,</L>
<L>And through th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>se veines, force passage to my heart
<STAGE>Aside.</STAGE></L>
<L><PB REF="32"/>Which is already <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eaz'd upon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bertol.</SPEAKER>
<L>I wait, Madam,</L>
<L>To know what your commands are; my designes</L>
<L>Exact me in another place.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Before</L>
<L>You have our licence to depart; if manners,</L>
<L>Civility of manners cannot teach you</L>
<L>T'attend our leasure, I must tell you, Sir,</L>
<L>That you are still our prisoner, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>or had you</L>
<L>Commission to free him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gonz.</SPEAKER>
<L>How's this, Madam?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurel.</SPEAKER>
<L>You were my substitute, and wanted power</L>
<L>Without my warrant to dispose of him.</L>
<L>I will pay backe his ransome ten times over,</L>
<L>Rather then quit my interest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bertol.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is</L>
<L>Against the law of armes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>But not of love:
<STAGE>Aside.</STAGE></L>
<L>Why, hath your entertainment, Sir, beene such</L>
<L>In your restraint, that with the wings of feare</L>
<L>You would flie from it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bertol.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know no man, Madame,</L>
<L>Enamour'd of his fetter<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, or delighting</L>
<L>In cold or hunger, or that would in reason</L>
<L>Preferre straw in a d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ngeon, before</L>
<L>A downe bed in a Palace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurel.</SPEAKER>
<L>How, come neerer;</L>
<L>Was his usage such?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gonz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, and it had beene worse,</L>
<L>Had I foreseene this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>O thou mis-sh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>p'd monster!</L>
<L>In thee it is confirm'd, that such as have</L>
<L>No share in na<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ures bounties, know no pitty</L>
<L>To such as have 'em<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Looke on him with my eyes,</L>
<L>And answer then, whether this were a man,</L>
<L>Whose <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>heekes of lovely fulnesse should be made</L>
<L>A prey to meagre famine? or these eyes</L>
<L><PB REF="32"/>Whose every glance store <HI>Cupids</HI> empti'd quiver,</L>
<L>To be dimm'd with tedious watching? or these lips,</L>
<L>These rudie lips, of whose fresh colour, cherries</L>
<L>And roses were but coppies, should grow pale</L>
<L>For want of Nectar? or these legges that beare</L>
<L>A burthen of more worth, then is supported</L>
<L>By <HI>Atla<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> wearied shoulders, should be cramp'd</L>
<L>With the weight of yron? O I could dwell ever</L>
<L>On this description!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bertoldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is this in di<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ision</L>
<L>Or pitty of me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurel.</SPEAKER>
<L>In your charity</L>
<L>Beleeve me innocent. Now you are my prisoner</L>
<L>You shall have fairer quarter, you will shame</L>
<L>The place where you have beene, should you now leave it</L>
<L>Before you are recover'd. I'll conduct you</L>
<L>To more convenient lodgings, and it shall be</L>
<L>My care to cherish you. Repine who dare;</L>
<L>It is our will. You'll follow mee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bertoldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>To the centre,</L>
<L>Such a <HI>Sybilla</HI> guiding me.
<STAGE>Exeunt <HI>Aurelia, Bertold<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gonz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who speakes first?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>We stand, as we had seen <HI>Medusas</HI> head!
<STAGE>All amaz'd.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pierio.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know not what to thinke, I am so amaz'd!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Roder.</SPEAKER>
<L>Amaz'd! I am thunderstrooke!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iacom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee are inchaunted,</L>
<L>And this is some illusion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adorn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heav'n forbid!</L>
<L>In darke despaire, it shewes a beame of hope.</L>
<L>Containe thy joy, <HI>Adorni.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Astut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Such a Princesse,</L>
<L>And of so long experienc'd reservednesse</L>
<L>Breake forth, and on the sudden, into flashes</L>
<L>Of more then doubted loosenesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gonz.</SPEAKER>
<L>They come againe,</L>
<L>Smiling, as I live: His arme circ<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ing her wast:</L>
<L>I shall runne mad: Some fury hath possess'd her.</L>
<L><PB REF="33"/>If I speake, I may be blasted. H<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, I'll <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>u<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>bl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>A prayer or two, and crosse my selfe, and then</L>
<L>Though the divell fart fire, have at him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let not, Sir,</L>
<L>The violence of my passions nourish in you</L>
<L>An ill opinion; or grant my carriag<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Out of the rode, and ga<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>be of private women,</L>
<L>'Tis still done with decorum. As I am</L>
<L>A Princesse, what I doe, is aboue cens<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re,</L>
<L>And to be imitated.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bertoldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gracious Madam,</L>
<L>Vouchsafe a little pawse, for I am so r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pt</L>
<L>Beyond my selfe, that 'till I have collected</L>
<L>My scatter'd faculties, I cannot tender</L>
<L>My resolution.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Consider of it,</L>
<L>I will not be long from you,
<STAGE><HI>Be<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>ldo walking by musing.</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gonzaga.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray I cannot!</L>
<L>This cursed object strangles my devotion!</L>
<L>I must speake, or I burst. Pray you faire Lady,</L>
<L>If you can in courtesie, direct mee to</L>
<L>The cha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>te <HI>Aurelia.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you blind<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>? who are we<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gonza.</SPEAKER>
<L>Another kind of thing. Her blood was govern'd</L>
<L>By her discretion, and not rul'd her reason<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>The reverence and Maj<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sty of <HI>Iun<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI></L>
<L>Shinde in her lookes, and comming to the campe,</L>
<L>Appear'd a second <HI>Palla<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</HI> I can see</L>
<L>No such divinities in you. If I</L>
<L>Without offence may speake my thoughts, you are,</L>
<L>As it were, a wanton <HI>H<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>len.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurelia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good, ere long</L>
<L>You shall know mee better.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gonz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, if you are <HI>Aurelia</HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>How shall I dispose of the Souldier?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Astut.</SPEAKER>
<L>May it please you</L>
<L>To hasten my dispatch?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="33"/>
<SPEAKER>Aurel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prefer your s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ites</L>
<L>Vnto <HI>Bertoldo,</HI> we will give him hearing,</L>
<L>And you'll finde him your best advocate.
<STAGE>Exit Aurelia</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Astut.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is rare!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gonz.</SPEAKER>
<L>What are we come to?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Roder.</SPEAKER>
<L>Grown up in a moment</L>
<L>A favorite!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferdi.</SPEAKER>
<L>He does take state already.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, no, it cannot be, yet but <HI>Ca<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>la,</HI></L>
<L>There is no stop betweene me and a crowne,</L>
<L>Then my ingratitude! a sinne in which</L>
<L>All sinnes are comprehended! Aide me vertue,</L>
<L>Or I am lost.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gonz.</SPEAKER>
<L>May it please your excellence</L>
<L>Second me, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> so horrid oathes,</L>
<L>And hell. deepe i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>precations made against it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Astu.</SPEAKER>
<L>The king your brother will thank you for t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>advāc∣ment</L>
<L>Of his affaires</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bertol.</SPEAKER>
<L>And yet who can hold out</L>
<L>Against such batteries, as her power and greatness<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Raise up against my weake defences!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gonz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir,
<STAGE><HI>Enter Aureli<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</HI></STAGE></L>
<L>Doe you dreame waking, Slight, shee's here againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>Walkes she on woollen fee<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aureli.</SPEAKER>
<L>You dwell too long</L>
<L>In your deliberation, and come</L>
<L>With a criples pace to that which you should <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ly to</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is confess'd, yet why should I to winne</L>
<L>From you, that hazzard all to my poore nothing,</L>
<L>By false play send you o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>f a looser from me?</L>
<L>I'am already too too much ingag'd</L>
<L>To the king my brothers anger; and who knowes</L>
<L>But that his doubts, and politick feares, should you</L>
<L>Make me his equall, may draw war upon</L>
<L>Your <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>rritories, were that breach made up</L>
<L><PB REF="34"/>I should with joy embrace, what now I feare</L>
<L>To touch but with due reverence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aureli.</SPEAKER>
<L>That hind<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rance</L>
<L>Is easily remov'd. I owe the king</L>
<L>For a royall visit<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> which I straight will pay him,</L>
<L>And having first reconcil'd you to his favour,</L>
<L>A dispensation shall meete with us,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am wholly yours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aure.</SPEAKER>
<L>On this booke seale it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gon.</SPEAKER>
<L>What hand and lip too, then the barga<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ne's sure,</L>
<L>You have no imployment for me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Aurel<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Yes <HI>Gonzaga,</HI></L>
<L>Provide a royall ship.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gonz.</SPEAKER>
<L>A ship? Saint <HI>Iohn,</HI></L>
<L>Whither are we bound now?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurel.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall know hereafter,</L>
<L>My lord your pardon, for my too much trenching upon your patience.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ador.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Camiola.</HI>
<STAGE>Whispers to Bertoldo</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurel.</SPEAKER>
<L>How doe you</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indisposed, but I attend you.
<STAGE>Exeunt</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>orn.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>The heavie curse that waites on perjurie,</L>
<L>And foule ingratitude, pursue thee ever.</L>
<L>Yet why from me this? In this breach of faith</L>
<L>My loyalty findes rew<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rd! what poysons him</L>
<L>Proves Mithridate to me! I have perform'd</L>
<L>All she commanded punctually, and now</L>
<L>In the cleare mirrour of my truth, she may</L>
<L>Behold his fal<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ehood. O that I had wings</L>
<L>To b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>are me to <HI>Palermo!</HI> This once knowne,</L>
<L>Must change her love into a just disdaine,</L>
<L>And worke her to compassion of my paine.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="scene">
<PB REF="34"/>
<HEAD>ACT. IV. SCENE. V.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Sylli. Camiola. Clarinda.</HI> At severall doores.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Sy<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Vndone! vndone! poore I that whilome was</L>
<L>The top and ridge of my house, am on the sudden</L>
<L>Turn'd to the pittifullest animal</L>
<L>Of the lignage of the <HI>Sylli<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>!</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cami.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's the matter?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syl.</SPEAKER>
<L>The king! breake gyrdle, breake!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cami.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why? what of him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hearing how far you doted on my person,</L>
<L>Growing envio<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s of my happines, and knowing</L>
<L>His brother, nor his favorite <HI>Fulgentio,</HI></L>
<L>Could get a sheepe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> eie from you, I being present,</L>
<L>Is come himselfe a suitor, with the awle</L>
<L>Of his authoritie to bore my nose,</L>
<L>And take you from me, Oh, oh, oh.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do not rore so;</L>
<L>The king!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syl.</SPEAKER>
<L>The king! yet loving <HI>Sylli</HI> is not</L>
<L>So sorrie for his owne, as your misfortune,</L>
<L>If the king should carrie you, or you beare him,</L>
<L>What a looser should you be? He can but make you</L>
<L>A queene, and what a simp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e thing is that</L>
<L>To the being my lawful spouse. The world can never</L>
<L>Affoord you such a hu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>band.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cami.</SPEAKER>
<L>I beleeve you,</L>
<L>But how are you sure the king is so inclin'd?</L>
<L>Did not you dreame this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syl.</SPEAKER>
<L>With these eyes I saw him</L>
<L>Dismisse his traine, and lightn<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>g from his co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ch,</L>
<L>Whispering <HI>Fulgentio</HI> in the ear<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>If so</L>
<L><PB REF="35"/>I ghesse the businesse</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syl.</SPEAKER>
<L>It can be no other</L>
<L>But to give me the bob, that being a matter</L>
<L>Of maine importance, yonder they a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e, I dare not</L>
<L>Be seene, I am so desperate, if you forsake me,
<STAGE>Exit Rob. Ful.</STAGE></L>
<L>Send me word that I may provide a willow ghyrlond</L>
<L>To weare when I drowne my selfe. O <HI>Sylli,</HI> ô <HI>Sylli</HI>!
<STAGE>Exit crying</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ful.</SPEAKER>
<L>It will be wo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>th your paines Sir to observe</L>
<L>The constancie and brav<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ry of her spirit,</L>
<L>Though great men tremble at your frownes, I dare</L>
<L>Hazzard my head, your majesty set off</L>
<L>With terror, cannot fright her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Robert.</SPEAKER>
<L>May she answer</L>
<L>My expectation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Fulg<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>There she is.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>My knees thus</L>
<L>Bent to the ear<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> (while my vowes are sent upward</L>
<L>For the safety of my Sover<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>igne) pay the duty</L>
<L>Due for so great an honor, in this favour</L>
<L>Done to your humblest hand-maid.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Robert.</SPEAKER>
<L>You mistake me,</L>
<L>I come not (Lady) that you may report,</L>
<L>T<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e king to do you honor, made your house</L>
<L>(He being there) his court, but to correct</L>
<L>Your stubborne disobedience. A pardon</L>
<L>For that, could you obtaine it, were well purchas'd</L>
<L>With this humility.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>A pardon Sir?</L>
<L>'Till I am conscio<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s of an offence.</L>
<L>I will not wrong <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y innocence to begge one,</L>
<L>What is my crime Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Look on him I favour,</L>
<L>By you sco<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n'd and negelected.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is that all S<SUP>r</SUP>.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rober.</SPEAKER>
<L>No minion, though that were too much. How can you</L>
<L>Answer the setting on your desperate brauo</L>
<L>To murther him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>With your leave, I must not kneele Sir.</L>
<L>Whi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e I replie to this: But thus rise up</L>
<L>In my defence, and tell you as a man</L>
<L>(since when you are <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>njust, the diety</L>
<L><PB REF="35"/>Which you may challenge as a King, part<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> from yo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>'Twas never read in holy writ, or morrall,</L>
<L>That subject<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> on their loyalty were oblig'd</L>
<L>To love their Soveraignes vices, your grace, Sir,</L>
<L>To such an undeserver is no vertue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Fulg<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>What <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hinke you now Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Say you should love wine,</L>
<L>You being the King, and c<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>se I am your subject,</L>
<L>Must I beever dr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nke? Tyrants, not King<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>By violence, from humble vassails force</L>
<L>The liberty of their s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>les. I co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ld not love him<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>And to compell a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ection, as I take it,</L>
<L>Is not found in your prer<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ative.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Excellent virgin!</L>
<L>How I admire her confidence<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>He complaines</L>
<L>Of wrong done him: but <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e no mo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> a King,</L>
<L>Vnlesse you do me right. Bu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ne yo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r decrees,</L>
<L>And of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>r lawes and statutes make a fire</L>
<L>To th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>we<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e froz<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> nu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>e of deli<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>quent<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</L>
<L>If he escape unpun<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sh'd. Doe your <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>dicts</L>
<L>Call it death in any man that breake<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> into</L>
<L>Anothers house to rob hi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, though of trifles<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>And shall <HI>Fulg<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="6 letters" DISP="••••••"/></HI> y<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ur <HI>Fulgentio</HI> live?</L>
<L>Who hath committed more then sacriledge</L>
<L>In the pollution of my cleare fame</L>
<L>By his malicious slanders<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Have you done this?</L>
<L>Answer truely on your life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fulgen.</SPEAKER>
<L>In the heat of blood</L>
<L>Some such thing I reported.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Out of my sight,</L>
<L>For I vow, if by t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ue pen<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nce thou win n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></L>
<L>This injur'd L<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>dy to sue out thy pardo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</L>
<L>Thy g<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ve is digg'd already.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>F<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lgen.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>By my owne folly</L>
<L>I have made a faire hand of't,
<STAGE>Exit Fulgen.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall know Lady</L>
<L><PB REF="36"/>While I w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>e a crowne, justice <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hall use her sword</L>
<L>To cut offenders o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>f, though neerest to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, now you sh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>w whose Deputy you are,</L>
<L>I now I bath your fe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t with teares, it cannot</L>
<L>Be censur'd superstition.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>You must rise.</L>
<L>Rise in our favour, and protection ever:
<STAGE>Kisses her</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Happy are <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>u<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>jects<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> when the prince is s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ill</L>
<L>Guided by justice, not his passionate will.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<TRAILER>The end of the fourth Act.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="5" TYPE="act">
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. V. SCEN<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. I.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Cami<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>la. Sylli.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>YOu see how tender I am of the q<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>iet</L>
<L>And peace of your a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>fection, and what great ones</L>
<L>I put off <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n y<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>r f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>vour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sylli.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> doe wisely.</L>
<L>Exceeding wisely! and when I have said,</L>
<L>I thanke you for'<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, be happy<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>And good reason,</L>
<L>In having such a blessing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syl.</SPEAKER>
<L>When yo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ve it,</L>
<L>Bat the baite is not yet ready. Stay <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he time,</L>
<L>While I triumph by my selfe, King, by your leave,</L>
<L>I have wip'd your royall nose, without a napkin,</L>
<L>You may cry willow, willow, for your brother,</L>
<L>I'll onely say goe by; for my fine favourite,</L>
<L>He may gra<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>, where b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>is <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> may wate<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Like a puppies ore a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t, while <HI>Sylli</HI></L>
<L>Out of his <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>wo-leav'd cherry-stone dish drinkes <HI>Nectar</HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>I cannot hold out any longer; he<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>v'n forgive me,</L>
<L>'Tis not tho first oath, I have broke, I must take</L>
<L>A little for a preparative.
<STAGE><HI>Offers <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> ki<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>se &amp; embrace her.</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Ca<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></HI></SPEAKER>
<L>By no meanes.</L>
<L><PB REF="36"/>If you forsweare your selfe we shall not prosper.</L>
<L>I'll rather loose my longing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sylli.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pret<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y soule!</L>
<L>How c<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ull it is of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e! let m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sse yet</L>
<L>Thy little dai<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ty foot <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>or't: that I <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m sure</L>
<L>Is out of my oath.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, if thou canst dispense with't</L>
<L>So fa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>e, I'll not be scrupulous; such a favour</L>
<L>My amorous shoomak<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r ste<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>les<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syl.</SPEAKER>
<L>O most rare leather!
<STAGE><HI>Kisses her shooe oft<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n</HI></STAGE></L>
<L>I doe begin at the lowest, but in time</L>
<L>I may g<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ow higher.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fie, you dwell too long there<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Rise, preth<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> rise<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
<STAGE><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Clarinda hast<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ly</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syl.</SPEAKER>
<L>O I am up already.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>How I abuse my houres! what newes with thee now?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Off with that gowne, 'tis mine, mine by your pro∣mise</L>
<L><HI>Signior Ador.</HI> is r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>turn'd! now upon entrance;</L>
<L>Off with it, off with it, Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be not so hasty,</L>
<L>Wh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n I goe to bed 'tis thine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syl.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have my grant too;</L>
<L>But doe you heare Lady, though I give way to this,</L>
<L>You must her<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>after aske my leave b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>fore</L>
<L>You part with things of moment.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Very good,</L>
<L>When I am yours, I will be govern'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweet obedience!
<STAGE>Ent. Ador.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are well return'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ador.</SPEAKER>
<L>I wish that the successe</L>
<L>Of my service had deserv'd it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lives <HI>Bertoldo</HI>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ador.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eturn'd with safety.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis not then</L>
<L>In the power of fate to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>dde <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o, or take from</L>
<L>My perfit happinesse: and yet he sho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ld</L>
<L>Have made me his first visit. <HI>Ador.</HI> So I think too</L>
<L>But he</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="37"/>
<SPEAKER>Syl.</SPEAKER>
<L>D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rst not appeare, I being present,</L>
<L>That's his excuse, I warrant you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speake, where is he?</L>
<L>With whom? who hath d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>erv'd mo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e from him? o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Can be of equall merit? I in this</L>
<L>Doe not except the King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ador.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee's at the Palace</L>
<L>With the Du<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>hesse o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <HI>Siena.</HI> One co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ch brought 'em hither.</L>
<L>Without a third. Hee's very gracious with h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r,</L>
<L>You may conceive the rest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>My jealous feares</L>
<L>Make me to apprehend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ador.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray you dismisse</L>
<L>Signior wisdome, and i'll make relation to yo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Of the particulars.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Servant, I would have you</L>
<L>To haste unto the Court.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syl.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will out-runne</L>
<L>A foote-man for your pleasure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>There observe</L>
<L>The Dutchesse traine and entertainment.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Feare not,</L>
<L>I will discover all that is of w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ight</L>
<L>To the liveries of her Pages, and her fo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>temen.</L>
<L>This is fit imployment for me.
<STAGE>Exit Syl.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gracious with</L>
<L>The Dutchesse! sure you said so?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ador.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will use</L>
<L>All possible brevity to enforme you, Madam,</L>
<L>Of what was trusted to me, and discharg'd</L>
<L>With faith and loyall duty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>I beleeve it<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Yo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> ransom'd him, and suppli'd his wants imagine</L>
<L>That is already spoken; and-what vowes</L>
<L>Of service he made to me is apparent;</L>
<L>His joy of me, and wonder too perspicuous;</L>
<L>Does not your <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>ry end so?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ador.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would the end</L>
<L><PB REF="37"/>Had answered the beginning, in a word,</L>
<L>Ingratitude, and perjury at the height</L>
<L>Cannot expresse him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take heed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ador.</SPEAKER>
<L>Truth is arm'd</L>
<L>And can defend it selfe. It must out, Madam.</L>
<L>I saw, the presence full, the amorous Dutchesse</L>
<L>Kisse and embrace him, on his part accepted</L>
<L>With equall ardor, and their willing hands</L>
<L>No sooner joyn'd, but a remove was publish'd,</L>
<L>And put in execution.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>The proofes are</L>
<L>Too pregnant. <HI>O Bertoldo!</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ador.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee's not worth</L>
<L>Your sorrow, Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tell mee, when you saw this</L>
<L>Did not you grieve as I do now to heare it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ador.</SPEAKER>
<L>His precipice from goodnesse raising mine,</L>
<L>And serving as a foyle to set my faith off,</L>
<L>I had little reason.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>In this you confesse</L>
<L>The divellish malice of your disposition.</L>
<L>As you were a man, you stood bound to lament it,</L>
<L>And not in flattery of false your hopes</L>
<L>To glory in it: when good men pursue</L>
<L>The path mark'd out by vertue, the bless'd Saints</L>
<L>VVith joy looke on it, and Seraphique Angels</L>
<L>Clap their celestiall wings in heavenly plaudits,</L>
<L>To be a scene of grace so well presented,</L>
<L>The fiends and men made up of envy mourning;</L>
<L>VVhere as now on the contray as far</L>
<L>As their divinity can partake of passion,</L>
<L>VVith me they weepe, beholding a faire Temple</L>
<L>Built in <HI>Bertoldo's</HI> loyalty turn'd to ashes</L>
<L>By the flames of his inconstancy, the damn'd</L>
<L>Rejoycing in the object: 'Tis not well</L>
<L>In you <HI>Adorni.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adorni.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhat a temper dwells</L>
<L>In this rare Virgin, can you pitty him</L>
<L>That hath shown none to you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="38"/>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must not be</L>
<L>Cruell by his example, you perhaps,</L>
<L>Expept now I should seeke recovery</L>
<L>Of what I have lost by teares, and with bent knees</L>
<L>Begge his compassion. No; my towring vertue</L>
<L>From the assurance of my merit scornes</L>
<L>To stoope so low. I'll take a nobler course,</L>
<L>And confident in the justice of my cause,</L>
<L>The King his brother, and new M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>stresse, judges,</L>
<L>Ravish him from her armes, you have the contract</L>
<L>In which he swore to marry her?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adorn.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis here Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>He shal be then against his wil my husband,</L>
<L>And when I have him, I'll so use him, doubt not,</L>
<L>But that your honesty being unquestion'd,</L>
<L>This writing with your testimony cleares all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ador.</SPEAKER>
<L>And buries me in the darke mists of error.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'll presently to Court, pray you give order</L>
<L>For my caroch.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adorn.</SPEAKER>
<L>A ca<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t for mee were sitter</L>
<L>To hurry me to the gallowes
<STAGE><HI>Exit Adorni<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>O false men!</L>
<L>Inconstant! perjur'd! my good Angell helpe mee</L>
<L>In these my extremities!
<STAGE>Enter Syll.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Syl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>i.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>If you ever will see brave sight,</L>
<L>Lose it not now. <HI>Bertoldo,</HI> and the Dutchesse</L>
<L>Are presently to be married. There's such pompe</L>
<L>And preparation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>If I marry, 'tis</L>
<L>This day or never.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sylli.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why with all my heart,</L>
<L>Though I break this, I'll keep the next oath I make</L>
<L>A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d then it is quit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Follow mee to my Cabinet,</L>
<L>You know my confessor, Father <HI>Paulo</HI>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syll.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes. Shall he</L>
<L>Doe the feate for us?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will give in writing</L>
<L><PB REF="38"/>Directions to him, and attire my selfe</L>
<L>Like a Virgin-bride, and something I will doe</L>
<L>That shall deserve mens praise, and wonder too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syl.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I to make all know, I am not shallow</L>
<L>Will have my points of Cuechineale and yellow.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. V. SCENE. II.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Lowd Musicke.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Astutio. Gonzaga. Roderigo. Iacomo. Pi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rio. Roberto. Bertoldo. Aurelia. Bishop.</HI> with Attendants.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rober.</SPEAKER>
<L>HAd our division beene greater, Madam,</L>
<L>Your clemency, the wrong being done to you</L>
<L>In pardon of it, l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ke the rod of concord</L>
<L>Must make a perfect union, once more</L>
<L>With a brotherly affection we receive you</L>
<L>Into our favour. Let it be your study</L>
<L>Hereafter to deserve this blessing, farre</L>
<L>Beyond your merit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Bert<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>As the Princesse grace</L>
<L>To me is without limit, my endeavours</L>
<L>With all obsequiousnesse to serve her pleasures</L>
<L>Shall know no bounds, nor will I being made</L>
<L>Her husband, forget the duty that</L>
<L>I owe her as a servant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurel.</SPEAKER>
<L>I expect not</L>
<L>But faire equality, since I well know</L>
<L>If that superiority be d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e</L>
<L>'Tis not to me, When you are made my consor<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>All the prerogatives of my high birth cancell'd</L>
<L>I'll practise the obedience of a wis<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</L>
<L>And freely pay it. Queenes themselves, if they</L>
<L>Make choice of their inferiors, onely aiming</L>
<L>To feed their sensuall appetites, and to raigne</L>
<L>Over their husbands, in some kinde commit</L>
<L><PB REF="39"/>Authoriz'd whoredome, nor will I be guilty</L>
<L>In my intent of such a crime.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gonza.</SPEAKER>
<L>This done,</L>
<L>As it is promis'd, Madam, may well stand for</L>
<L>A president to great women: but when once</L>
<L>The griping h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nger of desire is cloyd,</L>
<L>(And the poore foole advanc'd, brought on his kn<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></L>
<L>Most of your Eagle breed, I'll not say all</L>
<L>(Ever excepting you) challenge againe,</L>
<L>What in hot blood they parted from.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurel.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are ever.</L>
<L>An enemy of our sex, but you I hope Sir</L>
<L>Have better thoughts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>I dare not entertaine</L>
<L>An ill one of your goodnesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>To my power</L>
<L>I will enable him to prevent all danger</L>
<L>Envy can raise against your choice. One word m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re</L>
<L>Touching the Articles.
<STAGE>Enter Ful. Cam. Syl. Ador.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fulgen.</SPEAKER>
<L>In you alone</L>
<L>Lie all my hopes, you can or kill or save me,</L>
<L>But pitty in you, will become you better,</L>
<L>(Though I confesse in justice 'tis deni'd me)</L>
<L>Then too much rigor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will make your peace</L>
<L>As far as it lyes in me, but must first</L>
<L>Labour to ri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ht my selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or adde or alter</L>
<L>VVhat you thinke fit. In him I have my all,</L>
<L>Heaven make me thankfull for him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>On to the Temple</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay royall Sir, and as you are a King</L>
<L>Erect one here, in doing justice to</L>
<L>An injur'd mayd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurel.</SPEAKER>
<L>How's this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>O I am blasted!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have given so<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> proofe, sweet Lady, of my prompt∣nes</L>
<L>To doe you right, you need not therefore doubt me,</L>
<L>And rest assur'd, that this great worke dispatch'd,</L>
<L>You shall have audience and satisfaction</L>
<L><PB REF="39"/>To all you can demand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>To doe mee justice</L>
<L>Exacts your present care, and can admit</L>
<L>Of no delay. If e'r my cause be heard</L>
<L>In favour of your brother, you go<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> on Sir,</L>
<L>Your scepter cannot right mee. Hee's the man,</L>
<L>The guilty man, whom I accuse, and you</L>
<L>Stand bound in duty, as you are Supreame,</L>
<L>To be impartiall. Since you are a Iudge,</L>
<L>As a Delinquent, looke on him, and not</L>
<L>As on a brother; justice painted blinde</L>
<L>Inferres, her Ministers a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e oblig'd to heare</L>
<L>The cause and truth, the I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>dge determine of it,</L>
<L>And not sway'd, or by favour, or affection,</L>
<L>By a false glosse, or wrested comment alter</L>
<L>The true intent, and letter of the law.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor will I Madam,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurel.</SPEAKER>
<L>You seeme troubl'd, Sir,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gonz.</SPEAKER>
<L>His colour changes too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>The alteration</L>
<L>Growes from his guilt. The goodnesse of my cause</L>
<L>Begets such confidence in mee, that I bring</L>
<L>No hir'd tongue to plead for mee, that with gay</L>
<L>Rhetoricall flourishes may palli<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>e</L>
<L>That, which stripp'd naked, will appeare deform'd.</L>
<L>I stand here, mine owne advocate; and my <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ruth</L>
<L>Deliver'd in the plainest language, will</L>
<L>Make good it selfe, nor will I, if the King</L>
<L>Give suffrage to it, but admit of you,</L>
<L>My greatest enemy, and this stranger Prince,</L>
<L>To sit assistants with him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurel.</SPEAKER>
<L>I ne'r wrong'd you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>In your knowledge of the injury, I believe it,</L>
<L>Nor will you in your justice, when you are</L>
<L>Acquainted with my interest in this man</L>
<L>Which I lay claime to.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Roberto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let us take our seats,</L>
<L>What is your title to him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="40"/>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>By this contract</L>
<L>Seal'd solemnely before a reveren'd man,</L>
<L>I challenge him for my husband.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sylli.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha. was I</L>
<L>Sent for the Frier, for this? O <HI>Sylli! Sylli</HI>!</L>
<L>Some cordiall, or I faint.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rober.</SPEAKER>
<L>This writing is</L>
<L>Authenticall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rel.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>But done in heat of blood,</L>
<L>(Charm'd by her flatteries, as no doubt he was)</L>
<L>To be dispens'd with.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Adde this, if you please,</L>
<L>The distance and disparity betweene</L>
<L>Their births and fortunes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>What can inocence hope for</L>
<L>When such as sit her jugdes, are corrupted!</L>
<L>D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sparity of birth, or fortune urge you?</L>
<L>Or <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>yren</HI> charmes? or at his best in mee,</L>
<L>Wants to deserve him? Call some few daies backe,</L>
<L>And as he was, consider him, and you</L>
<L>Must grant him my inferiour. Imagine</L>
<L>You saw him now in fetters with his honour,</L>
<L>His liberty lost; with her blacke wings despaire</L>
<L>Circling his miseries, and his <HI>Gonzaga.</HI></L>
<L>Trampling on his afflictions; the great summe</L>
<L>Propos'd for his redemption; the King</L>
<L>Forbidding payment of it; this neere kinsmen,</L>
<L>With his protesting followers, and friends,</L>
<L>Falling off from him; by the whole world forsaken;</L>
<L>Dead to all hope, and buried in the grave</L>
<L>Of his calamities, and then waigh duly</L>
<L>What she deserv'd (whose merits now are doubted)</L>
<L>That as his better Angell in her bounties</L>
<L>Appeard unto him, his great ransome pa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>d,</L>
<L>His wants, and with a prodigall hand suppli'd,</L>
<L>Whether then being my manumised slave,</L>
<L>Hee ow'd not himselfe to mee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is this true?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="40"/>
<SPEAKER>Roberto.</SPEAKER>
<L>In his silence 'tis acknoledg'd</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gonzag.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you want</L>
<L>A witne<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>e to this purpose, I'll depose it:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>If I have dwel<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> too long on my deserving<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>To this unthankfull man, pray you pardon me,</L>
<L>The cause requir'd it. And though now I adde</L>
<L>A little in my painting to the life</L>
<L>His barbarous ingratitude, to deterre,</L>
<L>Others from imitation, let it meet with</L>
<L>A faire interpretation. This se<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pent,</L>
<L>Frozen to numnesse, was no sooner warm'd</L>
<L>In the bosome of my pitty, and compassion,</L>
<L>But in returne, he ruin'de his preserver</L>
<L>The prints the yrons had made in his flesh</L>
<L>Still ulcerous; but all that I had done</L>
<L>(My benefits in sand, or water written)</L>
<L>As they had never beene, no more remembred.</L>
<L>And on what ground; but his ambitious hopes</L>
<L>To gaine this Duchesse favour,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurelia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, the object,</L>
<L>Looke on it better (Lady) may excuse</L>
<L>The charge of his affection.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Camiol.</SPEAKER>
<L>The object</L>
<L>In wha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>? forgiue mee, modesty, if I say</L>
<L>You looke upon your forme in the false glasse</L>
<L>Of flattery, and selfe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> love, and that dece<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ves you,</L>
<L>That you were a Duchesse, as I take it, was not</L>
<L>Character'd on your face, and that not seene,</L>
<L>For other feature, make all these that are</L>
<L>Experienc'd in women, judges of 'em,</L>
<L>And if they are not Parasites, they must grant</L>
<L>For beauty without art, though you storme at it,</L>
<L>I may take <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he righ hand file.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gonzaga.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well said i'faith;</L>
<L>I see faire women on no termes will yeeld</L>
<L>Priority in beauty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Camiol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Downe proud heart!</L>
<L>Why doe I rise up in defence of that,</L>
<L><PB REF="41"/>Which, in my cherishing of it hath vndone mee.</L>
<L>No Madam, I recant, you are all beauty,</L>
<L>Goodnesse, and vertue, and poore I not worthy</L>
<L>As a soyle to set you off; enioy your conquest</L>
<L>But doe not tyranize. Yet as I am</L>
<L>In my lownesse from your height, you may looke on me,</L>
<L>And in your suffrage to me, make him know</L>
<L>That though to all men else I did appeare</L>
<L>The shame and scorne of women, hee stands bound</L>
<L>To hold me as her master-piece.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Roberto.</SPEAKER>
<L>By my life</L>
<L>You have show'n your selfe of such an abject temper,</L>
<L>So poore, and low conditiou'd, as I grieve for</L>
<L>Your neerenesse to mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>F<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rd.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>I am chang'd in my</L>
<L>Opinion of you Lady, and professe</L>
<L>The vertues of your minde, an ample fortune</L>
<L>For an absolute Monarch.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gonzaga.</SPEAKER>
<L>Since you are resolv'd</L>
<L>To damne your selfe, in your forsaking of</L>
<L>Your noble order for a woman, doe it</L>
<L>For this. You may search through the world, and meet not</L>
<L>With such another <HI>P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oenix.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurel.</SPEAKER>
<L>On the sudden</L>
<L>I feele all fires of love quench'd in the water</L>
<L>Of compassion, make your peace; you have</L>
<L>My free consent; for here I doe disclaime</L>
<L>All interest in you: and to further your</L>
<L>Desires, faire Maid, compos'd of worth and honour,</L>
<L>The dispensation procur'd by mee,</L>
<L>Fr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eing <HI>Bertoldo</HI> from his vow, makes way</L>
<L>To your embraces.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bertol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, how have I stray'd,</L>
<L>And wilfully, out of the noble tract</L>
<L>Mark'd mee by vertue! 'Till now, I was never</L>
<L>Truely a prisoner; to excuse my late</L>
<L>Captivity, I might alleage the malice</L>
<L>Of fortune; you that conquer'd me confessing</L>
<L><PB REF="41"/>Courage in my defence was no way wanting</L>
<L>But now I have surrendred up my strengths</L>
<L>Into the power of vice, and on my forehead</L>
<L>Branded with mine owne hand in capitall letters</L>
<L>D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sloyall, and Ingratefull, though barr'd from</L>
<L>Humane society, and hiss'd into</L>
<L>Some desert nere yet haunted with the curses</L>
<L>Of men and women, sitting as a judge</L>
<L>Vpon my guilty selfe, I must confesse</L>
<L>It justly falls upon me, and one teare</L>
<L>Shed in compassion of my suffrings more.</L>
<L>Then I can hope for.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>This compunc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ion</L>
<L>For the wrong that you have done me, though you should</L>
<L>Fix h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re, and your true sorrow move no further,</L>
<L>Will in respect I lov'd once, make these eies</L>
<L>Two springs of sorrow for you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>In your pittie</L>
<L>My cruelty shewes more monstrous, yet I am not,</L>
<L>Though most ingratfull, grown to such a height</L>
<L>Of impudence, as in my wishes onely</L>
<L>To aske your pardon. If as now I fall</L>
<L>Prostrate before your feete, you will vouchsafe</L>
<L>To act your owne revenge, treading upon me</L>
<L>As a viper eating through the bowels of</L>
<L>Your benefits, to whom with libertie</L>
<L>I owe my being, 'twill take from the burthen</L>
<L>That now is insupportable.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray you rise,</L>
<L>As I wish peace, and quiet to my soule</L>
<L>I do forgive you heartily, yet excuse me:</L>
<L>Though I deny my selfe a blessing that</L>
<L>By the favour of the Dutchesse seconded,</L>
<L>With your submission is offer'd to me</L>
<L>Let not the reason I alleage for't grieve you,</L>
<L>You have been false once. I have done. And if</L>
<L>When I am married (as this day I will be)</L>
<L>As a perfit signe of your attonement with me</L>
<L>You wish <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e joy, I will <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eceive it for</L>
<L><PB REF="42"/>Full satisfaction of all obligations</L>
<L>In which you stand bound to me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will doe it,</L>
<L>And what's more, in despite of sorrow, live</L>
<L>To see my selfe vndone, beyond all hope</L>
<L>To be made up againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syl.</SPEAKER>
<L>My blood begins</L>
<L>To come to my heart againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray you <HI>Signior Syl.</HI></L>
<L>Call in the holy Frier. Hee's prepar'd</L>
<L>For finishing the worke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syl.</SPEAKER>
<L>I knew I was</L>
<L>The man. Heaven make mee thankfull</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who is this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Astu.</SPEAKER>
<L>His Father was the banker of <HI>Palermo,</HI></L>
<L>And this the heyre of his great wealth, his wisdome</L>
<L>Was not hereditarie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Though you know me not,</L>
<L>Your Majesty owes me a round Sum, I have</L>
<L>A se<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>le, or two to witnesse, yet if you please</L>
<L>To weare my colours, and dance at my wedding<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>I'll never sue you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I'll grant yo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r suite,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Syl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Gracio<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s <HI>Maddona,</HI> Noble, Generall,</L>
<L>Brave Captaines and my quondam rivalls we<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r 'em</L>
<L>Since I am confident you dare not harbour</L>
<L>A thought, but that way currant.
<STAGE>Exit</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurel.</SPEAKER>
<L>For my part</L>
<L>I cannot ghesse the issue.
<STAGE>Enter Syl. with</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do your duty,</L>
<L>And with all speed you can, you may despatch us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Paulo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thus as a principal ornament to the Church</L>
<L>I sea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<L>How.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Ro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>So young and so religious.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pau.</SPEAKER>
<L>She has forsooke the world.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syl.</SPEAKER>
<L>And <HI>Syllie</HI> too,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> shall run mad.
<STAGE><HI>Syl thrust o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hence with the foole, proceede Sir</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="42"/>
<SPEAKER>Pau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Looke on this maid of honor now</L>
<L>Truely honor'd in her vow</L>
<L>She payes to heaven, vaine delight</L>
<L>By day, or pleasure of, the night,</L>
<L>She no more thinkes of this faire haire</L>
<L>(Favours for great kings to weare)</L>
<L>M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>w now be shorn. Her rich array</L>
<L>Chang'd into a homely gray.</L>
<L>The dainties with which she was fed</L>
<L>And her proud flesh pampered,</L>
<L>Must not be tasted, from the spring,</L>
<L>For wine<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> cold water we will bring</L>
<L>And with fasting mortifie</L>
<L>The feasts of sensuali<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y.</L>
<L>Her jewells, beads, and she must looke</L>
<L>Not in a glasse, but holy booke;</L>
<L>To teach her the nere erring way</L>
<L>To immortality. O may</L>
<L>She as she purposes to be</L>
<L>A Child new borne to piety,</L>
<L>Persever in in it, and good men</L>
<L>With Saints and Angels say Amen</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is the marriage! this the port! to which</L>
<L>My vowes must steere me, fill my spreading sayles</L>
<L>With the pure wind of your devotions for me,</L>
<L>That I may touch the secure haven, where</L>
<L>Eternall happinesse keepes her reside n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e,</L>
<L>Temptations to frailty never entring.</L>
<L>I am dead to the world, and thus dispose</L>
<L>Of what I leave behind me, and d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>viding</L>
<L>My state into three parts, I thus bequeath it.</L>
<L>The <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>rst to the faire Nunnery, to which</L>
<L>I dedicate the last, and better part</L>
<L>Of my fraile life; a second portion</L>
<L>To pious uses; and the third to thee</L>
<L><HI>Adorni,</HI> for thy true and faithfull service.</L>
<L>And ere I mytake lu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> farwel with hope</L>
<L>To finde a gran<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, may suite to you is that</L>
<L>You wou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d for my sake pardon this young man</L>
<L><PB REF="43"/>And to his merits love him, and no further.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thus confirme it.
<STAGE>Gives his hand to Fulgen. to Bertoldo</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cami.</SPEAKER>
<L>And as ere you hope</L>
<L>Like me to be made happy, I conjure you</L>
<L>To reassume your order; and in fighting</L>
<L>Bravely against the enemies of our faith</L>
<L>Redeeme your morgag'd honor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>I restore this
<STAGE>The white crosse.</STAGE></L>
<L>Once more brothers in armes,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'll live and die so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>To you my pious wishes. And to end</L>
<L>All differences, great Sir I beseech you</L>
<L>To be an arbitrator, and compound</L>
<L>The quarrell, long continuing betweene</L>
<L>The Duke and Dutchesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rober.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'll take it into</L>
<L>My speciall care.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am then at rest, now father
<STAGE>Exeunt Paulo. &amp; Camiola.</STAGE></L>
<L>Conduct me where you please.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>She well deserves</L>
<L>Her name, t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e Maid of Honor! <HI>Mny</HI> she stand</L>
<L>To all posterity, a faire example,</L>
<L>For noble Maides to imitate. Since to live</L>
<L>In wealth and pleasure is common; but to part with</L>
<L>Such poyson'd baites is rare, there being nothing</L>
<L>Vpon this S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oge of life to be commended,</L>
<L>Though well begun, till it be fully ended.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<TRAILER>The END.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

