<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2003-03-12</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Olivia Bottum</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Checked for TYPE="book". Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, etc.). Checked for signatures. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, and UNCLEARs. Corrected 19 $-groups by inserting appropriate letters. Checked for EPIGRAPHs and ARGUMENTs. Checked for startqs, endqs, oes, q;s, and Qs. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Checked for CLOSERs, TRAILERs, and BYLINEs. DONE 2003-03-12.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A07367">
<STC T="S">17750</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99849687</BIBNO>
<VID>14849</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>THE CITYE MATCH.</P>
<P>A COMOEDYE.</P>
<P>PRESENTED TO THE KING and QVEENE AT WHITE-HALL.</P>
<P>ACTED SINCE AT BLACK-FRIERS BY HIS MAIESTIES <HI>Servants.</HI></P>
<Q><BIBL>HORAT. de Arte Poet.</BIBL>
<P>Versibus exponi Tragicis res Comica non vult.</P></Q>
<P><HI>OXFORD,</HI> Printed by LEONARD LICHFIELD, Printer to the UNIVERSITY.</P>
<P><HI>Anno Dom.</HI> M. DC. XXXIX.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="to the reader">
<PB REF="2"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="3"/>
<PB REF="3"/>
<HEAD>TO THE READER</HEAD>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">T</SEG>He Author of this Poem, knowing how hardly the best things protect themselves from censure, had no ambition to make it this way publique. Holding workes of this light nature to be things which need an Apologie for being written at all. Nor estee∣ming otherwise of them, whose abilities in this kinde are most passable, then of Masquers, who spangle, &amp; glitter for the time, but tis through tinsell. As it was meerly out of Obe∣dience that he first wrote it, so when it was made, had it not been commanded from him, it had died upon the place, where it took life. Himselfe being so averse from raysing fame from the stage, that at the prefentment, he was one of the severest spectators there; nor ever show'd other signe whereby it might be knowne to be his, but his liberty to de∣spise it. Yet he hath at length consented it should passe the Presse; not with an Ayme to purchase a new Reputation, but to keep that which he hath already from growing worse. For understanding that some at <HI>London,</HI> without his Ap∣probation or allowance, were ready to print a false, imper∣fect Coppy, he was loth to be libell'd by his owne worke; or that his Play should appeare to the world with more then its own faults. <HI>Farewell.</HI></P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="prologue">
<PB REF="4"/>
<HEAD>THE PROLOGVE TO THE KING AND QUEENE.</HEAD>
<L>THE Author, Royall Sir, so dreads this Night,</L>
<L>As if for writing he were doomd to th'sight.</L>
<L>Or else, unlesse you doe protect his fame,</L>
<L>Y' had sav'd his Play, and sentenc'd him to th' flame.</L>
<L>For though your name, or power, were ith'reprive,</L>
<L>Such workes, he thinks, are but condemn'd to live.</L>
<L>Which, for this place being rescued from the fire,</L>
<L>Take ruine from th'advancement, and fall higher.</L>
<L>Though None, he hopes, sit here upon his wit,</L>
<L>As if he Poems did, or Playes commit.</L>
<L>Yet he must needs feare censure, that feares prayse,</L>
<L>Nor would write still wer't to succeed ith' Bayes.</L>
<L>For he is not oth' trade, nor would excell</L>
<L>In this kinde, where tis lightnesse to doe well.</L>
<L>Yet as the Gods refin'd base things, and some</L>
<L>Beasts foule ith' Heard grevv pure ith' Hecatombe;</L>
<L>And as the Oxe prepar'd, and crowned Bull</L>
<L>Are Offerings, though kept back, and Altars full:</L>
<L>So, Mighty Sir, this sacrifice being neere</L>
<L>The Knife at Oxford, which y' have kindled here,</L>
<L>He hopes twill from you, and the Queene, grow cleane,</L>
<L>And turne t' Oblation, what He meant a Scene.</L>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="prologue">
<PB REF="4"/>
<HEAD>THE PROLOGVE AT BLACK-FRIERS.</HEAD>
<L>WEre it his trade, the Author bid me say,</L>
<L>Perchance he'd beg you would be good to th' Play.</L>
<L>And I, to set him up in Reputation,</L>
<L>Should hold a Bason forth for Approbation.</L>
<L>But praise so gain'd, He thinks, were a Reliefe</L>
<L>Able to make his Comoedy a Briefe.</L>
<L>For where your pitty must your judgement be,</L>
<L>Tis not a Play, but you fir'd houses see.</L>
<L>Look not his quill, then, should petitions run;</L>
<L>No Gathering's heere into a Prologue spun.</L>
<L>Whither their sold Scenes be dislikt, or hit,</L>
<L>Are cares for them who eat by th' stage, and wit.</L>
<L>He's One, whose unbought Muse did never feare</L>
<L>An Empty second day, or a thinne share;</L>
<L>But can make th' Actors, though you come not twice,</L>
<L>No Loosers, since we act now at the Kings price.</L>
<L>Who hath made this Play publique, and the same</L>
<L>Power that makes Lawes, redeem'd this from the flame.</L>
<L>For th' Author builds no fame, nor doth aspire</L>
<L>To praise, from that which he condemn'd to th' fire.</L>
<L>He's thus secure, then, that he cannot winne</L>
<L>A Censure sharper then his own hath beene.</L>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dramatis personae">
<PB REF="5"/>
<HEAD>The Persons of the Play.</HEAD>
<LIST>
<LABEL>Warehouse.</LABEL>
<ITEM>An old Merchant.</ITEM>
<LABEL>Frank Plotwell.</LABEL>
<ITEM>His Nephew.</ITEM>
<LABEL>Cypher.</LABEL>
<ITEM>His Factor.</ITEM>
<LABEL>Baneswright.</LABEL>
<ITEM>Old Plotwell disguised.</ITEM>
<LABEL>Madam Aurelia.</LABEL>
<ITEM>Penelope Plotwell his daughter.</ITEM>
<LABEL>Seathrift.</LABEL>
<ITEM>A Merchant.</ITEM>
<LABEL><HI>M</HI><SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Seathrift.</HI></LABEL>
<ITEM>His Wife.</ITEM>
<LABEL>Timothy.</LABEL>
<ITEM>His Sonne.</ITEM>
<LABEL>Dorcas.</LABEL>
<ITEM>Susan Seathrift his daughter.</ITEM>
<LABEL>Bright.</LABEL>
<ITEM>Two Templers.</ITEM>
<LABEL>Newcut.</LABEL>
<ITEM>Two Templers.</ITEM>
<LABEL><HI>M</HI><SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Scruple.</HI></LABEL>
<ITEM>A Puritan Schoolemistresse.</ITEM>
<LABEL><HI>M</HI><SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Holland.</HI></LABEL>
<ITEM>A Seamster on the Exchange.</ITEM>
<LABEL>Quartfield.</LABEL>
<ITEM>A Captaine.</ITEM>
<LABEL>Salewit.</LABEL>
<ITEM>A Poet.</ITEM>
<LABEL>Roseclappe.</LABEL>
<ITEM>One that keeps an Ordinary.</ITEM>
<LABEL>Mill.</LABEL>
<ITEM>His wife.</ITEM>
<LABEL>Prentice.</LABEL>
<ITEM></ITEM>
<LABEL>Two Footmen.</LABEL>
<ITEM></ITEM>
<LABEL>Boy that sings.</LABEL>
<ITEM></ITEM>
</LIST>
<P>The SCENE LONDON.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 N="1" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="5"/>
<HEAD>ACTVS I.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA I.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Ware-house. Seathrift.</STAGE>
<L>I Promise you 'twill be a most rare plot.</L>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ware-h.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Citty, M<SUP>r</SUP> Seathrift, never yet</L>
<L>Brought forth the like; J would have them that have</L>
<L>Fin'd twice for Sheriffe mend it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seath.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mend it? Why</L>
<L>Tis past the wit oth' Court of Aldermen.</L>
<L>Next Merchant Taylor that writes Chronicles</L>
<L>Will put us in.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ware-h.</SPEAKER>
<L>For, since I tooke him home,</L>
<L>Though, Sir, my Nephew, as you may observe,</L>
<L>Seeme quite transfigur'd, be as dutifull</L>
<L>As a new prentice; in his talke declaime</L>
<L>Gainst revelling Companions, be as hard</L>
<L>To be entic'd from home as my doore posts▪</L>
<L>This reformation may but be his part,</L>
<L>And he may act his vertues. I have not</L>
<L>Forgot his riots at the Temple. You know S<SUP>r</SUP>—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seath.</SPEAKER>
<L>You told me M<SUP>r</SUP> <HI>Warehouse.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ware-h.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not the sea</L>
<L>When it devour'd my ships cost me so much</L>
<L>As did his vanities. A voyage to th' Indyes</L>
<L>Has been lost in a night. His dayly suits</L>
<L>Were worth more then the stock that set me up.</L>
<L>For which he knew none but the Silk-mans book,</L>
<L>And studied that more then the Law. He had</L>
<L>His Loves too, and his Mistresses; was enterd</L>
<L>Among the philosophicall Madams, was</L>
<L>As great with them as their Concerners, and I heare</L>
<L>Kept one of them in pension.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seath.</SPEAKER>
<L>My sonne too</L>
<L>Hath had his Errours; I could tell the time</L>
<L>When all the wine which I put off by whole sale</L>
<L>He took againe in quarts, and at the day</L>
<L>Vintners have paid me with his large scores. But</L>
<L>He is reformed too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ware-h.</SPEAKER>
<L>S<SUP>r</SUP>, we now are friends</L>
<L>In a designe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seath.</SPEAKER>
<L>And hope to be in time</L>
<L>Friends in Allyance, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ware-h.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile be free,</L>
<L>I think well of your sonne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seath.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who, Timothy?</L>
<L><PB N="2" REF="6"/>Believ't a vertuous boy, and for his sister</L>
<L>A very Saint.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ware-h.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mistake me not, I have</L>
<L>The like opinion of my Nephew, Sir,</L>
<L>Yet he is young, and so is your sonne, nor</L>
<L>Doth the Church-book say they are past our feares.</L>
<L>Our presence is their bridle now: Tis good</L>
<L>To know them well whom we doe make our Heires.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seath.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is most true.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ware-h.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, and how shall wee knowe</L>
<L>How They will use their fortune, or what place</L>
<L>We have in their affection without tryall?</L>
<L>Some wise men build their own Tombes, let us try</L>
<L>If we were dead whether our Heires vvould cry,</L>
<L>Or their long clokes: this plot vvill do't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seath.</SPEAKER>
<L>Twill make us</L>
<L>Famous upon the Exchange for ever. Ile home</L>
<L>And take leave of my vvife and sonne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ware-h.</SPEAKER>
<L>And Ile</L>
<L>Come to you at your Garden house▪ vvithin there.
<STAGE>Ex. Seath.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Cypher.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA II.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Warehouse. Cypher.</STAGE>
<L>NOvv <HI>Cypher,</HI> where's my Nephew?</L>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyph.</SPEAKER>
<L>In the Hall</L>
<L>Reading a letter vvhich a footman brought</L>
<L>Just now to him from a Lady Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ware-h.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Lady?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, Sir, a Lady in distresse; for I</L>
<L>Could overheare the fellow say she must</L>
<L>Sell her Coach Horses, and returne againe</L>
<L>To her Needle, if your Nephew not supply her</L>
<L>With mony.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ware-h.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is some honourable seamstresse.</L>
<L>I'me now confirmd: They say he keeps a Lady,</L>
<L>And this is she. well <HI>Cypher,</HI> tis too late</L>
<L>To change my project now. Be sure you keep</L>
<L>A Diary of his Actions, strictly marke</L>
<L>What company comes to him, if he stirre</L>
<L>Out of my house observe the place he enters.</L>
<L>Watch him till he come out: follow him disguised</L>
<L>To all his haunts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyph.</SPEAKER>
<L>He shall not want a spy Sir.</L>
<L>But Sir when you are absent if he draw not</L>
<L><PB N="3" REF="6"/>A Lattice to your doore, and hang a bush out—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ware-h.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hope he will not make my house a Taverne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir I'me no Sybils sonne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ware-h.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace here he comes.
<STAGE>Enter Plotwell in a sad posture.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA III.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Ware-house. Plotwell. Cypher.</STAGE>
<L>Good morrow Nephew: how now? sad? how comes</L>
<L>This melancholy?</L>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can I choose but weare</L>
<L>Clowdes in my face when I must venture, Sir,</L>
<L>Your reverend age to a long doubtfull voyage</L>
<L>And not partake your dangers?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ware-h.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fye, these feares</L>
<L>Though they become you, Nephew, are ominous.</L>
<L>When heard you from your Father?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw:</SPEAKER>
<L>Never since</L>
<L>He made the escape Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ware-h.</SPEAKER>
<L>I heare he is in Ireland:</L>
<L>I'st true he tooke your sister with him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>So</L>
<L>Her Mistresse thinks, Sir, one day she left the Exchange,</L>
<L>And has not since been heard of.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ware-h.</SPEAKER>
<L>And Nephew</L>
<L>How like you your new course? which place preferre you</L>
<L>The Temple or Exchange? where are, think you,</L>
<L>The wealthier Mines in the Indies, or</L>
<L>Westminster Hall?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir my desires take measure</L>
<L>And forme from yours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ware-h.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay tell me your minde plainely,</L>
<L>Ith' City tongue. I'de have you speake like <HI>Cypher.</HI></L>
<L>I doe not like queint figures, they doe smell</L>
<L>Too much o'th Innes of Court.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, my obedience</L>
<L>Is ready for all impressions which—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ware-h.</SPEAKER>
<L>Againe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir I preferre your kinde of life, a Merchant</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ware-h.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis spoken like my Nephew: Now I like you.</L>
<L>Nor shall I ere repent the benefits</L>
<L>I have bestow'd, but will forget all Errours,
<STAGE>Exit Cyph.</STAGE></L>
<L>As meere seducements: And will not only be</L>
<L>An Unkle but a Father to you: But then</L>
<L>You must be constant, Nephew.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Else I were blind</L>
<L>To my good fortune, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ware-h.</SPEAKER>
<L>Think man how it may</L>
<L><PB N="4" REF="7"/>In time make thee oth' Citie Senate, and raise thee▪</L>
<L>To th' sword and Cap of Maintenance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>(Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, &amp; make me</L>
<L>Sentence light bread, and pownds of butter on horse-back.)</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ware-h.</SPEAKER>
<L>Have Gates and Conduits dated from thy yeare▪</L>
<L>Ride to the Spittle on thy free beast.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>(Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes,</L>
<L>Free of your Company.)</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ware-h.</SPEAKER>
<L>Have the people vaile</L>
<L>As low to his trappings as if he thrice had fined</L>
<L>For that good times imployment.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>(Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or as if</L>
<L>He had his Riders vvisdome.)</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ware-h.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then the workes</L>
<L>And good deeds of the Citie to goe before Thee,</L>
<L>Besides a troop of Varlets.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>(Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, and I</L>
<L>To sleep the sermon in my Chaine and Scarlet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ware-h.</SPEAKER>
<L>How say you? Lets heare that.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>I say, Sir, I</L>
<L>To sit at sermon in my chaine and scarlet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ware-h.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis right, and be remembred at the Crosse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>And then at Sessions, Sir, and all times else,</L>
<L>Master Recorder to save me the trouble,</L>
<L>And understand things for me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ware-h.</SPEAKER>
<L>All this is possible,</L>
<L>And in the starres and windes: therefore deare Nephew,</L>
<L>You shall pursue this course, and to enable you</L>
<L>In this halfe yeare that I shall be away,</L>
<L><HI>Cypher</HI> shall teach you French, Italian, Spanish,</L>
<L>And other Tongues of Traffique</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall J not learne</L>
<L>Arithmetick too, Sir, and short-hand?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ware-h.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis well</L>
<L>Remembred, yes, and Navigation.
<STAGE>Enter Cypher.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, M<SUP>r</SUP> <HI>Seathrift</HI> saies you 'will loose the tyde,</L>
<L>The boat staies for you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ware-h.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, Nephew, at my return</L>
<L>As J heare of your carriage, you doe know</L>
<L>What my intentions are; and for a Token</L>
<L>How much I trust your reformation,</L>
<L>Take this key of my Counting-house, and spend</L>
<L>Discreetly in my absence. Farwell. Nay</L>
<L>No teares▪ Ile be here sooner then you think on't</L>
<L><HI>Cypher</HI> you know what you have to do.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyph.</SPEAKER>
<L>I warrant you, S<SUP>r</SUP>.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Teares? yes my melting eyes shall run, but it
<STAGE>Exit</STAGE></L>
<L>Shall be such teares as shall encrease the tide</L>
<L>To carry you from hence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come M<SUP>r</SUP> <HI>Plotwell</HI> shall I</L>
<L>Read to you this morning.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Read what? how the price.</L>
<L>Of sugar goes, how many pints of Olives</L>
<L>Goe to a jarre, how long wine workes at sea,</L>
<L><PB N="5" REF="7"/>What difference is in gaine betweene fresh herrings</L>
<L>And herrings red?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyph.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is fine, ha you</L>
<L>Forgot your Uncles charge?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prithee what was't?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyph.</SPEAKER>
<L>To learne the Tongues &amp; Mathematiques.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Troth</L>
<L>If I have tongue enough to say my prayers</L>
<L>Ith' phrase oth' Kingdome J care not; otherwise</L>
<L>I'me for no tongues but dry'd ones, such as will</L>
<L>Give a fine rellish to my backragg; and for Mathematiques,</L>
<L>I hate to travail by the Map, Me thinks
<STAGE>Enter▪ Bright &amp; Newcut.</STAGE></L>
<L>Tis riding post.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyph.</SPEAKER>
<L>I knew twould come to this.</L>
<L>Here be his Camerades.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>What my Fleetstreet friends?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Cypher.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA IV.</HEAD>
<STAGE>To Him Bright and Newcut.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>SAve you Merchant <HI>Plotwell.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Newc.</SPEAKER>
<L>M<SUP>r</SUP> <HI>Plotwell</HI></L>
<L>Citizen and Merchant, save you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is thy Uncle</L>
<L>Gone the wisht voyage?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, he's gone, and if</L>
<L>He dye by th' way hath bequeathd me but some</L>
<L>Twelve hundred pound a yeare in Kent, some three-</L>
<L>Score thousand pound in money, besides Jewels, Bonds,</L>
<L>And desperate debts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<L>And dost not thou fall downe</L>
<L>And pray to th' windes to sacrifice him to</L>
<L>Poore John and Mackrell?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or invoke some rock</L>
<L>To doe thee justice?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or some compendious Canon</L>
<L>To take him off ith' middle?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>And why my tender</L>
<L>Softhearted friends?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>What to take thee from the Temple</L>
<L>To make thee an old Juryman, a Whittington?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<L>To transforme thy plush to pennystone, and scarlet</L>
<L>Into a velvet Jacket which hath seene</L>
<L>Aleppo twice, is knowne to the great Turke,</L>
<L>Hath scapt three shipwracks to be left off to thee,</L>
<L>And knowes the way to Mexico as well as the Map?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>This Jacket surely was imploy'd in finding</L>
<L>The Northeast passage out. Or the same Jacket</L>
<L>That <HI>Coryat</HI> died in.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Very good.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<L>In <HI>Ovid</HI></L>
<L>There is not such a Metamorphosis</L>
<L><PB N="6" REF="8"/>As thou art now. To be turnd into a tree</L>
<L>Or some handsome beast is courtly to this.</L>
<L>But for thee, Franck, O Transmutation!</L>
<L>Of Satin chang'd to Kersy hose I sing.</L>
<L>Slid his shooes shine too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>They have the Gresham dye.</L>
<L>Dost thou not dresse thy selfe by 'em? I can see</L>
<L>My face in them hither.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Very pleasant Gentlemen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>And faith for how many yeares art thou bound?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe you take me for a prentice?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why then what office</L>
<L>Dost thou beare in the parish this yeare? Let's feele,</L>
<L>No batteries in thy head to signifie</L>
<L>Th'art Constable?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>No furious Iugge broke on it</L>
<L>In the Kings name?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did you contrive this scene</L>
<L>By the way Gentlemen?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, but the Newes</L>
<L>Thou shouldst turne Trades-man, and this Pagan dresse,</L>
<L>In which if thou shouldst dye thou wouldst be damned</L>
<L>For an Usurer, is comicall at the Temple.</L>
<L>We were about to bring in such a fellow</L>
<L>For an Apostate in our Antimasque.</L>
<L>Set one to keep the doore, provide halfe-crowne roomes,</L>
<L>For Ile set bills up of thee, what shall I</L>
<L>Give thee for the first day?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, or second?</L>
<L>For thou't endure twice or thrice comming in.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well my conceipted Orient friends, bright Offsprings</L>
<L>Oth' female silkworme, and Taylor male I deny not</L>
<L>But you look well in your unpaid for Glory.</L>
<L>That in these colours you set out the Strand,</L>
<L>And adorne Fleet-street. That you may laugh at me</L>
<L>Poore Working day oth' Citie, like two Festivals</L>
<L>Escapt out of the Almanacke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sirrah <HI>Bright,</HI></L>
<L>Didst look to heare such language beyond Ludgate?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thought all wit had ended at Fleet-bridge.</L>
<L>But wit that goes oth' the score, that may extend</L>
<L>If't be a Courtiers wit into Cheapside.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Mercer lives there does he? I warrant you</L>
<L>He has the patience of a burnt Heretique:</L>
<L>The very faith that sold to you these silkes</L>
<L>And thinks you'l pay for em is strong enough</L>
<L>To save the Infidell part oth' world, or Antichrist.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>W'are most mechannically abused.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let's teare</L>
<L><PB N="7" REF="8"/>His Jacket off.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>A match take that side</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold, hold.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>How fraile a thing old velvet is, it parts
<STAGE>They teare off his Iacket</STAGE></L>
<L>With as much ease and willingnes as two Cowards.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<L>The tenderst weed that ever fell a sunder.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha you your wits? what mean you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe, put on</L>
<L>One of thy Temple suits and accompany us,</L>
<L>Or else thy Dimmity breeches be mortall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>You will</L>
<L>Not strip me will you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<L>By thy visible eares we will.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>By this two handed Beaver; which is so thinne</L>
<L>And light a Butterflies wings put to't would make it</L>
<L>A Mercuries flying hat and soare aloft.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>But doe you know to how much danger</L>
<L>You tempt me? should my Uncle know I come</L>
<L>Within the ayre of Fleet-street—.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you make</L>
<L>Your selfe fit for a coach againe, and come</L>
<L>Along with us?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well my two resolute friends</L>
<L>You shall prevaile. But whether now are your</L>
<L>Lewd motions bent?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<L>Weel' dine at <HI>Roseclaps,</HI> there</L>
<L>We shall meet Captaine <HI>Quartfield,</HI> and his Poet,</L>
<L>They shall shew us another fish.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>But by the way we have agreed to see.</L>
<L>A Lady, you Mechanick.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>What Lady?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hast</L>
<L>Not thou heard of the New-sprung Lady?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>One</L>
<L>That keeps her Coachman, Foot-boy, woman, and spends</L>
<L>A thousand pound a yeare by wit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>How? wit?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<L>That is her patrimony, Sir; tis thought</L>
<L>The fortune she is borne to will not buy</L>
<L>A bunch of Turnips.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>She is no Gamester is she?</L>
<L>Nor carries false dice?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, but has a Tongue,</L>
<L>Wert in a Lawyers mouth, would make him buy</L>
<L>All young Heires neere him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>But does no man know</L>
<L>From whence she came?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>As for hir birth she may</L>
<L>Choose her own pedigree; it is unknowne</L>
<L>Whither she be descended of some Ditch,</L>
<L>Or Dutchesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<L>She's the wonder of the Court,</L>
<L>And talke oth' Towne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Her name?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<L>Aurelia.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'ue heard of her. They say she does fight duells,</L>
<L>And answers challenges in wit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>She has beene</L>
<L>Thrice in the field.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ith' the field?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, in <HI>Spring Garden.</HI></L>
<L>Has conquerd with no second but her woman.</L>
<L><PB N="8" REF="9"/>A Puritan, and has returnd with prizes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>And no drum beat before her?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, nor Colours</L>
<L>Flourisht. She has made a vow never to marry</L>
<L>Till she be won by Stratagem.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>I long</L>
<L>To see her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ith' name of Guild-hall who comes here?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Timothy.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA V.</HEAD>
<STAGE>To them Timothy.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>By your leave Gentlemen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>M<SUP>r</SUP> <HI>Timothy!</HI></L>
<L>Welcome from the New world. I lookt you should</L>
<L>Ha past through halfe the signes in Heaven by this.</L>
<L>And ha converst with Dolphins. What not gone</L>
<L>To sea vvith your Father?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>No faith, I doe not love</L>
<L>To goe to sea, it makes one lowsie, laies him</L>
<L>In vvooden sheets, and lands him a preservative</L>
<L>Against the plague. Besides, my Mother was</L>
<L>Afraid to venture me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Believ't she's wise,</L>
<L>Not to trust such a wit to a thinne frayle barck</L>
<L>Where you had saild vvithin three inches of</L>
<L>Becomming a Jonas. Besides the tossing, to have</L>
<L>All the fierce blustring faces in the Map</L>
<L>Swell more tempestuously upon you then</L>
<L>Lawyers preferrd, or Trumpeters. And vvhither</L>
<L>Were you bound now?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>I only came to have</L>
<L>Your judgement of my suit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Surely the Taylor</L>
<L>Has done his part.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>And my mother has done hers,</L>
<L>For she has paid for't. I never durst be seen</L>
<L>Before my Father out of Duretta and Serge.</L>
<L>But if he catch me in such paltry stuffes,</L>
<L>To make me looke like one that lets out mony,</L>
<L>Let him say <HI>Timothy</HI> vvas borne a foole.</L>
<L>Before he vvent he made me doe vvhat he list;</L>
<L>Now he's abroad Ile doe vvhat I list. What</L>
<L>Are these two? Gentlemen?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>You see they weare</L>
<L>Their Heraldry.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>But I mean can they roare,</L>
<L>Beat Drawers, play at dice, and court their Mistresse.</L>
<L>I mean forthwith to get a Mistresse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>But</L>
<L><PB N="9" REF="9"/>How comes this, M<SUP>r</SUP> <HI>Timothy,</HI> you did not</L>
<L>Rise such a gallant this morning.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alls on for that.</L>
<L>My Mother lost her Maiden-head that I</L>
<L>Might come first into th' world; and by Gods lid</L>
<L>Ile beare my selfe like the elder brother, I.</L>
<L>D'you think Ile all daies of my life frequent</L>
<L>Saint <HI>Antlins,</HI> like my sister? Gentlemen</L>
<L>I covet your acquaintance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your servant, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall be proud to know you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, my know∣ledge</L>
<L>Is not much worth; I me borne to a small fortune,</L>
<L>Some hundred thousand pound, if once my Father</L>
<L>Held up his hands in Marble, or kneeld in brasse.</L>
<L>What are you Inns of Court-men?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Catechisme</L>
<L>Were false should we deny it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall shortly</L>
<L>Be one my selfe, I learne to dance already,</L>
<L>And weare short clokes; I mean in your next Masque</L>
<L>To have a part, I shall take most extreamly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>You will inflame the Ladies, Sir. They'l strive</L>
<L>Who shall most privately convey Jewels.</L>
<L>Into your hand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is an excellent fellow;</L>
<L>Who is't?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rich <HI>Seathrifts</HI> sonne thats gone to sea</L>
<L>This morning with my Uncle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is this he</L>
<L>Whose sister thou shouldst marry? The wench that brings</L>
<L>Ten thousand pound.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Uncle would fain have me,</L>
<L>But I have cast her off.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith she's hand∣some,</L>
<L>And had a good wit, but her Schoole-Mistresse</L>
<L>Has made her a rank Puritan.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lets take him</L>
<L>Along with us and Captaine <HI>Quartfield</HI> shall show him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Twill be an excellent Comoedy, and afterwards</L>
<L>I have a project on him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gentlemen</L>
<L>Shall we dine at an Ordinary? You</L>
<L>Shall enter me among the Wits.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, I</L>
<L>Will but shift cloths then wee'l associate you.</L>
<L>But first you shall with us and see a Lady,</L>
<L>Rich as your Fathers chests and odde holes; and</L>
<L>Fresh as <HI>Pygmalions</HI> Mistresse newly wakened</L>
<L>Out of her Alablaster.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lead on;</L>
<L>I long to see a Lady and to salute her.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="2" TYPE="act">
<PB N="10" REF="10"/>
<HEAD>ACTVS II.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA I.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Aurelia. Dorcas.</STAGE>
<L>WHY we shall have you get in time the turne</L>
<L>Up of your Eyes, speak in the Nose, draw sighes</L>
<L>Of an ell long, and rayle at Discipline.</L>
<L>Would I could heare from <HI>Baneswright,</HI> ere Ile be torturd</L>
<L>With your precisenesse thus, Ile get dry palmes</L>
<L>With starching, and put on my smocks my selfe.</L>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Surely you may, and ayre'em too, there have been</L>
<L>Very devout and holy women that wore</L>
<L>No shift at all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Such Saints you meane as wore</L>
<L>Their Congregations, and swarm'd with Christian Vermin.</L>
<L>You'l hold cleane linnen Heresie?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Surely yes,</L>
<L>Cleane linnen in a Surplesse; That and powders</L>
<L>Doe bring dry summers, make the sicknesse rage,</L>
<L>And th' Enemy prevaile, It was revealed</L>
<L>To M<SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Scruple</HI> and her husband, who</L>
<L>Doe verily ascribe the German warre,</L>
<L>And the late persecutions, to curling,</L>
<L>False Teeth, and Oyle of <HI>Talck.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now she is in</L>
<L>A Lecturer will sooner hold his peace</L>
<L>Then she.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dor.</SPEAKER>
<L>And surely, as Master <HI>Scruple</HI> saies,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>That was her Schoole-master. One that cooles a feast</L>
<L>With his long grace, and sooner eats a Capon</L>
<L>Then blesses it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dor.</SPEAKER>
<L>And proves it very well</L>
<L>Out of a book that sufferd Martyrdome</L>
<L>By fire in Cheapside, since Amulets, and Bracelets,</L>
<L>And Love-locks were in use, the price of sprats,</L>
<L>Ierusalem Artichocks, and Holland Cheese,</L>
<L>Is very much increased, so that the Brethren,</L>
<L>Botchers I meane, and such poore zealous Saints,</L>
<L>As earne five groats a week under a stall,</L>
<L>By singing Psalmes, and drawing up of holes,</L>
<L>Can't live in their vocation, but are faine</L>
<L>To turne—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Old breeches.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Surely, Teachers and Prophets.</L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<PB N="11" REF="10"/>
<HEAD>SCENA II.</HEAD>
<STAGE>To Them Baneswright.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>O M<SUP>r</SUP> <HI>Baneswright,</HI> are you come? my woman</L>
<L>Was in her preaching fit, she only wanted</L>
<L>A Tables end.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Banesw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why whats the matter?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Never</L>
<L>Poore Lady had so much unbred holynesse</L>
<L>About her person; I am never drest</L>
<L>Without a sermon, but am forct to prove</L>
<L>The lawfulnesse of curling irons before</L>
<L>She'l crisp me in a morning; I must show</L>
<L>Text for the fashions of my gownes, she'l aske</L>
<L>Where Jewels are commanded, or what Lady</L>
<L>Ith' primitive times wore ropes of pearle or rubyes;</L>
<L>She will urge Councells for her litle ruffe</L>
<L>Calld in Northampton shire; and her whole service</L>
<L>Is a meere confutation of my clothes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Banesw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why Madam, I assure you time hath beene</L>
<L>However she be otherwise, when she had</L>
<L>A good quick wit, and would have made to a Lady</L>
<L>A serviceable sinner.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>She can't preserve</L>
<L>(The guift for which I took her) but (as though</L>
<L>She Were inspird from <HI>Ipswitch</HI>) she will make</L>
<L>The Acts and Monuments in sweet-meats; Quinces</L>
<L>Arraigned and burnt at a stake; all my banquets</L>
<L>Are persequutions, and <HI>Dioclesians</HI> dayes</L>
<L>Are brought for entertainment, and we eat Martyrs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Banesw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam she is farre gone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, Sir, she is</L>
<L>A Puritan at her needle too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Banesw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeed?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>She works religious petticoats; for flowers</L>
<L>She'l make Church Histories; her needle doth</L>
<L>So sanctify my Cushionets, besides</L>
<L>My smock-sleeves have such holy imbroderies,</L>
<L>And are so learned, that I feare in time</L>
<L>All my apparell will be quoted by</L>
<L>Some pure Instructer. Yesterday I went</L>
<L>To see a Lady that has a Parrot, my woman</L>
<L>While I was in discourse converted the fowle.</L>
<L><PB N="12" REF="11"/>And now it can speak nought but Knoxes workes,</L>
<L>So theres a parrot lost.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Banes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith Madam she</L>
<L>Was earnest to come to you, had I knowne</L>
<L>Her Mistresse had so bred her I would first</L>
<L>Ha preferd her to new England.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Surely, Sir,</L>
<L>You promised me when you did take my mony</L>
<L>To help me to a faithfull service, a Lady</L>
<L>That would be saved. Not one that loves profane,</L>
<L>Unsanctified fashions.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fly my sight</L>
<L>You gooddy <HI>Hofman,</HI> and keep your chamber till</L>
<L>You can provide your selfe some cure, or I</L>
<L>Will forthwith excommunicate your zeale,</L>
<L>And make you a silent waiting woman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Banes.</SPEAKER>
<L>M<SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Dorcas,</HI></L>
<L>If you'l be usher to that holy learned woman</L>
<L>That can heale broken shinnes, scald heads, and th' Itch,</L>
<L>Your schoole-mistresse, that can expound, and teaches</L>
<L>To knit in Chaldee, and work Hebrew samplers,</L>
<L>Ile hlpe you back againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dor.</SPEAKER>
<L>The motion sure is good</L>
<L>And I will ponder of it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>From thy zeale,
<STAGE>Ex. Dorcas.</STAGE></L>
<L>The frantick Ladies judgements, and Histriomastix,</L>
<L>Deliver me. This was of your preferring,</L>
<L>You must needs help me to another.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Banes.</SPEAKER>
<L>How</L>
<L>Would you desire her qualified, deformed</L>
<L>And crooked like some Ladies, who doe weare</L>
<L>Their women like black patches to set em of?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>I need no foile, nor shall I think I'me white</L>
<L>Only between two Moores; or that my nose</L>
<L>Stands wrong, because my womans doth stand right.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Banes</SPEAKER>
<L>But you would have her secret, able to keepe</L>
<L>Strange sights from th' knowledge of your Knight vvhen you</L>
<L>Are married, Madam, of a quick faining head?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>You vvrong me, <HI>Baneswright,</HI> she vvhom I vvould have,</L>
<L>Must to her handsome shape have vertue too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Banesw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well Madam I shall fit you. I doe know</L>
<L>A cholerick Lady which within these three weekes</L>
<L>Has, for not cutting her cornes vvell, put off</L>
<L>Three vvomen; and is now about to part</L>
<L>With th' fourth, just one of your description.</L>
<L>Next change oth' Moone, or vveather, vvhen her feet</L>
<L>Doe ake againe, I doe believe I shall</L>
<L>Pleasure your Ladiship.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Expect your reward.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Baneswright.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<PB N="13" REF="11"/>
<HEAD>SCENA III.</HEAD>
<STAGE>To Her Bright, Newcut, Timothy, Plotwell.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>LAdy, let me tast the Elizium of your lips.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why what are you? you will not leap me, Sir,</L>
<L>Pray know your distance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>What am I sweet Lady?</L>
<L>My Father is an Aldermans fellow, and I</L>
<L>Hope to be one in time.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then, Sir, in time</L>
<L>You may be remembred at the quenching of</L>
<L>Fired houses, when the bells ring backward, by</L>
<L>Your name upon the Buckets.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay they say</L>
<L>You have a good wit Lady, and I can finde it</L>
<L>Assoone as another: I in my time have been</L>
<L>Oth' University, and should have been a scholler.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>By the size of your wit, Sir, had you kept</L>
<L>To that profession, I can foresee</L>
<L>You would have been a great persecuter of Nature▪</L>
<L>And great consumer of rush Candles, with</L>
<L>As small successe, as if a Tortoise should</L>
<L>Day and night practise to run races: Having</L>
<L>Contemplated your selfe into ill lookes,</L>
<L>In pitty to soe much affliction,</L>
<L>You might ha past for learned: and 't may be,</L>
<L>If you had fallen out with the Muses, and</L>
<L>Scapt Poetry, you might have risen to scarlet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heres a rare Lady with all my heart, by this</L>
<L>Light Gentlemen, now have I no more language</L>
<L>Then a dumb parrot, a litle more shee'l jeere me</L>
<L>Into a fellow that turnes upon his toe</L>
<L>In a steeple and strikes quarters.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>And why should you</L>
<L>Be now so dainty of your lips? verily</L>
<L>They are not Virgins, they have tasted Man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>And may againe but then Ile be secur'd,</L>
<L>For the sweet ayre oth' parties. If you</L>
<L>Will bring it me confirm'd under the hands</L>
<L>Of foure sufficient Ladies that you are</L>
<L>Cleane men, you may chance kisse my woman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ladie,</L>
<L>Our lips are made of the same clay that yours,</L>
<L><PB N="14" REF="12"/>And have not been refused.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis right you are</L>
<L>Two Inns of Court-men.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, what then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Known Cladders</L>
<L>Through all the Towne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cladders?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, Catholick Lovers,</L>
<L>From Countrye Madams to your Glovers wife,</L>
<L>Or Laundresse; will not let poore Gentlewomen</L>
<L>Take physick quietly, but disturb their pills</L>
<L>From operation with your untaught visits.</L>
<L>Or if they be imployd, contrive small plots</L>
<L>Below staires with the Chamber-maid; commend</L>
<L>Her fragrant breath, which five yards of salutes,</L>
<L>At foure deflowers a Rose, at three kils spiders.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<L>What dangerous truths these are?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ravish a lock</L>
<L>From the yellow waiting-woman, use stratagems</L>
<L>To get her silver whistle, and way-lay</L>
<L>Her pewter knots or bodkin.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pretty, pretty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>You think you have abused us now?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile tell you,</L>
<L>Had I in all the world but forty Mark,</L>
<L>And that got by my needle and making socks;</L>
<L>And were that fortie Mark Mil-sixpences,</L>
<L>Spurroyals, Harry groats, or such odde coine</L>
<L>Of husbandry as in the Kings raigne now</L>
<L>Would never passe, I would despise you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lady,</L>
<L>Your wit will make you die a witherd virgin.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>We shall in time when your most tyrant tongue</L>
<L>Hath made this house a wildernesse, and you</L>
<L>As unfrequented as a states man fallen;</L>
<L>When you shall quarrel with your face and glasse,</L>
<L>Till from your pencill you have raisd new cheeks,</L>
<L>See you beg suitors, write Bills ore your doore,</L>
<L>Here is an ancient Lady to be let.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<L>You think you are handsome now, and that your eyes</L>
<L>Make star-shooting, and dart?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tmay be I doe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<L>May I not prosper if I have not seene</L>
<L>A better face in signes, or ginger-bread.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>yes, I for two pence oft have bought a better.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>What a sweet innocent looke you have!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fye gentlemen,</L>
<L>Abuse a harmlesse Lady thus, I can't</L>
<L>With patience heare your blasphemies. Make me</L>
<L>Your second Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>And make me your third.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>O prodigie to heare an Image speake.</L>
<L><PB N="15" REF="12"/>Why, Sir, I tooke you for a Mute ith' Hangings.</L>
<L>Ile tell the faces.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gentlemen doe I</L>
<L>Look like one of them Trojans?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis so, your face</L>
<L>Is missing here, Sir, pray step back againe</L>
<L>And fill the number; you I hope have more</L>
<L>Truth in you then to filch your selfe away,</L>
<L>And leave my roome unfurnisht.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>By this light</L>
<L>She'l send for a Constable straight and apprehend him</L>
<L>For the every.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why Lady doe you think me</L>
<L>Wrought in a Loome, some Dutch peece weavd at <HI>Mooreclack▪</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Surely you stood so simply, like a Man</L>
<L>Penning of Recantations, that I suspected</L>
<L>Y' had been a part of the Monopolie.</L>
<L>But now I know you have a tongue, and are</L>
<L>A very Man, Ile think you only dull,</L>
<L>And pray for better utterance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lady you make</L>
<L>Rash judgement of him, he was only struck</L>
<L>With admiration of your beauty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Truly</L>
<L>And so I was.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then you can wonder, Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes when he sees such miracles as you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>And love me can't you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Love you? By this hand</L>
<L>Ide love a dog of your sweet looks; I am</L>
<L>Enamour'd of you Lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, ha, ha, now surely</L>
<L>I wonder you weare not a cap; your case</L>
<L>Requires warme things, Ile send you forth a Cawdle.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>The plague of rotten teeth, wrincles, lowd lunges</L>
<L>Be with you Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Had I now pen and inke,</L>
<L>If I were urgd I'de faine know whether I</L>
<L>In conscience ought not to set down my selfe</L>
<L>No wiser then I should be.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gentlemen</L>
<L>How like you her wit?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wit? I verily</L>
<L>Believe she was begotten by some wit;</L>
<L>And he that has her, may beget plaies on her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<L>Her wit had need be good▪ it finds her house.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Her house? Tis able to find the Court, if she</L>
<L>Be chast to all this wit, I doe not think</L>
<L>But that she might be showne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>She speaks with salt,</L>
<L>And has a pretty scornefulnesse, which now</L>
<L>I'ue seen I'me satisfied.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come then away;</L>
<L>To <HI>Roseclaps.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lead on, Let us dine: This Lady</L>
<L><PB N="16" REF="13"/>Runnes in my head still.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Foot.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, My Lady prayes.
<STAGE>Enter a Footman.</STAGE></L>
<L>You would dismisse your company, she has</L>
<L>Some businesse with you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gentlemen walk softly,</L>
<L>Ile overtake you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Newcut</HI> 'slight her wit</L>
<L>is come to private meetings.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, J thought</L>
<L>She had some other vertues. Well make hast,</L>
<L>We'l stay without, when thou hast done informe us</L>
<L>What the rate is; if she be reasonable</L>
<L>Wee'l be her Customers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'are merry, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ex. Br. New. Tim.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Aurelia.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA IV.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Plotwell. Aurelia.</STAGE>
<L>NAy sister you may enter, they are gone.</L>
<L>I did receive your ticket this morning. What?</L>
<L>You look the Mine should run still?</L>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>O you are</L>
<L>A carefull brother, to put me on a course</L>
<L>That drawes the eyes oth' Towne upon me, and makes me</L>
<L>Discourse for Ordinaries, then leave me in't.</L>
<L>I will put off my Ladiship, and returne</L>
<L>To M' <HI>Holland,</HI> and to making shirts,</L>
<L>And bands againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hope you will not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>I</L>
<L>Repent I left th' Exchange.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith I should laugh</L>
<L>To see you there againe, and there serve out</L>
<L>The rest of your Jndentures, by managing</L>
<L>Your Needle well, and making Night-caps, by</L>
<L>A Chafing dish in winter mornings, to keep</L>
<L>Your fingers pliant. How rarely 'twould become you</L>
<L>To run ore all your shop to passengers</L>
<L>In a fine sale tune?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>What would you have me doe?</L>
<L>D'you think I'me the Dutch Virgin that could live</L>
<L>By th' sent of Flowers? Or that my familie</L>
<L>Are all descended of Chameleons,</L>
<L>And can be kept with ayre? Js this the way</L>
<L>To get a husband to be in danger to be</L>
<L><PB N="17" REF="13"/>Shut up for house-rent, or to weare a gowne</L>
<L>Out a whole fashion, or the same Jewels twice?</L>
<L>Shortly my neighbours will commend my clothes,</L>
<L>For lasting well, give them strange dates, and cry</L>
<L>Since your last Gorget and the blazing starre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prythee excuse me sister, I can now</L>
<L>Raine showers of silver into thy lap againe;</L>
<L>My Vncle's gone to sea, and has left me</L>
<L>The key to th' golden fleece. Thou shalt be still.</L>
<L>A Madam, <HI>Pen,</HI> and to maintaine thy Honour,</L>
<L>And to new dub thee take this. But sister, I
<STAGE>Gives her a Purse.</STAGE></L>
<L>Expected you ere this out of the Throng</L>
<L>Of suitors that frequent you, should have beene</L>
<L>Made a true Lady, not one in Type or showe.</L>
<L>I feare you are too scornefull, looke too high.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith brother 'tis no age to be put off</L>
<L>With empty education; few will make Ioyntures</L>
<L>To wit or good parts. I may dye a Virgin,</L>
<L>When some old widdow which at every cough</L>
<L>Resignes some of her teeth, and every night</L>
<L>Puts off her Leg as duly as french Hood,</L>
<L>Scarce weares her owne Nose, hath no eyes but such</L>
<L>As she first bought in <HI>Broad-street,</HI> and every morning</L>
<L>Is put together like some Instrument,</L>
<L>Having full Coffers shall be wooed, and thought</L>
<L>A youthfull Bride.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why sister will you like</L>
<L>A Match of my projection? you doe know</L>
<L>How ruinous our fathers fortunes are;</L>
<L>Before he broke you know there was a Contract</L>
<L>Betweene you and young <HI>Sea-thrift.</HI> What if I</L>
<L>Make it a wedding?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Marry a foole? in hope</L>
<L>To be a Lady Maioresse?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why sister, I</L>
<L>Could name good Ladyes that are faine to finde</L>
<L>Wit for themselves &amp; Knights too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have heard</L>
<L>Of one whose husband was so meek, to be</L>
<L>For need her Gentleman usher, and while she</L>
<L>Made visits above staires would patiently</L>
<L>Finde himselfe businesse at Tre-trip ith' Hall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>He's only City bred, one month of your</L>
<L>Sharp conversation will refine him; besides</L>
<L><PB N="18" REF="14"/>How long wilt be ere your dissembled state</L>
<L>Meet such another offer?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well Brother you shall</L>
<L>Dispose of my affections.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then sometime</L>
<L>This afternoone Ile bring him hither▪ doe you</L>
<L>Provide the Priest; your Dining roome will serve</L>
<L>As well as the Church.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will expect you.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt severall waies.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA V.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Captaine <HI>Quart-field</HI> beating <HI>Rose-clap. Sale-wit</HI> and <HI>Millicent</HI> labouring to part 'em.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quart</SPEAKER>
<L>Sirrah, Ile beat you into aire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good Captaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quartf.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will by Hector.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<L>Murder, murder, help.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quartf.</SPEAKER>
<L>You needy, shifting, cousning, breaking slave.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mill.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, M<SUP>r</SUP> <HI>Salewit,</HI> help to part 'em.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Salew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Captaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quartf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Aske me for mony, dog?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh! I am killd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mill.</SPEAKER>
<L>Help. Help.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Salew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay Captaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q.</SPEAKER>
<L>Men of my coat pay?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mill.</SPEAKER>
<L>Jle call in neighbours. Murder. Murder.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rascal</L>
<L>Jle make you trust and offer me petitions</L>
<L>To goe oth' score.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good, tis very good.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>How does thy head sweetheart?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away be quiet, <HI>Mill.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Salew.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Roseclap,</HI> you'l never leave this, I did tell you</L>
<L>Last time the Captaine beat you what a Lion</L>
<L>He is being askt for reckonings.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mill.</SPEAKER>
<L>So you did</L>
<L>Jndeed good M<SUP>r</SUP> <HI>Salewit</HI>; yet you must</L>
<L>Ever be foolish husband.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Salew.</SPEAKER>
<L>What if we</L>
<L>Doe owe you mony, Sir, ist fit for you</L>
<L>To aske it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, Sir, there is law; J say</L>
<L>No more, but there is law.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quartf.</SPEAKER>
<L>What law you Curre?</L>
<L>The law of Nature, Custome, Armes, and Nations,</L>
<L>Frees men of war from paiments.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, your Armes Cap∣taine,</L>
<L>None else.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q.</SPEAKER>
<L>No souldiers ought to pay.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sale.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor Poets:</L>
<L>All void of mony are privileged.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>What would you have,</L>
<L>Captaines and Poets, M<SUP>r</SUP> <HI>Salewit</HI> saies,</L>
<L>Must never pay.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Salew.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, nor be askt for monie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<L>Still I say there is law.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quartf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Say that againe,</L>
<L>And by <HI>Bellona</HI> J will cut thy throat.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="19" REF="14"/>
<SPEAKER>Mill.</SPEAKER>
<L>You long to see your braines out.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quartf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why you Mungrill,</L>
<L>You Iohn of all Trades, have we been your guests</L>
<L>Since you first kept a Taverne, when you had</L>
<L>The face and impudence to hang a bush</L>
<L>Out to three pints of Claret, two of Sack</L>
<L>In all the world?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Salew.</SPEAKER>
<L>After that, when you broke,</L>
<L>Did we here finde you out, customd your House,</L>
<L>And helpt away your victuals which had else</L>
<L>Laine mouldy on your hands?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<L>You did indeed,</L>
<L>And never paid for't. I doe not deny,</L>
<L>But you have been my Customers these two yeares,</L>
<L>My Jack went not, nor Chimney smoakt without you.</L>
<L>I will goe farther; your two mouths have been</L>
<L>Two as good eating Mouths as need to come</L>
<L>Within my doores, as curious to be pleased</L>
<L>As if you still had eaten with ready money:</L>
<L>Had still the meats in season; still drunk more</L>
<L>Then your Ordinary came to.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sale.</SPEAKER>
<L>And your conscience now</L>
<L>Would have this paid for?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<L>Surely so I take it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sale.</SPEAKER>
<L>Was ever the like heard?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qua.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis most unreasonable</L>
<L>He has a hardned conscience. Sirrah, Cheater,</L>
<L>You would be questioned for your reckonings, Rogue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe you informe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quartf.</SPEAKER>
<L>I heare one oth' Sheriffs</L>
<L>Paid for the boyling of a Carp a Mark.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Salew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most unheard of exactions!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet surely, Cap∣taine.</L>
<L>No man had cheaper reckonings then your selfe,</L>
<L>And M<SUP>r</SUP> <HI>Salewit</HI> here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quartf.</SPEAKER>
<L>How cheap?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<L>I say</L>
<L>No more good Captaine; not to pay is cheap,</L>
<L>A man would think.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quart.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, Dont you reckon Aire,</L>
<L>And make it deare to breath in your house, and put</L>
<L>The Nose to charges?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<L>Right, perfumd Aire, Captaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quartf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is not the standing of the salt an Item,</L>
<L>And placeing of the bread?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<L>A new way, Captaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quartf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is not the folding of your Napkins brought</L>
<L>Into the Bill?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pincht Napkins, Captaine, and laid</L>
<L>Like Fishes, Fowles, or Faces.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Salew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then remember</L>
<L>How you rate sallets, <HI>Roseclap</HI>; one may buy</L>
<L>Gardens as Cheap.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, M<SUP>r</SUP> <HI>Salewit,</HI> sallets</L>
<L>Taken from <HI>Euclide,</HI> made in <HI>Diagrams,</HI></L>
<L>And to be eaten in Figures.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quartf.</SPEAKER>
<L>And we must pay</L>
<L><PB N="20" REF="15"/>For your Inventions, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or you are damnd,</L>
<L>Good Captaine, you have sworne to pay this twelve-month.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quartf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace you lowd, bawling Curre; doe you disgrace me</L>
<L>Before these Gallants, See if I don't kill you.</L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="6" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA VI.</HEAD>
<STAGE>To Them Bright. Newcut. Timothy. Plotwell.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>SAve you Captaine <HI>Quartfield,</HI> and my brave Wit,</L>
<L>My man of <HI>Helicon,</HI> salute this Gentleman,</L>
<L>He is a City wit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Corporation</L>
<L>Went to the bringing of him forth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quartf.</SPEAKER>
<L>I embrace him;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Salew.</SPEAKER>
<L>And so doe I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are a Poet, Sir,</L>
<L>And can make Verses, I heare?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Salew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, I am</L>
<L>A servant to the Muses.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have made</L>
<L>Some speeches, Sir, in verse, which have been spoke</L>
<L>By a greene <HI>Robin Goodfellow</HI> from <HI>Cheapside Conduit,</HI></L>
<L>To my Fathers Company; and meane this afternoone</L>
<L>To make an <HI>Epithalamium</HI> upon my wedding.</L>
<L>A Lady fell in love with me this morning,</L>
<L>Ask M<SUP>r</SUP> Francis here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heart you spoile all,</L>
<L>Did not I charge you to be silent?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's true,</L>
<L>I had forgot. you are a Captaine, Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quartf.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have seen service, S<SUP>r</SUP>.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Captain I love</L>
<L>Men of the sword, and buffe, and if need were</L>
<L>I can roare too, and hope to sweare in time,</L>
<L>Doe you see, Captaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plot.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay Captaine we have brought you</L>
<L>A Gentleman of valour who has been</L>
<L>In <HI>Moore-fields</HI> often, marry it has beene</L>
<L>To squire his sisters, and demolish Custards</L>
<L>At <HI>Pimlico.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quartf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Afore me, M<SUP>r</SUP> <HI>Plotwell,</HI></L>
<L>I never hop't to see you in silk againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Salew.</SPEAKER>
<L>I lookt the next Lord Maiors day to see you oth' Livery,</L>
<L>Or one oth' Batchelour Whiflers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quartf.</SPEAKER>
<L>What is</L>
<L>Your Uncle dead?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>He may in time; he's gone</L>
<L>To sea this morning, Captaine, and J am come</L>
<L>Jnto your order againe. But hark you, Captaine,</L>
<L>What think you of a <HI>Fish</HI> now?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mad wags, mad wags.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="21" REF="15"/>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>By Heaven its true, here we have brought one with us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rich <HI>Seathrifts</HI> sonne, he'l make a rare sea-Monster.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quartf.</SPEAKER>
<L>And shall's be merry yfaith?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Salewit</HI> shal make</L>
<L>A song upon him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<L>And <HI>Roseclaps</HI> boy shall sing it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Salew.</SPEAKER>
<L>We have the properties of the last fish.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quartf.</SPEAKER>
<L>And if I</L>
<L>At dinner doe not give him sea enough,</L>
<L>And afterwards if I, and <HI>Salewit</HI> doe not</L>
<L>Showe him much better then he that showes the Tombs,</L>
<L>Let me be turnd into a Sword-fish my selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>A naturall change for a Captaine. How now <HI>Roseclap,</HI></L>
<L>Pensive and cursing the long Vacation?</L>
<L>Thou look'st as if thou meanst to breake shortly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<L>Aske</L>
<L>The Captaine why I am sad.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quartf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith Gentlemen,</L>
<L>I disciplin'd him for his rudenes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why these</L>
<L>Are Iudgements, <HI>Roseclap,</HI> for deare reckonings.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Art thou</L>
<L>The halfe Crowne fellow of the house?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, I</L>
<L>Doe keepe the Ordinary.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let's have wine enough;</L>
<L>I meane to drinke a health to a Lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Still</L>
<L>Will you betray your fortune? One of them</L>
<L>Will goe and tell her who you are, and spoyle</L>
<L>The Marriage.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Noe, peace. Gentlemen if you'l</L>
<L>Goe in wee'l follow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<L>Please you enter, dinner</L>
<L>Shall straight be set upon the board.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee'l expect you,
<STAGE>Ex: Br. New. Salew. Quart. Rosecl.</STAGE></L>
<L>Come Gentlemen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>But M<SUP>r</SUP> Francis, was that</L>
<L>The busines why she calld you backe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Believe it</L>
<L>Your Mothers smock shin'd at your birth, or else</L>
<L>You weare some Charme about you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not I truly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>It can not be she should so strangely dote</L>
<L>Vpon you else: slight had you stayd, I thinke</L>
<L>She would have wooed you her selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now I remember</L>
<L>One read my fortune once, and told my father</L>
<L>That I should match a Lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>How things fall out?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>And did she ask you who I was?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>I told her</L>
<L>You were a young Knight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Scarce come to th' years</L>
<L>Of your discretion yet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good still.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pl.</SPEAKER>
<L>And that a great Man</L>
<L>Did meane to beg you for his daughter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most rare.</L>
<L>This afternoone's the time?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith she</L>
<L>Looks you should use a litle Courtship first,</L>
<L>That done, let me alone to have the Priest</L>
<L>In readinesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>But were I not best aske</L>
<L><PB N="22" REF="16"/>My friends consent?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pl.</SPEAKER>
<L>How? Friends consent? thats fit</L>
<L>For none but Farmers sonnes, and Milk-maids. You shall not</L>
<L>Debase your judgement. She takes you for a wit,</L>
<L>And you shall match her like one.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then I will.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>But no more words to th' Gallants.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe you think</L>
<L>I am a sive and cannot hold.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gentlemen
<STAGE>Enter Roseclap.</STAGE></L>
<L>The company are sate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>It shall be yours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, Sir, your fortune claimes precedency.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="7" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA VII.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Ware-house. Sea-thrift. Cypher.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ware-h.</SPEAKER>
<L>FEtcht abroad by two Gallants say you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, Sir,</L>
<L>Assoone as you were gone; he only staid</L>
<L>To put on other clothes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seath.</SPEAKER>
<L>You say my sonne</L>
<L>Went with em too?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>And whether went they?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyph.</SPEAKER>
<L>I followd'em to <HI>Roseclaps</HI> Ordinary</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ware-h.</SPEAKER>
<L>And there you left em?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, Sir, Just before</L>
<L>I saw some Captaines enter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seath.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, I give</L>
<L>My sonne for lost, undone, past hope.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ware-h.</SPEAKER>
<L>There is</L>
<L>No more but this wee'l thither straight. You <HI>Cypher</HI></L>
<L>Have your instructions.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, let me alone</L>
<L>To make the story dolefull.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ware-h.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe, make you ready then▪</L>
<L>Now, M<SUP>r</SUP> <HI>Seathrift,</HI> you may see, what these
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
<L>Young men would doe left to themselves.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sea-th.</SPEAKER>
<L>My sonne</L>
<L>Shall know he has a sister.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ware-h.</SPEAKER>
<L>And my Nephew</L>
<L>That once he had an Uncle. To leave land</L>
<L>Unto an unthrift is to build on sand.</L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="3" TYPE="act">
<PB N="23" REF="16"/>
<HEAD>ACTVS III.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA I.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Bright. Newcut. Plotwell. Rosclap. hanging out the picture of a strange fish.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>FOre Jove the Captaine foxt him rarely.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<L>O Sir</L>
<L>He is used to it; this is the fift fish now</L>
<L>That he hath showne thus. One got him twenty pound.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<L>How <HI>Rosclap</HI>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why the Captaine kept him, Sir,</L>
<L>A whole weeke drunk, and showd him twice a day.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<L>It could not be like this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith I doe grant</L>
<L>This is the strangest fish. you I have hung</L>
<L>His other picture into th'fields, where some</L>
<L>Say tis an oregrowne Porcpisce; others say</L>
<L>Tis the fish caught in Cheshire; one to whom</L>
<L>The rest agree, said 'twas a Mermaid.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>S'light,</L>
<L><HI>Roseclap,</HI> shalt have a patent of him. The <HI>Birds</HI></L>
<L>Brought from <HI>Peru,</HI> the hairy <HI>Wench,</HI> the <HI>Camel,</HI></L>
<L>The <HI>Elephant, Dromedaries,</HI> or <HI>Winsor Castle,</HI></L>
<L>The <HI>Woman</HI> with dead flesh, or <HI>She</HI> that washes,</L>
<L>Threds needles, writes, dresses her children, playes</L>
<L>Oth' Virginalls with her feet, could never draw</L>
<L>People like this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New</SPEAKER>
<L>O that his Father were</L>
<L>At home to see him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or his Mother come,</L>
<L>Who followes strange sights out of Towne, and went</L>
<L>To <HI>Branford</HI> to a Motion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bid the Captaine hasten,</L>
<L>Or hee'l recover and spoile all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<L>Th'are here.</L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA. II.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter Quartfield and Salewit drest like two Trumpeters, keeping the doore</HI> M<SUP>rs</SUP> <HI>Seathrift and</HI> M<SUP>rs</SUP> <HI>Hol∣land with a Prentice before 'em as commers in.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quart.</SPEAKER>
<L>BEarback there.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sale.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray you doe not presse so hard.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quart.</SPEAKER>
<L>Make roome for the two Gentlewomen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M<SUP>rs</SUP>. <HI>Seath.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>What is't?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="24" REF="17"/>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Twelvepence a peece.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>M</HI><SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Holl.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>We will not give't. Q. Make roome</L>
<L>For them that will then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>O fortune here's his Mother.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>And who's the other?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>One M<SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Holland,</HI> the</L>
<L>Great seamstresse on th'Exchange.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>M</HI><SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Holl.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>We gave but a groat</L>
<L>To see the last fish.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quart.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gentlewoman, that</L>
<L>Was but an Irish Sturgeon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Salew.</SPEAKER>
<L>This came from</L>
<L>The Indies, and eats five Crownes a day in frye,</L>
<L>Oxe livers, and browne past.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>M</HI><SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Seath.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Well there's three shil∣lings,</L>
<L>Pray let us have good places now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quartf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beare back there.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>M</HI><SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Holl.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Look <HI>M</HI><SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Seathrift</HI> here be Gentlemen.</L>
<L>Sure tis a rare Fish.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>M</HI><SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Seath.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>J know one of'em,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>M</HI><SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Holl.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>And so doe I, his sister was my prentice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>M</HI><SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Seath,</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Lets take acquaintance with him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>M</HI><SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Seathrift.</HI></L>
<L>Hath the sight drawne you hither?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>M</HI><SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Seath.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Yes Sir I</L>
<L>And <HI>M</HI><SUP>rs</SUP> <HI>Holland</HI> here, my Gossip, past</L>
<L>This way and so cald in. Pray, M<SUP>r</SUP> <HI>Plotwell,</HI></L>
<L>Is not my sonne here? I was told he went</L>
<L>With you this morning.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall see him straight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ms <HI>Holl.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>When will the Fish begin, Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heart she makes him</L>
<L>A puppet play.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why now they only stay</L>
<L>For company, 't has sounded twice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M<SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Seath.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Indeed</L>
<L>I long to see this fish; J wonder whither</L>
<L>They will cut up his belly, they say a Tench</L>
<L>Will make him whole againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M<SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Holl.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Look M<SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Seathrift,</HI></L>
<L>What clawes he has.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M<SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Seath.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>For all the world like Crabs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M<SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Holl.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Nay marke his feet too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M<SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Seath.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>For all the world like Plaice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>Was ever better sport heard?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prythe peace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M<SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Holl.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Pray can you read that? Sir, I warrant you,</L>
<L>That tells where it was caught, and what fish tis.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Within this place is to be seene,</L>
<L>A wondrous Fish. God save the Queene.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>M</HI><SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Holl.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Amen, she is my customer, And I</L>
<L>Have sold her bonelace often.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why the Queene?</L>
<L>Tis writ the King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>That was to make the rime.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>Slid thou didst read it as 'twere some picture of</L>
<L>An <HI>Elzabeth</HI> fish.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quartf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bear back there.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Salew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Make room, you</L>
<L>Friend that were going to cut a purse there, make</L>
<L><PB N="25" REF="17"/>Way for the two old Gentlemen to passe.
<STAGE>Enter Ware-house &amp; Seathrift disguis'd.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wareh.</SPEAKER>
<L>What must we give?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quartf.</SPEAKER>
<L>We take a shilling Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Salew.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is no lesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seath.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray God your fish be worth it.</L>
<L>What is't a whale you take so deare?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quart.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is</L>
<L>A fish taken in the Indies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wareh.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray dispatch then,</L>
<L>And showt, us quickly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Salew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray forbeare, you'd have</L>
<L>Your head broke Cobler.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wareh.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yonder is my Nephew</L>
<L>In his old Gallantry.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seath.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who's there too? my wife?</L>
<L>And <HI>M</HI><SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Holland</HI>? Nay I lookt for them.</L>
<L>But where's my wise sonne?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ware-h.</SPEAKER>
<L>Masse I see not him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quartf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Keep out Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Salew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Waterman you must not enter.
<STAGE>Cypher presses in like a wa∣terman.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quartf.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is no place for scullers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyph.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must needs</L>
<L>Speak with one M<SUP>r</SUP> <HI>Plotwell.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quart.</SPEAKER>
<L>You must stay.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Salew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thrust him out.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyph.</SPEAKER>
<L>And one M<SUP>r</SUP> <HI>Seathrift</HI>
<STAGE>They thrust him out.</STAGE></L>
<L>On urgent businesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Salew.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are yet imployd</L>
<L>In waightier affaires, make fast the doore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quartf.</SPEAKER>
<L>There shall no more come in: come in boy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dont</L>
<L>They speak as if my sonne were in the roome?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ware-h.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, pray observe &amp; marke em.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quartf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gentlemē,</L>
<L>And Gentlewomen, you now shall see a sight,
<STAGE>Drawes a Curtain behind it Timo∣thy a sleepe like a strange fish.</STAGE></L>
<L>Europe nere show'd the like; behold this fish.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>M</HI><SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Holl.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>O strange looke how it sleeps.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>Iust like a Salmō</L>
<L>Upon a stall in fishstreet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>M</HI><SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Seath.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>How it snorts too,</L>
<L>Just like my husband.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ware-h.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis very like a man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seath.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thas such a nose and eyes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Salew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why tis a Man fish.</L>
<L>An Ocean Centaure, begot between a Syren</L>
<L>And a he stock fish.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seath.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray where tooke ye him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quartf.</SPEAKER>
<L>We tooke him strangely in the Indies, neere</L>
<L>The mouth of <HI>Rio de la plata,</HI> a sleepe</L>
<L>Upon the shore just as you see him now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>M</HI><SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Holl.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>How say y', a sleepe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ware-h.</SPEAKER>
<L>How? would he come to land?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seath.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis strange a fish should leave his Element.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quartf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Aske him what things the Coūtry told us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>You</L>
<L>Will scarce believe it now. This fish would walke you</L>
<L>Two or three mile oth'shore sometimes; break houses,</L>
<L>Ravish a naked wench or two, (for there</L>
<L>Women goe naked) then runne to Sea againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quartf.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Country has bin laid, and warrants granted</L>
<L>To apprehend him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ware-h.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe suspect these fellowes,</L>
<L>They lye as if they had patent for't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seath.</SPEAKER>
<L>The company</L>
<L><PB N="26" REF="18"/>Should every one believe his part, would scarce</L>
<L>Have faith enough among us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ware-h.</SPEAKER>
<L>Marke againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Salew.</SPEAKER>
<L>The States of Holland would have bought him of us</L>
<L>Out of a great designe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seath.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeed?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Salew.</SPEAKER>
<L>They offer'd</L>
<L>A thousand dollars.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quart.</SPEAKER>
<L>You cannot enter yet.
<STAGE>Some knock.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ware.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeed? so much? pray what to doe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Salew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why S<SUP>r</SUP>,</L>
<L>They were in hope in time to make this fish</L>
<L>Of faction 'gainst the <HI>Spaniard,</HI> and doe service</L>
<L>Vnto the state.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seath.</SPEAKER>
<L>As how?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Salew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, S<SUP>r</SUP>, next plate-fleet</L>
<L>To dive, bore holes i'th bottome of their ships,</L>
<L>And sinke em; you must think a fish like this</L>
<L>May be taught MACHIAVEL, and made a state-fish;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>As dogs are taught to fetch.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or Elephants</L>
<L>To dance on ropes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>And pray what Honour would</L>
<L>The States have given him for the service?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quartf.</SPEAKER>
<L>That,</L>
<L>Sir, is uncertaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Salew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha made him some sea Count;</L>
<L>Or't may be Admirall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then, sir, in time,</L>
<L>Dutch Authors that writ <HI>Mare Liberum,</HI></L>
<L>Might dedicate their books to him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Salew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes being</L>
<L>A fish advanc't, and of great place. Sing boy.</L>
<L>You now shall heare a song upon him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>Listen</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe they not act it rarely?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>If 'twere their trade</L>
<L>They could not doe it better.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seath.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heare you that sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ware-h.</SPEAKER>
<L>Still I suspect.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M<SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Holl.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>I warrant you this fish</L>
<L>Will shortly be in a Ballad.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Salew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Begin boy</L>
</SP>
<Q><TEXT LANG="eng">
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="song">
<HEAD>Song.</HEAD>
<L>We show no monstrous Crocodile,</L>
<L>Nor any prodigy of Nile.</L>
<L>No Remora that stops Your fleet,</L>
<L>Like sergeants Gallants in the street.</L>
<L>No sea-horse, which can trot or pace,</L>
<L>Or swimme false gallop, post, or race.</L>
<L>For crooked Dolphins we not care,</L>
<L>Though on their back a fidler were.</L>
<L>The like to this fish which we shew,</L>
<L>Was nere in Fishstreet Old, or New.</L>
<L>Nor ever servd to' th'sheriffs bord,</L>
<L>Or kept in souse for the Major Lord.</L>
<L>Had old Astronomers but seene</L>
<L>This fish, none else in Heaven had been.</L>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT></Q>
<SP>
<PB N="27" REF="18"/>
<SPEAKER><HI>M</HI><SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Holl.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>The song has wakned him, look, he stirres.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh,</L>
<L>Captaine—pox—take—you—Captaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>M</HI><SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Sea.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Hark he speaks.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh-my—stomack.-</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wa.</SPEAKER>
<L>How's this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Se.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile pawn my life</L>
<L>This is imposture.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh—Oh—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plot.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heart the Captaine</L>
<L>Did not give him his full load.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wareh.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can your fish</L>
<L>Speak friends? the proverb saies th'are mute.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile tell you</L>
<L>You will admire how docile he is, and how</L>
<L>Hee'l imitate a man; tell him your name</L>
<L>He will repeat it after you; he has heard me</L>
<L>Calld Captaine and my fellow curse sometimes,</L>
<L>And now you heard him say pox take you Captaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Salew.</SPEAKER>
<L>And yesterday I but complaind my stomack</L>
<L>Was over chargd, &amp; how he minds it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New</SPEAKER>
<L>strange?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>J is it not?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>The towardnesse of a fish.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Salew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would you think when we caught him he should speak</L>
<L>Drake, Drake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>And did he?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes and <HI>Hawkins</HI>;</L>
<L>A signe he was a fish that swum there, when</L>
<L>These two compast the world.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<L>How should he learne</L>
<L>Their names J wonder.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Salw.</SPEAKER>
<L>From the saylers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<L>That may be.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>He'l call for drink like me, or any thing</L>
<L>He lacks.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>O-God-my-head.-</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>D'you heare him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>T.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh,</L>
<L>Hostesse—a—bason—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>slid he'l spew.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>No matter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quart.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay J have seene him foxt, and then maintaine</L>
<L>A drunken Dialogue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>M</HI><SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Holl.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Lord how J long</L>
<L>To heare a litle. Pray try him with some questions,</L>
<L>Will you, my friend?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quartf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sometimes he will be fullen,</L>
<L>And make no answers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Salew.</SPEAKER>
<L>That is when he's angred,</L>
<L>Or kept from drinke long.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quart.</SPEAKER>
<L>But Ile try him: M<SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Sea.</HI></L>
<L>To see what Creatures may be brought to.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quart.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tim,</L>
<L>You are drunke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Plague take you Captaine—Oh—Lord</L>
<L>You—made—me—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sea.</SPEAKER>
<L>S'death my sonnes name.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim</SPEAKER>
<L>D' you call him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>He'l answer to no name but that.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q.</SPEAKER>
<L>And <HI>Tim,</HI></L>
<L>What thinke you of a wench now?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh Ime sicke</L>
<L>Where is she, Oh.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seath.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile lay my life this fish</L>
<L>Is some confederate Rogue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quart.</SPEAKER>
<L>I drinke t' you, <HI>Timothy,</HI></L>
<L>In sack.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh Oh.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quart.</SPEAKER>
<L>A health, <HI>Tim.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>I can drink</L>
<L>No more, Oh.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Salew.</SPEAKER>
<L>What not pledge your Mistresse?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh,</L>
<L>Let me alone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Salew.</SPEAKER>
<L>He is not in the mood now.</L>
<L>Sometimes you'd wonder at him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quartf.</SPEAKER>
<L>He is tired</L>
<L>With talking all this day. That and the heat</L>
<L><PB N="28" REF="19"/>Of company about him, dull him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ware-h.</SPEAKER>
<L>Surely,</L>
<L>My friends, it is to me a miracle</L>
<L>To heare Fish speak thus.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quartf.</SPEAKER>
<L>So, Sir, 't has been</L>
<L>To thousands more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Salew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come now next Michaelmas,</L>
<L>Tis five yeares we have showne him in most Courts</L>
<L>In Christendome, and you will not believe</L>
<L>How with meere travelling and observation,</L>
<L>He has improv'd himselfe, and brought away</L>
<L>The language of the Country.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seath.</SPEAKER>
<L>May not I</L>
<L>Aske him some questions?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quartf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, you may, but he</L>
<L>Will answer none but one of us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>M</HI><SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Sea.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>He's used,
<STAGE>Knocking at doore.</STAGE></L>
<L>And knowes their voices.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Salew.</SPEAKER>
<L>He is so M<SUP>s</SUP>. Now</L>
<L>We'l open doore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wareh.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well my beliefe doth tell me</L>
<L>There is a mist before our eyes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seath.</SPEAKER>
<L>I mar'le</L>
<L>My wise sonne mist this show.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quart.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good people, we</L>
<L>Doe show no more to day; if you desire
<STAGE>They draw the Cur∣taine before him.</STAGE></L>
<L>To see, come to us in <HI>Kings-street</HI> to morrow</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M<SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Holl.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Come Gossip let us goe, the Fish is done.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>M</HI><SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Seath.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>By your leave Gentlemen. Truly tis a dainty fish.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Exit M</HI><SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Seath. M</HI><SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Holland and Prentice.</HI></STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA III.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter to them Cypher like a Water-man.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyph.</SPEAKER>
<L>PRay which is M<SUP>r</SUP> <HI>Plotwell?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'me he friend,</L>
<L>What is your businesse?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, I should speake with</L>
<L>Yong M<SUP>r</SUP> <HI>Seathrift</HI> too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, at this time,</L>
<L>Although no Crab like you, to swim backward, he is</L>
<L>Of your element.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Upon the water?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>No</L>
<L>But something that lives int. If you but stay</L>
<L>Till he have slept himselfe a land Creature, you may</L>
<L>Chance see him come a shore here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh—my—head—</L>
<L>Oh—Captaine—M<SUP>r</SUP> <HI>Francis</HI>—Captaine—Oh.—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plot.</SPEAKER>
<L>That is his voice Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seath.</SPEAKER>
<L>Death o my soule my son?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyph.</SPEAKER>
<L>He is in drink, Sir, is he?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Surely friend,</L>
<L>You are a witch, he is so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then I must tell</L>
<L>The newes to you, tis sad.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile hear't as sadly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Uncle, Sir, and M<SUP>r</SUP> <HI>Seathrift</HI> are</L>
<L><PB N="29" REF="19"/>Both drownd some 8 mile below <HI>Greenwitch.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Drownd?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyph.</SPEAKER>
<L>They went ith' Tilt boat, Sir, and J was one</L>
<L>Oth' oares that rowed 'em, a Cole-ship did ore run us,</L>
<L>I scapt by swimming, the two old Gentlemen</L>
<L>Took hold of one another, and sunk together.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>How some mens prayers are heard? we did invoke</L>
<L>The sea this morning, and see, the <HI>Thames</HI> has took 'em.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>It cannot be, such good newes, Gentlemen,</L>
<L>Cannot be true.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ware-h.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis very certaine, Sir,</L>
<L>Twas talke upon th' <HI>Exchange.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seath.</SPEAKER>
<L>We heard it too</L>
<L>In <HI>Pauls</HI> now as we came.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>There friend, there is</L>
<L>A fayre for you; I'me glad you scapt; I had
<STAGE>Gives him many.</STAGE></L>
<L>Not knowne the newes so soone else.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, excuse me,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plot.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, it is conscience; J doe believe you might</L>
<L>Sue me in <HI>Chancery.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, you show</L>
<L>The vertues of an Heyre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ware-h.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you rich <HI>Ware-house</HI></L>
<L>Heyre, Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, Sir, his transitory pelfe,</L>
<L>And some twelve hundred pound a yeare in earth,</L>
<L>Is cast on me. Captaine, the houre is come,</L>
<L>You shall no more drink. Ale, of which one draught</L>
<L>Makes Cowards, and spoiles valour; nor take off</L>
<L>Your moderate quart-glasse. I intend to have</L>
<L>A Musket for you, or glasse Canon, with</L>
<L>A most capacious barrell, which we'l charge,</L>
<L>And discharge with the rich valiant grape of</L>
<L>My Uncles sellar, every charge shall fire</L>
<L>The glasse, and burne it selfe ith' filling, and look</L>
<L>Like a Peece going off.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quartf.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall be glad</L>
<L>To give thanks for you, Sir, in pottle draughts,</L>
<L>And shall love Scotch cole for this wrack the better,</L>
<L>As long as I know fuell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then my Poet,</L>
<L>No longer shall write Catches, or thinne Sonnets,</L>
<L>Nor preach in verse, as if he were suborn'd</L>
<L>By him that wrote the whip, to pen leane Acts,</L>
<L>And so to overthrow the stage for want</L>
<L>Of salt or wit. Nor shall he need torment</L>
<L>Or persecute his Muse; but I will be</L>
<L>His God of wine t'inspire him. He shall no more</L>
<L>Converse with the five yard butler, who like Thunder</L>
<L>Can turne beere with his voice, and roare it sower;</L>
<L><PB N="30" REF="20"/>But shall come forth a <HI>Sophocles,</HI> and write</L>
<L>Things for the Buskin. Insteed of <HI>Pegasus,</HI></L>
<L>To strike a spring with's hoofe, we'l have a steele</L>
<L>Which shall but touch a <HI>But,</HI> and straight shall flow</L>
<L>A purer, higher, wealthier <HI>Helicon.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Salew.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Frank,</HI> Thou shalt be my <HI>Phoebus.</HI> My next Poem</L>
<L>Shall be thy Uncles Tragoedie or the life</L>
<L>And death of two <HI>Rich Merchants.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gentlemen,</L>
<L>And now yfaith what think you of the fish?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ware-h.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why as we ought, Sir, strangely.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>But d'you think</L>
<L>It is a very fish?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seath.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis a man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>This valiant Captaine and this man of wit</L>
<L>First foxt him, then transform'd him. we will wake him</L>
<L>And tell him the newes. Ho M<SUP>r</SUP> <HI>Timothy!</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Plague take you Captaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>What does your sack work still?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where am I?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come y'have slept enough.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>M<SUP>r</SUP> <HI>Timothy!</HI></L>
<L>How in the name of fresh Cod came you changed</L>
<L>Into a sea Calfe thus?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<L>Slight, Sir, here be</L>
<L>Two Fishmongers to buy you; beat the price</L>
<L>Now y'are awake, your selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>How's this? my hands</L>
<L>Transmuted into Clawes? my feet made flownders?</L>
<L>Arrayd in Finnes, and scales? arn't you</L>
<L>Ashamd to make me such a Monster? pray</L>
<L>Help to undresse me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>We have rare newes for you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>No letter from the Lady I hope?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Father</L>
<L>And my grave Uncle, Sir, are cast away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>How?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>They by this have made a meale</L>
<L>For Jacks and Salmon. They are drownd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fall downe</L>
<L>And worship sea-coales, for a ship of them</L>
<L>Has made you, Sir, an Heyre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>This fellow here</L>
<L>Brings the auspicious newes: And these two friends</L>
<L>Of ours confirme it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis too true, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well,</L>
<L>We are all mortall; but in what wet case</L>
<L>Had J been now, if I had gone with him.</L>
<L>Within this fortnight I had been converted</L>
<L>Into some Pike, you might ha cheapned me.</L>
<L>In <HI>Fish-street</HI>; J had made an Ordinary,</L>
<L>Perchance at the Mermaid: Now could I cry</L>
<L>Like any Image in a fountaine which
<STAGE>He faines to weepe.</STAGE></L>
<L>Runs Lamentations. O my hard misfortune!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="31" REF="20"/>
<SPEAKER>Seath.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fie Sir, good truth it is not manly in you,
<STAGE>He feignes to weepe.</STAGE></L>
<L>To weep for such a slight losse as a father.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe not cry for that.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seath.</SPEAKER>
<L>No?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>no; but to think</L>
<L>My Mother is not drownd too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seath</SPEAKER>
<L>I assure you,</L>
<L>And thats a shrewd mischance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>For then might I</L>
<L>Ha gone to th' Counting house and set at liberty</L>
<L>Those harmelesse Angels, which for many yeares</L>
<L>Have been condemned to darknesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>You'd not doe</L>
<L>Like your penurious Father, who was wont</L>
<L>To walk his dinner out in <HI>Pauls,</HI> whiles you</L>
<L>Kept Lent at home, and had, like folk in seiges,</L>
<L>Your meales weighed to you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeed they say he was</L>
<L>A Monument of <HI>Pauls.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, he was there</L>
<L>As constant as <HI>Duke Humphrey.</HI> I can show</L>
<L>The prints where he sate holes ith' loggs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>He wore</L>
<L>More pavement out with walking then would make</L>
<L>A row of new stone-Saints, and yet refused</L>
<L>To give to th' reparation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>I've heard</L>
<L>Heed make his Jack goe emptie to cousen neighbours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, when there was not fire enough to warme</L>
<L>A Mastick patch t' apply to his wives Temples</L>
<L>In great extremity of tootach. This is</L>
<L>True, M<SUP>r</SUP> <HI>Timothy,</HI> ist not?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes. Then Linnen.</L>
<L>To us was stranger then to <HI>Capuchins.</HI></L>
<L>My flesh is of an Order with wearing shirts</L>
<L>Made of the sacks that brought ore <HI>Cutchyneele,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Copprice,</HI> and <HI>Indico.</HI> My sister weares</L>
<L>Smocks made of Curran-bags.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seath.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile not endure it.</L>
<L>Lets show our selves.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ware-h.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay heare all first.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy Uncle</L>
<L>Was such another <HI>Plotwell</HI>; I have heard</L>
<L>He still last left th' <HI>Exchange</HI>; and would commend</L>
<L>The wholsomenesse oth' ayre in <HI>Moore-fields,</HI> when</L>
<L>The clock struck three sometimes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Surely my selfe,</L>
<L><HI>Cypher</HI> his Factor, and an ancient Cat,</L>
<L>Did keepe strict diet, had our Spanish fare,</L>
<L>Foure Olives among three. My Uncle would</L>
<L>Look fat with fasting; I ha knowne him surfet</L>
<L>Upon a bunch of Raysins, swoone at sight</L>
<L>Of a whole joynt, and rise an Epicure
<STAGE>They undisguise.</STAGE></L>
<L>From halfe an Orange.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ware-h.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gentlemen tis false.</L>
<L><PB N="32" REF="21"/>Cast off your Clowd. D'you know me, Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Uncle!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sea.</SPEAKER>
<L>And doe you know me, Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Father!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay,</L>
<L>We'l open all the plot, reveale your selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Cypher</HI> the waterman!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Salewit</HI> away;
<STAGE>Exit Qu. Salewit.</STAGE></L>
<L>I feele a tempest comming.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ware.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you struck</L>
<L>With a <HI>Torpedo</HI> Nephew?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seath.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha you seen too</L>
<L>A <HI>Gorgons</HI> head that you stand speechlesse? or</L>
<L>Are you a fish in earnest?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>It begins to thunder.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<L>We will make bold to take our leaves.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ware.</SPEAKER>
<L>What is</L>
<L>Your Captaine fled?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seath.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay Gentlemen, forsake</L>
<L>Your Company?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, we wave businesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Troth</L>
<L>It is not kindly done.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now, M<SUP>r</SUP> <HI>Seathrift,</HI>
<STAGE>Ex. Br. New.</STAGE></L>
<L>You see what Mourners we had had, had we</L>
<L>Been wrackt in earnest. My grievd Nephew here</L>
<L>Had made my sellar flow with teares, my wines</L>
<L>Had chargd glasse Ord'nance, our funeralls had been</L>
<L>Bewaild in pottle draughts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seath.</SPEAKER>
<L>And at our graves</L>
<L>Your Nephew and my Sonne had made a <HI>Panegyrick,</HI></L>
<L>And opend all our vertues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ungrateful Monster.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Unnaturall villaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wareh.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou Enimy to my bloud.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou worse then Parricide.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>Next my sinnes I doe</L>
<L>Repent I am thy Uncle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sea.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I thy Father.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wareh.</SPEAKER>
<L>Death O my soule, did J when first thy Father</L>
<L>Broke in estate, and then broke from the Counter</L>
<L>Where M<SUP>r</SUP> <HI>Seathrift</HI> laid him in the hole,</L>
<L>For debt among the ruines of the City,</L>
<L>And Trades like him blowne up, take thee from dust,</L>
<L>Give thee free education, put thee in</L>
<L>My own faire way of traffique; nay decree</L>
<L>To leave thee Jewels, Land, my whole estate,</L>
<L>Pardond thy former wildnesse, and couldst thou sort</L>
<L>Thy selfe with none but idle Gallants, Captaines,</L>
<L>And Poets, who must plot before they eat,</L>
<L>And make each meale a stratagem? Then could none</L>
<L>But J be subject of thy impious scoffes?</L>
<L>I swoone at sight of meat; I rise a Glutton</L>
<L>From halfe an Orange; Wretch, forgetfull wretch;</L>
<L>Fore Heaven I count it treason in my bloud</L>
<L>That gives thee a relation. But J'le take</L>
<L>A full revenge. Make thee my Heyre? J'le first</L>
<L><PB N="33" REF="21"/>Adopt a slave, brought from some Gally; One</L>
<L>Which Lawes doe put into the Inventory,</L>
<L>And men bequeath in Wills with stooles, &amp; brasse pots.</L>
<L>One who shall first be houshold stuffe, then my Heyre.</L>
<L>Or to defeat all thy large aimes J'le marry;</L>
<L><HI>Cypher,</HI> goe finde me <HI>Baneswright</HI>; he shall straight</L>
<L>Provide me a wife. I will not stay to let</L>
<L>My resolution coole. Be she a wench</L>
<L>That every day puts on her Dowry, weares</L>
<L>Her fortunes, has no portion, so she be</L>
<L>Young and likely to be fruitfull, J'le have her;</L>
<L>By all thats good I will; this afternoone;</L>
<L>I will about it straight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Se.</SPEAKER>
<L>I follow you.
<STAGE>Ex. Ware. Cyph.</STAGE></L>
<L>And as for you <HI>Tim Mermaid, Triton, Haddock,</HI></L>
<L>The wondrous <HI>Indian Fish</HI> caught neere <HI>Peru,</HI></L>
<L>Who can be of both Elements, your sight</L>
<L>Will keep you well. Here J doe cast thee off,</L>
<L>And in thy roome pronounce to make thy sister</L>
<L>My heyre; it would be most unnaturall</L>
<L>To leave a <HI>Fish</HI> Land. Lasse, Sir, one of your</L>
<L>Bright sinnes and gills must swim in seas of sack,</L>
<L>Spout rich Canaries up like Whales in Maps.</L>
<L>I know you'l not endure to see my Jack</L>
<L>Goe empty, nor weare shirts of Copprice bags,</L>
<L>Nor fast in <HI>Pauls,</HI> you. J doe hate thee now,</L>
<L>Worse then a Tempest, Quick-sand, Pyrate, Rock,</L>
<L>Or fatall Leake, I or a Privy seale.</L>
<L>Goe let the Captaine make you drunk, and let</L>
<L>Your next change be into some Ape, (tis stale</L>
<L>To be a <HI>Fish</HI> twice) or some active <HI>Baboone.</HI></L>
<L>And when you can find mony out, betray</L>
<L>What wench ith' Roome has lost her maiden-head;</L>
<L>Can mount to'th King, and can doe all your feats,</L>
<L>If your fine chaine, and yellow coat come neere</L>
<L>Th' <HI>Exchange,</HI> Jle see you, so I leave you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plot.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now
<STAGE>Ex. Sea.</STAGE></L>
<L>Were there a dextrons beame and two-pence hemp,</L>
<L>Never had man such cause to hang himselfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have brought my selfe to a fine passe too▪ Now</L>
<L>Am J fit only to be caught, and put</L>
<L>Into a pond to leap Carps, or beget</L>
<L>A goodly race of Pickrel▪</L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="scene">
<PB N="34" REF="22"/>
<HEAD>SCENA. IV.</HEAD>
<STAGE>To them Quartfield. Salewit. Roseclap, and Baneswright.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quartf.</SPEAKER>
<L>HOw now mad Lads, what? is the storme broke up?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Salew.</SPEAKER>
<L>What sad like brokē Gamsters? M<SUP>r</SUP> <HI>Timothy</HI></L>
<L>'Slight who would think your Father should lay weeles</L>
<L>To catch you thus?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>If ever I be drunk</L>
<L>With Captaines more—.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where's <HI>Bright</HI> and <HI>Newcut</HI>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Salew.</SPEAKER>
<L>They</L>
<L>Were sent for to the <HI>Temple,</HI> but left word</L>
<L>They would be here at supper.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are sure friends,</L>
<L>To leave us in distresse:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quartf.</SPEAKER>
<L>What a mad plot</L>
<L>These two old Merchants had contriv'd, to faine</L>
<L>A voyage, then to hunt you out disguised,</L>
<L>And heare themselves abused?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Salew.</SPEAKER>
<L>We heard all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quart.</SPEAKER>
<L>If J had staid they had paid me for a Captaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Salew.</SPEAKER>
<L>They had a fling at me. But doe you think</L>
<L>Your Uncle in this furious mood will marry?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>He deeply swore it; if he doe, the slight</L>
<L>Upon the cards, the hollow dye, <HI>Park corner,</HI></L>
<L>And <HI>Shooters hill</HI> are my revenue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes,</L>
<L>And as for me, my destiny will be</L>
<L>To fight by th' day, carry my Kitchen, and</L>
<L>Collation at my back, weare orderly</L>
<L>My shirt in course, after 't has been the shift</L>
<L>Of a whole Regiment in the <HI>Low-Countries.</HI></L>
<L>And after all returne with halfe a leg,</L>
<L>One arme perchance, my nose shot off, to move</L>
<L>Compassion in my father, who in pitty</L>
<L>To so much ruine my be brought to buy</L>
<L>Some place for me in an Hospitall, to keep me</L>
<L>From Bridges, Hill-tops, &amp; from selling switches.
<STAGE>Ent. Rosecl.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yonders your Uncle at the field dore talking</L>
<L>With <HI>Baneswright,</HI> as hot, and earnest for a wench,</L>
<L>As a recovered <HI>Monsieur.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quartf.</SPEAKER>
<L>What is this <HI>Baneswright</HI>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Salew.</SPEAKER>
<L>A fellow much imploid about the Towne,</L>
<L>That contrives Matches. One that brings together</L>
<L>Parties that never saw, or ever met,</L>
<L><PB N="35" REF="22"/>Till't be for good and all. Knowes to a penny</L>
<L>Estates and Joyntures; J'le undertake he has</L>
<L>Now lying by him unprovided some twenty</L>
<L>Widdowes of all fortunes that want husbands,</L>
<L>And men that want wives, and at an houres warning</L>
<L>Can make things ready for the Priest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quartf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let us</L>
<L>Devise to get him hither and crosse the Match.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have great interest in him, the fellow loves me.</L>
<L>Could I speake with him and draw him to be</L>
<L>An Actor in't, J have a stratagem</L>
<L>That can redeeme all, and turne the plot
<STAGE>Enter Baneswright.</STAGE></L>
<L>Upon these sage heads.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Salew.</SPEAKER>
<L>By <HI>Minerva,</HI> look,</L>
<L>Heres <HI>Baneswright.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plot.</SPEAKER>
<L>M<SUP>r</SUP> <HI>Baneswright!</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ban.</SPEAKER>
<L>Save you Gal∣lants.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are imploid I heare to find a wife out</L>
<L>For my young sprightly Uncle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Banes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, he has</L>
<L>Retain'd me to that purpose. I just now</L>
<L>Came from him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>And doe you meane the match</L>
<L>Shall then proceed?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Banesw.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have a Leiger wench</L>
<L>In readinesse, he's gone to put himselfe</L>
<L>Into fit ornaments, for the solemnitie.</L>
<L>I'me to provide the Priest and Licence, we goe</L>
<L>Some two houres hence to Church.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Death you Pander.</L>
<L>Forbid the banes or I will cut your wizzell;</L>
<L>And spoile your squiring in the dark; J've heard</L>
<L>Of your lewd function, Sirrah; you preferre</L>
<L>Wenches to Bawdy-houses, Rascall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Banesw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good, Sir.</L>
<L>Threaten me not in my vocation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why <HI>Baneswright</HI> you can be but paid, say I</L>
<L>Procure the wench, a friend of mine; and double</L>
<L>Your bargaine, such a faire reward me thinks</L>
<L>Should make thee of my project. Thou dost know</L>
<L>My fortunes are ingaged, and thou maist be</L>
<L>The happy instrument to recover 'em.</L>
<L>Be my good Angell once, I have a plot</L>
<L>Shall make thee famous.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quartf.</SPEAKER>
<L>By <HI>Mars</HI> deny, and I</L>
<L>Will act a Tragoedy upon thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Banes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gentlemen,</L>
<L>I am a friend to wit, but more to you, Sir.</L>
<L>Of whose misfortunes I will not be guilty.</L>
<L>Though, then, your Uncle have imploid me, and</L>
<L>Have deeply sworne to wed this afternoone,</L>
<L><PB N="36" REF="23"/>A wife of my providing, if you can</L>
<L>O'rereach the angry Burgesse, Sir, and bring</L>
<L>His wisdome to the Ginne, show me the way</L>
<L>I'le help to lay the trap.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quartf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now thou art</L>
<L>An honest hearted pimp, thou shalt for this</L>
<L>Be drunk in <HI>Vine Dee,</HI> Rascall: I'le begin</L>
<L>A Runlet to thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gentlemen lets in,</L>
<L>I'le tell you my designe; you, <HI>Salewit,</HI> must</L>
<L>Transforme your selfe to a <HI>French Deacon.</HI> J</L>
<L>have parts for <HI>Bright</HI> and <HI>Newcut</HI> too. Mischiefe</L>
<L>Upon their absence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Salew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee'l send for 'em.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plot.</SPEAKER>
<L>And</L>
<L>For M<SUP>r</SUP> <HI>Timothy</HI> J have a project</L>
<L>Shall make his father everlastingly</L>
<L>Admire his wit, and aske him blessing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quart.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come,</L>
<L>Lets in and drink a health to our successe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'me for no healths unlesse the glasse be lesse.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="4" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACTVS IIII.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA I.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Stathrift. M</HI><SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Seathrift. M</HI><SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Holland. M</HI><SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Scruple.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seath.</SPEAKER>
<L>I did commit her to your charge that you</L>
<L>Might breed her, <HI>M</HI><SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Scruple,</HI> and doe require</L>
<L>Her at your hand. Here be fine tricks, indeed;</L>
<L>My daughter <HI>Susan</HI> to be stolne a week,</L>
<L>And you conceale it; you were of the plot,</L>
<L>I doe suspect you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M<SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Scru.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, will you but heare</L>
<L>Me meekly?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seath.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, J'le never trust againe</L>
<L>A woman with white eyes, that can take notes,</L>
<L>And write a Comment on the Catechisme.</L>
<L>All your devotion's false; ist possible</L>
<L>She could be gone without your knowledge?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M<SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Scru.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Will you</L>
<L>Attend me, M<SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Seathrift</HI>? If my husband</L>
<L>To weane her from love courses, did not take</L>
<L>More paines with her then with his Tuesday Lectures,</L>
<L>And if J did not every day expound</L>
<L>Some good things to her gainst the sinne oth' flesh,</L>
<L><PB N="37" REF="23"/>For feare of such temptations, to which fraile girles</L>
<L>Are very subject, let me never more</L>
<L>Be thought fit to instruct young Gentlewomen,</L>
<L>Or deale in Tent-stitch. Who ere twas that seduced her,</L>
<L>She took my daughter <HI>Emlins</HI> gowne and ruffe,</L>
<L>And left her owne clothes: and my Schollers say</L>
<L>She often would write Letters.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seath.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why tis right</L>
<L>Some silenc't Minister has got her: that J</L>
<L>Should breed my daughter in a Conventicle!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>M</HI><SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Seath.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Pray husband be appeas'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seat.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are a foole.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>M</HI><SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Seath.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>You heare her M<SUP>s</SUP> could not help it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seath.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor</L>
<L>Your sonne help being a fish.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>M</HI><SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Holl.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Why, Sir, was he</L>
<L>The first that was abus'd by Captaines?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seath.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe</L>
<L>You talke like prating Gossips.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>M</HI><SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Holl.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Gossips? slight</L>
<L>What Gossips, Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>M</HI><SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Seath.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>What Gossips are we? speak.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seath.</SPEAKER>
<L>J'le tell you since youd know: my wife and you,</L>
<L>Shrill <HI>M</HI><SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Holland,</HI> have two tongues, that when</L>
<L>Th'are in conjunction, are busier, and make</L>
<L>More noise then country faires, and utter more tales</L>
<L>Then blind-folkes, Mid-wives, Nurses. Then no show</L>
<L>Though't be a Jugler scapes you. You did follow</L>
<L>The <HI>Elephant</HI> so long, and King of <HI>Sweden,</HI></L>
<L>That people at last came in to see you. Then</L>
<L>My sonne could not be made a <HI>Fish,</HI> but who</L>
<L>Should I finde there much taken with the sight</L>
<L>But you two? I may now build Hospitals,</L>
<L>Or give my mony to <HI>Plantations.</HI>
<STAGE>Exit Seath.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>M</HI><SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Seath.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Lets follow him, come <HI>M</HI><SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Scruple.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>M</HI><SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Holl.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Just</L>
<L>As your <HI>Sue</HI> left her Schoole-mistresse, my <HI>Pen</HI></L>
<L>Left me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>M</HI><SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Scru.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>They'l come againe J warrant you.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA II.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Plotwell. Aurelia.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>SIster tis so projected, therefore make</L>
<L>No more demurres, the life of both our fortunes</L>
<L>Lies in your carriage of things well▪ think therefore</L>
<L>Whither you will restore me, and advance</L>
<L><PB N="38" REF="24"/>Your own affaires, or else within this week</L>
<L>Fly this your lodging, like uncustomd sinners,</L>
<L>And have your Coach-horses transformd to Rent,</L>
<L>Have your apparell sold for properties,</L>
<L>And you returne to Cut-work. By this hand</L>
<L>If you refuse all this must happen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, Sir,</L>
<L>Necessitie which hath no Law, for once</L>
<L>Shall make me oth' conspiracy, and since</L>
<L>We are left wholy to our wits, Let's show</L>
<L>The power and vertue of 'em; if your <HI>Baneswright</HI></L>
<L>Can but perswade my Uncle, I will fit</L>
<L>Him with a Bride.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Scene is laid already;</L>
<L>I have transformd an English Poet into</L>
<L>A fine French Teacher, who shall joyne your hands</L>
<L>With a most learned legend out of <HI>Rablais.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>But for my true groom who you say comes hi∣ther</L>
<L>For a disguised Knight, I shall think I wed</L>
<L>His Fathers Counting-house, and goe to bed</L>
<L>To so much Bullion of a man▪ Faith I've</L>
<L>No minde to him, brother, he hath not wit enough</L>
<L>To make't a lawfull marriage.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plot.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y' are deceivd,</L>
<L>I'le undertake by one weekes Tutoring,</L>
<L>And carrying him to Plaies and Ordinaries,</L>
<L>Engaging him in a quarrell or two, and making</L>
<L>Some Captaine beat him, to render him a most</L>
<L>Accomplisht Gallant. Or say he be borne, sister,</L>
<L>Under the City planet, pray what wise Lady</L>
<L>Desires to match a wise Knight? you'd marry some</L>
<L>Philosopher now, that should every night</L>
<L>Lye with you out of <HI>Aristotle,</HI> and loose</L>
<L>Your maiden-head by Demonstration.</L>
<L>Or some great statesman, before whom you must sit</L>
<L>As silent and reservd as if your looks</L>
<L>Had plots on forreine Princes, and must visit</L>
<L>And dresse your selfe by <HI>Tacitus.</HI> What he wants</L>
<L>In Naturals, his fortunes will make up</L>
<L>In Honours, <HI>Pen</HI>; when hee's once made a Lord,</L>
<L>Who'l be so sawey as to think he can</L>
<L>Be impotent in wisdome? She that marries</L>
<L>A foole, is an <HI>Hermaphrodite,</HI> the Man</L>
<L><PB N="39" REF="24"/>And wife too, sister. Besides tis now too late,</L>
<L>He'l be here presently, and comes prepar'd</L>
<L>For <HI>Hymen.</HI> I took up a footman for him,</L>
<L>And left him under three tyremens hands, besides</L>
<L>Two Barbers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, Sir, I must then accept him</L>
<L>With all his imperfections, J have</L>
<L>Procur'd a Sir <HI>Iohn</HI> yonder.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw</SPEAKER>
<L>Who ist?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>One</L>
<L>That preaches the next parish once a week
<STAGE>Enter a Footman</STAGE></L>
<L>A sleep for thirty pounds a yeare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Foot.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here is</L>
<L>A Knight desires your Ladiship will give</L>
<L>Him audience.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis no Knight Embassadour?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Foot.</SPEAKER>
<L>He rather lookes like a Knight oth' Sun.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis He.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let him come in.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plot.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you be coy now, <HI>Pen,</HI>
<STAGE>Ex. Foot.</STAGE></L>
<L>You spoile all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, Sir, I'le be affable.</L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA III.</HEAD>
<STAGE>To them Timothy fantastically drest, and a Footman.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>HEre he comes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sirrah, wait me in the Hall,</L>
<L>And let your feet stink there; your ayre's not fit,</L>
<L>To be endured by Ladies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>What quarrell with</L>
<L>Your Footman, Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hang him, he casts a sent</L>
<L>That drownes my perfumes, and is strong enough</L>
<L>To cure the Mother or Palsie. Doe I act</L>
<L>A Knight well?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>This imperiousnesse becomes you</L>
<L>Like a Knight newly dubd, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>What saies the Lady?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speak lower, J've prepar'd her, show your selfe</L>
<L>A Courtier now she's yours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>If that be all</L>
<L>I'le Court her as if some Courtier had begot me</L>
<L>Ith' Gallery at a Masque.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, this Gentleman</L>
<L>Desires to kisse your hands.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>And lips too Lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, you much honour both.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, I know that,</L>
<L>Else Ide not kisse you. Yesterday J was</L>
<L>In company with Ladies and they all</L>
<L>Long'd to be toucht by me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>You cannot cure</L>
<L>The <HI>Evill,</HI> Sir, nor have your lips the vertue</L>
<L>To restore ruines, or make old Ladies young?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith all the vertue that they have, is that</L>
<L><PB N="40" REF="25"/>My lips are knighted. J am borne, sweet Lady,</L>
<L>To a poore fortune that will keep my selfe,</L>
<L>And Foot-man, as you see, to beare my sword</L>
<L>In <HI>Cuerpo</HI> after me I can at Court,</L>
<L>If J would show my gilt ith' <HI>Presence,</HI> look</L>
<L>After the rate of some five thousands</L>
<L>Yearely in old rents, and were my Father once</L>
<L>Well wrapt in seare-cloth, I could fine for Sheriffe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heart you spoile all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plot.</SPEAKER>
<L>She verily believd</L>
<L>Y'had nere a father.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lives your father, then Sir?</L>
<L>That Gentleman told me he was dead.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis true,</L>
<L>I had forgot my selfe, he was drownd, Lady,</L>
<L>This morning, as he went to take possession</L>
<L>Of a summer house and land in the <HI>Canaries.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now y'have recoverd all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>D' you think I have</L>
<L>Not wit enough to lye?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Break your minde to her,</L>
<L>She does expect it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>But Lady this is not</L>
<L>The businesse which J came for.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'me at leisure</L>
<L>To heare your businesse, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mark that.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeed,</L>
<L>Sweet Lady, I've a motion which was once</L>
<L>Or twice this morning in my mouth, and then</L>
<L>Slipt back againe for feare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cowards nere won</L>
<L>Ladies, or Forts, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Say then I should feele</L>
<L>Some motions, Lady, of affection; might</L>
<L>A man repaire <HI>Pauls</HI> with your heart, or put it</L>
<L>Into a Tinder-box?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>How meane you, Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why is your heart a stone, or flint?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be plain, Sir,</L>
<L>I understand you not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not understand me?</L>
<L>Y' are the first Lady that ere put a man</L>
<L>To speak plaine English; some would understand</L>
<L>Riddles, and signes; say J should love you, Lady?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>There should be no love lost, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Say you so?</L>
<L>Then by this aire my teeth eene water at you;</L>
<L>I long to have some Off-spring by you; we</L>
<L>Shall have an excellent breed of wits; J meane</L>
<L>My youngest sonne shall be a Poet; and</L>
<L>My Daughters, like their Mother, every one</L>
<L>A wench oth' game. And for my eldest sonne,</L>
<L>He shall be like me, and inherit. Therefore</L>
<L>Lets not deferre our joyes, but goe to bed</L>
<L><PB N="41" REF="25"/>And multiply.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Soft, Sir, the Priest must first</L>
<L>Discharge his office. I doe not mean to marry
<STAGE>Enter Dorcas out of her Puritan dresse</STAGE></L>
<L>Like Ladies in <HI>New England,</HI> where they couple</L>
<L>With no more ceremony then birds choose their Mate</L>
<L>Upon S<SUP>t</SUP> <HI>Valentines</HI> day.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam the Preacher</L>
<L>Is sent for to a Churching, and doth aske</L>
<L>If you be ready, he shall loose, he saies,</L>
<L>His Chrysome else.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>O miracle! out of</L>
<L>your litle Ruffe, <HI>Dorcas,</HI> and in the fashion?</L>
<L>Dost thou hope to be saved?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray Madam doe not</L>
<L>Abuse me; J will tell you more anon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tell him shees comming.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, please you par∣take</L>
<L>Of a slight banquet?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Just as you are sate
<STAGE>Exit Dorcas.</STAGE></L>
<L>I'le steale the Priest in.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pl.</SPEAKER>
<L>When you are joind,</L>
<L>Be sure you doe not oversee, but straight</L>
<L>Retire to bed, she'l follow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis not three</L>
<L>A clock ith' afternoone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis but drawing</L>
<L>Your Curtaines and you doe create your night.</L>
<L>All times to Lovers and New married folkes</L>
<L>May be made dark.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>J will then. By this Roome</L>
<L>She's a rare Lady. J doe almost wish</L>
<L>I could change sexe, and that she might beget</L>
<L>Children on me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay will you enter?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ladie,</L>
<L>Pray will you show the way.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most Citie like,</L>
<L>'Slid take her by the arme, and lead her in.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your arme sweet Lady.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA IV.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Bright. Newcut.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>BUt are you sure th' are they?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le not believe</L>
<L>My treacherous eies againe, but trust some dog</L>
<L>To guid me, if J did not see his Uncle</L>
<L>Comming this way, and <HI>Baneswright</HI> with him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who,</L>
<L>The fellow that brings Love to banes, and banes</L>
<L>To bare thighes 'bout the towne?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<L>The very same, Sir;</L>
<L>The Citie <HI>Cupid</HI> that shoots arrowes betwixt</L>
<L>Partie and partie. All the difference is,</L>
<L><PB N="42" REF="26"/>He has his eyes, but they he brings together</L>
<L>Sometimes doe not see one another till</L>
<L>Till they meet ith' Church.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>What say you now if <HI>Ware-house</HI></L>
<L>Should in displeasure marry?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis so, this fellow</L>
<L>In's company confirmes me. Tis the very businesse</L>
<L>Why <HI>Plotwell</HI> has sent for us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here they come.</L>
<L>Prithee lets stand and overheare 'em.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stand close then.</L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA. V.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Ware-house. Baneswright.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ware-h.</SPEAKER>
<L>MAdam <HI>Aurelia</HI> is her name?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ban.</SPEAKER>
<L>Her father</L>
<L>Was, Sir, an Irish <HI>Baron,</HI> that undid</L>
<L>Himselfe by house-keeping.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>As for her birth</L>
<L>I could wish it were meaner. As many Knights</L>
<L>And Justices of peace as have been of</L>
<L>The Family are reckoned into th' portion;</L>
<L>She'l still be naming of her <HI>Ancestors,</HI></L>
<L>Aske Jointure by the <HI>Heralds</HI> booke, and I</L>
<L>That have no <HI>Coat,</HI> nor can show <HI>azure Lions,</HI></L>
<L>In <HI>Fields</HI> of <HI>Argent,</HI> shall be scornd; she'l think</L>
<L>Her Honour wrongd to match a man that hath</L>
<L>No <HI>Scutcheons</HI> but them of his <HI>Company,</HI></L>
<L>Which once a yeare doe serve to trim a Lighter</L>
<L>To <HI>Westminster</HI> and back againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ban.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are</L>
<L>Mistaken, Sir. This Lady as she is</L>
<L>Descended of a great house, so she hath</L>
<L>No Dowrie but her <HI>Armes.</HI> She can bring only</L>
<L>Some <HI>Libbards</HI> heads, or strange beasts, which you knowe</L>
<L>Being but Beasts, let them derive themselves</L>
<L>From <HI>Monsters</HI> in the <HI>Globe,</HI> and lineally</L>
<L>Proceed from <HI>Hercules</HI> labours, they will never</L>
<L>Advance her to a husband equall to</L>
<L>Her selfe in birth, that can give Beasts too. She</L>
<L>Aimes only to match one that can maintaine</L>
<L>Her some way to her state. She is possest</L>
<L>What streames of gold you flow in, Sir,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ware-h.</SPEAKER>
<L>But can she</L>
<L>Affect my age?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Banes.</SPEAKER>
<L>I askt her that; and told her</L>
<L><PB N="43" REF="26"/>You were about some threescore, S<SUP>r</SUP>, and ten;</L>
<L>But were as lusty as one of twenty, (or</L>
<L>An aged <HI>Eunuch</HI>)</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ware-h.</SPEAKER>
<L>And what replyed shee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bans.</SPEAKER>
<L>shee,</L>
<L>Like a true <HI>Lucrece,</HI> answerd it was fit</L>
<L>For them to Marry by the Church booke, who</L>
<L>Came there to coole themselves; But to a Mind</L>
<L>Chast and indued with vertue, age did turne</L>
<L>Love into Reverence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or S<SUP>r</SUP> Reverence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prythe observe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ware-h.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is shee so vertuous then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Banes.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis all the fault shee has, she will out-pray</L>
<L>A Preacher at <HI>S</HI><SUP>t</SUP> <HI>Antlins</HI>; and divides</L>
<L>The day in exercise; I did commend</L>
<L>A great <HI>Precisian</HI> to her for her woman.</L>
<L>Who tells me that her Lady makes her quilt</L>
<L>Her smocks before for kneeling.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ware-h.</SPEAKER>
<L>Excellent Creature!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Banes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then, Sir, she is so modest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ware-h.</SPEAKER>
<L>Too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Banes.</SPEAKER>
<L>The least</L>
<L>Obscene word shames her, a lascivious Figure</L>
<L>Makes her doe pennance; and she maintaines the Law</L>
<L>Which forbids fornication, doth extend</L>
<L>To kissing too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ware-h.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thinke the time an age</L>
<L>Till the solemnity be past.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Banes.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have</L>
<L>Prepared her, S<SUP>r</SUP>, and have so set you out!</L>
<L>Besides, I told her how you had cast of</L>
<L>Your <HI>Nephew,</HI> and to leave no doubt that you</L>
<L>Would ere be reconcil'd, before she went</L>
<L>To Church would settle your estate on her,</L>
<L>And on the Heyres of her begotten.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ware-h.</SPEAKER>
<L>To make all sure,</L>
<L>Wee'l call upon my Lawyer by the way,</L>
<L>And take him with us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Banes.</SPEAKER>
<L>you must be married, S<SUP>r</SUP>,</L>
<L>At the <HI>French</HI> Church, J have bespoke the Priest;</L>
<L>One that will joyne you i'th right <HI>Geneva</HI> forme,</L>
<L>Without a licence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ware-h.</SPEAKER>
<L>But may a man</L>
<L>Wed in a strange tongue?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Banes.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have brought together</L>
<L>Some in <HI>Italian,</HI> S<SUP>r</SUP>, the Language doth</L>
<L>Not change the substance of the Match; you know</L>
<L>No licence will be granted, all the Offices</L>
<L>Are before-hand bribed by your <HI>Nephew.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ware-h.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well,</L>
<L>Lets to the Lady straight, to crosse him, I</L>
<L>Would marry an <HI>Arabian,</HI> and be at charge</L>
<L>To keepe one to interpret, or be married</L>
<PB N="42" REF="27"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="43" REF="27"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<L><PB N="44" REF="28"/>In <HI>China</HI> Language, or the tongue thats spoke
<STAGE>Exit Ware. and Banes.</STAGE></L>
<L>By the great <HI>Cham.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now <HI>Newcut,</HI> you perceive</L>
<L>My divination's true, this fellow did</L>
<L>Portend a wedding.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<L>Plague oth' prognostication.</L>
<L>Who'd thinke that Madam were the Partye?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh S<SUP>r</SUP>,</L>
<L>Shee'l call this wit to wed his baggs, and lye</L>
<L>With some <HI>Platonick</HI> servant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<L>What if we</L>
<L>Before we goe to <HI>Plotwell,</HI> went to her</L>
<L>And striv'd to disswade her?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lets make hast,</L>
<L>They'l be before us else.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="6" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA. VI.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Timothy unbuttoning himselfe. Aurelia. Plotwell. Dorcas. Foot-man.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>BY this hand Lady you shall not deny me:</L>
<L>Since we are coupled, I shall thinke the Priest</L>
<L>Has not done all, as long as I'me a Virgin.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you not stay till night, Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Night? No faith,</L>
<L>I've sworne to get my first child by day, you may</L>
<L>Be quicke by night.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plot.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, your Knight speaks reason.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will both speake and doe it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well Sir, since</L>
<L>There is no remedy, your beds prepared;</L>
<L>By that time you are layed I'le come, Meane time</L>
<L>Ile pray that Gentleman to conduct you, There's</L>
<L>My Foot-man to plucke of your stockins.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweet Lady stay not long.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plot.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le promise for her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith I admire your temperance to let
<STAGE>Ex. Tim. Pl. &amp; Footman.</STAGE></L>
<L>Your Bride-groom goe to bed and you not follow.</L>
<L>Were J in your case J should ha gone first,</L>
<L>And warm'd his place.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well wench but that thou hast</L>
<L>Reveal'd thy selfe unto me, I'de admire</L>
<L>To heare a Saint talke thus. To one that knowes not</L>
<L>The Mystery of thy strange conversion, Thou</L>
<L>Wouldst seeme a Legend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith I have told you all,</L>
<L>Both why I left my Schoole-Mistresse, who taught me</L>
<L>To confute Curling-Irons, and why I put</L>
<L>My selfe on this adventure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well wench my brother</L>
<L><PB N="45" REF="28"/>Has had his plots on me, and Ile contribute</L>
<L>My helpe to worke thy honest Ones on him.</L>
<L>Doe but performe thy taske well and thou winn'st him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dor</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me alone; never was man so fitted
<STAGE>Enter Foot-man.</STAGE></L>
<L>With a chast Bride, as I will fit his Uncle.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Foot.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam your Knight doth call most fiercely for you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prithee, goe tell him some businesse keepes me yet,</L>
<L>And bid him stay himselfe with this kisse.</L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="7" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA. VII.</HEAD>
<STAGE>As they kisse.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter to them Bright. Newcut.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>BY your leave Madam, what for practise sake</L>
<L>Kissing your woman? Lord how a Ladies lips</L>
<L>Hate Idlenesse, and will be busied, when</L>
<L>The rest lyes fallow, And rather then want action</L>
<L>Be kind within themselves, an't be t'enjoy,</L>
<L>But the poore pleasure of contemplation!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<L>And how doe you find her Madam?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay wench.</L>
<L>Does it not grieve you now, and make you sigh,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lord,</L>
<L>And very passionately accuse Nature,</L>
<L>And say she was too hard to make your woman</L>
<L>Able to kisse you only and doe no more?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>Js it not pittie but besides the guift</L>
<L>Of making <HI>Cawdles,</HI> and using of her <HI>Pencill,</HI></L>
<L>She had the trick oth'other sexe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Me thinks</L>
<L>Your own good breeding might instruct you that</L>
<L>My house is not a new Foundation, where</L>
<L>You might, paying the rate, approach, be rude,</L>
<L>Give freedome to your unwasht Mouthes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dor.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lady</L>
<L>Keepes no poore <HI>Nuns</HI> that sinne for victuals, for you,</L>
<L>With whom this dead vacation you may trade</L>
<L>For old silke stockins and halfe shirts. They say</L>
<L>You doe offend oth' score, and sinne in chalke,</L>
<L>And the dumbe walls complaine you are behinde</L>
<L>Jn pension; so that your distressed Vestalls,</L>
<L>Are faine to foot their stockins, pay the Brewer,</L>
<L><PB N="46" REF="29"/>And Land-Lords-rent in <HI>woman-kind,</HI> and long</L>
<L>More earnestly for the Terme then <HI>Norfolke</HI> Lawyers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why you have got a second, Ladie, your woman</L>
<L>Doth speake good Countrey language.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<L>Offers at wit,</L>
<L>And showes teeth for a jest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>We heare you are</L>
<L>To marry an old Citizen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then surely</L>
<L>You were not deafe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<L>And doe you mean his age,</L>
<L>Which hath seene all the Kingdome buried thrice,</L>
<L>To whom the heate of <HI>August</HI> is <HI>December</HI>;
<STAGE>Ex. Dorcas.</STAGE></L>
<L>Who, were he but in <HI>Italy</HI> would save</L>
<L>The charge of <HI>Marble</HI> vaults, and coole the ayre</L>
<L>Better then <HI>ventiducts,</HI> shall freeze betweene</L>
<L>Your melting armes? Doe but consider, he</L>
<L>But marries you as he would doe his furres,</L>
<L>To keepe him warme.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>But he is rich, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then,</L>
<L>In wedding him you wed more infirmities</L>
<L>Then ever <HI>Gallen</HI> wrot of; He has paines</L>
<L>That put the Doctors to new experiments.</L>
<L>Halfe his diseases in the Citie bill</L>
<L>Kill hundreds weekly. Alone Hospitall</L>
<L>Were but enough for him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<L>Besides,</L>
<L>He has a cough that nightly drownes the <HI>Bell-man</HI>;</L>
<L>Calls up his Familie; all his neighbours rise</L>
<L>And goe by it, as by the <HI>Chimes</HI> and <HI>Clock.</HI></L>
<L>Not fowre loame walls, nor saw dust put between,</L>
<L>Can dead it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet he still is rich.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>Jf this</L>
<L>Cannot affright you, but that you will needs</L>
<L>Be blind to wholesome counsill, and will marry</L>
<L>One who by th' course of Nature ought t' have been</L>
<L>Rotten before the Queens time, and in Iustice</L>
<L>Should now have been some threescore yeares a Ghost,</L>
<L>Let pitty move you; Jn this Match you quite</L>
<L>Dostroy the hopes and fortunes of a Gentleman,</L>
<L>For whom had his penurious Uncle starv'd</L>
<L>And pin'd himselfe his whole life, to encrease</L>
<L>The riches he deservest' inherit it</L>
<L>Had been his dutie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur</SPEAKER>
<L>You meane his Nephew <HI>Plotwell</HI>;</L>
<L>A prodigall young man; one whom the good</L>
<L>Old man his Uncle kept to th' Inns of Court,</L>
<L>And would in time ha made him <HI>Barrester;</HI></L>
<L><PB N="47" REF="29"/>And raisd him to his sattin <HI>Cap,</HI> and <HI>Biggon,</HI></L>
<L>In which he might ha sold his breath farre dearer,</L>
<L>And let his tongue out at a greater price,</L>
<L>Then some their Mannors. But he did neglect</L>
<L>These thriving meanes; followd his loose companions,</L>
<L>His <HI>Brights</HI> and <HI>Newcuts</HI>; two, they say, that live</L>
<L>By the new Heresie <HI>Platonick Love.</HI></L>
<L>Can take up silks upon their strengths, and pay</L>
<L>Their Mercer with an Infant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>Newcut!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<L>I,</L>
<L>J doe observe her Character; well then</L>
<L>You are resolvd to marry?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Were the Man</L>
<L>A statue, so it were a golden one,</L>
<L>I'de have him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray then take along to Church</L>
<L>These few good wishes. May your husband prove</L>
<L>So jealous to suspect that when you drink</L>
<L>To any man you kisse the place where his</L>
<L>Lips were before, and so pledge meetings. Let him</L>
<L>Think you doe Cuckold him by looks; and let him</L>
<L>Each night, before you goe to rest, administer</L>
<L>A solemne oath, that all your thoughts were chast</L>
<L>That day, and that you sleep with all your hayres.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<L>And which is worse, let him forget he lay</L>
<L>With you himselfe, before some Magistrate</L>
<L>Sweare twas some other, and have it believ'd</L>
<L>Upon Record.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sister J've left your Bridegroome,</L>
<L>Under this key lockt in, t' imbrace your pillow.
<STAGE>Enter Plotw.</STAGE></L>
<L>Sure he has eat <HI>Eringoes,</HI> he's as hot—</L>
<L>He was about to fetch you in his shirt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hows this? his sister?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New</SPEAKER>
<L>J conceive not this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pl.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Noble friends, you wonder now to heare</L>
<L>Me call her sister.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith, Sir, we wonder more</L>
<L>She should be married?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'ft be your sister, we</L>
<L>Have labourd her she should not match her Uncle,</L>
<L>And bring forth Riddles, Children that should be</L>
<L>Nephews to their Father, and to their Uncle sonnes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>I laugh now at your ignorance: why these</L>
<L>Are projects, Gentlemen; fine ginns, and projects.</L>
<L>Did <HI>Roseclaps</HI> boy come to you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pl.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have</L>
<L>A rare Scene for you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<L>The boy told us you were</L>
<L>Upon a stratagem.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>I've sent for <HI>Roseclap,</HI></L>
<L><PB N="48" REF="30"/>And Captaine <HI>Quartfield</HI> to be here. J have</L>
<L>Put <HI>Salewit</HI> into orders, he's inducted</L>
<L>Into the <HI>French Church,</HI> you must all have parts;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prithee speak out of Clowds.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pl.</SPEAKER>
<L>By this good light</L>
<L>Twere Justice now to let you both dye simple,</L>
<L>For leaving us so scirvily.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<L>We were</L>
<L>Sent for in hast by th' <HI>Benchers,</HI> to contribute</L>
<L>To one of'em thats <HI>Reader.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come with me,</L>
<L>I'le tell you then. But first J'le show you a sight</L>
<L>Much stranger then the <HI>Fish.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, heres <HI>Barneswright</HI></L>
<L>And an old Merchant doe desire accesse.
<STAGE>Enter Dorcas.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bid 'em come in.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gentlemen, fall off.
<STAGE>Ex. Dorcas.</STAGE></L>
<L>If we be seene the plot is spoild. Sister,</L>
<L>Now look you doe your part well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>J am perfect.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Plot. Br. Newc.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="8" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA VIII.</HEAD>
<STAGE>To Her Baneswright. Ware-house. Dorcas.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Banes.</SPEAKER>
<L>MAdam, this is the Gentleman J mention'd,</L>
<L>I've brought him here, according to my function</L>
<L>To give you both an enterview; if you</L>
<L>Be ready, the Church and Priest are.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is this, Sir,</L>
<L>The wealthy Merchant?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Banes.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Madam,</HI> this is He</L>
<L>That if you'l weare the price of <HI>Baronies,</HI></L>
<L>Or live at <HI>Cleopatra's</HI> rate can keep you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come you a Suitor, Sir, to me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ware-h.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes Lady,</L>
<L>I did imploy my speaker there, who hath</L>
<L>I hope inform'd you with my purpose.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Surely,</L>
<L>Your speaker then hath errd; I understood</L>
<L>Him for my woman, if you can like her, Sir,</L>
<L>It being for ought I heare, all one to you,</L>
<L>I've woo'd her for you. But for my selfe, could you</L>
<L>Endow me with the streame that ebbs and flowes</L>
<L>In waves of gold, J hope you doe not think</L>
<L>Ide so much staine my birth as to be bought</L>
<L>To match into a <HI>Company</HI>▪ Sir, plainely,</L>
<L>I'me matcht already.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ware-h.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Baneswright,</HI> did not you</L>
<L>Tell me she'd have me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Banesw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith, Sir, I have eares</L>
<L><PB N="49" REF="30"/>That might deceive me, but I did dreame waking</L>
<L>If she were not the party. <HI>Madam,</HI> pray you</L>
<L>One word in private.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le prevent you; tis true,</L>
<L>My Brother laid the Scene for me, but since</L>
<L>W'have changd the plot, and tis contriv'd, my woman</L>
<L>Shall undertake my part.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ban.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am instructed.</L>
<L>I was mistaken, Sir, indeed the Lady</L>
<L>Spoke to me for her <HI>Gentlewoman.</HI> How</L>
<L>Doe you affect her, Sir? you see she is</L>
<L>As handsome as her Ladie, and her birth</L>
<L>Not being so high she will more size with you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ware-h.</SPEAKER>
<L>I say, J like her best. Her Ladie has</L>
<L>Too much great house in her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ban.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis right, this you</L>
<L>May governe as you list. I'le motion't: <HI>Ladie,</HI></L>
<L>Pray pardon our mistake, indeed our Errand</L>
<L>Was chiefly to your <HI>Gentlewoman.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir,</L>
<L>She's one whose fortune J so much intend,</L>
<L>And yours, Sir, are so faire, that though there be</L>
<L>Much disproportion in your age, yet J</L>
<L>Will over-rule her, and she shall referre</L>
<L>Her selfe to be disposd by me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ware-h.</SPEAKER>
<L>You much</L>
<L>Oblige me, <HI>Madam.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Dorcas,</HI> this is the Merchant</L>
<L>I have provided for you, he is old,</L>
<L>But he has that will make him young, much Gold.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dor.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Madam,</HI> but that I should offend against</L>
<L>Your care as well as my preferment, J de</L>
<L>Have more experience of the Man, J meane</L>
<L>To make my husband. At first sight to marry,</L>
<L>Must argue me of lightnesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Princes, <HI>Dorcas,</HI></L>
<L>Doe wooe by pictures, and Ambassadours,</L>
<L>And match in absent Ceremonies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dor.</SPEAKER>
<L>But</L>
<L>You look for some great portion, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wareh.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faire Mistresse,</L>
<L>Your vertues are to me a wealthy Dowry.</L>
<L>And if you love me J shall think you bring</L>
<L>More then the <HI>Indies.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dor.</SPEAKER>
<L>But, Sir,'t may be</L>
<L>You'l be against my course of life. J love</L>
<L>Retirement, must have times for my Devotion,</L>
<L>Am litle us'd to company, and hate</L>
<L>The vanity of visits.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ware-h.</SPEAKER>
<L>This makes me</L>
<L>Love you the more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then J shall never trust you</L>
<L><PB N="50" REF="31"/>To goe to sea, and leave me; I shall dreame</L>
<L>Of nought but stormes, and Pyrats. Every winde</L>
<L>Will break my sleep.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>J'le stay at home.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, there</L>
<L>Is one thing more; J heare you have a Nephew,</L>
<L>You meane to make your Heyre. I hope you will</L>
<L>Settle some Joynture on me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>He's so lost</L>
<L>In my intents that to revenge my selfe,</L>
<L>I take this course. But to remove your doubts,</L>
<L>I've brought my <HI>Lawyer</HI> with blank deeds,</L>
<L>He shall put in your Name, and J, before</L>
<L>We goe to Church will seale'em.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dorc.</SPEAKER>
<L>On these termes</L>
<L>Where is your Priest, Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>He expects me at</L>
<L>The <HI>French Church,</HI> Mistresse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, when you have seald, Sir,</L>
<L>I'le beare a part in the solemnity.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="5" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACTVS V.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA I.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Plotwell. Aurelia. Bright. Newcut. Quartfield. Salewit. Roseclap. two Footmen. Cypher.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>WEll Sister, by this hand J was afraid</L>
<L>You had marr'd all; but I am well content</L>
<L>You have out-reacht me. If she doe act it well now,</L>
<L>By <HI>Iove</HI> I'le have her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>She hath studied all</L>
<L>Her <HI>Cues</HI> already.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gentlemen, how doe</L>
<L>You like the project?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>Theirs was dull and cold</L>
<L>Compared to ours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<L>Some <HI>Poet</HI> will steale from us</L>
<L>And bring't into a Comoedy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quartf.</SPEAKER>
<L>The jest</L>
<L>Will more inspire then sack.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have got <HI>Cypher</HI></L>
<L>Over to our side too; He has been up and down
<STAGE>Ent. Salewit</STAGE></L>
<L>To invite Guests to th' wedding. How now <HI>Salewit, like a Curat</HI></L>
<L>Are they gone home?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Salew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes faith, for better, for worse;</L>
<L>I've read a Fiction out of <HI>Rablais</HI> to 'em,</L>
<L>In a religious tone, which he believes</L>
<L>For good <HI>French Liturgie.</HI> When J had done</L>
<L>There came a Christning.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>And didst thou baptize</L>
<L>Out of thy <HI>Rablais</HI> too?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Salew.</SPEAKER>
<L>No faith, J left 'em</L>
<L><PB N="51" REF="31"/>In expectation of their <HI>Pastor.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>Newcut,</L>
<L>Who does he look like in that dresse?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hum? why</L>
<L>Like a <HI>Geneva Weaver,</HI> in black, who left</L>
<L>The <HI>Loome</HI> and entred into th' <HI>Ministery</HI></L>
<L>For conscience sake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well Gentlemen you all</L>
<L>Doe know your parts, you Captaine, and <HI>Baneswright</HI></L>
<L>Goe get your properties. For you two, These</L>
<L>Two <HI>Mules</HI> shall carry you in greater state,</L>
<L>And more ease then the <HI>Fistula.</HI> You sister</L>
<L>We'l leave unto your <HI>Knight,</HI> to come anon.</L>
<L><HI>Roseclap</HI> and J will thither straight. You <HI>Cypher</HI></L>
<L>Know what you have to doe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sale.</SPEAKER>
<L>And as for me</L>
<L>I'me an invited Guest, and am to blesse</L>
<L>The <HI>Venison</HI> in <HI>French,</HI> or in a Grace</L>
<L>Of broken <HI>English.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quartf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Before we doe divide</L>
<L>Our Army, let us dip our Rosemaries</L>
<L>In one rich bowle of sack to this brave girle,</L>
<L>And to the Gentleman that was my <HI>Fish.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<L>Agreed, Agreed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Captaine you shall dip first.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA II.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Ware-house. Dorcas.</STAGE>
<L>MY dearest <HI>Dorcas,</HI> welcome. Here you see</L>
<L>The house you must be mistresse of, which with</L>
<L>This kisse I doe confirme unto you.</L>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Forbeare, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wareh.</SPEAKER>
<L>How wife, refuse to kisse me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, unlesse</L>
<L>A sweeter ayre came from you; y' have turnd my stomack.</L>
<L>I wonder you can be so rude to aske me,</L>
<L>Knowing your <HI>Lungs</HI> are perisht.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wareh.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is rare.</L>
<L>That I should live to this great age, and never</L>
<L>Till now know I was rotten!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dor.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall never</L>
<L>Endure your Conversation; I hope you have</L>
<L>Contriv'd two <HI>Beds,</HI> two <HI>Chambers,</HI> and two <HI>Tables</HI>;</L>
<L>It is an <HI>Article</HI> that I should live,</L>
<L>Retir'd, that is, a part.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wareh.</SPEAKER>
<L>But pray you wife</L>
<L>Are you in earnest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dor.</SPEAKER>
<L>D'you think Jle jest with age?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you not lie with me then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did ever Man</L>
<L>Of your haires ask such questions? J doe blush</L>
<L>At your unreasonablenesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay then—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ist fit J should be buried?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wareh.</SPEAKER>
<L>I reach you not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="52" REF="32"/>
<SPEAKER>Dor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why to lye with you were a direct <HI>Emblem</HI></L>
<L>Of going to my grave.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wareh.</SPEAKER>
<L>I understand you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dor.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le have your picture set in my wedding ring</L>
<L>For a <HI>Deaths</HI> head.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wareh.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe conceave you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dor.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'de</L>
<L>Rather lie with an ancient <HI>Tombe,</HI> or embrace</L>
<L>An <HI>Ancestor</HI> then you. D'you think I'le come</L>
<L>Between your winding sheets? For what? to heare you</L>
<L>Depart all night, and fetch your last groane? and</L>
<L>Ith' morning finde a Deluge on the floore,</L>
<L>Your Entrailes floating, and halfe my husband spit</L>
<L>Upon the Arras?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ware.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am married—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then,</L>
<L>For your abilities, should twelve good women</L>
<L>Sit on these reverend locks, and on your heat,</L>
<L>And naturall appetite, they would just finde you</L>
<L>As youthfull as a Coffin, and as hot</L>
<L>As th' sultry winter that froze ore the <HI>Thames;</HI></L>
<L>They say the hard time did begin from you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wareh.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good, I am made the curse of <HI>Watermen.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your humours come frost from you, and your nose</L>
<L>Hath ycicles in <HI>Iune.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>Assist me patience.</L>
<L>Why heare you mistresse, you that have a feaver,</L>
<L>And Dog daies in your bloud, if you knew this</L>
<L>Why did you marry me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, ha, ha.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>She laughs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dor.</SPEAKER>
<L>That your experienced ache, that hath felt springs</L>
<L>And falls this forty yeare, should be so dull</L>
<L>To think J have not them that shall supply</L>
<L>Your cold defects.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have your servants then?</L>
<L>And I am forkt? hum?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe you think</L>
<L>A woman young, high in her bloud—.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>And hot</L>
<L>As <HI>Goats,</HI> or <HI>Marmosites</HI>—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Apt to take flame at</L>
<L>Tvery temptation—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>And to kindle at</L>
<L>Ehe picture of a Man—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would wed dust, ashes,</L>
<L>A Monument, unlesse she were—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>Crackt, tried,</L>
<L>And broken up?—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Right, Sir, or lackt a Cloke?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mischiefe and Hell, and was there none to make</L>
<L>Your cloke but I?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not so well lin'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>O you</L>
<L>Staid for a wealthie Cuckold, your tame beast</L>
<L>Must have his guilded hornes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, Sir, Besides</L>
<L>Your age being impotent, you would I knew</L>
<L>In conscience winke at my stolne helps, if I</L>
<L><PB N="53" REF="32"/>Took comfort from abroad.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, yes, yes, yes,</L>
<L>You shall be comforted, I will maintaine</L>
<L>A <HI>Stallion</HI> for you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dor.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will have friends come to me</L>
<L>So you'l conceale.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas, I'le be your Pander;</L>
<L>Deliver letters for you, and keep the doore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dor.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le have a woman shall doe that.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>O impudence!</L>
<L>Unheard of impudence!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then, Sir, I'le look</L>
<L>Your Coffers shall maintaine me at my rate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>How's that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why like a Ladie; for I doe mean</L>
<L>To have you Knighted.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall rise to honour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dor.</SPEAKER>
<L>D'you think I'le have your <HI>Factor</HI> move before me,</L>
<L>Like a Device stirr'd by a wier, or like</L>
<L>Some grave Clock wound up to a regular pace?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, you shall have your Usher, <HI>Dame,</HI> to stalk</L>
<L>Before you like a buskind <HI>Prologue,</HI> in</L>
<L>A stately, high, majestick motion, bare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dor.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe expect it; yes, Sir, and my Coach,</L>
<L>Six horses, and <HI>Postilion</HI>; foure are fit</L>
<L>For them that have a charge of Children; you</L>
<L>And I shall never have any.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>If we have,</L>
<L>All <HI>Middlesex</HI> is Father.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then Jle have</L>
<L>My Footman to run by me when I visit,</L>
<L>Or take the ayre sometimes in <HI>Hide-park.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>You,</L>
<L>Besides being chast, are good at Races too?</L>
<L>You can be a <HI>Iockey</HI> for a need?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'are pleasant, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why hark you, hark you, Mistresse, you told me</L>
<L>You lov'd retirement, loved not visits, and bargaind</L>
<L>I should not carry you abroad.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dor.</SPEAKER>
<L>You? no;</L>
<L>Ist fit I should be seen at <HI>Court</HI> with you?</L>
<L>Such an odde sight as you, would make the <HI>Ladies</HI></L>
<L>Have melancholy thoughts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>You bound me too</L>
<L>I should not goe to Sea, you lov'd me so</L>
<L>You could not be without me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not if you staid</L>
<L>Above a yeare; for should I, in a long voyage,</L>
<L>Prove fruitfull, I should want a father to</L>
<L>The Infant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most politiquely kinde,</L>
<L>And like a Whore perfect ith' mystery.</L>
<L>It is beyond my sufferance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray, Sir, vex,</L>
<L>I'le in, and see your Jewels, and make choice</L>
<L>Of some for every day, and some to weare
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
<L><PB N="54" REF="33"/>At Masques.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis very good. Two daies.</L>
<L>Of this I shall grow mad, or, to redeeme</L>
<L>My selfe, commit some outrage—O—O—O.</L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA III.</HEAD>
<STAGE>To him Plotwell. and Roseclap.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>SIr, I am sorry such a light offence</L>
<L>Should make such deep impressions in you; But that</L>
<L>which more afflicts me then the losse of my</L>
<L>Great hopes, is, that y'are likely to be abus'd, Sir,</L>
<L>Strangely abus'd, Sir, by one <HI>Baneswright.</HI> I heare</L>
<L>You are to marry.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did you heare so?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam <HI>Aurelia's</HI> woman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>What of her, Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, Sir, I thought it duty to informe you,</L>
<L>That you were better match a ruind <HI>Bawd</HI>;</L>
<L>One ten times cured by <HI>sweating,</HI> and the <HI>Tub,</HI></L>
<L>Or paind now with her fiftieth <HI>Ach,</HI> whom not</L>
<L>The power of <HI>Vsquebaugh,</HI> or heat of feavers</L>
<L>Quickens enough to wish; one of such looks,</L>
<L>That Judges of Assize, without more proofe,</L>
<L>Suspect, arraigne, and burn for witchcraft.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why pray?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>For she being past all motions, impotence</L>
<L>Will be a kinde of chastity, and you</L>
<L>Might have her to your selfe, but here is one</L>
<L>Knowes this to be—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>An arrant whore?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<L>I see</L>
<L>You have heard of her, Sir; Indeed she has</L>
<L>Done pennance thrice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>How say you, pennance?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rosc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, Sir,</L>
<L>And should have sufferd—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>Carting should she not?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<L>The <HI>Marshall</HI> had her, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>I sweat, I sweat.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<L>She's of knowne practice, Sir: the clothes she weares</L>
<L>Are but her <HI>quarters sinnes,</HI> she has no linnen</L>
<L>But what she first offends for.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>O blest Heaven</L>
<L>Look downe upon me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, Sir, which is more,</L>
<L>She has three children living, has had foure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>How? Children? Children say you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plot.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ask him Sir,</L>
<L>One by a <HI>French Man.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<L>Another by a <HI>Dutch.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>A third, Sir, by a <HI>Moore</HI>; borne of two colours.</L>
<L><PB N="55" REF="33"/>Just like a <HI>Sergeants Man.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why she has known then</L>
<L>All <HI>Tongues</HI> and <HI>Nations.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<L>She has been layne with far∣ther</L>
<L>Then ever <HI>Coryat</HI> travaild, and layne in</L>
<L>By two parts of the Map, <HI>Afrique,</HI> and <HI>Europe.</HI></L>
<L>As if the <HI>State</HI> maintaind her to allay</L>
<L>The heat of <HI>Forrainers.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVar.</SPEAKER>
<L>O—O—O—O.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>What aile you, Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>O <HI>Nephew</HI> I am not well,</L>
<L>J am not well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plot.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hope you are not married.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is too true.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<L>God help you then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>Amen;</L>
<L><HI>Nephew</HI> forgive me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas good Gentleman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plot.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would you trust <HI>Baneswright,</HI> Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Nephew</HI> in Hell</L>
<L>There's not a torment for him; O that I could</L>
<L>But see that cheating <HI>Rogue</HI> upon the rack now:</L>
<L>I'de give a thousand pound for every stretch,</L>
<L>That should enlarge the <HI>Rogue</HI> through all his joints,</L>
<L>And but just show him hell, and then recall</L>
<L>His broking soule, and give him strength to suffer</L>
<L>His torture often; J would have the <HI>Rascall</HI></L>
<L>Think hanging a reliefe, and be as long</L>
<L>A dying as a chopt <HI>Eele,</HI> that the <HI>Divell</HI></L>
<L>Might have his soule by peeces. who's here? a Saylor?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Cypher like a Saylor.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA. IV.</HEAD>
<STAGE>To them Cypher.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyph.</SPEAKER>
<L>ARe you, Sir, <HI>Ware-house,</HI> the rich Merchant?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>war.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir,</L>
<L>My name is <HI>Ware-house.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then you are not, Sir,</L>
<L>So rich by two ships as you were.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVar.</SPEAKER>
<L>How meane you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your two ships, Sir, that were now comming home</L>
<L>From <HI>Ormus</HI> are both cast away; the wrack</L>
<L>And burden on the place was valewd at</L>
<L>Some forty thousand pound. All the men perisht,</L>
<L>By th' violence of the storme, only my selfe</L>
<L>Preserv'd my life by swimming, till a ship</L>
<L>Of <HI>Bristoll</HI> took me up, and brought me home</L>
<L>To be the sad reporter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Was nothing sav'd?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Two small Caskes; one of blew Figs, the other</L>
<L>Of pickeld <HI>Mushromes</HI>; which serv'd me for bladders,</L>
<L>And kept me up from sinking. Twas a storme</L>
<L><PB N="56" REF="34"/>Which, Sir, J will describe to you. The Winds</L>
<L>Rose of a sudden with that tempestuous force—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prithee no more; I have heard too much. Would I</L>
<L>Had been ith' tempest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good your worship give</L>
<L>A poore sea-faring man your charitie,</L>
<L>To carry me back againe. I'me come aboue</L>
<L>A hundred mile to tell you this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe in,</L>
<L>And let my <HI>Factor</HI> if he be come in,</L>
<L>Reward thee, stay and sup to.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thank your Worship.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why should I not now hang my selfe? Or if
<STAGE>Ex. Cyp.</STAGE></L>
<L>It be a fate that will more hide it selfe,</L>
<L>And keep me from discredit, tie some weight</L>
<L>About my neck, to sink me to the bottome</L>
<L>Oth' <HI>Thames,</HI> not to be found, to keep my body,</L>
<L>From rising up and telling tales. Two wracks?</L>
<L>And both worth forty thousand pound there? why</L>
<L>That landed here, were worth an hundred. J</L>
<L>Will drown my selfe; I nothing have to doe</L>
<L>Now in this world but drown my selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fie these</L>
<L>Are desperate resolutions. Take heart, Sir,</L>
<L>There may be waies yet to relieve you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVar.</SPEAKER>
<L>How?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why for your lost ships, say, Sir, I should bring</L>
<L>Two oth' <HI>Assurance Office</HI> that should warrant</L>
<L>Their safe returne, tis not knowne yet. Would you</L>
<L>Give three parts to secure the fourth?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'de give</L>
<L>Ten to secure one.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, Sir, and for your Wife,</L>
<L>Say J should prove it were no lawfull match;</L>
<L>And that she is another Mans? you'd take</L>
<L>the peece of service well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, and repent</L>
<L>That when I had so good an Heyre begot</L>
<L>Unto my hand, I was so rash to aime</L>
<L>At one of my own dotage.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plot.</SPEAKER>
<L>Say no more, Sir,</L>
<L>But keep the <HI>Saylor</HI> that he stir not. Wee'l
<STAGE>Exit Plotwell &amp; Roscl.</STAGE></L>
<L>About it straight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>How much I was deceiv'd</L>
<L>To think ill of my <HI>Nephew.</HI> In whose revenge</L>
<L>I see the Heavens frowne on me; Seas and Winds</L>
<L>Swell and rage for him against me. But J will</L>
<L>Appease their furies, and be reconciled.</L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="scene">
<PB N="57" REF="34"/>
<HEAD>SCENA. V.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>To him Sea-thrift. M</HI><SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Sea-thrift. M</HI><SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Holland▪ M</HI><SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Scruple.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>M</HI><SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Sea.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>MUch joy to you, Sir, you have made quick dis∣patch</L>
<L>I like a man that can love, wooe, &amp; wed,</L>
<L>All in an houre, my husband was so long</L>
<L>A getting me, so many friends consents</L>
<L>Were to be askt, that when we came to Church</L>
<L>Twas not a Marriage, but our times were out,</L>
<L>And we were there made free of one another.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>M</HI><SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Holl.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>I lookt to find you abed, and a young <HI>Sheriffe</HI></L>
<L>Begot by this. My husband, when I came</L>
<L>From Church, by this time had his Cawdle; I</L>
<L>Had not a Garter left, nor he a point.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>M</HI><SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Scru.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Surely all that my husband did the first</L>
<L>Night we were married, was to call for one</L>
<L>Of his wrought Caps more, to allay his Rheume.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>M</HI><SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Holl.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>We heare y'haue matcht a Courtier, Sir, a Gallant;</L>
<L>One that can spring fire in your Bloud, and dart</L>
<L>Fresh flames into you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>M</HI><SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Sea.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, you are not merry.</L>
<L>Me thinks you doe not look as you were married.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>M</HI><SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Holl.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>You rather look as you had lost your <HI>Love.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>M</HI><SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Scru.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Or, else as if your <HI>Spouse</HI> Sir, had rebukt you</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sea.</SPEAKER>
<L>How is it, Sir? you feel have brought along</L>
<L>My <HI>Fidlers</HI> with me; my <HI>Wife</HI> and <HI>M</HI><SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Holland</HI></L>
<L>Are good winde Instruments. Tis enough for me</L>
<L>To put on sadnesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>You, Sir, have no cause.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seath.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not I? aske <HI>M</HI><SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Scruple.</HI> I have lost</L>
<L>My <HI>Daughter,</HI> Sir she's stolne. Then, Sir, I have</L>
<L>A spend thrift to my sonne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warch.</SPEAKER>
<L>These are felicities</L>
<L>Compard to me. You have not matcht a Whore, Sir,</L>
<L>Nor lost two ships at sea.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor you, J hope.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Truth is you are my friends. I am abus'd,</L>
<L>Grossely fetcht over. I have matcht a <HI>Stewes</HI>;</L>
<L>The notedst woman oth' Towne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>M</HI><SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Seath.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Indeed J heard</L>
<L>She was a <HI>Chamber-maid.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>M</HI><SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Holl.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>And they by their place,</L>
<L>Doe wait upon the <HI>Lady,</HI> but belong</L>
<L><PB N="58" REF="35"/>Unto the <HI>Lord.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sea.</SPEAKER>
<L>But is this true?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here was</L>
<L>My <HI>Nephew</HI> just now, and one <HI>Roseclap,</HI> who tell me</L>
<L>She has three Children living; one <HI>dapple grey,</HI></L>
<L>Halfe <HI>Moore,</HI> halfe <HI>English.</HI> Knowes as many men</L>
<L>As she that sinnd by th' <HI>Calendar,</HI> and divided</L>
<L>The nights oth' yeare with severall men.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Blesse me good∣nesse!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then like a mad condemnd to all misfortunes,</L>
<L>J have estated her in all I have.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sea.</SPEAKER>
<L>How?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>Under hand &amp; seale, Sir, irrecoverably.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Salewit.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="6" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA. VI.</HEAD>
<STAGE>To them Sale-wit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>M</HI><SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Holl.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>LOok <HI>M</HI><SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Scruple</HI> here's your husband.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sale.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bee</L>
<L>The leave ofe the faire <HI>Companee.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>M</HI><SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Scrup.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>My Husband?</L>
<L>His cold keeps him at home. surely J take</L>
<L>This to be some <HI>Dutch Elder.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Were is</L>
<L>The <HI>Breed</HI> an <HI>Breed-groome</HI>? Oh, <HI>Monsieur,</HI> J'me com't</L>
<L>To give you zhoy, and blesse your <HI>Capòn</HI>; were</L>
<L>Is your faire <HI>Breed</HI>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>O <HI>Monsieur,</HI> you have joynd me</L>
<L>To a chast Virgin. Would when J came to you</L>
<L>Y' had used your Ceremonies about my Funerall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Foonerall</HI>? Is your <HI>Breed</HI> dead?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would she were.</L>
<L>I'de double your Fee, <HI>Monsieur,</HI> to burie her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ee can but leetle <HI>English.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, J see</L>
<L>You are but new come over.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Dover</HI>? Tere</L>
<L>Eelanded.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>J, Sir, pray walk in; that doore</L>
<L>Will land you in my dining roome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ee tank you.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is the <HI>Priest</HI> that married us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sea.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is</L>
<L>A <HI>French-man</HI> ist not?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>Twas at the <HI>French Church.</HI></L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="7" TYPE="scene">
<PB N="59" REF="35"/>
<HEAD>SCENA VII.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter to them two Footmen bearing the Frame of a great Picture. Curtains drawne.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Foot.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>SEt'em down gently, so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Foo.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>They make me sweat▪</L>
<L><HI>Pictures</HI> quoth you? slight they have weight enough</L>
<L>To be the <HI>Parties.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Foot.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>My Lady, Sir, has sent</L>
<L>A Present to your wife.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>What Ladie pray?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Foot.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Madam <HI>Aurelia,</HI> Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Foot.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, they are</L>
<L>A brace of <HI>Pictures</HI> with which my Ladie praies</L>
<L>She will adorne her <HI>Chamber.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ware.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Male Pictures</HI> pray,</L>
<L>Or <HI>Female</HI>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Foot.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Why d'you aske?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ware-h.</SPEAKER>
<L>Because me thinks</L>
<L>It should be <HI>Mars</HI> and <HI>Venus</HI> in a Net,</L>
<L><HI>Aretines</HI> postures, or a naked <HI>Nymph,</HI></L>
<L>Lying asleep, and some lascivious <HI>Satyr</HI></L>
<L>Taking her lineaments. These are pictures which</L>
<L>Delight my wife.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Foot.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>These are <HI>Night-peeces,</HI> Sir,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>M</HI><SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Holl.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Lord how I long to see'em? I have at home</L>
<L>The finest ravisht <HI>Lucrece!</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>M</HI><SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Scru.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>So have I</L>
<L>The finest fall of <HI>Babylon!</HI> There is</L>
<L>A fat <HI>Monk</HI> spewing <HI>Churches,</HI> save your presence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>M</HI><SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Holl.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Pray will you open 'em.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Foot.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>My <HI>Lady</HI> charged us</L>
<L>None should have sight of 'em, Sir, but your wife.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>Because you make so dainty, I will see'em.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Foot.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Tis out of our Commission.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>But not of mine.
<STAGE>Draws the Curtaine within are discovered Bright. &amp; Newcut.</STAGE></L>
<L>Hell and damnation!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Foot.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>How d'you like 'em, Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>M</HI><SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Holl.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Look they are picturd in their clothes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>M</HI><SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Sea.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>They stir too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Foot.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, they are drawn to life; a <HI>Masters</HI> Hand</L>
<L>Went to 'em, I assure you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>Out Varlets, Bawds,</L>
<L>Panders, avoid my house. O Divell! are you
<STAGE>They come out.</STAGE></L>
<L>My wives <HI>Night-peeces</HI>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, you are rude, uncivill,</L>
<L>And would be beaten.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<L>We cannot come in private</L>
<L>On businesse to your wife, but you must be</L>
<L>Inquisitive Sir? Thank God tis in your own house,</L>
<L>The place protects you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>If such an Insolence</L>
<L>Scape unreveng'd, henceforth no <HI>Ladies</HI> shall
<STAGE>Enter Dor.</STAGE></L>
<L>Have secret servants.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here she comes, we'l ask</L>
<L><PB N="60" REF="36"/>If she gave you Commission to be so bold.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why this is far beyond example rare.</L>
<L>Now J conceive what is <HI>Platonick</HI> Love,</L>
<L>Tis to have men like <HI>Pictures</HI> brought disguised,</L>
<L>To Cuckold us with vertue.
<STAGE>They whisper.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="8" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA VIII.</HEAD>
<STAGE>To them Dorcas.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dor.</SPEAKER>
<L>HE would not offer't would he?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>We have been</L>
<L>In danger to be searcht; hereafter we</L>
<L>Must first be questiond by an <HI>Officer,</HI></L>
<L>And bring it under hands we are no Men,</L>
<L>Or have nought dangerous about us, before</L>
<L>We shall obtaine accesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<L>We doe expect</L>
<L>In time your Husband to preserve you chast,</L>
<L>Should keep you with a gard of <HI>Eunuchs</HI>; or</L>
<L>Confine you, like <HI>Italians,</HI> to a roome</L>
<L>Where no <HI>male Beast</HI> is pictur'd, least the sight</L>
<L>Of ought that can beget, should stir desires.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dor.</SPEAKER>
<L>I mar'le, Sir, who did licence you to prie,</L>
<L>Or spie out any friends that come to me;</L>
<L>It showes an unbred Curiosity;</L>
<L>Which J'le correct hereafter, you will dare</L>
<L>To break up Letters shortly, and examine</L>
<L>My <HI>Taylor,</HI> least when he brings home my gowne</L>
<L>There be a Man in't. J'le have whom I list,</L>
<L>In what disguise I list, and when I list,</L>
<L>And not have your fower eies so sawcy, to peep,</L>
<L>As if you by prevention meant to kill</L>
<L>A <HI>Basilisk.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mistresse, doe what you list,</L>
<L>Send for your Couch out, lie with your Gallants there</L>
<L>Before us all. Or if you have a minde</L>
<L>To fellowes that can lift weights, I can call</L>
<L>Two <HI>Footmen</HI> too:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sea.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are too patient, Sir.</L>
<L>Send for the <HI>Marshall,</HI> and discharge your house.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>M</HI><SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Sea.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Truly a handsome woman, what pittie tis</L>
<L><PB N="61" REF="36"/>She is not honest?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>M</HI><SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Holl.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Two proper Gentlemen too.</L>
<L>Lord that such <HI>Pictures</HI> might be sent to me.</L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA ULTIMA.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter to them Plotwell and Roseclap. with Baneswright and Quartfield disguised.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVar.</SPEAKER>
<L>O <HI>Nephew</HI> welcome to my ransome; here</L>
<L>My house is made a new <HI>Erection</HI>; Gallants</L>
<L>Are brought in varied formes. Had I not lookt</L>
<L>By providence into that frame, These two</L>
<L>Had been conveighd for <HI>Night-peeces</HI> and <HI>Lantskips</HI></L>
<L>Into my chast <HI>Brides</HI> chamber. Till now she took</L>
<L>And let her selfe out; now she will be able</L>
<L>To hire, and buy <HI>Offenders.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plot.</SPEAKER>
<L>J'le ease you, Sir.</L>
<L>We Two have made a full discovery of her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<L>She's marri'd to another man, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good.</L>
<L><HI>Nephew</HI> thou art my blessed <HI>Angell:</HI> who</L>
<L>Are these two?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Two that will secure your <HI>Ships</HI>;</L>
<L>Sent by the <HI>Office.</HI> Seale you, Sir, Th' have brought</L>
<L>Th' <HI>Assurance</HI> with'em.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Nephew</HI> thou wert borne</L>
<L>To be my deare preserver</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is dutie, Sir,</L>
<L>To help you out with your misfortunes. Gentlemen,</L>
<L>Produce your <HI>Instruments.</HI> Uncle put your seale,
<STAGE>They subscribe seal &amp; deliver interchangeably</STAGE></L>
<L>And write your name here, they will doe the like</L>
<L>To the other parchment. So, now deliver.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe deliver this as my <HI>Act</HI> and <HI>Deed.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ban. Quart.</SPEAKER>
<L>And we this as our <HI>Act</HI> and <HI>Deed.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray Gen∣tlemen</L>
<L>Be witnesse here. Vpon a doubtfull Rumour</L>
<L>Of two <HI>Ships</HI> wrackt as they return'd from <HI>Ormus,</HI></L>
<L>My Uncle Covenants to give three parts</L>
<L>To have the fourth secured. And these two here
<STAGE>Sea. Ros Br. New. subscribe as wit∣nesses.</STAGE></L>
<L>As <HI>Delegates</HI> of the Office, undertake</L>
<L>At that rate to assure them. Uncle now</L>
<L>Call forth the <HI>Saylor,</HI> and send for the Priest
<STAGE>Ent. Sale. ▪ Cyph.</STAGE></L>
<L>That married you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>Look here they come.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plot.</SPEAKER>
<L>First then,</L>
<L>Not to afflict you longer, Uncle, since</L>
<L>We now are quit, know, all this was my project.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>How?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plot.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your two Ships are richly landed: if</L>
<L><PB N="62" REF="37"/>You'l not believe me, here's the <HI>Saylor,</HI> who
<STAGE>Cyph. undisguises.</STAGE></L>
<L>Transformd to <HI>Cypher,</HI> can tell you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis very true, Sir.</L>
<L>I hired this travailing case of one oth' <HI>Sailors,</HI></L>
<L>That came in one of 'em. They lie at <HI>Black-wall.</HI></L>
<L>Troth I in pitty, Sir, to M<SUP>r</SUP> <HI>Plotwell,</HI></L>
<L>Thought it my duty to deceive you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>Very well, Sir.</L>
<L>What are these <HI>Masquers</HI> too?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plot.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith, Sir, these
<STAGE>Ex. Cyph. they un∣disguise.</STAGE></L>
<L>Can change their formes too. They are two friends</L>
<L>Worth threescore thousand pound, Sir, to my use.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Baneswright,</HI> and Captain <HI>Quartfield!</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay old boy</L>
<L>Th' hast a good penny-worth on't. The jest is worth</L>
<L>Three parts of foure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ban.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith, Sir, we hope you'l pay</L>
<L><HI>Tunnage</HI> and <HI>Poundage</HI> into th' bargaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>O</L>
<L>You are a precious <HI>Rogue,</HI> you ha preferr'd me</L>
<L>To a chast <HI>Lucrece,</HI> Sirrah.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ban.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your <HI>Nephew,</HI> Sir,</L>
<L>Hath married her with all her faults, They are</L>
<L>New come from <HI>Church.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>How?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wonder not, Sir, you</L>
<L>Were marri'd but in jest. Twas no <HI>Churchforme,</HI></L>
<L>But a fine Legend out of <HI>Rablais.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Troth
<STAGE>Salw. undis∣guises.</STAGE></L>
<L>This reverend weed cast off, I'me a lay <HI>Poet,</HI></L>
<L>And can not marry unless't be in a <HI>Play,</HI></L>
<L>In the <HI>fift Act,</HI> or so; and thats almost</L>
<L>Worne out of fashion too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>M</HI><SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Sea.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>These are the two</L>
<L>That showd my sonne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>M</HI><SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Holl.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Lets have our mony back.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>But Uncle for the Joynture, you have made her,</L>
<L>J hope you'l not retract. That and three parts</L>
<L>Of your two Sips, besides what you will leave</L>
<L>Us at your death, will make a pretty stock</L>
<L>For young beginners.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>Am I o'rereacht so finely?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sea.</SPEAKER>
<L>But are you married, Sir, in earnest?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plot.</SPEAKER>
<L>Troth,</L>
<L>We have not been abed yet, but may goe,</L>
<L>And no Law broken.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then I must tell you, Sir,</L>
<L>Y' have wronged me, and I look for satisfaction.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why? I beseech you, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, were not you</L>
<L>Betrotht once to my daughter?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>M</HI><SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Seath.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>And did not I,</L>
<L>And Ms <HI>Holland</HI> help to make you sure?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plot.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe confesse it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beare witnesse, Gentlemen,</L>
<L>He doth confesse it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plot.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le sweare it too, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why</L>
<L>Then have you matcht this woman?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plot.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why? because</L>
<L>This is your Daughter, Sir, I'me hers by Conquest,</L>
<L><PB N="63" REF="37"/>For this daies service.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ist possible I should</L>
<L>Be out in my own child so?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M<SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Sea.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>I told you husband.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M<SUP>s</SUP> <HI>Scru.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Surely my spirit gave me it twas she.</L>
<L>And yet to see, now you have not your <HI>Wire,</HI></L>
<L>Nor <HI>Citie Ruffe</HI> on, Mistresse <HI>Sue,</HI> how these</L>
<L>Clothes doe beguile. Jntruth I took you for</L>
<L>A <HI>Gentlewoman.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here be rare plots indeed.</L>
<L>Why how now, Sir, these young heads have outgone us.</L>
<L>Was my Sonne oth' plot too?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plotw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith, Sir, he</L>
<L>Is marryed too; I did strike up a wedding
<STAGE>Ent. Tim. Aur.</STAGE></L>
<L>Between him and my sister,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Look, Sir,</L>
<L>They come without their Maiden heads.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why this</L>
<L>Is better still. Now, Sir, you might have askt</L>
<L>Consent of <HI>Parents.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray forgive me, Sir.</L>
<L>I thought I had match a Ladie, but she proves—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Much better, Sir; I'de chide you as a <HI>Fish</HI></L>
<L>But that your choice pleads for you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mother pray</L>
<L>Salute my wife, and tell me if one may not</L>
<L>Lie with her lips; nay you too, M<SUB>r</SUB> <HI>Holland</HI>;</L>
<L>You taught her to make <HI>Shirts</HI> and <HI>Bonelace</HI>; she's</L>
<L>Out of her time now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mr <HI>Holl.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>I release her, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>I took your sister for a Ladie, <HI>Nephew.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plot.</SPEAKER>
<L>I kept her like one, Sir, my <HI>Temple</HI> scores</L>
<L>Went to maintaine the Title, out of hope</L>
<L>To gaine some great match for her, which you see</L>
<L>Is come to passe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, M<SUP>r</SUP> <HI>Seathrift,</HI> things</L>
<L>Are just fallen out as we contrivd'em; I</L>
<L>Grieve not I am deceived. Believe me, <HI>Gentlemen,</HI></L>
<L>You all did your parts well; twas carried cleanly;</L>
<L>And though I could take some things ill of you</L>
<L>Faire Mistresse, yet twas plot, and I forget it;</L>
<L>Lets in and make 'em Portions.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lead the way, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ban.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray stay a litle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>More Revelations yet?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ban.</SPEAKER>
<L>I all this while have stood behinde the Curtaine;</L>
<L>You have a brother, Sir, and you a father.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plot.</SPEAKER>
<L>If he doe live, I have.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ban.</SPEAKER>
<L>He in his time</L>
<L>Was held the wealthiest Merchant on th' <HI>Exchange.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis true, but that his shipwracks broke him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ban.</SPEAKER>
<L>And</L>
<L>The debt for which he broke I heare you have
<STAGE>Baneswr. undisguises</STAGE></L>
<L>Compounded.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sea.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am paid it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ban.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then I thank you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="64" REF="38"/>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>My brother <HI>Plotwell!</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ban.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sonne I wish you joy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plot.</SPEAKER>
<L>O my blest starres! my Father.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ban.</SPEAKER>
<L>And to you fayre Mistresse</L>
<L>Let it not breed repentance that I have,</L>
<L>For my security to scape your Father,</L>
<L>A while descended from my selfe to this</L>
<L>Unworthy shape. Now I can cast it off,</L>
<L>And be my true selfe. I have a ship which fame</L>
<L>Gave out for lost but just now landed too</L>
<L>Worth twenty thousand pounds towards your Match.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Better and better still.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVell what was want∣ing</L>
<L>Unto our joyes and made these <HI>Nuptials</HI></L>
<L>Imperfect. Brother you by your discovery
<STAGE>Enter Cypher.</STAGE></L>
<L>Have fully added.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, The two <HI>Sheriffs</HI> are</L>
<L>Within and have both brought their Wives.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Feast</L>
<L>Intended for my wedding shall be yours.</L>
<L>To which I adde may you so love, to say</L>
<L>When old, your time was but one Marriage Day.</L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
<BACK>
<DIV1 TYPE="epilogue">
<PB REF="38"/>
<HEAD>THE EPILOGVE AT WHITE-HALL.</HEAD>
<L>THE <HI>Author</HI> was deceiv'd, for should the Parts,</L>
<L>And Play which you have seen, plead Rules &amp; Arts,</L>
<L>Such as strict <HI>Criticks</HI> write by, who refuse</L>
<L>T'allow the <HI>Buskin</HI> to the <HI>Comick Muse,</HI></L>
<L>Whose Region is the People, every straine</L>
<L>Of Royalty being Tragick, though none slaine:</L>
<L>He'd now, <HI>Great Sir,</HI> hold all his Rules untrue,</L>
<L>And thinks his best Rule is the <HI>Queen</HI> and <HI>You.</HI></L>
<L>He should have searcht the Stories of each Age,</L>
<L>And brought five Acts of <HI>Princes</HI> on the Stage.</L>
<L>He should have taken measure, and rais'd sport,</L>
<L>From persons bright, and glorious as your <HI>Court</HI>▪</L>
<L>And should have made his Argument to be</L>
<L>Fully as high, and great as <HI>They</HI> that see.</L>
<L>Here, he confesseth, you did nothing meet</L>
<L>But what was first a Comoedy ith' street:</L>
<L><HI>Cheapside</HI> brought into verse, no passage strange</L>
<L>To any here that hath been at th' <HI>Exchange.</HI></L>
<L>Yet he hopes none doth valew it so low</L>
<L>As to compare it with my <HI>Lord Maiors</HI> show.</L>
<L>Tis so unlike, that some, he feares, did sit,</L>
<L>Who missing <HI>Pageants</HI> did or'esee the wit.</L>
<L>Since then his Scenes no pomp or Highnesse boast,</L>
<L>And low things graced show <HI>Princes Princes</HI> most,</L>
<L><HI>Your Royall</HI> smiles will raise't, and make him say,</L>
<L>He onely wrote, your liking made the <HI>Play.</HI></L>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="epilogue">
<PB REF="39"/>
<HEAD>THE EPILOGVE AT BLACK-FRIERS.</HEAD>
<L>ONce more the <HI>Author,</HI> ere you rise, doth say</L>
<L>Though he have publique warrant for his play,</L>
<L>Yet he to th' <HI>Kings</HI> command needs the <HI>Kings Writ</HI></L>
<L>To keep him safe, not to b'arraign'd for <HI>Wit.</HI></L>
<L>Not that he feares his name can suffer wrack</L>
<L>From them who six-pence pay, and six-pence crack.</L>
<L>To such he wrote not; though some parts have been</L>
<L>So like here, that They to Themselves came in.</L>
<L>To Them who call't reproofe to make a face,</L>
<L>Who think they judge when they frown ith'wrong place;</L>
<L>Who if they speak not ill oth' <HI>Poet,</HI> doubt</L>
<L>They loose by th' Play, nor have their two shillings out,</L>
<L>He saies, he hopes, they'l not expect he'd wooe,</L>
<L>The Play being done, they'd end their sowre looks too.</L>
<L>But before you who did true Hearers sit,</L>
<L>Who singly make a box, and fill the Pit,</L>
<L>Who to his <HI>Comoedy</HI> read, and unseen,</L>
<L>Had thronged <HI>Theaters,</HI> and <HI>Black-Friers</HI> been,</L>
<L>He for his Doome stands; your <HI>Hands</HI> are his <HI>Bayes</HI>;</L>
<L>Since They can onely clap, who know to praise.</L>
<PB REF="39"/>
</DIV1>
</BACK>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

