<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2006-01-20</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Jonathan Blaney</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, etc.). Checked for signatures. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, and UNCLEARs. Corrected 4 $s of 264. Converted 260 $s to GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc". Checked spacing of foreign GAPs. Checked for EPIGRAPHs and ARGUMENTs. Checked for startqs, endqs, oes, q;s, and Qs. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Checked for CLOSERs, TRAILERs, and BYLINEs. DONE.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="A07330">
<STC T="S">17717</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99847796</BIBNO>
<VID>12857</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT>
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>THE TRAGEDIE OF CLEOPATRA Queen of <HI>Aegypt.</HI></P>
<P>By <HI>T. M.</HI></P>
<P>Acted 1626.</P>
<Q><BIBL>Luc.</BIBL>
<L>—quantùm impulit Argos,</L>
<L>Iliacasque domos facie Spartana nocenti,</L>
<L>Hesperios auxit tantùm <HI>Cleopatra</HI> furores.</L></Q>
<P>LONDON, Printed by <HI>Thomas Harper</HI> for <HI>Thomas Walkly,</HI> and are to be sold at his shop at the flying Horse neer <HI>York</HI> House 1639.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>TO THE MOST ACCOMPLISH'D S<SUP>r</SUP>. <HI>Kenelme Digby.</HI></HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>S<SUP>r</SUP>.</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">T</SEG>Hat it pleased you to cast an eye of favour upon these poor Plays has given me the boldnesse, not only to publish them (which I thought not to have done) but to shelter them, though most unworthy, under that name, to which for authority and approbation the richest pieces that this nation can boast, might be proud to flie. You are to learning what learning is to others a gracefull ornament; and known not on∣ly able to receive, but fit to make that which we call literature; it being nothing else but rules and observations drawne at the first from such able natures as yours is; and by your daily con∣versation is better expressed, then wee by wri∣ting can define it. Your composition was made to justifie those old Philosophers who resembled a man to the whole world. For as in the world
<PB REF="3"/>
all varieties do meet to make a perfect harmony<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> so in the largnesse of your soule the severall a∣bilities of most different Nations are conjoyned to an honourable advantage of one entire tem∣per, where the predominancies are magnanimi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ty, prudence, and gentlenesse. But I dare not offer to crowd into a narrow Epistle your nobl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Character, which will require a longer Trea∣tise and a better pen. For the defects in these two Plays, I that have already been so much obliged to your goodnesse in other matters, can∣not here despaire of your forgivenesse, which i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> the only thing that puts confidence into</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED><HI>Your most obliged and devoted servant</HI> Tho. May.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<HEAD><PB REF="3"/>THE TRAGEDIE OF CEOPATRA.</HEAD>
<DIV1 N="1" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus Primus.</HEAD>
<STAGE>TITIUS, PLANCUS, CANIDIUS.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TITIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L><SEG REND="decorInit">S</SEG>Hame and dishonour to the Roman name</L>
<L>A triumph held at Alexandria</L>
<L>Only to honour <HI>Cleopatraes</HI> pride?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ah <HI>Marcus,</HI> this Aegyptian Queen was made</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> be the ruine of <HI>Antonius.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CA.</SPEAKER>
<P><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> be the pleasure of <HI>Antonius.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PL.</SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ow can you jest <HI>Canidius,</HI> on a theame</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> sad?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CA.</SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <HI>Plancus</HI> can you prophecie</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> sadly on so merry an occasion,</L>
<L><PB REF="4"/>As is the love of Ladies?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let <HI>Canidius</HI></L>
<L>Have his own way, <HI>Munatius,</HI> tis in vain</L>
<L>To talk to him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would you could let me have</L>
<L><HI>Antonius</HI> his way, upon condition</L>
<L>I suffer'd you to censure gravely of it,</L>
<L>And prophecie my ruine. But my Lords,</L>
<L>You were as good be merry too, and take</L>
<L>Your share of pleasure in th'Aegyptian Court.</L>
<L>You'l do no good with these perswasions.</L>
<L>He loves the Queen, and will do so in spite.</L>
<L>Of our morality.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis too too true,</L>
<L>That face of hers, that beauty in the bud</L>
<L>Not fully blown, in yeers of innocence</L>
<L>(If any yeers of hers were innocent)</L>
<L>Set off with no adulterisme of art,</L>
<L>Nor cloath'd with state and pompous Majestie,</L>
<L>But in a fortune clouded and distrest</L>
<L>A wretched prisoner in her brother's Court,</L>
<L>Yet then I say that charming face could move</L>
<L>The manly temper of wise <HI>Julius Caesar,</HI></L>
<L>That <HI>Ma<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></HI> in heat of all his active warre,</L>
<L>When he pursu'd the flying <HI>Pompey</HI> hither,</L>
<L>His sword yet reeking in <HI>Pharsa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es</HI> slaughter</L>
<L>At sight of her became a dot<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ng Lover:</L>
<L>And could we think that our <HI>Antonius</HI></L>
<L>A man not master of that temperance</L>
<L>That <HI>Caesar</HI> had, could finde a strength to guard</L>
<L>His soul against that beauty now set off</L>
<L>With so much wealth and majesty?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="4"/>
<SPEAKER>CA.</SPEAKER>
<L>No surely.</L>
<L>I did not think <HI>Antonius</HI> was an Eunuch.</L>
<L>Nor could I have believ'd he had been worthy</L>
<L>To be a successour in <HI>Caesa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> power,</L>
<L>Unlesse he had succeeded him in her.</L>
<L>Great <HI>Julius</HI> noble acts in warre and state</L>
<L>Assur'd the world that he was wise and valiant:</L>
<L>But if he had not falne in love with her</L>
<L>I should have much suspected his good nature.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PL.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay then, <HI>Canidius,</HI> it shall be yours.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or what indeed were greatnesse in the world</L>
<L>If he that did possesse it, might not play</L>
<L>The wanton with <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t? this Aegyptian Queen</L>
<L>Is a state beauty, and ordain'd by fate</L>
<L>To be possest by them that rule the world.</L>
<L>Great <HI>Pompey's</HI> sonne enjoy'd her first, and pluck'd</L>
<L>Her Virgin blossome. When that Family,
<STAGE>Plutarch.</STAGE></L>
<L>Whose ruine fill'd the World, was overthrown,</L>
<L>Great <HI>Iul<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>us</HI> next came in as conquerour</L>
<L>To have his share, and as he did in power,</L>
<L>Succeeded him in <HI>Cleopatrae,</HI> love.</L>
<L>Now our <HI>Antonius</HI> takes his turn, and thinks</L>
<L>That all the legions▪ all the swords, that came</L>
<L>To make his greatnesse up when <HI>Julius</HI> dy'd,</L>
<L>Could give no greater priviledge to him</L>
<L>Then p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>wer to be the servant to this Queen.</L>
<L>Thus whosoere in Rome be conquerour</L>
<L>His laurell wreath is <HI>Cleopatraes</HI> love.</L>
<L>And to speak justly of her, Nature teem'd</L>
<L>To build this woman for no meaner height.</L>
<L>Her soule is full of greatnesse, and her wit</L>
<L>Has charms as many as her beauty has.</L>
<L>With Majestie beyond her sex she rules</L>
<L><PB REF="5"/>Her spatious Kingdomes, and all neighbour Princes</L>
<L>Admire her parts. How many languages</L>
<L>Speaks she with elegance? Embassadors</L>
<L>From th' Aethiopians, Arabs, Troglodites,
<STAGE>Plut.</STAGE></L>
<L>From th' Hebrews, Syrians, Medes, and Parthians</L>
<L>Have in amazement heard this learned Queen</L>
<L>Without the aid of an interpreter</L>
<L>In all their severall tongues returne their answers;</L>
<L>When most of her dull predecessor Kings</L>
<L>Since <HI>Ptolemaeus Philadelphus</HI> time</L>
<L>Scarce understood th' Aegyptian tongue, and some</L>
<L>Had quite forgot the Macedonian.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TI.</SPEAKER>
<P>How well <HI>Canidius</HI> descants on this theame!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PLA.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'll lay my life it pleases him; the man</L>
<L>Is deep in love, and pity tis he has</L>
<L>So great a rivall as <HI>Antonius.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well use your wit upon me; but I doubt</L>
<L>If any man could search your secret thoughts,</L>
<L>Tis envy, not morality that makes</L>
<L>You taxe his love, how gravely ere you talke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TI.</SPEAKER>
<L>But can <HI>Canidius</HI> think it should be just</L>
<L>In our <HI>Antonius</HI> to forsake for her</L>
<L>His lawfull wife the good <HI>Octavia?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then like a Roman let me answer, <HI>Marcus.</HI></L>
<L>Is it become a care worthy of us</L>
<L>What woman <HI>Antony</HI> enjoys? have we</L>
<L>Time to dispute his matrimoniall faults,</L>
<L>That have already seen the breach of all</L>
<L>Romes sacred laws, by which the world was bound?</L>
<L>Have we endur'd our Consuls state and power</L>
<L>To be subjected by the lawlesse arms</L>
<L><PB REF="5"/>Of private men, or Senators proscrib'd,</L>
<L>And can we now consider whether they</L>
<L>That did all this, may keep a wench or no?</L>
<L>It was the crime of us, and Fate it self</L>
<L>That <HI>Antony</HI> and <HI>Caesar</HI> could usurpe</L>
<L>A power so great; beyond which we can suffer</L>
<L>No more worth thinking of. Nor were't to us</L>
<L>Any great fortune if <HI>Antonius</HI></L>
<L>Were honest of his body.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PLA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Have we then,</L>
<L>Who have been greatest Magistrates, quite lost</L>
<L>All shew of liberty, and now not dare</L>
<L>To counsell him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CA.</SPEAKER>
<L>A shew of liberty</L>
<L>When we have lost the substance, is best kept</L>
<L>By seeming not to understand those faults</L>
<L>Which we want power to mend. For mine own pa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></L>
<L>I love the person of <HI>Antonius</HI>;</L>
<L>And through his greatest loosenesse can discern</L>
<L>A nature here, honester then <HI>Caesars.</HI></L>
<L>And if a warre do grow twixt them (as surely</L>
<L>Ambition would ere long finde out a cause</L>
<L>Although <HI>Octavia</HI> had not been neglected)</L>
<L>Rather then Rome should still obey two Lords,</L>
<L>Could wish that all were <HI>Anthony's</HI> alone.</L>
<L>Who would, I think, be brought more easily</L>
<L>Then <HI>Caesar,</HI> to resigne the government.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would I could think that either would do so.</L>
<L>Here comes her servant <HI>Mardio.</HI>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Mardio.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Noble Lords,</L>
<L>The Queen by mee entreats your company</L>
<L>At supper with the Lord <HI>Antonius.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="6"/>
<SPEAKER>CA.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Marcio</HI> return our humble services,</L>
<L>Wee 'll instantly attend her. Now my friends,</L>
<L>Can you a while put off austerity,</L>
<L>And rigid censures, to be freely merry?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TI.</SPEAKER>
<P>It may be so. Wee'll try what wine can do.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>A Feast preparing.</HI> EUPHRONIUS, GLAUCUS, CHARMIO.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>EU.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Glaucus,</HI> let more of this perfume be got.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GLA.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have enough in readinesse; or else</L>
<L>'Twould be too late to think on't now, the Queen</L>
<L>Is upon entrance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>EU.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Charmio,</HI> art thou sure</L>
<L>Those tapers stand just as the Queen commanded?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis the same order that <HI>Antonius</HI></L>
<L>When last he feasted here, so much admir'd;</L>
<L>And said 'mongst all the curiosities
<STAGE>Plutarch.</STAGE></L>
<L>That he had seen, the placing of those lights.</L>
<L>Did not the least affect him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>EU.</SPEAKER>
<L>Though the Romans</L>
<L>In power and warl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ke state exceed us farre,</L>
<L>Yet in our Court of Aegypt they may learn</L>
<L>Pleasure and bravery, but art thou sure</L>
<L>That all things here are well?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CHA.</SPEAKER>
<L>As exquisite</L>
<L>As the Queens wish would have it. Hark they come.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="6"/>ACHOREUS <HI>the Priest,</HI> ANTONIUS, CLEOPATRA, CANIDIUS, TITIUS, PLANCUS.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLE.</SPEAKER>
<L>To say, my Lord, that you are welcome hither</L>
<L>Were to disparage you, who have the power</L>
<L>To make your self so, what ere you see</L>
<L>In Aegypt is your own.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AN.</SPEAKER>
<L>What Aegypt holds</L>
<L>If I be judge, not all the world besides</L>
<L>Can equalize.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLE.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will't please you take</L>
<L>Your place, and these your noble Roman friends?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AN.</SPEAKER>
<L>Father <HI>Achoreus,</HI> sit you neer to mee.</L>
<L>Your holy Orders, and great age, which shews</L>
<L>The Gods have lov'd you well, may justly challenge</L>
<L>A reverence from us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLE.</SPEAKER>
<L>Great <HI>Julius Caesar</HI></L>
<L>Did love my father well; he oft was pleas'd</L>
<L>At houres of leisure to conferre with him</L>
<L>About the nature of our Nile, of all</L>
<L>The mysteries of Religion, and the wonders</L>
<L>That Aegypt breeds.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ACH.</SPEAKER>
<L>He had a knowing soule,</L>
<L>And was a master of Philosophy</L>
<L>As well as Warre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AN.</SPEAKER>
<L>How like the spangled sky</L>
<L>These tapers make the high-arch'd roofe to show?</L>
<L>While <HI>Cleopatra</HI> like bright <HI>Cynthia</HI></L>
<L>In her full orbe more guilds the cheerfull night.</L>
<L><PB REF="7"/>Shee's still at full; yet still me thinks she vexes,</L>
<L>And grows more fair and more majesticall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLE.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lords, you Romans, whose victorious arms</L>
<L>Have made you Masters of the world, possesse</L>
<L>Such full and high delights in Italy,</L>
<L>That our poor Aegypt can present no pleasure</L>
<L>Worth your acceptance: but let me entreat</L>
<L>You would be freely merry, and forgive</L>
<L>Your entertainment.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANT.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis an entertainment</L>
<L>That might invite and please the Gods. Me thinks,</L>
<L><HI>Jove</HI> should descend, while <HI>Cle<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>patra's</HI> here,</L>
<L>Disguis'd for love, as once for fear he was,</L>
<L>When bold <HI>Typh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>us</HI> scal'd the starry sky,</L>
<L>And all the Gods disguis'd in Aegypt lurk'd.</L>
<L>Love were a nobler cause then fear to bring him,</L>
<L>And such a love as thine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLE.</SPEAKER>
<L>If I could think</L>
<L>That ere great <HI>Jove</HI> did play such feats as those,</L>
<L>I'de now beleeve that he were here disguis'd,</L>
<L>And took the noble shape of <HI>Anthony</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANT.</SPEAKER>
<L>This complement so farre transcends, it leaves</L>
<L>No answer for a wit so dull as mine.</L>
<LG>
<HEAD>A Song.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L><HI>NOt hee, that knows how to acquire</HI></L>
<L><HI>But to enjoy, is blest.</HI></L>
<L><HI>Nor does our happinesse consist</HI></L>
<L><HI>In motion, but in rest.</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="7"/>
<L><HI>The Gods passe man in blisse, because</HI></L>
<L><HI>They toile not for more height;</HI></L>
<L><HI>But can enjoy, and in their own</HI></L>
<L><HI>Eternall rest delight.</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><HI>Then, Princes, do not toile, nor care;</HI></L>
<L><HI>Enjoy what you possesse.</HI></L>
<L><HI>Which whilest you do, you equallize</HI></L>
<L><HI>The Gods in happinesse.</HI></L>
</LG>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TI.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Minutius Plancus,</HI> I was thinking now</L>
<L>How <HI>Hannibal</HI> was charm'd at Capua,</L>
<L>When that delicious place had mollifi'd</L>
<L>His rough and cruell soul, and made him learn</L>
<L>The lessons of soft love, and luxury.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PLA.</SPEAKER>
<L>There was no cause, <HI>Marcus,</HI> for such a thought.</L>
<L>For our <HI>Antonius</HI> in the heat of all</L>
<L>His active life knew how to revell well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANT.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let this soft Musique cease, and louder sound.</L>
<L>This second course is mine. Call in <HI>Lucilius.</HI></L>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> LUCILIUS <HI>with three Crowns.</HI></STAGE>
<L>Fair <HI>Cleopatra,</HI> for addition
<STAGE>Plutarch.</STAGE></L>
<L>To what thou hold'st, the world-commanding Rome</L>
<L>Presents these Crowns, and by my hand invests</L>
<L>Thee, <HI>Cleopatra</HI> Queen of wealthy <HI>Cyprus,</HI></L>
<L>Of Coelosyria, and Phoenicia.</L>
<L>Blush no<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, my Love, nor let Romes bounty force</L>
<L>Thy modesty▪ these Crowns from thy fair brow</L>
<L>Receive more lustre then they can bestow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="8"/>
<SPEAKER>TI.</SPEAKER>
<P>I think he need not greatly fear her blushing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PLA.</SPEAKER>
<L>No <HI>Marcus</HI> no; alas these petty Kingdomes</L>
<L>(Though too too great to be so ill bestow'd)</L>
<L>Are not the scope of her ambitious aymes!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLE.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, I dare not make excuse, or plead</L>
<L>Unworthinesse, where once <HI>Antonius</HI> wisdome</L>
<L>Has made election to conferre his favours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANT.</SPEAKER>
<L>Admire not, friends; the God-like power of Rome</L>
<L>Is more declar'd by what it gives away
<STAGE>Plutarch.</STAGE></L>
<L>Then what it holds. But these are still our owne</L>
<L>And <HI>Cleopatra</HI> Romes deserving friend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CA.</SPEAKER>
<L>I cannot choose but think how fit a state</L>
<L>For <HI>Cleopatra Cyprus</HI> Kingdome is;</L>
<L>And shall believe that it was ominous</L>
<L>That noble <HI>Julius Caesar</HI> after all</L>
<L>Those foure rich triumphs which he held at Rome</L>
<L>When he resolv'd with like magnificence</L>
<L>To build a Temple to the Goddesse <HI>Venus,</HI></L>
<L>From whom his house derive their pedigree</L>
<L>Within his stately Temple, to expresse</L>
<L>The Image of that Goddesse, he set up</L>
<L>Fair <HI>Cleopatraes</HI> figure in the place</L>
<L>Supposing her to be the Queen of Love.</L>
<L>You know my Lord Antonius, this is true,</L>
<L>And Cyprus ever was fair <HI>Venus</HI> Ile.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AN.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Twas well observ'd noble <HI>Canidius.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CA.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fill me some wine. Health to the Cyprian Queen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AN.</SPEAKER>
<L>Drink it to me <HI>Canidius</HI>; and I thank thee.</L>
<L>Let it go round, my ftiends.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="8"/>
<SPEAKER>CLE.</SPEAKER>
<L>I ever thought</L>
<L>My self much bound to brave <HI>Canidius</HI></L>
<L>Since I was happy in his company.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AN.</SPEAKER>
<L>How fit it is, no other <HI>Cyprian</HI> Queen,</L>
<L>But <HI>Cleopatra</HI> shall the Poëts know,</L>
<L>Whose fancies now shall raise that Kingdome higher.</L>
<L>More amorous now will <HI>Paphos</HI> mountains show,</L>
<L>And all those flowery Meads▪ the Fields of love,</L>
<L>Ore which no windes but Western ever blow.</L>
<L>The aire it self will yield a sweeter breath</L>
<L>While <HI>Cleopatra</HI> reignes the Cyprian Queen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PLA.</SPEAKER>
<P>How amorous in his language he is grown.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TI.</SPEAKER>
<L>The times, I fear <HI>Minutius,</HI> will require</L>
<L>A rougher language shortly. We shall heare</L>
<L>Assoon as any news can come from Rome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AN.</SPEAKER>
<L>But long ago was I enforc'd to know</L>
<L>That <HI>Cleopatra</HI> was the Queen of love,</L>
<L>When first I met thee in Cilicia,
<STAGE>Plut,</STAGE></L>
<L>And down the silver stream of <HI>Cydnus,</HI> thou</L>
<L>In <HI>Venus</HI> shape cam'st sayling, while the aire</L>
<L>Was ravish'd with thy Musick, and the windes</L>
<L>In amorous gales did kisse thy silken sayls.</L>
<L>Thy maids in Graces habits did attend,</L>
<L>And boys, like <HI>Cupids,</HI> painted quivers bore,</L>
<L>While thousand <HI>Cupids</HI> in those starry eyes</L>
<L>Stood ready drawn to wound the stoutest hearts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLE.</SPEAKER>
<L>You came like <HI>Mars</HI> himself in threatning arm<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>To ruine me, and my poor Country then.</L>
<L>I took that shape, because I knew no strength</L>
<L>No power on earth was able to resist</L>
<L>The conquering fury of <HI>Antonius.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="9"/>
<SPEAKER>AN.</SPEAKER>
<L>That face of thine resisted me, and did</L>
<L>So sweetly conquer, I was proud to yield;</L>
<L>And more rejoyc'd in that captivity,</L>
<L>Then any Roman in a triumph did.
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Hipparchus.</STAGE></L>
<L>How now, what news with thee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HIP.</SPEAKER>
<P>Letters from Rome, my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AN.</SPEAKER>
<P>From whom?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HIP.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Geminius.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AN.</SPEAKER>
<L>To morrow wee'll peruse them. No affairs</L>
<L>Of what import or height so ere, shall have</L>
<L>Power to disturbe the pleasures of this night.</L>
<L>Our theam to night is love, which oft has made</L>
<L>The Thunderer himself a while lay by</L>
<L>The weary burden of his government.</L>
<L>Come lead away.</L>
<L>'Twere fit to read them now.</L>
<L>None knows what gain a little time may be</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AN.</SPEAKER>
<L>You may peruse them <HI>Titius</HI>; lead away.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
<STAGE><HI>Manent</HI> TITIUS, PLANCUS.</STAGE>
<L>Can no affairs of what import so ere</L>
<L>Break one nights pleasure? well <HI>Antonius,</HI></L>
<L>The tottering state thou holdst, must be supported</L>
<L>By nobler vertues, or it cannot stand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PLA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cyprus, Phoenice, Coelosyria,</L>
<L>Three wealthy Kingdoms got with Roman bloud,</L>
<L>And our forefathers valour, given away</L>
<L>As the base hire of an adulterous bed.</L>
<L>Was <HI>Cyprus</HI> conquer'd by the sober vertue</L>
<L>Of <HI>Mar<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>us Cato,</HI> to be thus bestow'd?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="9"/>
<SPEAKER>TI.</SPEAKER>
<P>This act will please yong <HI>Caesar.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PLA.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twill displease</L>
<L>The Senate, <HI>Marcus,</HI> and <HI>Antonius</HI> friends.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas, he knows not what true friendship means,</L>
<L>But makes his friends his slaves, and which is worse</L>
<L>Slaves to his lusts and vices; could he else</L>
<L>Slight our advise so? men, whom Rome has seen</L>
<L>Wearing her highest honours, and of birth</L>
<L>As great as his. Unlesse he change his minde</L>
<L>I shall believe my friendship was ill plac'd,</L>
<L>And strive to place it better.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PLA.</SPEAKER>
<L>This last act</L>
<L>Will quickly be at Rome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TI.</SPEAKER>
<L>They have enough</L>
<L>Already, noble <HI>Plancus</HI>; think you not</L>
<L>It will be censur'd that the Roman name</L>
<L>Was much dishonour'd by that base surprize
<STAGE>Dio. Cass. Plutarch.</STAGE></L>
<L>Of <HI>Artuvases</HI> the Armenian King?</L>
<L>Whom through the streets of Alexandria</L>
<L>He led in triumph bound with golden chains</L>
<L>Forcing the captive King, (if all his threats</L>
<L>Could have enforc'd so much) prostrate t' adore</L>
<L>Proud <HI>Cleopatra,</HI> as if all his acts,</L>
<L>And all the honour of his armes were due</L>
<L>To her and not to Rome. <HI>Calvisius</HI> too
<STAGE>Plutarch.</STAGE></L>
<L>In Senate late accus'd him for bestowing</L>
<L>On <HI>Cleopatra</HI> that so farre renown'd</L>
<L>And famous Library of Pergamus,</L>
<L>In which there were two hundred thousand Books.</L>
<L>How many such wilde actions have her charms</L>
<L>Enforc'd his weaknesse to?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="10"/>
<SPEAKER>PLA.</SPEAKER>
<L>His Testament,</L>
<L>Which now at Rome the Vestall Virgins keep,</L>
<L>Of which we two are privy to the sealing,</L>
<L>Should it be known, would stirre all Romans hate,</L>
<L>Willing his bodie, though he dy'd at Rome,
<STAGE>Dio▪ Plutarch▪</STAGE></L>
<L>To be interr'd at Alexandria.</L>
<L>But if a warre 'twixt him and <HI>Caesar</HI> grow</L>
<L>(As needs it must, although not yet declar'd)</L>
<L>For <HI>Caesar</HI> now is levying men and money</L>
<L>Through Italy, Spain, France and Germany,</L>
<L>Against what foe can his designe be bent</L>
<L>But our <HI>Antonius?</HI> if a warre I say</L>
<L>Twixt them should happen, tell me, noble <HI>Titius,</HI></L>
<L>What should we do?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TI.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fight for <HI>Antonius.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PLA.</SPEAKER>
<L>True friend, were he himself, or were there hope,</L>
<L>Or possibility he could be so.</L>
<L>But shall our valour toile in sweat and bloud</L>
<L>Only to gain a Roman Monarchy</L>
<L>For <HI>Cleopatra,</HI> and th'eff<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>minate rout</L>
<L>Of base <HI>Canop<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>?</HI> shall her timbrels fright</L>
<L>Romes C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>p toll, and her advanced pride</L>
<L>Tread on the ne<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ks of captive Senators?</L>
<L>Or, which <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> more, shall th' earths Imperiall seat
<STAGE><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></STAGE></L>
<L>Remove from Rome to Aegypts swarthy sands?</L>
<L>For who can tell if mad <HI>Antonius</HI></L>
<L>Have promis'd her, as <HI>C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>us Marius</HI> once</L>
<L>Promis<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> the Samnites, to transferre the state?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TI.</SPEAKER>
<L>It may be so, his dotage is enough</L>
<L>To grant it her, her pride enough to aske it.</L>
<L><HI>Manutius Plan<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>us,</HI> in this whole discourse</L>
<L>Thou speak'st my very thoughts no more, here comes</L>
<L><PB REF="10"/><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ucilius,</HI> whither so fast?
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Lucilius.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LU.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lords,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>own to the Fort to wait upon the Consuls,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he Roman Consuls both, <HI>Titus Domitius,</HI>
<STAGE>Dio. Sueton.</STAGE></L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd <HI>Caius S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ssius</HI> are from Rome arriv'd</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ere at Pelusium, what the matter is</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s not yet known.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PLA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee'll go along with thee;</L>
<L>This now begins to look like businesse, <HI>Marcus.</HI>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="2" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus Secundus.</HEAD>
<STAGE>ANTONIUS, SOSSIUS, DOMITIUS, CANIDIUS, TITIUS, PLAN∣CUS, VENTIDIUS.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AN.</SPEAKER>
<L>TIs not the place, nor marble wals that make</L>
<L>A Senate lawfull, or decrees of power,</L>
<L>But convocation of the men themselves</L>
<L>The sacred order by true Magistrates.</L>
<L>Then Rome is here; here both her Consuls are,</L>
<L>Here are her axes, and her falces born,</L>
<L>And no small number of that sacred order</L>
<L>Are here assisting, when the barbarous Gaules</L>
<L>Had taken Rome, when all the Senate fled,</L>
<L>And with <HI>Cam<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>llus</HI> their Dictator then</L>
<L><PB REF="11"/>At <HI>Veii</HI> liv'd, Rome then at Veii was,</L>
<L>As now in Aegypt. Fathers, know the face,</L>
<L>Of your assembly, know your lawfull power.</L>
<L>Consult, decree, and act what ere may be</L>
<L>Happy, and prosperous tor the Common-wealth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SOS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whilst power of laws, whilst reverence of the Senate,</L>
<L>And due respect t' a Consuls dignity</L>
<L>Could give protection to the Consuls persons</L>
<L>We did maintain thy cause <HI>Antonius</HI></L>
<L>Against proud <HI>Caesars</HI> faction. Now since laws</L>
<L>Are put to silence, and the Senate forc'd,</L>
<L>The Consuls sacred priviledge infring'd</L>
<L>By rage and lawlesse armes, we are expell'd,</L>
<L>And suffer banishment to be restor'd,</L>
<L>And re-indeniz'd by thy conquering sword.</L>
<L>Now justly draw it. Fate approves thy cause,</L>
<L>And on thy conquest sets a glorious prize,</L>
<L>Greater then all thy former wars could give▪</L>
<L><HI>Sextus Pompeius, Marcus Lepidus</HI></L>
<L>Are ruin'd both, and all competitors</L>
<L>Are tane away; Fortune has left but one</L>
<L>To share the world with thee; nor canst thou share</L>
<L>The world with him, his pride would barre thy right▪</L>
<L>And <HI>Caesar's</HI> glory dim <HI>Antonius</HI> light.</L>
<L>Thou canst not shine unlesse alone thou shine.</L>
<L>Or all the world, or nothing must be thine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOM.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Consulship, that was design'd to thee,</L>
<L>The Senate have revoked, and decree</L>
<L>'Gainst <HI>Cleopatra</HI> warre, but meant 'gainst thee.</L>
<L>What would their malice dare <HI>Antonius,</HI></L>
<L>Had Fortune frown'd, thy Kings and Provinces</L>
<L>Revolted from thee, that dare now p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ovoke</L>
<L>Thy growing fortunes and assisting Gods?</L>
<L>Their injury has made thy quarrell just.</L>
<L><PB REF="11"/>Be speedy then, and lose no time of action:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SOS.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Caesar</HI> is needy; his Italian souldiers
<STAGE>Dio. Plutarch.</STAGE></L>
<L>Are apt to mutiny for want of pay,</L>
<L>And might with ease be tempted to revolt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAN.</SPEAKER>
<L>We need them not; our strengths are greater farre</L>
<L>Then <HI>Caesar's</HI> are; our praeparations readier.</L>
<L>Nought but delay can question our successe.</L>
<L>Shall we decree the warre?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AN.</SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tay noble Romans;</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>efore we publish a Decree, or shew</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he reason our arms so justly tane;</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eigh but with me the means and strength we have.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>now worthy friends it is no desperate warre</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>our valours are engag'd in; briefly thus:</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ur Roman strength is nineteen Legions.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>en Kings in person will attend our Camp,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he Kings of Africk, Comagena, Thrace,
<STAGE>Plutarch.</STAGE></L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pper Cilicia, Paphlagonia,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>f Cappadocia, Pontus, Palaestine,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>f rich Arabia, and Galatia.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ur strength at Sea five hundred fighting ships</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ell rigg'd and mann'd: our treasuries are full;</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd twenty thousand talents to the warre</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oes <HI>Cleopatra</HI> freely contribute.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hy speak I more? the Crown of all my strength,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ur loves and spirits are. The injuries</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> which we ground our just and lawfull warre,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> briefly these. <HI>Caesar</HI> unjustly holds</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hose Provinces, and armies all, that late
<STAGE>Dio. Plutarch.</STAGE></L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>long'd to <HI>Pompey</HI> and to <HI>Lepidus</HI></L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>fusing to divide them, or deliver</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he moity which appertains to me</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ough oft demanded by my friends at Rome,</L>
<L><PB REF="12"/>And letters from my self▪ besides he levies</L>
<L>Both men and money ore all Italy,</L>
<L>Which country, as you know, by our agreement</L>
<L>Belongs to both, and should be held in common.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TI.</SPEAKER>
<P>Most true.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CA.</SPEAKER>
<L>These wrongs are past all sufferance.</L>
<L>Thy warre is but defensive, to regain</L>
<L>Thine own unjustly taken.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOM.</SPEAKER>
<P>The warre's just.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SOSS.</SPEAKER>
<L>And <HI>Caesar</HI> the beginner of these broyls</L>
<L>From whom the wrong first sprung, most justly may</L>
<L>Be judg'd an enemy to the peace of Rome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AN.</SPEAKER>
<L>If Fortune aid us in a cause so just,</L>
<L>And we return victorious, noble Romans,</L>
<L>I make a vow, and let it be recorded,</L>
<L>Within two moneths after the warre is ended,
<STAGE><HI>Di<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI></STAGE></L>
<L>I will lay down the government I hold,</L>
<L>And freely then resigne my power again</L>
<L>Unto the Senate and the people of Rome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SOSS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let it be six moneths rather; for two moneths
<STAGE><HI>Di<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI></STAGE></L>
<L>Will be too short a time to settle it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOM.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ssius</HI> speaks well, my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANT.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let it be so,</L>
<L>And all the Gods assist me as I mean</L>
<L>A just and true performance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CA.</SPEAKER>
<L>All the Gods</L>
<L>Preserve <HI>Antonius</HI> father of his Country.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="12"/>
<SPEAKER>OMN.</SPEAKER>
<P>Author and Champion of our liberty.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Exeunt. manent</HI> TIT<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>S, PLANCUS.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TI.</SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>et them believe that list; for me, I think</L>
<L>The resignation of a power so great</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ill be a temperance too great for him</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re to expresse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PLA.</SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r if he would, he must</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ke leave of <HI>Cleopatra,</HI> and her pride</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ill hardly grant him that.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TI.</SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>or will I fight</L>
<L>To make her Mistris of the world and him▪</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ave you consider'd, noble friend of what</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e lately spake?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PLA.</SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd am resolved <HI>Marcus.</HI></L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he friends and followers we shall bring with us</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ill make us welcome guests to <HI>Caesars</HI> side.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> seems the City favours <HI>Caesar</HI> much</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hat both the Consuls fled from Rome for fear.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>or is our action base; the scorns and wrongs</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> have endur'd at <HI>Cleopatraes</HI> hands
<STAGE>Plutarch.</STAGE></L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ould tempt a moyle to fury, and both sides</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tand equall yet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TI.</SPEAKER>
<P><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ome let's away; tis time.
<STAGE>Dio.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PLA.</SPEAKER>
<P><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>gypt farewell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TI.</SPEAKER>
<P><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>arewell <HI>Antonius.</HI>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="13"/>SELEUCUS, GLAUCUS.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SE.</SPEAKER>
<L>How suddenly the Scene is changed here</L>
<L>From love and banquets to the rough alarms</L>
<L>And threatning noise of warre!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GLA.</SPEAKER>
<L>The change, <HI>Seleucus</HI></L>
<L>Is not so suddain as you speak; this storm</L>
<L>Has been expected long; the two great Lords</L>
<L>Of all the Roman world, <HI>Antonius</HI></L>
<L>And <HI>Caesar</HI> have in heart been enemies</L>
<L>These many yeers; and every man has wonder'd</L>
<L>'T has been withheld so long, considering</L>
<L>How much complaining has been daily made</L>
<L>By them, their friends, and factions 'gainst each other</L>
<L>Whose cause is justest let the Gods determine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SE.</SPEAKER>
<L>No other justice then ambition</L>
<L>Makes them to draw their swords; no other cause</L>
<L>Then that the world cannot endure two Suns.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GLA.</SPEAKER>
<L>The thing that troubles me, <HI>Seleucus</HI>▪ is</L>
<L>I hear it spoken in the Court, the Queen</L>
<L>Her self in person will associate</L>
<L><HI>Antonius</HI> to the warre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SE.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hear that rumour;</L>
<L>But hope it is not true, how nakedly</L>
<L>And in what great confusion would this land</L>
<L>Be left! and what addition can her person</L>
<L>Among so many Roman Legions</L>
<L>Bring to <HI>Antonius?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GLA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let us enquire</L>
<L>The certainty; I fain would be resolv'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="13"/>
<SPEAKER>SE.</SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> necessity must know, before</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he Queen can go, that order may be taken</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>bout the Fort I keep, what strength she means</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o leave within it in her absence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GLA.</SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rue,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hat reason will excuse thee for enquiring.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>CLEOPATRA, CANIDIUS.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLE.</SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oble <HI>Canidius,</HI> I'll entrust no more,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>or use more circumstances; for I know</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o whom I have referr'd my businesse,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd trust your wisdome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CA.</SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oyall <HI>Cleopatra.</HI></L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> so fortify'd with reasons now
<STAGE>Plutarch.</STAGE></L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hat maugre <HI>Sossius</HI> and <HI>Domitius</HI></L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ith all their best perswasions, I'll prevaile</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> shall not stay behinde; fear it not Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLE,</SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ave Roman, wear this jewell for my sake;</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd be possest of <HI>Cleopatraes</HI> love.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>cond my suit, there lies not in my power</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>thing to grant I should deny <HI>Canidius.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CA.</SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he favours, Madam, you can give, have power</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> oblige the greatest Monarchs of the World.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLE.</SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> ready, worthy friend; he'll straight be here.
<STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Can.</STAGE></L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>one but <HI>Canidius</HI> has the power to work</L>
<L><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ntonius</HI> in this action, which the rest</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ll all oppose, I know; a thing on which</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y state, my hopes, and fortunes all depend.</L>
<L><PB REF="14"/>He must perswade <HI>Antonius</HI> to take</L>
<L>Me with him to the warre; for if I stay</L>
<L>Behinde him here, I run a desperate hazard;</L>
<L>For should <HI>Octavia</HI> enterpose her self</L>
<L>In this great warre (as once before she did)</L>
<L>And make her brother, and her husband friends</L>
<L>Wher's <HI>Cleopatra</HI> then? but here he comes.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>ANTONIUS, CLEOPATRA.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AN.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweet <HI>Cleopatra,</HI> I should plead excuse</L>
<L>For leaving thee awhile, but that the cause</L>
<L>Is of a nature so immense and high,</L>
<L>And brings effects of such advantage home,</L>
<L>That thou I know art pleas'd it should be so;</L>
<L>And with a patience canst resolve to bear</L>
<L>So small an absence, that my wish'd return</L>
<L>May call thee mistris of the subject world.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLE.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cannot <HI>Antonius</HI> then be fortunate</L>
<L>If <HI>Cleopatra</HI> go? <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s there in me</L>
<L>So bad an <HI>Omen?</HI> did I think there were,</L>
<L>Not for the world would I desire to bear</L>
<L>You company but rather die at home.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AN.</SPEAKER>
<L>Farre are my thoughts from giving entertainment</L>
<L>To such fond dreams. I would not venture thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLE.</SPEAKER>
<L>My life and fortunes both depend on yours.</L>
<L>As much in Aegypt will my danger be,</L>
<L>As in your army, and my torment more,</L>
<L>To die each houre for feare: and to remain</L>
<L>In sad suspence till messengers can bring</L>
<L>The news so farre: but if my company</L>
<L>Distast my Lord, I cannot wish his grief.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="14"/>
<SPEAKER>AN.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can <HI>Cleopatra</HI> think her heavenly presence,</L>
<L>Can be distastfull, or not valued more</L>
<L>Then all joys else; parted from thee I think,</L>
<L>All places sad, all lands disconsolate,</L>
<L>Before this life I prize thy company,</L>
<L>But must not have it now, do not entreat;</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> have deny'd it to my self already.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd in the Camp should be asham'd to rise</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rom <HI>Cleopatraes</HI> arms, when wars <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ough noise</L>
<L>Shakes all the world, when Kings and Senators</L>
<L>Are venturing lives and fortunes in my service.</L>
<L>Oh stay behinde! and let thy presence make</L>
<L>Egypt a place, to which I would desire</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>f <HI>Caesar's</HI> fortune conquer, to retire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLE.</SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>f that should happen (which the Gods avert)</L>
<L>What land, alas! could comfort me, or lend</L>
<L>A safe retreat to vanquish'd <HI>Antony?</HI></L>
<L>Thou would'st disdain to draw a wretched breath,</L>
<L>And I as much should scorn captivity.</L>
<L>But I had thought the Roman <HI>Antony</HI></L>
<L>Had lov'd so great a Queen with nobler love;</L>
<L>Not as the pleasure of his wanton bed</L>
<L>Or mistris only of some looser houres,</L>
<L>But as a partner in his highest cares,</L>
<L>And one whose soul he thought were fit to share</L>
<L>In all his dangers, all his deeds of honour.</L>
<L>Without that love I should disdain the other.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AN.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do not mistake me, noble Queen, I know</L>
<L>Thy brest is full of high heroike worth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLE.</SPEAKER>
<L>How can you think it so, that could so long</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n times of peace and pleasure recreate</L>
<L>Your self with me in Aegypt Court; yet now</L>
<L><PB REF="15"/>When honour calls, reject my company?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AN.</SPEAKER>
<L>I should desire it rather then my life;</L>
<L>But that my Roman friends are all against it.</L>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> SOSSIUS, DOMITIUS, CANIDIUS.</STAGE>
<L>See here they come, if they agree tis done.</L>
<L>Now noble friends on whose oraculous counsels</L>
<L>And matchlesse valour my whole fate depends,</L>
<L>Speak what you think, should <HI>Cleopatra</HI> go</L>
<L>In person to the warre, or stay behinde?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SO.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have delivered my opinion,</L>
<L>And so has my Colleague.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AN.</SPEAKER>
<P>What thinks <HI>Canidius</HI>?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CA.</SPEAKER>
<L>I think tis fit, my Lord, the Queen, whose bounty</L>
<L>Has brought so great assistance to the warre,</L>
<L>Should not be left behinde, besides her presence</L>
<L>Will much encourage her Aegyptian souldiers,</L>
<L>Of which a great part of the fleet consists.
<STAGE>Plutarch.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AN.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis true <HI>Canidius.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLE.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let not my sex</L>
<L>Disparage me, for which of all those Kings</L>
<L>That now in person serve <HI>Antonius</HI></L>
<L>Have more experience in affairs of weight</L>
<L>Then I, my Lord, which have so long been privy</L>
<L>To your high counsels, and in love to you</L>
<L>And your designes who should compare with me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AN.</SPEAKER>
<P>What think you friends? you heare <HI>Canidius.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOM.</SPEAKER>
<P>If you be pleas'd, I will subscribe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="15"/>
<SPEAKER>SOS.</SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> I,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> things go so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLE.</SPEAKER>
<P><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> wishes are effected.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AN.</SPEAKER>
<P><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, and <HI>Plancus</HI> are both fled to <HI>Caesar.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAN.</SPEAKER>
<P><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> shall not need their help my Lord, at all.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AN.</SPEAKER>
<P><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> me, let's away.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLE.</SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> strengths are ready all,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> wait but your command.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AN.</SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>oke like <HI>Bellona.</HI></L>
<L><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>idius,</HI> return you to your charge</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> bring those sixteen Cohorts down to sea; <HI>Plutarch.</HI></L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> me at Samos with them, both the Consuls</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> go along with me. Great Father <HI>Mars,</HI></L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> all you Gods, that from the skies behold</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Roman labours, whose propitious aid</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>vanc'd my fortunes to so great an height,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ke perfect that, which you your selves begun.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> is the swords last work, the judging houre</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Nations fates, of mine and <HI>Caesar</HI>'s power.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> which the stars and destinies attend,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> all the fortunes of Mankinde depend.
<STAGE>Exeunt</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ACHOREUS.</SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hat dire portents sent from the wrathfull Gods?</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hreaten th'astonish'd world? What plagues are those</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hich in the skies prodigious face I read?</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>umultuous Nature teems with monstrous births,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> if the throws would break her labouring wombe.</L>
<L><PB REF="16"/>What ruine lesse then <HI>Chaos</HI> shall involve</L>
<L>The mourning face of Nature? what great fate,</L>
<L>What kinde of mischief is it? oh ye Gods,</L>
<L>Why did you adde to wretched men a care</L>
<L>So past their strength to bear, to let them know</L>
<L>By sad presages their ensuing woe?</L>
<L>Unknown and sec<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>et let your vengeance be,</L>
<L>And none foresee their following misery;</L>
<L>But hope as well as fear. <HI>Jove</HI> hide thy dooms;</L>
<L>Keep shut, oh fates, your adamantine books!</L>
<L>Let not the bainfull curiosity</L>
<L>Of humane knowledge search your secret counsels,</L>
<L>And read your purposes, to nourish so</L>
<L>A killing fear before the danger grow.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> SELEUCUS, GLAUCUS.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SE.</SPEAKER>
<P>That Comet's gone.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GLA.</SPEAKER>
<L>It mov'd directly upward,</L>
<L>And did not vanish till it seem'd to reach</L>
<L>The firmament.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ACH.</SPEAKER>
<P>What talk you of my sonnes?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GLA.</SPEAKER>
<P>That Comet, father, ore the Graecian Sea.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ACH.</SPEAKER>
<L>It was a strange one both for form and greatnesse,</L>
<L>And bodes some mischief whersoere it light.</L>
<L>The Gods avert it from our Aegypts coast.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SE.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Pinnarius Scarpus</HI> had received news</L>
<L>That Italy and Rome it self are fill'd</L>
<L>With prodigies: an ugly Owle of late</L>
<L>Did fly into the house of Concord first,</L>
<L><PB REF="16"/>Thence being driven away it pearch'd again</L>
<L>Within the Temple of the peoples <HI>Genius.</HI></L>
<L>There, though all striv'd, it neither could be caught,</L>
<L>Nor driven away, but flew at leisure out.</L>
<L>A sacred Trophey on Mount Aventine,
<STAGE>Dio.</STAGE></L>
<L><HI>Victoriaes</HI> Image on the Theater
<STAGE>Dio.</STAGE></L>
<L>By suddain tempests were thrown down and broken.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GLA.</SPEAKER>
<L>In Rome and other parts of Italy</L>
<L>Sudden and strangely kindled fires have done</L>
<L>Exceeding waste; and we are certifi'd</L>
<L>That now Sicilian Aetna nourishes
<STAGE>Dio.</STAGE></L>
<L>More horrid flames then usually it does,</L>
<L>And farther casts his scorching entrails forth,</L>
<L>Blasting the fields and burning up the corn.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SE.</SPEAKER>
<L>A two-legg'd Dragon in Etruria
<STAGE>Dio.</STAGE></L>
<L>Full fourscore foot in length was lately seen,</L>
<L>Which after much annoyance of the Country</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t self with lightning was consum'd at last.</L>
<L>But these portents do threaten Italy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ACH.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas, my sonne, there need no prodigies</L>
<L>To shew the certain losse of Italy.</L>
<L>For on both sides do Roman Eagles stand,</L>
<L>And Rome must bleed who ere be conquerour,</L>
<L>Besides her liberty for ever lost</L>
<L>When this sad field is fought: but that's not all,</L>
<L>What clime so farre, what region so remote,</L>
<L>But that the Roman fortune reaches thither?</L>
<L>All nations share in this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GLA.</SPEAKER>
<L>What hast thou got</L>
<L>By all thy conquest Rome, by all the bloud</L>
<L>Which thy ambition through the world has shed,</L>
<L>But rais'd a power, which now thou canst not rule,</L>
<L><PB REF="17"/>Nourish'd a Lion to devoure thy self?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SE.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would none but Roman bloud might quench the fire</L>
<L>Of Romes dissentions, and no land beside</L>
<L>Be forc'd to pay the forfeit of their pride.</L>
<L>With evill <HI>Omen</HI> did Aeneas first</L>
<L>Transport the reliques of Troyes fatall fire</L>
<L>To Italy, that kindled greater there</L>
<L>It might at last like lightning through the world</L>
<L>Rend every Nation. Was it not enough,</L>
<L>That first your conquests strew'd the earth with slaugh¦ter</L>
<L>And dy'd all Regions with their natives blouds,</L>
<L>But your dissentions still must tear the world?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ACHO.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'll go within, and make an offering</L>
<L>To great <HI>Osiris.</HI>
<STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Achoreu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GLA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well may it succeed.</L>
<L>Aegypt will flourish if <HI>Antonius</HI> conquer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SE.</SPEAKER>
<L>If he should fall, the fury of the warre</L>
<L>Would light on Aegypt most, and we should rue</L>
<L>That ere <HI>Antonius</HI> lov'd this haplesse land.</L>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> MARDIO.</STAGE>
<L>Oh Gentlemen, the strongest news, that ere</L>
<L>Was seen in Aegypt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GLA.</SPEAKER>
<P>What's that <HI>Mardio?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thousands of people with astonishment</L>
<L>And fear beheld it: on those fruitfull plains</L>
<L>That Southward ly from Alexandria,</L>
<L>Where never rain was known to fall before,
<STAGE><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></STAGE></L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> whole showers of blo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d, whose colour set</L>
<L><PB REF="17"/>A purple die upon those verdant fields;</L>
<L>And in the clouds that horrid noise was heard</L>
<L>That meeting armies make, beating of drums.</L>
<L>Shrill trumpets sound, armor against armor clashing,</L>
<L>As if the bloud that fell, dropp'd from the wounds
<STAGE>Dio.</STAGE></L>
<L>Those aëry battails made.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GLA.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is more strange</L>
<L>Then all the rest: this is our own <HI>Seleucus.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SE.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well Gentlemen, I'll to Pelusium,</L>
<L>And fortifie the town to keep our foes,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>f foes be conquerours, from entring there.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GLA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, and our friends, if they be vanquished,</L>
<L>Keep out our friends, <HI>Seleucus,</HI> if their presence</L>
<L>May pluck a warre, and ruine on our heads.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SE.</SPEAKER>
<L>As there's occasion wee'll determine that.</L>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> ACHOREUS.</STAGE>
<L>Avert your ange<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, Gods, if all too late</L>
<L>Our prayers came not now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GLA.</SPEAKER>
<L>What is it father?</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>our looks, I see, are full of ruth and wo.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ACHO.</SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> wretched Aegypt, ah unhappy land</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> what hast thou so stor'd the wrath of heaven?</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he grieved God refus'd his offering</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ellowing aloud that all the Temple rung,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd from his sacred eys the tears run down.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ould I could contradict, or not beleeve</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he skill which surest observations teach.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>his signifies a change of government.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="18"/>
<SPEAKER>GLA.</SPEAKER>
<P>What heaven is pleas'd to send, we much endure.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ACO.</SPEAKER>
<L>True sonne; and let a wise man place his strengths</L>
<L>Within himself, nor trust to outward aids.</L>
<L>That whatsoever from the Gods can come</L>
<L>May finde him ready to receive their doom.
<STAGE><HI>Exeu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="3" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus Tertius.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> PINNARIUS SCARPUS <HI>with Souldiers.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PIN.</SPEAKER>
<L>TIs not <HI>Antonius,</HI> worthy souldiers,</L>
<L>But Rome herself to whom you owe your valours</L>
<L>What he could claim, you have perform'd already;</L>
<L>And serv'd him truly, whilst he was to you</L>
<L>A Generall, to Rome a Magistrate.</L>
<L>You are discharg'd from all obedience</L>
<L>You ow'd to him, by fate it self, and may</L>
<L>Nay, ought to follow him, whom Roman fates</L>
<L>Appoint your Generall, the noble <HI>Caesar</HI></L>
<L>Great <HI>Julius</HI> heir, not to his name alone</L>
<L>But spirit and fortunes, which have both appear'd</L>
<L>In this so great and finall a defeat</L>
<L>Given to <HI>Antonius.</HI> Before we knew not</L>
<L><PB REF="18"/><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o whom the Gods and Fortune had assign'd</L>
<L>Our service souldiers; now they have declar'd.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd let us follow where they please to lead.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>or faith is impious striving to sustain</L>
<L>That side, whose fall the Gods themselves ordain.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SOL.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>esar, Caesar, Caesar.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PIN.</SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>our judgments guide you right; for could you think</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o small a strength as ours could raise again</L>
<L>The desperate state of faln <HI>Antonius,</HI></L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nder whose ruine all those legions sunk?</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hat madnesse were it, souldiers to preferre</L>
<L>A hopelesse civill warre before the weal</L>
<L>And peace of Rome? and desperatly provoke</L>
<L>The prosperous fortunes of victorious <HI>Caesar</HI>?</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> have already to <HI>Cornelius Gal<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>us</HI>
<STAGE>Dio.</STAGE></L>
<L>By letter signify'd our purposes.</L>
<L>Who sent from <HI>Caesar</HI> now is marching hither,</L>
<L>To joyn his strength with ours: but ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>k his Drum</L>
<L>Give notice of his comming.</L>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> GALLUS.</STAGE>
<L>Hail <HI>Pinnarius.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PIN.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ah hail <HI>Cornelius Gallus,</HI></L>
<L>Most wish'd for, an most happily arriv'd</L>
<L>At Paraetonium.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GAL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Victorious <HI>Caesar</HI></L>
<L>With love and favour greets <HI>Pinnarius Scarpus,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Caesar,</HI> then whom the world acknowledges</L>
<L>No other power; whom Fortune now has made</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ole Lord of all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="19"/>
<SPEAKER>PI.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, and my souldiers</L>
<L>With Paraetonium are at <HI>Caesar's</HI> service.</L>
<L>Whither's <HI>Antonius</HI> fled?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GAL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hither to Aegypt</L>
<L>With <HI>Cleopatra</HI>? 'Twas a victory</L>
<L>So strangely given away, as not the like</L>
<L>In former times I think has ere been heard;</L>
<L>On which especially so great a price</L>
<L>As the sole sway of all the world depended.</L>
<L>The Fleets encountred both, while with the Camps</L>
<L>On either shore stood to behold the fight,
<STAGE><HI>Di<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>▪</HI></STAGE></L>
<L>Heer the Caesarian, there the Antonian Fleet</L>
<L>With equall hopes came on, with fury equall.</L>
<L>And long maintain'd a sharpe and cruell fight,</L>
<L>With mutuall slaughter, while the Oceans face▪</L>
<L>Was forc'd to lose his colour, and rceive</L>
<L>A crimson die. The ships <HI>Antonius</HI> had</L>
<L>Were tall, and slowly did like Castles move.</L>
<L>But <HI>Caesar's</HI> small, yet quick and active, stirr'd
<STAGE>Dio▪ Florus▪ Plutarch▪</STAGE></L>
<L>On every side with all advantages.</L>
<L>Long fortune doubted, and bright victory</L>
<L>Knew not which way to lean, but kept them both</L>
<L>In equall ballance; till <HI>Antonius</HI></L>
<L>Himself at last betray'd his glorious hopes.</L>
<L>For when his Mistris <HI>Cleopatra</HI> fled,
<STAGE>Plutarch▪ Dio▪ Florus▪</STAGE></L>
<L>Although a while within his manly breast</L>
<L>The Roman honour strove 'gainst wanton love,</L>
<L>Love got the conquest, and <HI>Antonius</HI></L>
<L>Fled after her, leaving his souldiers there</L>
<L>To sell their lives in vain; who many houres</L>
<L>Though he were fled, made good the navall fight.</L>
<L>And had <HI>Antonius</HI> stay'd, it may be fear'd</L>
<L><HI>Caesar</HI> had not prevail'd: at last the Fleet</L>
<L>Wanting their Admirall, though not without</L>
<L><PB REF="19"/>Much slaughter, fled, or yielded all to <HI>Caesar.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PIN.</SPEAKER>
<P>But what became of all his strength on land?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GAL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, there's the wonder, there's <HI>Antonius</HI> madnesse,</L>
<L>And such a madnesse as will strike amazement</L>
<L>To all that heare it told: after his flight</L>
<L>He nere return'd, though in the campe he had</L>
<L>Under the conduct of <HI>Canidius</HI></L>
<L>And other Captains nineteen legions</L>
<L>Fresh and unfought, which might with reason hope</L>
<L>Had he been there, to have recover'd all.</L>
<L>They still remayn'd encamped, and though oft</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ollicited by <HI>Caesar</HI> to revolt</L>
<L>Were kept from yielding, by <HI>Canidius</HI></L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n hope of <HI>Antony's</HI> return. Untill</L>
<L><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>anidius</HI> fearing his own souldiers minds
<STAGE>Plutarch.</STAGE></L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd <HI>Caesar's</HI> anger fled away by night,</L>
<L>They then despairing yielded all to <HI>Caesar.</HI></L>
<L>Who by this time I think's arriv'd in Aegypt.</L>
<L>About Pelusium.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PI.</SPEAKER>
<P>Will you view the town?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GAL.</SPEAKER>
<P>With all my heart, noble <HI>Pinnarius.</HI>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> CaeSAR, AGRIPPA, TITIUS, PLAN∣CUS, THYRE<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>S, EPAPHRODI∣TUS, PROCULEIUS.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cae.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ntonius</HI> then with <HI>Cleopatra's</HI> fled</L>
<L>To Alexandria.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AGR.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis certain, <HI>Caesar.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="20"/>
<SPEAKER>PHA.</SPEAKER>
<L>They say the vanquish'd Queen most cunningly:
<STAGE>Dio▪</STAGE></L>
<L>(Fearing it seems, to be excluded else</L>
<L>From her own Kingdome) fain'd her self victorious,</L>
<L>Landing in Aegypt with triumphant songs</L>
<L>Her ships all crown'd with laurell, to deceive</L>
<L>The credulous people: where being enter'd once</L>
<L>She leaves unpractis'd no strange tyranny;</L>
<L>And, as we hear, to win the Parthan King</L>
<L>Unto her side, beheaded <HI>Artavasdes</HI>
<STAGE><HI>Di<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>▪</HI></STAGE></L>
<L>King of Armenia, and the Parthians <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o,</L>
<L>Who was her prisoner, that <HI>Artavasdes,</HI></L>
<L>Whom <HI>Anthony</HI> so basely had surpris'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TI.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Caesar,</HI> 'twere fit to take Pelusium</L>
<L>Before we march to Alexandria.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cae.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twas our intent, good <HI>Titius,</HI> not to leaue</L>
<L>A town of that import behinde our backs.</L>
<L>Go <HI>Proculeius,</HI> summon it, and know</L>
<L>W<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e her the Governour will yield or no.
<STAGE>Exit. Pro▪</STAGE></L>
<STAGE>Enter. Servant.</STAGE>
<L>What news with thee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SER.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Caesar,</HI> a messenger</L>
<L>From <HI>Cleopatra</HI> craves admittance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cae.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bring him.</L>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> EUPHRONIUS.</STAGE>
<L>Queen <HI>Cleopatra</HI> to great <HI>Caesar</HI> wishes</L>
<L>All health and victory; and humbly proffers</L>
<L>Her self and all her fortunes to his service:
<STAGE><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>▪</STAGE></L>
<L>In token of which she here presents by mee</L>
<L><PB REF="20"/>This Crown and Scepter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TI.</SPEAKER>
<P><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rave and ominous.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>EUP.</SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>umbly entreating <HI>Caesar's</HI> noble favour</L>
<L>To her and hers; the rest of her desires</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o please it <HI>Caesar</HI> to peruse the same,</L>
<L>This letter holds.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PLA.</SPEAKER>
<P><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> warrant a love-lettet.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cae.</SPEAKER>
<P>But tell me first, where is <HI>Antonius?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>EUP.</SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ll truly tell (though it may seem to some</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ncredible) that great <HI>Antonius</HI></L>
<L>A man of late in conversation</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o free, and full of jollity, in a strange</L>
<L>Deep melancholly has retir'd himself
<STAGE><HI>Plut. Strabo lib.</HI> 17.</STAGE></L>
<L>To <HI>Pharos</HI> Ile; where like Athenian <HI>Timon,</HI></L>
<L>Who did professe a hatred to mankinde,</L>
<L>And fled all company, he lives alone;</L>
<L>And on the solitary shore has built</L>
<L>A little house to feed his frantike humour,</L>
<L>And imitate that <HI>Timon's</HI> life, whose name</L>
<L>He takes unto himself: no friends at all</L>
<L>Nor servants are admitted to his presence,</L>
<L>But only two, Roman <HI>Lucilius</HI></L>
<L>And <HI>Aristocrates</HI> the Graecian.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cae.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not <HI>Cleopatra?</HI> then I doubt the man</L>
<L>Grows weary of these worldly vanities.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AGR.</SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> never heard of such a change as this.</L>
<L>Give me the letter. I'll peruse it now
<STAGE>He reads.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="21"/>AGRIPPA, AGR. CaeSAR.
<STAGE>they retire.</STAGE></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here the woman writes</L>
<L>That for her liberty, and to confirme</L>
<L>The Crown of Aegypt to her self and children</L>
<L>To gratifie my favour she has hid
<STAGE>Dio▪ Plutarch▪</STAGE></L>
<L>Within her pallace a great masse of gold.</L>
<L>Unknown t' <HI>Antonius.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AGRI.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis like ennough,</L>
<L>For <HI>Cleoptraea's</HI> rich, and long has been,</L>
<L>Besides the sacriledge she lately did</L>
<L>In robbing all the Temples of the Gods</L>
<L>About these parts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cae.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would not lose this gold,</L>
<L>Nor willingly let <HI>Cleopatra</HI> die</L>
<L>Before her person have adorn'd my triumph.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AGR.</SPEAKER>
<L>That will be hard to bring to passe, and must</L>
<L>Be wrought with subtilty: you must not send</L>
<L>A threatning message back; for if you do,</L>
<L>All's lost, her life, her gold and all are vanish'd.</L>
<L>For <HI>Cleopatra,</HI> as in all her acts</L>
<L>It has appear'd, is of a wondrous spirit,</L>
<L>Of an ambition greater then her fortunes</L>
<L>Have ever been, though she so long have sway'd</L>
<L>A soveraignty ore half the Roman world,</L>
<L>Trod on the necks of humbled Kings, and rul'd</L>
<L><HI>Antonius</HI> as her slave: her haughty spirit</L>
<L>Will never stoop so much as to a thought</L>
<L>Of such captivity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cae.</SPEAKER>
<L>I do not mean</L>
<L><PB REF="21"/>To let her know my minde, or once suspect</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> I can help it, but I have it now.</L>
<L><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hyreus</HI> come hither; I must now rely</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pon thy wisdome, care, and diligence</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> an employment that concerns me neerly.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ut I am confident: go with this fellow
<STAGE>Dio. Plutarch.</STAGE></L>
<L>To Alexandria; use to the Queen</L>
<L>Thy best and most perswasive Oratory.</L>
<L>Tell her I love her, and extremly dote</L>
<L>On her admired beauty, thou art wise</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd need'st no great instructions; the successe</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> do not doubt, the woman's credulous,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd thinks all men are bound to be in love</L>
<L>With that insnaring face; if thou perceive</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he will be wrought on, winne her to betray</L>
<L><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ntonius</HI> to my hand: the way to woo her</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> leave good <HI>Thyreus</HI> to thy eloquence</L>
<L>And cunning working of it: spare thy reply
<STAGE><HI>to</HI> Euph.</STAGE></L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>id him come hither. Commend my hearty love</L>
<L>To <HI>Cleopatra</HI>; bid her fear no ill</L>
<L>From me at all. What I desire from her</L>
<L>My freed man <HI>Thyreus</HI> has commission</L>
<L>To utter to her self. <HI>Epaphroditus,</HI></L>
<L>So see him well rewarded.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>EPA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Health to <HI>Caesar.</HI>
<STAGE><HI>Exeunt.</HI> Epa. <HI>&amp;</HI> Euph.</STAGE></L>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> PROCULEIUS.</STAGE>
<L>The Governour is stout, and does resolve</L>
<L>To stand th' extremest hazard of the warre</L>
<L>Before he yield Pelusium.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cae.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let him rue</L>
<L>His stubborn loyalty, souldiers make ready</L>
<L>For the assault; 'tis shame so small a town▪</L>
<L><PB REF="22"/>Should stay our fortune in the full carreer.
<STAGE>Exeunt▪</STAGE></L>
<STAGE>ANTONIUS <HI>disguis'd like</HI> TIMON, <HI>reading.</HI></STAGE>
<L><HI>Here bury'd do I lie; thou gentle wave</HI>
<STAGE>Calli<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mah<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Epigr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> <HI>de</HI> Ti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mone▪</STAGE></L>
<L><HI>Keep hatefull man from treading</HI> Ti∣mons <HI>grave.</HI></L>
<L><HI>Reader be gone; enquire no more of me,</HI></L>
<L><HI>A curse upon thee whatsoere thou be.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANT.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good, good; oh <HI>Timon,</HI> Athens nere could boast</L>
<L>A wise philosoher but thee. Thou knew'st</L>
<L>The nature of all men, that all were false;</L>
<L>True <HI>Timon,</HI> true, they are all Knaves indeed.</L>
<L>Thou wisely hat'st that wicked thing call'd man,</L>
<L>Whom other forced Philosophers admire,</L>
<L>And call a noble creature, and partaker</L>
<L>Of divine nature: they were fools, fools <HI>Timon,</HI></L>
<L>All other Sects were fools, and I will follow</L>
<L>No sect but thine; I am a Timonist.</L>
<L>That's not enough, <HI>Timon</HI> himself I am.</L>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> LUCILIUS, ARISTOCRATES.</STAGE>
<L>Yonder he sits, see <HI>Aristocrates</HI></L>
<L>How much unlike that great <HI>Antonius,</HI></L>
<L>Whose person late so many legions guarded,</L>
<L>So many Kings attended as their Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ARI.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Antonius,</HI> where? thou art deceiv'd <HI>Lucilius,</HI></L>
<L>That's <HI>Timon</HI> man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LU.</SPEAKER>
<L>How canst thou jest at this</L>
<L>This wofull passion, which alone's enough</L>
<L>To melt his foes and <HI>Caesar</HI> into tears.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ARI.</SPEAKER>
<L>We feed this foolish passion, to give way,</L>
<L><PB REF="22"/><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd keep aloof thus. I'll go to him. <HI>Timon.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AN.</SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>a! what art thou? be gone I say from me.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>et you to <HI>Caesar</HI> man: I hate you all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ARI.</SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> hate thee, <HI>Timon</HI>; dost thou think 'tis love</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>as brought me hither? I am come to vex thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AN.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh welcome, what's thy name? i'st <HI>Alcibi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>des?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ARI.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hast thou forgot me?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANT.</SPEAKER>
<P>Dost thou hate all men?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ARI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why dost thou think me so unnaturall</L>
<L>To love a man? but may we not love women?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AN.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, they may be belov'd; provided always</L>
<L>That they be false.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ARI.</SPEAKER>
<L>True <HI>Timon,</HI> wicked women</L>
<L>May be belov'd, because they ruine men.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANT.</SPEAKER>
<L>Right, right; and now I better think upon't</L>
<L>I'll set no gallowses or gibbets up</L>
<L>As I entended once, for men to come</L>
<L>And hang themselves, I'll keep a bawdy house.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ARI.</SPEAKER>
<L>A better way by farre, 'twill ruine moe,</L>
<L>I wonder, <HI>Timon,</HI> at that foolish plot</L>
<L>That I have heard, that in thy gardens once</L>
<L>In Athens thou did'st set up gallowses</L>
<L>For men in discontent to hang themselves.</L>
<L>How few think'st thou would be so mad to do it?</L>
<L>But to a wench they'll come, and then the office</L>
<L>That thou shalt have will be of more account.</L>
<L><PB REF="23"/>For where have you a man of any fashion</L>
<L>That now adays turnes hangman; but a Pandar</L>
<L>Is on employment that befits a Statesman,</L>
<L>A thing requires good parts and gravity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANT.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'de try that course; but tis too slow a plot.</L>
<L>Oh for a speedy way to kill the world</L>
<L>I have done somewhat in my days; my wars</L>
<L>And bloudy battels were not made in vain.</L>
<L>For I was once <HI>Antonius,</HI> and a Roman,</L>
<L>As in the wars of Troy <HI>Pythagoras</HI></L>
<L>Before that transmigration of his soul,</L>
<L>Had been <HI>Euphorbus.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AN.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou art like him still.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANT.</SPEAKER>
<L>And when I was <HI>Triumvir</HI> first at Rome,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AN.</SPEAKER>
<L>That was a time indeed, then I could heare</L>
<L>Of those good deeds, which must be still a comfort</L>
<L>To your good consciences, though they be past.</L>
<L>When Rome was fill'd with slaughter, flow'd with bloud.</L>
<L>But they perchance were Knaves that were proscrib'd▪</L>
<L>And might have done more mischief had they liv'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AN.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, they were honest men; I look'd to that.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ARI.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Twas well, and carefully.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AN.</SPEAKER>
<L>Behold the list.</L>
<L>But one among the rest most comforts me,</L>
<L>That talking fellow <HI>Cicero,</HI> that us'd</L>
<L>To taxe the vicious times, and was forsoeth</L>
<L>A lover of his Country.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="23"/>
<SPEAKER>ARI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Out upon him,</L>
<L>Then he was rightly serv'd: for is it fit</L>
<L>In a well govern'd state such men should live</L>
<L>As love their Country? had 't not been for him</L>
<L><HI>Catiline's</HI> plot had thriv'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AN.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis true, I'm sure</L>
<L><HI>Caesar</HI> was on that side, he favour'd it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ARI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, <HI>Caesar</HI> understood himself; ther's hope</L>
<L>That this young <HI>Caesar</HI> too will prove as good</L>
<L>A Patriot as ere his father was.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANT.</SPEAKER>
<L>He will do reason man: he is of nature</L>
<L>Cruell enough; in that proscription</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t did appear; but now he'll reigne alone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ARI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh for such factions as were then a foot</L>
<L>To rend the state, and fill the world with slaughter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANT.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh, let me hug thee <HI>Alcibiade<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</HI></P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> CANIDIUS, LUCILIUS.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CA.</SPEAKER>
<P><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s that he yonder? w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>t strange shape is that?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LU.</SPEAKER>
<L>None talks with him but <HI>Aristocrates,</HI></L>
<L>Who following his own way, and suiting just</L>
<L>With his conceit thinks to reclaim him so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CA.</SPEAKER>
<L>The news, that I shall bring, will make him worse,</L>
<L>And fright that little reason that is left</L>
<L>Quite from his brest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="24"/>
<SPEAKER>LU.</SPEAKER>
<L>It cannot so <HI>Canidius</HI>;</L>
<L>Perchance to hear th'extremity of all</L>
<L>Will cure his fit; it cannot make him worse.</L>
<L>For death it self were better and more noble.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CA.</SPEAKER>
<L>How weak a thing is man that seats his hopes</L>
<L>In fortunes slippery, and unconstant favours,</L>
<L>And seeks no surer strengths to guard his soul?</L>
<L>Wanting a strong foundation, he is shaken</L>
<L>With every winde, orethrown by every storm.</L>
<L>And what so frequent as those storms in fortune?</L>
<L>Whose fairest weather never brings assurance</L>
<L>Of perpetuity but come what will</L>
<L>I'll tell him all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LU.</SPEAKER>
<P>Do, good <HI>Canidius.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANT.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well <HI>Alcibiades,</HI> I am resolv'd</L>
<L>I'll to the wars again, and either conquer</L>
<L>Mine enemies, or take a course to starve</L>
<L>And kill up my own souldiers, and so be</L>
<L>Reveng'd on some body: One of these two</L>
<L>May easily be brought to passe. How think'st thou?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ARI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, yes: but lets to Court, and there consult.</L>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> MARDIO.</STAGE>
<L>See who comes here, now for our bawdy project▪</L>
<L>Here is a servant I must needs preferre</L>
<L>Well vers'd in bawdry, Master of the art.</L>
<L>Come neer brave <HI>Mardio,</HI> come.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAR.</SPEAKER>
<L>My businesse</L>
<L>Is not to you;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="24"/>
<SPEAKER>ARI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mark him but well, and tell me</L>
<L>How he would execute the place.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAR.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord,</L>
<L>The Queen entreats your presence at the Palace,</L>
<L>The grieved Queen, who in your absence pines,</L>
<L>Who suffers in your grief.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ARI.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well urg'd old <HI>Eunuch.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANT.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha! what of her? will she revolt to <HI>Caesar?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAR.</SPEAKER>
<P>She's farre from that, my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANT.</SPEAKER>
<P>What i'st he says?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ARI.</SPEAKER>
<L>He says the constitution of her body</L>
<L>Cannot hold out unlesse you visit her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAR.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Queen shall know it, <HI>Aristocrates.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ARI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did you not say she pin'd and languish'd Sir,</L>
<L>And what's the difference? tell your tale yourself.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANT.</SPEAKER>
<P>What does she say? does she not hate me man?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh no my Lord, she loves you as her life.</L>
<L>No spite of fortune that she has endur'd,</L>
<L>Or can hereafter fear, grieves her so much</L>
<L>As does your absence and strange melancholy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ARI.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well <HI>Mardio,</HI> thou art fittest for the place.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAN.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord <HI>Antonius?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="25"/>
<SPEAKER>AN.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha! mo men upon us?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CA.</SPEAKER>
<L>I come to bring thee heavy news <HI>Antonius.</HI></L>
<L>The forces all, which thou didst leave encamp'd</L>
<L>At Actium, horse and foot are gone to <HI>Caesar.</HI></L>
<L>And all th' auxiliary Kings; no strength</L>
<L>At all is left thee, but what here thou hast</L>
<L>At Alexandria.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AN.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LU.</SPEAKER>
<P>This sinks into him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CA.</SPEAKER>
<P>It makes a deep impression in his passion.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ARI.</SPEAKER>
<P>And may perchance expell his other fit.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AN.</SPEAKER>
<L>All you here yet! then I have friends I see.</L>
<L>But tell me, can you be so mercifull</L>
<L>As to forgive that most unmanly fit</L>
<L>I have been in? oh, I am all in blushes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CA.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord, take better comfort.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AN.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dearest friends.</L>
<L>I will be proof 'gainst any fortune now.
<STAGE>Plutarch.</STAGE></L>
<L>Come let's together to the Court, and there</L>
<L>Drown sadnesse in rich cups of Meroë wine,</L>
<L>And laugh at Fortunes malice, for your sight</L>
<L>More cheers my spirits, then her frowns can dull them.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Exeun<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</HI></STAGE>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="4" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="25"/>
<HEAD>Actus Quartus.</HEAD>
<STAGE>CLEOPATRA, GLAU∣CUS.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GLA.</SPEAKER>
<L>MAdam, all drugs with pain and torment kill</L>
<L>That kill with speed. No easie way to death</L>
<L>Is wrought but by a slow and lingring course,</L>
<L>Where Natures strength is by degrees subdu'd,</L>
<L>And yielding so decayes insensibly.</L>
<L>No art at all can make a drug that's quick</L>
<L>And gentle too. No poyson but the Aspe</L>
<L>Of all the mortall brood of Libyaes Snakes</L>
<L>Kils with a suddain, and yet easie death</L>
<L>As if brought forth to contradict our skill</L>
<L>By envious Nature, who disdains frail man</L>
<L>Should hope to finde her secrets wholly out.</L>
<L>None but that Serpent, Madam, can effect
<STAGE>Plutarch.</STAGE></L>
<L>What you desire; of which I here have brought.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLE.</SPEAKER>
<L>Leave it good <HI>Glaucus</HI>; leave the potion too.</L>
<L>Tis quick, thou sayst.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GLA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes Madam; but too painfull</L>
<L>And violent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="26"/>
<SPEAKER>CLE.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well leave them both with me.
<STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Glaucus.</STAGE></L>
<L>Let none adventure on prosperity</L>
<L>But with a spirit still prepar'd to die.</L>
<L>Let them keep certain death still in their power</L>
<L>That dare be great and happy, nought but that</L>
<L>Frees states when they are fall'n. Well did wise</L>
<L>And liberall Nature on mankinde bestow</L>
<L>A gift so soveraigne as power to die,</L>
<L>An Antidote 'gainst Fortunes cruelty,</L>
<L>That is the deere preservative, that must</L>
<L>Controll the spite of Fortune, and redeem</L>
<L>A wofull life from lothed servitude.</L>
<L>One venome's gentle; tother rough and cruell.</L>
<L>But tis not safe to trust mine honour so,</L>
<L>On doubtfull props: the poysons both may fail▪</L>
<L>Or differ farre from what vain fame reports</L>
<L>Their operation. Tis experience</L>
<L>That must confirme me. <HI>Mardio</HI> is return'd.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Mardio <HI>with two prisoners.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here are two men, Madam, condemn'd for murder</L>
<L>To cruell death, and are to die to morrow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLE.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come neerer both, and tell me, dare you die?
<STAGE>Dio.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 PRI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Great Queen, necessities strict law imposes
<STAGE>Plutarch.</STAGE></L>
<L>That doom upon us; in forc'd actions</L>
<L>Courage can have no triall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLE.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dare you die</L>
<L>A lesse dishonorable way, to scape</L>
<L>The common hangman's hand, and from a Queen</L>
<L>Receive your death, and that an easier death?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="26"/>
<SPEAKER>BOTH.</SPEAKER>
<P>Most willingly, great Queen; we are prepar'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLE.</SPEAKER>
<L>Give them their lots, <HI>Mardio</HI>; the shortest lot</L>
<L>Is to die first.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 PRI.</SPEAKER>
<P>That lot is mine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLE.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Aspe shall be thy fate: now Aspe confirme</L>
<L>What fame reports of thee; stay thou thy draught</L>
<L>Till he be dead: feel'st thou no pain?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 PRI.</SPEAKER>
<P>A faintnesse seizes me, and I would sleep.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAR.</SPEAKER>
<L>How gently he lies down? and scarcely strives</L>
<L>Against his death at all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLE.</SPEAKER>
<L>I think he's dead</L>
<L>Already. Sure he feels but little pain.</L>
<L>I am confirm'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAR.</SPEAKER>
<P>He's dead and stiffe already.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLE.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee'll try no more, as for thy draught of poyson</L>
<L>Thus we discharge thee of it, and from death</L>
<L>Doom'd by the law our royall pardon frees thee.</L>
<L>Publish it <HI>Mardio.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PRI.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Gods preserve</L>
<L>Royall and gracious <HI>Cleoptrae's</HI> life.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLE.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am resolvd'; nought but the Libyan Aspe</L>
<L>Shall be renown'd for <HI>Cleopatraes</HI> death.</L>
<L>Thou precious worme, that canst redeem alone</L>
<L>The losse of honour at a rate so easie,</L>
<L>That kill'st as gently as the hand of age,</L>
<L><PB REF="27"/>And art miscall'd a plague of Africa,</L>
<L>Since thou alone mak'st barren Afrike envy'd,</L>
<L>By other lands, though fruitfull, wanting thee.</L>
<L>Who crosse the Seas, and hence at highest price</L>
<L>Transporr the Aspe as choisest Merchandise.</L>
<L>On thee I trust, one gentle touch of thine</L>
<L>Can free this life from lothed servitude,</L>
<L>From <HI>Caesar's</HI> triumph, the base peoples mocks,</L>
<L>Proud <HI>Liviaes</HI> scorn, and mad <HI>Octaviaes</HI> spight.</L>
<L>But why are all my thoughts turn'd to despair?</L>
<L>Why think I now of death? me thinks my <HI>Genius</HI></L>
<L>Checks this cold fear, and Fortune chiding tels me</L>
<L>I am ungratefull to distrust, her now.</L>
<L>My race of life and glory is not run,</L>
<L>Nor <HI>Cle<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>patraes</HI> fortunes yet arriv'd</L>
<L>At that great height that must eternize her,</L>
<L>And fix her glorious name aboue the stars.</L>
<L>I long to hear what answer <HI>Caesar</HI> sends.</L>
<L>I do not know his temper, but he's young;</L>
<L>And why should I desp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ir? are <HI>Cupid's</HI> fires</L>
<L>Extinguish'd quite? are all his arrows spent?</L>
<L>Or is this beauty, that can boast the conquest</L>
<L>Of <HI>Julius Caesar</HI>; and great <HI>Antony,</HI></L>
<L>So waned now, it cannot move the temper</L>
<L>Of one, whom youth makes fit for <HI>Cupid's</HI> conquest?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> EUPHRONLUS, THYREUS.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>EUP.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, your gifts were more graciously receiv'd,</L>
<L>And <HI>Caesar</HI> with a smiling brow return'd</L>
<L>All seeming love and friendship; he has sent</L>
<L>His free'dman <HI>Thyreus</HI> to attend your highnesse,</L>
<L>And to impart his counsels to your ea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="27"/>
<SPEAKER>CLE.</SPEAKER>
<P>He's welcome to us. What's great <HI>Caesar's</HI> will.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Euphro.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>THY.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Caesar's</HI> best wishes, royall <HI>Cleopatra,</HI></L>
<L>None but your fairest self can ratifie.</L>
<L>No power on earth can give what <HI>Caesar</HI> wants</L>
<L>But you, great Queen. For let your Majesty</L>
<L>Give credit to poor <HI>Thyreus</HI> though the meanest</L>
<L>Of all the servants that attend on <HI>Caesar,</HI></L>
<L>Ther's none about him is more neer in trust</L>
<L>To whom he's pleased to impart his thoughts▪</L>
<L>And secret wishes: nothing but your love</L>
<L>Can crown his happinesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLE.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are no subject</L>
<L>For <HI>Caesar's</HI> mocks though in our worst of fortune</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>THY.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are the Queen of Fortune, and still ho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></L>
<L>A lasting Scepter ore that fickle Goddesse</L>
<L>(Fickle to others, to you true and constant)</L>
<L>Your radiant light lends that blinde Goddesse eyes▪</L>
<L>And guides her to your service, making all</L>
<L>Actions, nay losses steps to greater honour.</L>
<L>The late defeat at Actium, which your errour</L>
<L>Perchance miscals a losse, was Fortunes labour</L>
<L>To make you greater, and remove your brightnesse</L>
<L>Which was ill plac'd (as Diamonds coursly set)</L>
<L>From old <HI>Antonius</HI> to yong <HI>Caesar's</HI> love,</L>
<L>A fitter sphere for those fair eys to shine in.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLE.</SPEAKER>
<L>Without these courtings, <HI>Thyreus,</HI> if great <HI>Caesar</HI></L>
<L>Please to embrace our friendship, we and Aegypt</L>
<L>Shall do him faithfull service.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>THY.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mighty Queen,</L>
<L><PB REF="28"/>If my rude speech have err'd, I humbly beg</L>
<L>That you would please to think it zeal in me</L>
<L>To do my master service, and such service</L>
<L>As he esteems the best, to gain your love,</L>
<L>I oft have heard him (let your Majesty</L>
<L>Not be offended with that truth I utter)</L>
<L>Ravish'd with fame of your perfections,</L>
<L>And noble spirit; call <HI>Antonius</HI> happy,</L>
<L>Whom fortune brought to Aegypt, to behold</L>
<L>That Queen, whom he so much desir'd to see.</L>
<L>But when his ey<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> beheld your portraiture</L>
<L>Drawn by a skilfull, and a faithfull hand;</L>
<L>He oft would say it was a likely seat</L>
<L>To hold those Graces. Such perfections</L>
<L>Were fit for none but <HI>Caesar's</HI> to admire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLE.</SPEAKER>
<L>There was a <HI>Caesar,</HI> lov'd me once; but I</L>
<L>Am not so proud to think it was my merit,</L>
<L>Though he would say I did deserve farre more</L>
<L>Then he could utter, that great <HI>Julius,</HI></L>
<L>Whose name and actions fill'd the triple world.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>THY.</SPEAKER>
<L>Though all in him were great, yet nothing greater</L>
<L>Then his adopting so divine an heire.</L>
<L>This <HI>Caesar,</HI> Madam, for your dearest love,</L>
<L>Besides that power and greatnesse, which the world</L>
<L>Both knows and fears, brings such a youth and beautie</L>
<L>To plead for him, as in a mean estate</L>
<L>Might move a Princesse love: which that your eys</L>
<L>may better read, I here from him present</L>
<L>His true, and most unflatter'd portrairure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLE.</SPEAKER>
<L>The fairest form that ere these eys beheld.</L>
<L>Where all the best of each best modell meets,</L>
<L><HI>Cupid's</HI> sweet smiles, lodg'd in the eye of <HI>Mars,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Ga<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ymed's</HI> che<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>k th' Imperiall brow of <HI>Jove</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="28"/>Where love and majesty are proud to dwell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>THY.</SPEAKER>
<P>His age, great Queen, is yet not thirty yeers.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLE.</SPEAKER>
<L>I nere till now saw beautie: but <HI>Thyreus</HI></L>
<L>May we repose a confidence in thee</L>
<L>As our true friend? we will deserve thy love.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>THY.</SPEAKER>
<L>To do divinest <HI>Cleopatra</HI> service</L>
<L>Is all poor <HI>Thyreus</HI> pride: in serving you</L>
<L>I best discharge my dutie to my master.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLE.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then briefly thus; because I would not have</L>
<L>Any take notice of long privacie</L>
<L>Twixt thee and me, and instantly w'expect</L>
<L><HI>Antonius</HI> here, I will devise some means</L>
<L>How to deserve great <HI>Caesar's</HI> love, and act</L>
<L>What he shall thank us for: mean while stay here</L>
<L>With us, good <HI>Thyreus,</HI> for we cannot yet</L>
<L>Dispatch thee with that message we entend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>THY.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will attend your highnesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLE.</SPEAKER>
<L>Till anone</L>
<L>Farewell, good <HI>Thyreus</HI>: but be neer about us.</L>
<STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Thyreus▪</STAGE>
<L>What more then this could all the fates contrive?</L>
<L>What more then <HI>Caesars</HI> love could I have wish'd</L>
<L>On which all power, all state, and Glories wait.</L>
<L>But oh the weak and fluctuating state</L>
<L>Of humane frailty still too much deprest</L>
<L>Or rais'd too much 'twixt fears and flattring hopes!</L>
<L>But hence base fear; a Princely confidence</L>
<L>Fits <HI>Cleopatraes</HI> minde and beautie better.</L>
<STAGE><PB REF="29"/><HI>Enter</HI> ANTONIUS, CANIDIUS, LUCIIIUS, ARISTOCRATES.</STAGE>
<L>My dearest Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AN.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ah sweetest <HI>Cleopatra,</HI></L>
<L>In this embrace, and this Ambrosiake kisse</L>
<L>I am again possest of all my wealth,</L>
<L>Of all my fortunes. Had the angry Gods</L>
<L>Purpos'd to wreak their fury fully on me</L>
<L>They had not left my life so sweet a comfort.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLE.</SPEAKER>
<L>Possest of you I stand above the reach</L>
<L>Of Fortunes threatning, or proud <HI>Caesar's</HI> power.</L>
<L>Nought but your grief, and melancholly had</L>
<L>Power to deject my spirits.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AN.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy true worth</L>
<L>Deserves a happier friend, that could bestow</L>
<L>Not take alone his happinesse from thee.</L>
<L>In thy sweet love, and these my faithfull friends</L>
<L>I still am happy, I have lost no friends.</L>
<L>All that are gone from me to <HI>Caesar's</HI> side,</L>
<L>Ingratefull <HI>Titius</HI> and <HI>Domitius.</HI></L>
<L><HI>Plancus, Silanus, Dellius</HI> and <HI>Hipparchus,</HI></L>
<L>Were Fortunes friends not mine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLE.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let's in and feas<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>▪</L>
<L>This day we'll dedicate to mirth and freedome:</L>
<L>To crown your welcome hither.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AN.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweetly spoken.</L>
<L>Let not a woman teach us souldier<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>To be magnanimous.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="29"/>
<SPEAKER>CLE.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thi? feast we'll stile</L>
<L>The feast of fellow-dyers: for no band
<STAGE>Plutarch.</STAGE></L>
<L>No tie of friendship is so firme as that</L>
<L>They live in love that mean to die together.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>CaeSAR, AGRIPPA, TITIUS, PLANCUS, ARIUS.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cae.</SPEAKER>
<L>Grave <HI>Arius,</HI> in thy troubled looks I read</L>
<L>Fear for thy native Alexandria;</L>
<L>But banish fear, and know thy power with <HI>Caesar,</HI></L>
<L>If they obey our summons, none shall die.</L>
<L>But though to th' utmost they resist, thy will</L>
<L>Shall rule our Justice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Humble <HI>Arius.</HI></L>
<L>Is too much honour'd in great <HI>Caesar's</HI> favour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cae.</SPEAKER>
<L>We give but what we owe, a debt so great</L>
<L>As mine to thee can nere be overpay'd.</L>
<L>Great <HI>Alexander,</HI> whose victorious hand</L>
<L>Founded that City, whose eterniz'd name</L>
<L>For ever honours it, though in great deeds</L>
<L>He past our glory farre, shall not exceed</L>
<L><HI>Caesar</HI> in piety: he oft would say</L>
<L>He ought a better being to his Master</L>
<L>Then to father; one meer naturall,</L>
<L>The other mentall, and diviner farre.</L>
<L>Who's that?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="30"/><HI>Enter</HI> EPAPHRODITUS <HI>with</HI> FERGUS.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>EPA.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Fergusiu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> the Philosopher</L>
<L>Condemn'd to death by you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cae.</SPEAKER>
<P>Dispatch him then.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>EPA.</SPEAKER>
<P>He craves a word with <HI>Arius</HI> ere he die.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ARI.</SPEAKER>
<P>What is it brother?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FER.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ah good <HI>Arius,</HI>
<STAGE>Plutarch.</STAGE></L>
<L>Wisemen, if truly wise, save wise men still.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ARI.</SPEAKER>
<P>Most mighty <HI>Caesar.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cae.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Arius,</HI> no more,</L>
<L>I know what thou desir'st; <HI>Fergusius</HI> live;</L>
<L>That thou know'st him has sav'd thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FER.</SPEAKER>
<L>Victorie,</L>
<L>And fame still wait on <HI>Caesar.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cae.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let's away</L>
<L>And march with speed to Alexandria.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AGR.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Caesar,</HI> your horse are weary: 'tis not fit</L>
<L>Too much to toil them, for I fear a sally</L>
<L>From Alexandria.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cae.</SPEAKER>
<P>They dare not man.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AGR.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Antonius</HI> is strong in well-provided</L>
<L>And skilfull horsemen; and despair of favor</L>
<L><PB REF="30"/>(Since twice you have refus'd his propositions)</L>
<L>Will put another valour into him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cae.</SPEAKER>
<P>What conquest can <HI>Antonius</HI> hope for here?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AGR.</SPEAKER>
<L>His hopes (as nere as I conjecture them)</L>
<L>Are to break through your troops, and get to Sea.</L>
<L>For yet he has a Fl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>et, that may transport him</L>
<L>To other lands, to gather new supplyes.</L>
<L>But any fortune would prove higher farre</L>
<L>To him, then staying here, without all hope</L>
<L>To be shut up in a besieged town.</L>
<L>In my opinion let your march be <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>▪</L>
<L>And gentle; that the horse may be refresh'd.</L>
<L>And we prevent the worst.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cae.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let it be so.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> LUCILIUS, ARISTOCRATES.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LU.</SPEAKER>
<L>How formlesse is the forme of man the soul,</L>
<L>How various still how different from it self?</L>
<L>How falsly call'd Queen of this little world?</L>
<L>When she's a slave, and subject not alone</L>
<L>Unto the bodies temperature, but all</L>
<L>The storms of Fortune.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ARI.</SPEAKER>
<L>What occasion</L>
<L>Make thee thus offer at Philosophy?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LU.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where hast thou liv'd thou shouldst not know th' occa∣sion?</L>
<L>The fits and changes of <HI>Antonius</HI></L>
<L>Are theam enough: how strange a loving soule</L>
<L>Is the late hater of mankinde become!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="31"/>
<SPEAKER>ARI.</SPEAKER>
<L>That is not strange, he's out of breath with cursing</L>
<L>And now 'tis time to stop his mouth with kissing.</L>
<L>But what can he conceive of this same <HI>Thyreus</HI></L>
<L>That holds such secret conference with her?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LU.</SPEAKER>
<P>He cannot choose but see it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ARI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Unlesse love</L>
<L>Have blinded him, she carries it so plainly.</L>
<L>Well, I shall think if there be knavery in't,</L>
<L>(As knavery there must be) that <HI>Cleopatra</HI></L>
<L>Is not so subtle as we took her for.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LU.</SPEAKER>
<L>He must be told it, if he will not see</L>
<L>Upon my life there is some plot of treason</L>
<L>Which yet may be discover'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ARI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heer they come</L>
<L>Let us go fetch <HI>Antonius</HI> if we can.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>CLEOPATRA, THYREUS.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLE.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pelusium shall be rendred up to <HI>Caesar</HI>
<STAGE>Dio. Plutarch.</STAGE></L>
<L>By our command to our Lievtenant there</L>
<L><HI>Seleucus,</HI> whose obedience we not doubt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>THY.</SPEAKER>
<L>Noblest of Queens, you make Imperiall <HI>Caesar</HI></L>
<L>As much a debtor to your courtesie</L>
<L>As he's already captive to your beauty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLE.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor do we wrong <HI>Antonius</HI> at all</L>
<L>In giving up a town which is our own▪</L>
<L>It may be thought tis done to weaken him▪</L>
<L><PB REF="31"/>Alas, <HI>Antonius</HI> is already fall'n</L>
<L>So low, that nothing can redeem him now</L>
<L>Nor make him able to contest with <HI>Caesar.</HI></L>
<L>He has not only lost his armies strength</L>
<L>But lost the strength of his own soul, and is not</L>
<L>That <HI>Antony</HI> he was when first I knew him.</L>
<L>I can do <HI>Caesar</HI> now no greater service.</L>
<L>Though I shall never want a hear<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> to do it.</L>
<L>But we shall quickly see th' event of things;</L>
<L><HI>Antonius</HI> now is desperate, and puts</L>
<L>His hopes upon the fortune of one sally,</L>
<L>Which will be suddenly perform'd, before</L>
<L>That thou canst bear a message back to <HI>Caesar.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>ANTONIUS, LUCILIUS, ARISTO∣CRATES.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AN.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hands on that <HI>Thyreus</HI> there, to prison with him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>THY.</SPEAKER>
<P>To prison!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANT.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes; away with him I say.
<STAGE>Plutarch.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>THY.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Caesar</HI> would not have us'd your messenger</L>
<L>So ill.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AN.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou wert no Messenger to me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLE.</SPEAKER>
<P>For my sake dearest Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AN.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh for your sake?</L>
<L>I cry you mercy Lady, bear him hence.
<STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Thyreu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</STAGE></L>
<L>I had forgot that <HI>Thyreus</HI> was your servant.</L>
<L>But what strange act should he perform for you?</L>
<L><PB REF="32"/>Is it to help you to a happier friend?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLE.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can you suspect it? was my truest love</L>
<L>So ill bestow'd? Can he, for whose dear sake</L>
<L>A Queen so highly born as I preferr'd</L>
<L>Love before fame, and fondly did neglect</L>
<L>All names of honour when false <HI>Fulvia,</HI></L>
<L>And proud <HI>Octavia</HI> had the name of wives,
<STAGE>Plutarch.</STAGE></L>
<L>Requite me thus? ungratefull <HI>Anthony</HI>;</L>
<L>For now the fury of a wronged love</L>
<L>Justly provokes my speech.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANT.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh <HI>Cleopatra,</HI></L>
<L>It is not <HI>Thyreus</HI> but this heart of mine</L>
<L>That suffers now, deep wounded with the thought</L>
<L>Of thy unconstancie: did Fortune leave</L>
<L>One only comfort to my wretched state</L>
<L>And that a false one? for what conference</L>
<L>Couldst thou so oft, and in such privacie</L>
<L>With <HI>Caesar's</HI> servant hold, if true to me?</L>
<L>Which with the rack I could enforce from him.</L>
<L>But that I scorn to do.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLE.</SPEAKER>
<L>You do not scorn</L>
<L>To wrong with base unworthy jealousies</L>
<L>A faithfull heart: but if you think me false</L>
<L>Heer sheath your sword: make me the subject rather</L>
<L>Of manly rage then childish jealousie.</L>
<L>It is a nobler crime, and fitter farre</L>
<L>For you to act, easier for me to suffer.</L>
<L>For live suspected I nor can nor will.</L>
<L>The lovely Aspe, which I with care have kept▪</L>
<L>And was intended a preservative</L>
<L>'Gainst <HI>Caesar's</HI> crueltie, I now must use</L>
<L>Against <HI>Antonius</HI> basenesse a worse fo</L>
<L><PB REF="32"/>Then <HI>Caesur</HI> is: farewell, till death approve</L>
<L>That I was true, and you unjust in love.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANT.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay <HI>Cleopatra,</HI> dearest Love, forgive me</L>
<L>Let not so small a winde have power to shake</L>
<L>A love so grown as ours: I did not think</L>
<L>That thou wert false: my heart gave no consent</L>
<L>To what my tongue so rashly uttered.</L>
<L>Nor could I have out-liv'd so sad a thought.</L>
<L>Let <HI>Thyreus</HI> be releast, and sent to <HI>Caesar.</HI></L>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> CANIDI<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>S.</STAGE>
<L>Now is the time to sally forth, my Lord,</L>
<L>The fo is tir'd with marching, and your horse</L>
<L>Are readie all, and wait the signall only.</L>
<L>The least delay loses the action.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANT.</SPEAKER>
<L>I come <HI>Canidius</HI>; dearest Love farewell.</L>
<L>Few houres will tell thee what <HI>Antonius</HI> is.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLE.</SPEAKER>
<L>How timorous is guilt? how are my thoughts</L>
<L>Distracted sadly now? on every side</L>
<L>My dangers grow: for should <HI>Antonius</HI></L>
<L>Return in safety home, and know what past</L>
<L>'Twixt me and <HI>Thyreus,</HI> I have lost his heart,</L>
<L>And cannot choose but fear him: if he die</L>
<L>I am not confident of <HI>Caesar's</HI> love.</L>
<L>'Twas but a servants tongue I built upon.</L>
<L>'Tis best to make all sure: within there, <HI>Ei<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>a.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>EIRA.</SPEAKER>
<P>Madam!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLE.</SPEAKER>
<P>Are all things readie in the tombe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="33"/>
<SPEAKER>EI.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, Madam; <HI>Carmi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'s</HI> there and <HI>Mar<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>io.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLE.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then thither will I go, if fate contrive</L>
<L>A future state of happinesse for me,</L>
<L>It is my castle: if my death they doom,</L>
<L>I am possest already of a tombe.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="5" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus Quintus.</HEAD>
<STAGE>ANTONIUS, LUCILIUS, ARISTOCRATES.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AN.</SPEAKER>
<L>DEfeated are my troops, my fleet revolted,</L>
<L>The Seas and Lands are lost; and nothing now</L>
<L>Is left <HI>Antonius</HI> but a Roman hand,</L>
<L>A sword and heart to die. You truest servants,</L>
<L>Whose faith and manly constancie upbraids</L>
<L>This wicked age, and shall instruct the next,</L>
<L>Take from a wretched hand this legacie.</L>
<L>Fortune has made my will, and nought but this</L>
<L>Can I bequeath you. Carry it to <HI>Caesar</HI>;</L>
<L>If he be noble, it contains enough</L>
<L>To make you happier then <HI>Antonius</HI> can.</L>
<L><PB REF="33"/>My glasse of life and Empire now is run,</L>
<L>And from this hand expects a period.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LU.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord, take fairer hopes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AN.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fie, fie, <HI>Lucilius</HI>;</L>
<L>Lose not thy former merits in perswading</L>
<L>A man, whom once thou lov'dst to such a shame</L>
<L>As to preferre a loath'd captivity</L>
<L>Before a noble death.</L>
<L>Thy looks speak grief
<STAGE>Dio.</STAGE></L>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> EROS.</STAGE>
<L>Speak <HI>Eros,</HI> wher's the Queen?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ERO.</SPEAKER>
<L>She's dead my Lord.
<STAGE>Plutarch.</STAGE></L>
<L>When those unhappy tydings came to her</L>
<L>Of your defeat, she straight shut up her self</L>
<L>Within her tombe, and dy'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AN.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh <HI>Cleopatra,</HI></L>
<L>Why have I lingred thus, that thou a woman</L>
<L>Should'st teach so old a souldier how to die?</L>
<L>Fortune, I blame not thee; I have enjoy'd</L>
<L>What thou could'st give, and on the envy'd top</L>
<L>Of thy proud wheel have long unshaken stood.</L>
<L>Whom Kings have serv'd, and Rome her self obey'd;</L>
<L>Whom all the Zones of earths diffused Globe,</L>
<L>That know inhabitants, have known, and fear'd.</L>
<L>Nor is my fall so much degenerate.</L>
<L>My strength no arms but Roman arms subdue, <HI>Plutarch.</HI></L>
<L>And none, but Monarch of the world succeeds.</L>
<L>Glutted with life and Empire now I go</L>
<L>Free and undaunted to the shades below.</L>
<L>Here <HI>Eros,</HI> take this sword, perform the promise</L>
<L>Which thou hast made, to kill me whensoere</L>
<L><PB REF="34"/>I should command: make no reply in words.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will be true or die. Stand fair; your <HI>Eros</HI></L>
<L>Will be your Usher to th'Elizian fields.
<STAGE>Kils himself.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AN.</SPEAKER>
<L>What hast thou done unfaithfull faithfull <HI>Eros</HI>
<STAGE>Dio. Plutarch.</STAGE></L>
<L>Too kindly cruell, falsly vertuous?</L>
<L>I'll trust no more, to be no more directed</L>
<L>By such examples: but we must be speedie.</L>
<L>The gates ere this time are set ope to <HI>Caesar.</HI></L>
<L>Fair <HI>Cleopatra,</HI> I am comming now</L>
<L>To dwell with thee, and ever to behold</L>
<L>Thy heavenly figure, where nor time nor death</L>
<L>Shall make divorce of our eternall loves.</L>
<L>Thus, thus I come to thee: unfaithfull sword▪</L>
<L>I never knew thee slow in giving death</L>
<L>Till this sad houre, some friendly hand lend aid▪</L>
<L>And with another wound release my soule.</L>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> MARDIO.</STAGE>
<L>Where is my Lord <HI>Antonius?</HI> Oh sad sight</L>
<L>The Queen enclosed in her tombe desir'd</L>
<L>To take her last leave of you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AN.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is she living?</L>
<L>Tis welcome news, convey me quickly, friends,
<STAGE>Plutarc. Dio. Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
<L>Oh quickly thither, that I may expire</L>
<L>That breath that's left in <HI>Cleopatrae's</HI> arms.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="34"/>AGRIPPA, GALLUS, EPAPHRODITUS, PROCULEIUS, <HI>Citizens.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AGR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Go you, <HI>Epaphroditus,</HI> and besiege</L>
<L>The Palace, to surprize <HI>Antonius</HI>;</L>
<L>You <HI>Proculeius,</HI> and <HI>Cornelius Gallus,</HI></L>
<L>Go presently to <HI>Cleopatraes</HI> tombe,</L>
<L>Wo her with all your art and eloquence</L>
<L>With all assurances of <HI>Caesar's</HI> love</L>
<L>To leave that place, and yield her person to him.</L>
<L>Spare no attempts of force or policy</L>
<L>To draw her thence: for you the Citizens</L>
<L>Of Alexandria, cheer your fainting hearts,</L>
<L>I'll mediate in your behalf to <HI>Caesar,</HI></L>
<L>To spare the City.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thanks to the most noble</L>
<L>And good <HI>Agrippa.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AGR.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heer he comes himself.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> CaeSAB, ARIUS, TITIUS, PLANCUS.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cae.</SPEAKER>
<L>The palenesse of your fear declares your guilt.</L>
<L>But that, though nere so great, shall not exceed</L>
<L>Our clemencie, to let you know it was</L>
<L>Your happinesse to be subdu'd by us.</L>
<L>Mercy shall rule our just severitie.</L>
<L>First for your founder <HI>Alexanders</HI> sake,
<STAGE>Plutarch. Dio.</STAGE></L>
<L>Next for the love of reverent <HI>Arius</HI></L>
<L>Our Master heer<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> whose goodnesse far out-weighs</L>
<L><PB REF="35"/>All your offences and rebellions.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIT.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Caesar</HI> in goodnesse, as in greatnesse, bears</L>
<L>Equalitie with <HI>Jove.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> ACHOREUS.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ACHO.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hail mighty <HI>Caesar.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cae.</SPEAKER>
<P>What's he?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ARI.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Achor<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>us, Osiris</HI> Priest,</L>
<L>A good and holy man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cae.</SPEAKER>
<L>We dare believe thee,</L>
<L>And therfore welcom him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ACHO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Please it great <HI>Caesar,</HI></L>
<L>To give <HI>Achoreus</HI> leave to wait on him</L>
<L>Into the ancient Temples of our Gods</L>
<L>To shew th' Aegyptian rites and mysteries,</L>
<L>And all the Deities that we adore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cae.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most willingly <HI>Achoreus,</HI> I would see
<STAGE>Dio.</STAGE></L>
<L>Gods, but not Oxen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TI.</SPEAKER>
<P>He has blank'd the Priest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cae.</SPEAKER>
<L>I fain would see great <HI>Alexander's</HI> herse
<STAGE>Sueton·</STAGE></L>
<L>The mansion once of so divine a soul</L>
<L>A spirit greater then the world it self,</L>
<L>Whom the world fear'd but could not satisfie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ACH.</SPEAKER>
<L>Within the vault of our Pyramides</L>
<L><PB REF="35"/>His bodie yet all whole may <HI>Caesar</HI> see.</L>
<L>And all the bodies of our <HI>Ptolomeys.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cae.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'd see Kings only, not dead carcasses.
<STAGE>Sueton. Dio.</STAGE></L>
<L>But see, <HI>Epaphroditus</HI> is return'd.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> EPAPHRODITUS, LVCILIUS, ARISTOCRATES.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cae.</SPEAKER>
<P>Speak man, where is <HI>Antonius?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>EP.</SPEAKER>
<P>Slain, my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cae.</SPEAKER>
<P>How? slain? what hand durst do it?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>EPA.</SPEAKER>
<P>His own hand.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cae.</SPEAKER>
<L>That was our fear: cruell <HI>Antonius.</HI></L>
<L>Too cruell to thy self, to Rome, and me</L>
<L>How white a day have all the people lost?</L>
<L>How great might <HI>Caesar's</HI> happinesse have been</L>
<L>Had but the fates permitted me to lay</L>
<L>These conquering arms aside, and once again</L>
<L>Embrace thee, dear <HI>Antonius,</HI> as a friend</L>
<L>Thou worthy aider of my infant fortunes,
<STAGE>Plutarch.</STAGE></L>
<L>Thou brave revenger of great <HI>Julius</HI> death,</L>
<L>Witnesse these tears, though I were forc'd to warre</L>
<L>(Whilst thou preferring forreigne love before</L>
<L><HI>Caesar's</HI> alliance, did'st reject my kindred,</L>
<L>And scorn my love) I still could honour thee.</L>
<L>But since too cruell fate denies to me</L>
<L>So great an happinesse as to expresse</L>
<L>This love to thee alive, let thy dear ghost</L>
<L>Behold my Pietie, and see the honours</L>
<L><PB REF="36"/><HI>Caesar</HI> will do to thy sad funerall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LU.</SPEAKER>
<P>Most royall <HI>Caesar</HI>-like dissimulation.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ARI.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hope how ere 'twill serve our turns <HI>Lucilius.</HI></L>
<L>Now is the fittest time.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cae.</SPEAKER>
<P>What men are these?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>EPAP.</SPEAKER>
<L>Two of <HI>Antonius</HI> truest servants, <HI>Caesar,</HI></L>
<L>Who bring a letter from their dying Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cae.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me peruse it well, it shall be granted.</L>
<L>Your lives and fortunes both are safe, and since</L>
<L>We ever lov'd fidelitie, you shall</L>
<L>If so you like, be welcome to our service,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LU.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis our desire; our lives and fortunes ever</L>
<L>Shall do great <HI>Caesar</HI> true and faithfull service</L>
<L>As they before did to <HI>Antonius.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cae.</SPEAKER>
<P>Where did he die?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>EPA.</SPEAKER>
<L>In <HI>Cleopatraes</HI> arms</L>
<L>By her with ropes let up into the tombe,</L>
<L>After his deadly wound.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cae.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is she there still?</L>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> GALLUS.</STAGE>
<L>Now I shall know; speak <HI>Gallus,</HI> what's the news?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GAL.</SPEAKER>
<L>We came and call'd at <HI>Cleopatraes</HI> tombe,
<STAGE>Dio. Plutarch.</STAGE></L>
<L>Who from above made answer, and deny'd</L>
<L><PB REF="36"/>To yield herself, but upon <HI>Caesar's</HI> word.</L>
<L>When I with best persuasions strove to winne her,</L>
<L>And held her talk awhile, whilst <HI>Proculeius</HI></L>
<L>On tother side the tombe espy'd a place</L>
<L>That open stood, by which the Queen receiv'd</L>
<L>Dying <HI>Antonius,</HI> which he scaling enter'd</L>
<L>Behinde the Queen: but had he not been speedy</L>
<L>She there had slain herself: a maid of hers</L>
<L>Spy'd <HI>Proculeius</HI> entring, and aloud</L>
<L>Cry'd out oh Queen thou art surpriz'd alive.</L>
<L>She drawing a short poniard was restrain'd</L>
<L>By <HI>Proculeius,</HI> who both held her hand</L>
<L>And spake her fair; at last obtain'd so much</L>
<L>By strong persuasions of your clemencie</L>
<L>He drew her thence, and got her to the Palace.</L>
<L>Where now she is, and <HI>Proculeius</HI> stays.</L>
<L>But her desire is still to speak with you.</L>
<L>Till when from us she will admit no comfort.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cae.</SPEAKER>
<L>We will in person presently go see her.</L>
<L>Protect me <HI>Pallas</HI> 'gainst false <HI>Venus</HI> charms.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
<STAGE>CLEOPATRA <HI>in mourning.</HI></STAGE>
<L>Known mischiefs have their cure; but doubts have none,</L>
<L>And better is despair then fruitlesse hope</L>
<L>Mixt with a killing fear: my thoughts are now</L>
<L>More black and balefull then this sad attire.</L>
<L>If <HI>Caesar</HI> come, I do not fear his chiding</L>
<L>I have a certain Antidote 'gainst that.</L>
<L>'Tis not his anger, but his love afflicts</L>
<L>My doubting soul, whether that love will prove</L>
<L>Fained or true, yet may straight apppear.</L>
<L><PB REF="37"/>He's not so old, nor I so ignorant</L>
<L>But that his actions, gestures, words, and looks</L>
<L>Will make his heart lie open to my view.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> CaeSAR, <HI>and</HI> EPAPHRO∣DITUS.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cae.</SPEAKER>
<L>How sweet a sorrow dwels upon that brow!</L>
<L>How would she look in smiling dalliance?</L>
<L>Oh pardon me thou powerfull God of love,</L>
<L>That durst presume to tempt thy Deitie.</L>
<L>Forgive my confidence. I now excuse</L>
<L><HI>Antonius</HI> weaknesse, but stay there my heart,</L>
<L>My vertuous <HI>Livia</HI> is more fair then she,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLE.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hail mighty Prince; for that high name the Gods.
<STAGE>Dio. Plutarch.</STAGE></L>
<L>Who reft me of it, have bestow'd on thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cae.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rise <HI>Cleopatra, Caesar's</HI> victory</L>
<L>Takes nought from you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLE.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh let me never rise</L>
<L>Till <HI>Caesar</HI> grant my suit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cae.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good Queen stand up,</L>
<L>And freely speak what you desire:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLE.</SPEAKER>
<L>I beg</L>
<L>A boon but small, which <HI>Caesar</HI> nere deni'd</L>
<L>His greatest enemies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cae.</SPEAKER>
<L>And can you think</L>
<L>I should deny it you? Do but expresse it▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="37"/>
<SPEAKER>CLE.</SPEAKER>
<L>That thou would'st kill me <HI>Caesar</HI>; I have liv'd</L>
<L>These many yeers too long: I should have dy'd
<STAGE>Dio.</STAGE></L>
<L>When that great Worthy, that renowmed <HI>Caesar</HI></L>
<L>Was basely murther'd in Romes Capitoll.</L>
<L>Surviving him was my unhappinesse.</L>
<L>But I have liv'd to see his sonne inherit
<STAGE>Dio.</STAGE></L>
<L>His state and Empire, and controll the world.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cae.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be cheery <HI>Cleopatra,</HI> fear no wrong</L>
<L>At <HI>Caesar's</HI> hands.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLE.</SPEAKER>
<L>Death is no wrong at all.</L>
<L>I have deserv'd it, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cae.</SPEAKER>
<L>But can you think</L>
<L>That we, whose clemencie so many men</L>
<L>And stubborn enemies so oft have prov'd,</L>
<L>Should now at last be cruell to a Queen?</L>
<L>But we must chide you, that so long together</L>
<L>Have sided with <HI>Antonius,</HI> and with him</L>
<L>Conspir'd the wrack of Rome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLE.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's soon excus'd.</L>
<L>If 'twere a crime to love <HI>Antonius</HI>
<STAGE>Dio. Plutarch.</STAGE></L>
<L>(Which I confesse I did, and his large favours</L>
<L>Truly deserv'd it) think it was not mine</L>
<L>But fates own crime, that first allotted me</L>
<L>To his protection: had your share of rule</L>
<L>In Egypt lyen, I had been <HI>Caesars</HI> friend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cae.</SPEAKER>
<L>Besides with men and money you give aid</L>
<L>To <HI>Caius Cassius</HI> in Philippi field</L>
<L>Who murther'd <HI>Caesar</HI> in the Capitoll.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="38"/>
<SPEAKER>CLE.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Caesar,</HI> as false as truth it self is true.</L>
<L>I was accused to <HI>Antonius</HI>
<STAGE>Plutarch. Appian.</STAGE></L>
<L>For that before; but in Cilicia</L>
<L>I quickly cleer'd those causelesse jealousies,</L>
<L>Witnesse thou glorious starre, which the great soule</L>
<L>Of noble <HI>Julius,</HI> when he left the earth,</L>
<L>Added to heaven, how innocent I am</L>
<L>From any fault in that: but <HI>Caesar</HI> know
<STAGE>Dio.</STAGE></L>
<L>Against thy father not the act alone,</L>
<L>But even suspition shall be purg'd with death.</L>
<L>I can no longer live.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cae.</SPEAKER>
<L>What have I done?</L>
<L>I fear my rashnesse has too far betray'd
<STAGE>Dio.</STAGE></L>
<L>My thoughts to <HI>Cleopatra</HI>: gentle Queen</L>
<L>Be comforted; expect at <HI>Caesar's</HI> hand</L>
<L>Nothing but love and friendship: do not wrong</L>
<L>My goodnesse with unjust suspition</L>
<L>All former grievances are quite forgot.</L>
<L>Your port and state shall be maintain'd at full.</L>
<L>Your houshold servants not diminished.</L>
<L><HI>Epaphroditus,</HI> see the Queen attended</L>
<L>As fits her stare and honour; and till next</L>
<L>We visit you, rest with a full assurance</L>
<L>Of our best love and friendship.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLE.</SPEAKER>
<L>All the payment</L>
<L>That my poor fortunes can return to <HI>Caesar</HI></L>
<L>Is thanks and service.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cae.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Epaphroditus.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>EPAP.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Caesar.</HI>
<STAGE><HI>they whisp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r.</HI></STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="38"/>
<SPEAKER>CLE.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes. whisper on; you cannot over-reach</L>
<L>My jealousies: no signes of love at all,
<STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Caesar.</STAGE></L>
<L>No smile, nor amorous glance, I was deceiv'd,</L>
<L>And meerly coosen'd by base <HI>Thyreus.</HI></L>
<L>But I must hide my fears, and cleer this brow</L>
<L>The better to effect my purposes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>EPA.</SPEAKER>
<P>How fares your Majesty?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLE.</SPEAKER>
<L>Never so well</L>
<L>As now I am, I did not think great <HI>Caesar</HI></L>
<L>Had been so full of love and courtesie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>EPA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh Madam, <HI>Caesar's</HI> th' unexampled mirrour</L>
<L>Of royaltie, and does as far exceed</L>
<L>All petie Kings in goodnesse as in power.</L>
<L>And if my humblest services in ought</L>
<L>May give content to royall <HI>Cleopatra</HI></L>
<L>I shall be proud to be commanded still.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLE.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thanks good <HI>Epaphroditus.</HI></L>
<L>That love is true that's shew'd in mis<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ry.</L>
<L>But what have I forgot? I had a note</L>
<L>Of some particulars I meant to give</L>
<L>To <HI>Caesar's</HI> hand and quite forgot it here.</L>
<L>Nor would I trust the cariage of a thing</L>
<L>Of so great consequence to every hand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>EPA.</SPEAKER>
<P>Will you command my service?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLE.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall rest</L>
<L>Indebted to your love; <HI>Caesar</HI> will thank you.</L>
<L>It much concerns both his estate and mine.
<STAGE>Dio.</STAGE></L>
<L><PB REF="39"/>Be speedy good <HI>Epaphroditus,</HI> for</L>
<L>I long to heare his answer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>EPA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fear not Madam.</L>
<L>A quick performance, it rejoyces me</L>
<L>To see her look so cheerily again.
<STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Epa.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLE.</SPEAKER>
<L>So now my trouble is remov'd, I come,</L>
<L>I come my dearest Lord <HI>Antonius,</HI></L>
<L>Never till now thy true and faithfull love.</L>
<L>My much abused Lord, do not disdain</L>
<L>Or blush t'acknowlege <HI>Cleopatra's</HI> name</L>
<L>When tears and bloud have wash'd her spotted soul▪</L>
<L>Wert thou alive again, not all the world</L>
<L>Should shake my constancie, or make divorce</L>
<L>Twixt thee and mee: but since too late, alas,</L>
<L>My tears of sorrow come, I'll follow thee,</L>
<L>And beg thy pardon in the other world.</L>
<L>All crimes are there for evermore forgot.</L>
<L>There <HI>Ariadne</HI> pardons <HI>Theseus</HI> falshood.</L>
<L><HI>Dido</HI> forgives the perjur'd Prince of Troy,</L>
<L>And <HI>Troilus</HI> repentant <HI>Cressida.</HI></L>
<L>Though false to thee alive, I now am come</L>
<L>A faithfull lover of thy dust and combe.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> AGRIPPA, GALLUS, <HI>and two</HI> Psyls.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GAL.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Marcus Agrippa,</HI> I have here provided</L>
<L>As <HI>Caesar</HI> gave in charge two Libyan <HI>Psyls.</HI></L>
<L>All Afrik yields not fitter for his purpose.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AGRI.</SPEAKER>
<P>They look like likely ones.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="39"/>
<SPEAKER>GAL.</SPEAKER>
<L>They have been prov'd,</L>
<L>And have already on my souldiers,</L>
<L>When they were bit by Serpents, done strange cures,</L>
<L>Past all belief or hope, recall'd fled life</L>
<L>Back to his mansion, and beyond the power</L>
<L>Of <HI>Aesculapius</HI> have suck'd and charm'd</L>
<L>The mortall venome from their dying limbs.</L>
<L>These two, <HI>Agrippa</HI> in their infancy</L>
<L>Their doubting sires to try their lawfull births
<STAGE>Plinius. Solinus. Lucanus.</STAGE></L>
<L>(As Eagles try their Eaglets 'gainst the Sun)</L>
<L>Expos'd to mortall Serpents, and were so</L>
<L>Confirm'd in what they sought, the trembling Snakes</L>
<L>Durst not assault the Infants.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> CaeSAR.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AG.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here he comes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cae.</SPEAKER>
<P>Are those the men?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GAL.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, <HI>Caesar.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cae.</SPEAKER>
<L>Carry them</L>
<L>To <HI>Cleopatraes</HI> Palace; let them wa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></L>
<L>Neer to <HI>Epaphroditus.</HI> What's the news?</L>
<L>How fares the Queen?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>EPA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Never more cheery Sir.</L>
<L>Her looks expresse her hopes; nor in her words</L>
<L>Can she conceal her inward cheerfulnesse.</L>
<L>But one thing, Sir, she sai'd she had forgot,</L>
<L>Which neerly did concern both you and her;</L>
<L>And that in such a cause she durst not trust</L>
<L>A common messenger, requesting me</L>
<L>To give it to your hands.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="40"/>
<SPEAKER>Cae.</SPEAKER>
<L>She has deceiv'd thee,</L>
<L>And all of us; the worst that I could fear</L>
<L>Is come to passe: oh run <HI>Epaphroditus,</HI></L>
<L>I'll follow thee with all the speed I can.</L>
<L>But all too late, I fear, our speed will come.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> CLEOPATRA <HI>crown'd, attended by</HI> GLAUCUS, MARDIO, EIRA, CHARMIO, <HI>shee takes her state.</HI> ANTHONY's <HI>Herse brought in</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLE.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is my second Coronation day;</L>
<L>But nobler then the first, and fuller farre</L>
<L>Of reall honour, and magnificence.</L>
<L>Nor till this pompous houre was <HI>Cleopatra</HI></L>
<L>A perfect Queen, alas, I did not sway</L>
<L>A Scepter over fortune, or command</L>
<L>As now I do, the destinies themselves.</L>
<L>I wore a painted honour, a meer shadow</L>
<L>Of Royall state, and such a feeble Crown</L>
<L>As warre could threaten, treason undermine,</L>
<L>And every puffe of Fortune blow it off.</L>
<L>My state is constant now, my thoughts above</L>
<L>The fear of dangers or opposing foes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAR.</SPEAKER>
<P>What new addition has she got off state?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GLA.</SPEAKER>
<P>I cannot tell, nor can I guesse her meaning.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLE.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Glaucus</HI> and <HI>Mardio,</HI> leave the room a while.</L>
<STAGE><HI>Exeunt</HI> Glaucus <HI>and</HI> Mardio.</STAGE>
<L>Come hither Girles, I will no longer hide</L>
<L>My joys from you; in such attire as this</L>
<L>I go to meet my dear <HI>Antonius.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="40"/>
<SPEAKER>CHAR.</SPEAKER>
<P>Madam, he's dead.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLE.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas, thou art deceiv'd.</L>
<L>He lives my <HI>Charmio</HI> in the other world,</L>
<L>And stays for me; I have been too too slack</L>
<L>In comming to him: this that here lies dead</L>
<L>Was but the house that lodg'd my dearest Lord,</L>
<L>That earthly Mansion, that did once contain</L>
<L>The kindest, noblest, and the truest soule</L>
<L>That ever liv'd; and this our second meeting</L>
<L>Is farre more sweet, and full of noble love</L>
<L>Then when we first met in Cilicia,</L>
<L>When our magnificence and pomp did fill</L>
<L>The world with wonder and astonishment.</L>
<L>Why weep you girles? is it to see your Mistris</L>
<L>Greater then ere in Glory? if you lov'd me,</L>
<L>You'd weep to see great <HI>Cleopatra</HI> led</L>
<L>A wretched captive through the streets of Rome</L>
<L>Before proud <HI>Caesar's</HI> chariot, mock'd and flowted,</L>
<L>And from a Queen become <HI>Octaviaes</HI> drudge.</L>
<L>No, no, my girles, I will be still my self</L>
<L>And from this seat of state look down in scorn</L>
<L>On Rome, and <HI>Caesar's</HI> threats as things below me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>EI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor heer shall my attendance leave you, Madam,</L>
<L>I'll wait upon you to th'Elisian shades.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CHAR.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nor will poor <HI>Charmi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> be left behinde.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLE.</SPEAKER>
<L>My earthly race is run, and I descend</L>
<L>As great a ghost as <HI>Theban Semele,</HI></L>
<L>When her ambitious love had sought and met</L>
<L>The Thunderers embraces, when no Pile</L>
<L>Of earthly wood, but <HI>Jove's</HI> celestiall fire</L>
<L>Consum'd her beauties reliques, and sent down</L>
<L><PB REF="41"/>Her soul from that Majestick funerall.</L>
<L>Farewell thou fading remnant of my Love.</L>
<L>When I am gone, I'll leave these earthly parts</L>
<L>To keep thee company: never to part,</L>
<L>But dwell together, and dissolve together.</L>
<L>Come Aspe, possesse thy mansion; freely feed</L>
<L>On these two hils, upon whose snowy tops</L>
<L>The winged <HI>Cupid</HI> oft has taken stand,</L>
<L>And shot from thence the proudest hearts on earth.</L>
<L>Corruption now, and rottennesse must seize</L>
<L>This once admired fabrick, and dissolve</L>
<L>This flesh to common elements again▪</L>
<L>When skilfull nature, were she strictly bound</L>
<L>To search through all her store-house would be pos'd</L>
<L>To tell which piece was <HI>Cleopatra</HI> once.</L>
<L>Sweet Aspe, I feel thy▪ touch, and life begins</L>
<L>From these cold limbs to take her gentle flight.</L>
<L>A slumber seizes me; farewell my girles.</L>
<L>Thus let the Romans finde me dead, and know</L>
<L>Maugre the power of Rome, and <HI>Caesar's</HI> spleen</L>
<L>That <HI>Cleopatra</HI> liv'd, and di'd a Queen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CHAR.</SPEAKER>
<L>She's dead, and <HI>Eira</HI> too. I heare a noise.</L>
<L>There is no dallying now; I must bespeedy,</L>
<L>And use the common and sure way to death.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>She stabs her self.</STAGE>
<STAGE><PB REF="41"/><HI>Enter</HI> CaeSAR, AGRIPPA, TITIUS, PLANCUS, GALLUS, EPAPHRODITUS, PROC<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>LEIUS.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cae.</SPEAKER>
<L>We come too late, and all in vain I fea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Our care has been.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>EPA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here lies her servant bleeding,</L>
<L>Not dead: speak <HI>Charmio,</HI> how dy'd the Queen?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CHA<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>A death that well beseem'd her royall birth.
<STAGE><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AGR.</SPEAKER>
<L>See <HI>Caesar,</HI> see; the mark upon her brest,</L>
<L>And here the fatall authour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cae.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twas the Aspe.</L>
<L>Be speedie now, and use your utmost power
<STAGE>Sueton. Dio.</STAGE></L>
<L>You skilfull <HI>Psyls,</HI> call back this royall soul</L>
<L>To her fair seat, and take from <HI>Caesar's</HI> bounty</L>
<L>Above your wish: suck thou the wounded place,</L>
<L>And mutter thou thy strongest charms to fright</L>
<L>Pale death from thence, and you in<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ernall Gods,</L>
<L>If ere to humane prayers you could lend</L>
<L>An exorable eare, 'tis <HI>Caesar</HI> begs,</L>
<L><HI>Caesar,</HI> whose sword has sent to your black shades</L>
<L>A hundred thousand souls, and still has power</L>
<L>T'enlarge your Empire, begs in lieu of all</L>
<L>But restitution of one soul alone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TI.</SPEAKER>
<P>How royally she dy'd?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PLA.</SPEAKER>
<L>No conquer'd Prince.</L>
<L>Did ever finde a nobler way to death.</L>
<L><PB REF="42"/>Had feeble <HI>Perseus</HI> known so brave a course,</L>
<L>He had redeem'd his captive life from shame.</L>
<L>And not depriv'd the Conquerour of fame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cae.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is there no hope?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PSY.</SPEAKER>
<P>She's gone past all recoverie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cae.</SPEAKER>
<L>We will no longer strive 'gainst destiny.</L>
<L>Though thou art dead, yet live renowm'd for ever;</L>
<L>And let this action speak thee to the world</L>
<L>A fo not shaming <HI>Caesar's</HI> victory.</L>
<L>No other Crown or Scepter after thine</L>
<L>Shall Aegypt honour: thou shalt be the last</L>
<L>Of all the raigning race of <HI>Ptolomey</HI>:</L>
<L>And all, and more then what thy letter crav'd</L>
<L>Will <HI>Caesar</HI> grant with dead <HI>Antonius</HI></L>
<L>In richer state then ere proud <HI>Memphis</HI> saw
<STAGE>Sueton. Dio. Plutarch.</STAGE></L>
<L>Her Kings inter'd shall <HI>Cleopatra</HI> lye.</L>
<L>Thy dying figure carv'd in fairest stone</L>
<L>Shall my triumphant chariot wear, for all</L>
<L>To gaze and wonder at thy form and worth.</L>
<L>Aegypt no more a Kingdome, now a Province</L>
<L><HI>Cornelius Gallus,</HI> is thy government.</L>
<L>And here let <HI>Caesar</HI> sheath the civill sword,</L>
<L>Whose fatall edge these twenty years has ripp'd</L>
<L>The bleeding <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ntrails of afflicted Rome.</L>
<L>Heer let our labours end: advance brave friends</L>
<L>Our prosperous Eagles home to Italy,</L>
<L>To reap the fruit of all our wars and toils,</L>
<L>And fill great Rome with conquer'd Aegypts spoils.</L>
</SP>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
<BACK>
<DIV1 TYPE="dramatis personae">
<PB REF="42"/>
<HEAD>The Speakers.</HEAD>
<P><TABLE>
<ROW>
<CELL>Antoniani,</CELL>
<CELL>Aegytii,</CELL>
<CELL>Caesarei.</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL><LIST>
<ITEM>Marcus Antonius.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Marcus Titius.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Munatius Plancus.</ITEM>
<ITEM>C. Canidius Crassus.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Caius</ITEM>
<ITEM>Titius Domitius.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Lucilius.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Aristocrates.</ITEM>
</LIST></CELL>
<CELL><LIST>
<ITEM>Cleopatra,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Eira</ITEM>
<ITEM>Charmio.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Achoreus.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Sossius.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Seleucus.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Glaucus.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Mardio.</ITEM>
</LIST></CELL>
<CELL><LIST>
<ITEM>Caesar Augustus.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Marcus Agrippa</ITEM>
<ITEM>Cornelius Gallus.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Pinnarius Scar∣pus.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Euphroneus.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Proculeius.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Thyreus.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Epaphroditus.</ITEM>
</LIST></CELL>
</ROW>
</TABLE></P>
<P><HI>The Scene AEGYPT.</HI></P>
</DIV1>
</BACK>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

