<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2006-07-17</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Elspeth Healey</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Proofed text and corrected markup.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A07507">
<STC T="S">17892</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99847840</BIBNO>
<VID>12902</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT>
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>THE PHOENIX, AS It hath beene sundry times Acted by the Children of Paules, And presented before his Maiestie.</P>
<P><FIGURE>
</FIGURE></P>
<P>LONDON Printed by <HI>E.A.</HI> for <HI>A,</HI> I, and are to be solde at the signe of the white horse in Paules-Church∣yard. 1607.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="play">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>THE Phoenix:</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter the old Duke of Ferrara, Nobles, Proditor, Lussurioso, and Infesto, with Attendants.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du</SPEAKER>
<L>MY Lordes,</L>
<L>Know that we far from any naturall pride</L>
<L>Or touch of temporall sway, haue seene our face</L>
<L>In our graue counsels foreheads: where doth stand</L>
<L>Our truest glasse, made by Times wrinckled hand.</L>
<L>We know wee're old, my daies proclayme me so:</L>
<L>Fortie-fiue yeres, I'ue gently ruld this Dukedome,</L>
<L>Pray heauen it be no fault,</L>
<L>For there's as much disease, though not to th' eye,</L>
<L>In too much pittie, as in Tyrannie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Infest.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your grace hath spoke it right.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know that life</L>
<L>Has not long course in me, twill not be long</L>
<L>Before I show that Kinges haue mortall bodies</L>
<L><PB REF="3"/>As well as Subjects, therefore to my comfort,</L>
<L>And your succesfull hopes I haue a Sonne</L>
<L>Whome I dare boast of;—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whome we all do boast off,</L>
<L>A Prince elder in vertues then in yeares,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Infest.</SPEAKER>
<L>His iudgement is a Father to his youth,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, I, would he were from Court,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Infest.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our largest hopes grow in him,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>And tis the greatest pittie Noble Lord,</L>
<L>He is vntraueld,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis indeede my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Had he but trauaile to his time and Vertue—oh hee should neere returne agen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>It shall be so, what is in hope begun,</L>
<L>Experience quickens, trauaile confirmes the man,</L>
<L>Who's else liues doubtfull, and his daies oft sorye,</L>
<L>"Who's rich in Knowledge, ha's the stocke of glorye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most true my royall Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Some one attend our Sonne.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Prince attended by Fidelio.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Infest.</SPEAKER>
<L>See, heere hee comes my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh you come well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis alwaies my desire my worthy Father.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Serious studyes, &amp; those fruitfull howres</L>
<L>That grow vp into iudgement, well become</L>
<L>Your birth, and all our loues: I weepe that you are my sonne,</L>
<L>But Vertuously I weepe, the more my gladnes:</L>
<L>We haue thought good and meete by the consent</L>
<L>Of these our Nobles, to moue you toward Trauaile,</L>
<L>The better to approue you to your selfe</L>
<L>And giue your apter power, foundation:</L>
<L>To see affections actually praesented,</L>
<L>Ee'n by those men that owe them, yeeld more profit,</L>
<L>I more content, then singly to reade of them,</L>
<L>"Since loue or feare, make Writers partiall,</L>
<L>The good and free example which you finde,</L>
<L><PB REF="3"/>In other Countries, match it with your owne,</L>
<L>The ill to shame the ill, which will in time,</L>
<L>Fully instruct you how to set in frame,</L>
<L>A kingdome all in peeces.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Honoured Father,</L>
<L>With care and duetie I haue listned to you,</L>
<L>What you desire, in me it is obedience,</L>
<L>I doe obey in all, knowing for right,</L>
<L>"Experience is a Kingdomes better sight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh tis the verie lustre of a Prince,</L>
<L>Trauaile! tis sweete and generous,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>He that knowes how to obey, knowes how to reigne</L>
<L>And that true knowledge haue we found in you,</L>
<L>Make choice of your Attendants.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Theyr soone chose, only this man my Lord, a lo∣uing seruant of mine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>What none but he?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe intreate no more,</L>
<L>For that's the benefit a priuate Gentleman</L>
<L>Enioyes beyond our state, when he notes all,</L>
<L>Himselfe vnnoted,</L>
<L>For should I beare the fashion of a prince,</L>
<L>I should then win more flatterie, then profit,</L>
<L>And I should giue e'm time &amp; warning then</L>
<L>To hide their Actions from me, if I appeare a Sunne,</L>
<L>Theile run into the shade with their ill deedes,</L>
<L>And so preuent me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>A little too wise, a little too wise to liue long.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duk.</SPEAKER>
<L>You haue answered vs with wisdome, let it be.</L>
<L>Things priuate are best known through priuacy.</L>
<STAGE>Exeūt</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Manet Phoenix and Fidelio.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay you my elected seruant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<L>My kinde Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Duke my Father has a heauy burthen,</L>
<L>Of yeares vpon him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord it seemes so, for they make him stoope.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Without dissemblance hee is deepe in age,</L>
<L><PB REF="4"/>He bowes vnto his graue, I wonder much</L>
<L>Which of his wilde Nobilitie it should bee</L>
<L>(For none of his sad counsell has a voyce in't)</L>
<L>Should so farre trauaile into his consent,</L>
<L>To set me ouer into other Kingdomes.</L>
<L>Vpon the stroke and minute of his death?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, tis easier to suspect them all,</L>
<L>Then truly to name one.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Since it is thus,</L>
<L>By absence, ile obey the Duke my father,</L>
<L>And yet not wrong my selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid</SPEAKER>
<L>Therein my Lord,</L>
<L>You might be happie twice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoen.</SPEAKER>
<L>So it shall bee,</L>
<L>Ile stay at home, and trauaile;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would your Grace</L>
<L>Could make that good.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<P>I can, &amp; indeed a Prince need no trauaile farther then his owne Kingdome, if hee applie himselfe fayth∣fullye, worthie the glorie of himselfe and expectation of others: and it would appeare farre nobler industrie in him, to reforme those fashions that are alreadye in his Countrey, then to bring newe ones in, which haue nei∣ther true forme nor fashion; to make his Court an Owle, Cittie an Ape, and the Countrey a Wolfe, prey∣ing vpon the ridiculous pride of eyther, and therefore I holde it a safer sterne vpon this luckie aduantage, since my father is nere his setting, and I vpon the Easterne hil to take my rise, to look into the heart &amp; bowels of this Dukedome, and in disguise, marke all abuses readie for Reformation or Punishment.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Giue me but leaue vnfainedly to admire you,</L>
<L>Your wisdome is so spacious and so honest,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoen.</SPEAKER>
<P>So much haue the complaints and suits of men, seauen, nay seauenteene yeares neglected, stil interposd by coine and great enemies, preuaild with my pittie, that
<PB REF="4"/>
I cannot otherwise thinke but there are infectious dea∣lings in most offices, and foule misteries throughout al Professions: and therefore I nothing doubt but to find trauaile ynough within my selfe, and Experience I fear too much: nor will I be curious to fit my bodie to the humblest forme and bearing, so the labor may be fruit∣full: for how can abuses that keepe lowe, come to the right view of a Prince, vnlesse his lookes lie leuell with them, which else will be longest hid from him, hee shall be the last man sees 'em.</P>
<L>For oft betwene Kings Eyes, and subiects Crimes</L>
<L>Stands there a barre of brybes, the vnder office</L>
<L>Flatters him next aboue it: he the next,</L>
<L>And so of most, or manye, Euerie Abuse will chuse a brother,</L>
<L>Tis through the world, this Hand will rub the other.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<L>You haue set downe the worlde briefly my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoen.</SPEAKER>
<L>But how am I assur'd of faith in thee?</L>
<L>Yet I durst trust thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let my soule be lost,</L>
<P>When it shall loose your secrets: nor will I onely bee a preseruer of them, but if you so please an assister.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoen.</SPEAKER>
<L>It suffices:</L>
<L>That King stands sur'st who by his vertue rises</L>
<L>More then by birth or blood, that Prince is rare,</L>
<L>Who striues in youth to saue his age from care,</L>
<L>Let's be preparde away.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Phoen.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile follow your Grace,</L>
<L>Thou wonder of all Princes, President, and Glorie,</L>
<L>True Phoenix, made of an vnusuall straine,</L>
<L>"Who labours to reforme is fit to raigne.</L>
<L>How can that King be safe that studies not</L>
<L>The profite of his people? See where comes</L>
<L>The best part of my heart, my loue.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Neece.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neece.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, I am bound to find you, I heard newly</L>
<L><PB REF="5"/>Of suddaine Trauaile which his grace intends</L>
<L>And onely but your selfe to accompany him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<L>You heard in that, little beside the truth,</L>
<L>Yet not so suddaine as to want those manners,</L>
<L>To leaue you vnregarded.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neece.</SPEAKER>
<L>I did not thinke, so vnfashionably of you:</L>
<L>How long is your returne?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis not yet come to me, scarce to my Lord,</L>
<L>Vnlesse the Duke referre it to his pleasure,</L>
<L>But long I thinke it is not, the Dukes age,</L>
<L>(If not his apt experience) will forbid it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neec.</SPEAKER>
<L>His grace commaunds, I must not think amisse, farwell</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay stay, and take this comfort,</L>
<L>You shall heare often from vs, ile direct</L>
<L>Where you shall surely knowe, and I desire you</L>
<L>Write me the Truth, how my new father in lawe, the</L>
<L>Captaine beares himselfe toward my Mother,</L>
<L>For that marriage, knew nothing of my minde,</L>
<L>It neuer flourisht in any part of my affection.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neece.</SPEAKER>
<L>Me thinkes sha's much disgrac'd herselfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nothing so: if he be good &amp; wil abide the touch, a Captaine may marrie a Lady, if hee can saile into her good will.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neece.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeede thats all,</L>
<STAGE>Exit</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis al in al, commend me to thy brest, farwel.</L>
<L>So by my Lords firme pollicy we may see,</L>
<L>To present view, what absent formes would be.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit. Fidelo.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter the Captaine with Souldiering fellowes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<L>There's Noble purchase Captaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay admirable purchase.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3</SPEAKER>
<L>Ynough to make vs proud for euer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hah?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<L>Neuer was opportunitie so Gallant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="5"/>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why you make me madde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2</SPEAKER>
<L>Three Ships not a poope lesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3</SPEAKER>
<P>And euerieone so wealthily burdned vpon my manhood.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pox on't, and now am I tyed ee'n as the Deuil would ha't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<P>Captaine, of all men liuing I wold ha' sworne thou wouldst nere haue married.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>S'foot, so would I my selfe man, giue mee my Due, you know I ha sworne all heauen ouer and ouer:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<L>That you haue y faith.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why goe too then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<P>Of a man that has tasted salt water to commit such a fresh Tricke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why tis abhominable I grant you now I see't:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<L>Had there beene fewer Women—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2</SPEAKER>
<L>And among those Women fewer Drabs—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3</SPEAKER>
<L>And among those Drabs fewer pleasing—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then t'ad beene something:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<P>But when there are more women, more common pretty sweete hearts, then euer any age could boast off.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>And I to play the Artificer and marrie: to haue my wife daunce at home, and my Ship at Sea, and both take in salt water together: oh Leiftenant thou'rt hap∣pie, thou keepst a Wench.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<P>I hope I am happyer then so Captaine, for a my Troth shee keepes me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>How? is there anye such fortunate man brea∣thing? and I so miserable to liue honest? I enuie thee Lieutenant, I enuie thee, that thou art such a happye Knaue, heres my hand among you, share it equally, Ile to sea with you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2</SPEAKER>
<L>There spoke a Noble Captaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lets heare from you, there will be newes shortly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<L>Doubt it not Captaine.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>What lustfull passion came aboord of mee, that
<PB REF="6"/>
I should marrye, was I drunke? yet that cannot altoge∣ther holde, for it was foure a clocke 'ith morning, had it beene fiue, I would ha sworne it: that a man is in danger euerie minute to be cast away, without hee haue an ex∣traordinarie Pilot that can performe more then a man can doe: and to say truth too, when 'ime abroad what can I doe at home? no man liuing can reach so farre: &amp; what a horrible thing t'would bee to haue hornes brought me at Sea, to looke as if the Deuill were 'ith ship: and all the greate Tempestes would bee thought of my Raysing, to bee the generall cursse of all Mer∣chants: and yet they likely are as deepe in as my selfe, and thats a comfort: O that a Captaine should liue to be marryed! nay, I that haue beene such a Gallant salt-theefe, should yet liue to be marryed: What a fortu∣nate Elder Brother is he, whose father being a Ramish Plough-man, himselfe a perfumde Gentleman, spen∣ding the labouring reeke from his Fathers: Nosthrils in Tobacco: the sweate of his Fathers bodye in monthlye Phisickc for his pretty quesie Harlot: he sowes a pace 'ith Countrie: the Taylor oretakes him i'th Cittie, so that often times before the Corne comes to Earning, tis vp to the eares in high Collars, and so at euerie haruest the Reapers take paines for the Mercers, ha! why this is stirring happinesse indeede, would my father had held a plow so, and fed vpon squeaz'd Curds and Onions, that I might haue bath'd insensualitie: but hee was too ruttish himselfe to let me thriue vnder him, cansumde me before hee got me, &amp; that makes me so wretched, now to be shackled with a wife, &amp; not greatly rich nei∣ther.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter his Lady.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>Captaine, my Husband.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>S'life call me husband agen, &amp; ile play the Cap∣taine and beate you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="6"/>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<P>What ha's disturb'd you sir, that you now looke so like an Enemie vpon me?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe make a Widdower, hang thy selfe,</L>
<L>How comes it that you are so opposite</L>
<L>To loue and kindenes? I deserue more Respect,</L>
<L>But that you please to be forgetfull of it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>For loue to you, did I neglect my state,</L>
<L>Chide better fortunes from me,</L>
<L>Gaue the world talke, laide all my friendes at waste.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Captaine.</SPEAKER>
<L>The more foole you, could you like none but me?</L>
<L>Could none but I supplye you?</L>
<L>I am sure you were sued to▪ by far worthyer men,</L>
<L>Deeper in wealth and Gentrie.</L>
<L>What couldst thou see in me, to make thee doate so on me,</L>
<P>If I knowe, I am a Villaine: what a torments this? why didst thou marry me? you thinke as most of your insatiate Widdowes, that Captaines can doe wonders, when 'lasse the name do's often proue the better man.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<P>That which you vrge, should rather giue me cause to repent then your selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then to that end I doo't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>What a miserable state am I led into?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Seruus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap:</SPEAKER>
<L>How now sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seruus:</SPEAKER>
<L>Count Proditer is now alighted.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>What, my Lord: I must make much of him, heele one day write me Cuckold: tis good to make much of such a man, ee'n to my face, hee plyes it hard I thanke him:—</P>
<STAGE>Enter Proditer.</STAGE>
<P>what, my worthy Lord!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod:</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile come to you in order Captaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap:</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh thats in order: a kisse is the Gammoth to pricksong.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me salute you Captaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="7"/>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>My deere esteemed Count, I haue a life for you:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heare you the newes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>What may it be my Lord?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord, the Dukes Sonne is vpon his tra∣uaile to seuerall Kingdomes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap,</SPEAKER>
<P>May it bee possible my Lord, and yet so little rumord?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tak't of my Truth, nay, twa's well manag'd, thinges are as they are handled: but all my care is still, pray heauen hee returne safe, without danger Cap∣taine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, is there any doubt to bee had of that my Lord?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>I by my faith Captaine.</L>
<L>Princes haue priuate enemies, and great:</L>
<L>Put case a man should grudge him, for his Vertues:</L>
<L>Or enuie him, for his wisdome: why you know</L>
<L>This makes him lye bare brested to his foe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's ful of certaintie my Lord, but who be his Attendants?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thence Captaine comes the feare, but singlie attended neither (my best gladnes) only by your Sonne in Law <HI>Fidelio.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is it to be beleeu'd? I promise you my Lord then I beginne to feare him my selfe, that fellow will vndoe him: I durst vndertake to corrupt him with twelue pence ouer and aboue, and thats a small matter: ha's a whorish Conscience, hee's an inseperable Knaue, and I could neere speake well of that fellow.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<P>All wee of the younger house, I can tell you do doubt him much,—the Ladyes remoou'd, shall we haue your sweete soscietie Captaine?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Though it bee in mine owne house, I desire I may follow your Lordship.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>I loue to auoide strife,</L>
<L>Not many monthes <HI>Phoenix</HI> shall keepe his life.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="7"/>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>So, his way is in, he knowes it,</L>
<L>We must not be vncurteous to a Lord,</L>
<P>Warne him our house t'were vilde: his presence is an honour, if he lie with our wiues, tis for our credite, wee shall be the better trusted, tis a signe wee shall liue ith world: O Tempests and Whirlewinds (who but that man whom the forefinger cannot daunt, that makes his shame his liuing:) Who but that man I say, could en∣dure to be throughly married? Nothing but a diuorce can relieue me: any way to be rid of her would rid my torment: if all meanes faile Ile kil, or poyson her, and purge my fault at sea: but first Ile make gentle Trie of a Diuorce: But how shal I accuse her subtle honestie? Ile attach this Lords comming to her, take hold of that: ask counsell: and now I remember, I haue acquaintance with an olde craftie Client, who by the puzzle of suites &amp; shifting of Courts, has more tricks &amp; starting holes, then the dizzie pates of fifteene Atturneys: one that has beene muzled in Law like a Beare, and lead by the Ring of his spectacles from office to office: him Ile seeke out with haste, all paths Ile tread,</P>
<L>All deathes Ile die ere I die married.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Proditor with the Captaines wife.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Puh, you doe resist me hardly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lad.</SPEAKER>
<L>I beseech your Lordship cease in this,</L>
<P>Tis neuer to be grāted: if you come as a friend vnto my honour and my husband, you shall be euer welcome, if not, I must intreate it—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why assure your selfe, Madame, tis not the fashion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lad.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis more my griefe my Lord, such as my selfe are iudg'd the worse for such.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith y' are too nice, youle see me kindly forth:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>And honourably welcome.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="8"/><HI>Enter a Groome before Phoenix, and Fidelio, alighting into an Inne.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Groome.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gentlemen, y' are moste neately welcome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y' are very cleanelye Sir, prethee haue a care to our Geldings.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Groome.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Geldings shall be well considered.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Considered?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sirha, what Guesse do's this Inne holde now?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Groome.</SPEAKER>
<L>Some fiue and twentie Gentlemen besides their beastes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Their Beastes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Groome.</SPEAKER>
<P>Their wenches I meane sir, for your worship I nowes those that are vdder men are beastes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>How do's your Mother sit?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Groo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Verie well in health I thanke you heartily sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe .</SPEAKER>
<L>And so is my Mare y faith.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Groome.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile doe her commendations indeede sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well kept vp Shuttle-cocke:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>But what olde fellow was he that newly aligh∣ted before vs?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who he? as arrant a craftie fellow as ere made wa∣ter on horsebacke: some say hee's as good as a Lawyer, (marrie 'ime sure hee's as bad as a Knaue) if you haue a∣ny suites in lawe, hee's the fittest man for your compa∣nie: ha's beene so▪ toward and lug'd himselfe▪ that hee is able to affoo<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="broken" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d you more knauish counsell for tenne groates, then another for ten shillings.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<P>A fine fellowe: but doe you know him to be a Knaue, and will lodge him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Groom.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your worship begins to talke idlely, your bed shall be made presently; if we should not lodge knaues, I wonder how we should bee able to liue honestlye, are there honest men enough thinke you in a Terme time to fill all the Innes in the towne, and as far as I can see▪ a knaues Gelding eats no more hay then an honest mans: nay theeues Gelding eates lesse, ile stād too't, his Maist∣er
<PB REF="8"/>
allowes him a better Ordnarie: yet I haue my eight∣pe<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="broken" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ce day &amp; night, twere more for our profit I wus, you were all theeues, if you were so contented: I shall bee cald for: giue your worships good morrow.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>A royall knaue y faith: wee haue hapned into a Godly Inne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Assure you my L. they belong al to one church.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<P>This shold be some olde busie turbulent fellowe: villanous Law-worme, that eates holes into poore mēs causes.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Tangle with two suters.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<L>May it please your worship to giue me leaue?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tang.</SPEAKER>
<P>I giue you leaue sir, you haue your <HI>Veniam,</HI> now fill me a browne Toste sirha.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Groom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you haue no drink too't sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tang.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is that a question in lawe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Groom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, in the lowest Court: 'ith Sellor sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tang.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me haa't remou'd presently sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Groome.</SPEAKER>
<L>It shall bee done sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now as you were saying Sir, ile come to you immediately too.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh verie wel sir:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tang.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'me a little busie sir,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<L>But as how sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tang.</SPEAKER>
<L>I pray sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha's brought me into the Court, marry my aduer∣sarie ha's not declarde yet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tang.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Non declarauit Aduersarius</HI> saist thou: what a Villain's that, I haue a tricke to doe thee good: I will get thee out a Proxe, &amp; make him declare with a Poxe to him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<L>That wil make him declare to his fore griefe, I thank your good worship: but put case he doe declare?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tang.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Si declarasset,</HI> If he should declare there,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<L>I would be loath to stād out to the iudgement of that Court</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tang.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Non ad iudicium,</HI> doe you feare corruption? then ile releeue you agaen: you shall get a <HI>Supers<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>diae, Non molest andam;</HI> and <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> it big her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="9"/>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<L>Verie good.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now if it should euer come to a <HI>Testificandum,</HI> what be his witnesses?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<L>I little feare his witnesses.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tan.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Non metuis testes?</HI> more valiant man then <HI>Orestes</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<P>Please you sir to dissolue this into Wine, Ale, or Beere, I come a hundred mile to you I protest, and leaue all other counsell behind me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay you shal alwayes finde me a sound Card, I stoode not ath Pillorie for nothing in eightie eight, all the world knowes that: now let me dispatch you sir; I come to you <HI>Presenter.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith the partie hath remou'd both bodie and cause with a <HI>habeas corpus.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Has he that knauerie? But has hee put in baile aboue canst tell?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2</SPEAKER>
<L>That I can assure your worship, he has not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why then thy best course shall be, to lay out more money, take out a <HI>Procedendo,</HI> and bring downe the cause and him with a Vengeance.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2</SPEAKER>
<L>Then he will come indeed</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tan.</SPEAKER>
<P>As for the other partie, let the <HI>Audita querela</HI> alone, take me out a special <HI>Supplicauit,</HI> which will cost you inough, and then you pepper him. For the first partie after the <HI>Procedendo</HI> youle get costs, the cause be∣ing sound, youle haue a Iudgement, <HI>Nunc pro Tunc,</HI> youl get a <HI>Venire facies</HI> to warne your Iurie, a <HI>Decem tales</HI> to fill vp the number, and a <HI>Capias vt Legatum</HI> for your execution.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2</SPEAKER>
<L>I thanke you my learned counsell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<P>What a busie Caterpiller's this? let's accost him in that maner.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Content my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<P>O my olde admirable fellow, how haue I all this while thirsted to salute thee? I knew thee in Octauo of the Duke.—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="9"/>
<SPEAKER>Tang.</SPEAKER>
<L>In Octauo of the Duke: I remember the yere well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe,</SPEAKER>
<L>Bi<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h masse a lustie proper man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tang.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh was I?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>But still in lawe▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Still in Law. I had not breath'd else now, tis verie marrow, verie manna to me to be in law: ide been dead ere this else: I haue found such sweete pleasure in the vexation of others, that I could wish my yeares o∣uer and ouer agen, to see that fellow a Begger, that bawling Knaue a Gentleman: a matter brough<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> 'een to a iudgement to day, as far as ere t'was to begin again to morowe: O <HI>Raptures</HI> I heere a writ of <HI>Demur,</HI> there a <HI>Procedendo,</HI> heere a <HI>Sui surrara,</HI> there a <HI>Capiendo,</HI> Tricks, Delayes▪ Money-lawes:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is it possible olde Lad?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tang.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue beene a Tearme-trotter my selfe anye time this fiue and fortie yeares, a goodly time &amp; a gra∣tious: in which space I ha beene at least sixteen times beggard, and got vp agen: and in the mire agen, that I haue stunke agen, and yet got vp agen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>And so cleane and handsome how?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tan.</SPEAKER>
<P>You see it apparantly▪ I cānot hide it frō you: nay more, in <HI>foelice hora</HI> bee it spoken, you see i'me olde, yet haue I at this present, nine and twentie sutes in Lawe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Deliuer vs man!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tang.</SPEAKER>
<L>And all not worth forthy shillings.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>May it <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> cu'd?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tang.</SPEAKER>
<L>The pleasure of a man is all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>An olde fellow and such a stinger.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tang.</SPEAKER>
<P>A stake puld out of my hedge, theres one: I was well beaten I remember, that's two: I tooke one a bed with my wife agen her will, that's three: I was cal'd cuckold for my labour▪ that's foure: I tooke ano∣ther a bed agen, that's fiue thē one cald me wittal that's sixe: he kild my Dog for Barking, sea<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>en: my Maide Seruant was knockt at that time, eight: my wife miscar∣ryed
<PB REF="10"/>
with a push, Nine, <HI>&amp; sic de coeteris,</HI> I haue so vext and beggerd the whole parish, with processe, Suppoe∣neas, and such like molestations, they are not able to spare so much readie mony from a Tearme, as woulde set vp a new Weather-cocke: the Church-wardens are faine to goe to law with the Poores mony.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fie, fie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tan.</SPEAKER>
<P>And I so fetch vp al the men euery Tearm time that tis impossible to be at ciuill cuckoldry, within our selues, vnlesse the whole country rise vpon our wiues.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<L>A my faith a prettie pollicie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay an excellent stratagem: but of all I most wonder at the continuall substance of thy wit, that ha∣uing had so many suits in law from time to time, thou hast still mony to relieue 'em.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha's the best fortune for that, I neuer knew him without.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why doe you so much wonder at that? why this is my course: my Mare and I come vp some fiue dayes before a Tearme.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoen.</SPEAKER>
<L>A good <HI>Decorum.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here I Lodge as you see amongst Innes, and places of most receit—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Verie wittily.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tan.</SPEAKER>
<P>By which aduantage I diue into Country mens causes, furnish 'em with knauish counsell, little to their profite, buzzing into their Eares, this course, that writ, this office, that <HI>Ʋltimum refugium,</HI> as you know I haue words enow for the purpose.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Enow a conscience y faith.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Enow a law, no matter for conscience. For which busie and laborious sweating curtesie, they can∣not chuse but feede me with mony, by which I main∣taine mine owne suits: ho, ho, ho.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why let me hug thee, Caper in mine armes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Another speciall tricke I haue, no body must
<PB REF="10"/>
know it, which is, to prefer most of those men to one Atturney whom I affect best, to answere which kind∣nesse of mine, he will sweat the better in my cause, and doe them the lesse good, tak't of my worde, I helpt my Atturney to more Clients the last Tearme then he will dispatch all his life time: I did it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoen.</SPEAKER>
<L>What a noble memorable deed was there?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Groome.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Groo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Groo.</SPEAKER>
<P>There's a kind of captaine, verie robustiously enquires for you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tan.</SPEAKER>
<P>For me? a man of warre: a man of law is fit for a man of warre: we haue no leysure to say prayers: wee both kill a Sunday mornings: Ile not be long from your sweete companie.</P>
<STAGE>Exit</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoen.</SPEAKER>
<L>O no I beseech you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<L>What captaine might this be?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou Angell sent amongst vs, sober Law.</L>
<L>Made with meeke Eyes, perswading Action,</L>
<L>No lowd immodest Tongue, voic'd like a virgin,</L>
<L>And as chaste from sale,</L>
<L>Saue onely to be heard, but not to raile.</L>
<L>How has abuse deform'd thee to all Eyes?</L>
<L>That where thy vertues sat, thy vices rise,</L>
<L>Yet why so rashly for one villaines fault▪</L>
<L>Doe I arraigne whole man? Admired Law,</L>
<L>Thy vpper parts must needes be sacred, pure,</L>
<L>And incorruptible, th'are graue and wise,</L>
<L>T'is but the drosse beneath 'em, and the clowdes</L>
<L>That get betweene thy glorie and their praise,</L>
<L>That make the visible and foule Eclipse,</L>
<L>For those that are neere to thee, are vpright,</L>
<L>As noble in their conscience, as their birth,</L>
<L>Know that damnation is in euery bribe,</L>
<L>And rarely put it from 'em: rate the Presenters,</L>
<L>And scourge 'em with fiue yeares imprisonment,</L>
<L><PB REF="11"/>For off ring but to tempt 'em.</L>
<L>Thus is true iustice exercisde and vsde,</L>
<L>"Woe to the giuer when the Bribe's refusde.</L>
<L>Tis not their wil, to haue law worse then warre,</L>
<L>Where still the poor'st die first,</L>
<L>To send a man without a sheete to his graue,</L>
<L>Or burie him in his Papers.</L>
<L>Tis not their minde it should be, nor to haue</L>
<L>A sute hang longer then a man in chaines</L>
<L>Let him be nere so fastned, they least know</L>
<L>That are aboue, the tedious steps below.</L>
<L>I thanke my time, I doe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<L>I long to know what captaine this should be:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phaen.</SPEAKER>
<L>See where the Bane or euery cause Returnes.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Tangle, with Captaine.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<L>S'foote tis the captaine my father in law, my L.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phaen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take heede.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Diuorse shall rest then, and the fiue hun∣dred crownes shall stand in full force and vertue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then doe you wisely Captaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>A way sayle I, fare thee well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tan.</SPEAKER>
<L>A lustie cracke or winde goe with thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>But ah!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hah:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Remember a Scriuener</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile haue him for thee. Why thus am I sought after by all professions; heer's a weather beaten Cap∣taine, who not long since newe married to a Ladie wi∣dow, would now faine haue sued a Diuorce betweene her and him, but that her honestie is his onely hinde∣rance: to be rid of which, he do's determine to turne her into white mony, and there's a Lord his Chapman has bid fiue hundred Crownes for her alreadie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<L>How?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or for his part, or whole in her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phaen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, do she <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="bleedthrough" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>eaue to sell his wife?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="11"/>
<SPEAKER>Tang.</SPEAKER>
<P>His wife? I bith masse, he would sell his soule if he knew what Merchant would lay out money vppon't, and some of 'em haue need of one they sweare so fast.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phae.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, I neuèr heard of the like.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tang.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Non audiuisti,</HI> didstnere heere of that tricke? why Pistor a Baker sold his wife tother day to a cheese∣monger, that made Cake and Cheese: another to a Co∣ferer: a third to a common player: why you see tis cō∣mon: nere feare the Captaine, be ha's not so much witte to bee a praesident himselfe: I promisd to furnish him with an odde Scriuener of mine owne▪ to draw the bar∣gaine, and sale of his Lady, your horses stand heere Gentleman.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phae.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, I, I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tang.</SPEAKER>
<P>I shall bee busilye plung'd till towards bed time, aboue the chin in <HI>profundis.</HI></P>
<STAGE>Exit</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phae.</SPEAKER>
<L>What monstrous daies are these?</L>
<L>Not onely to be vicious, most men study,</L>
<L>But in it to be vgly, striue to exceed,</L>
<L>Each other in the moste deformed deede.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Was this her priuate choice? did shee neglect</L>
<L>The presence and opinion of her friends, for this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phae.</SPEAKER>
<L>I wonder who that one should be,</L>
<L>Should so disgrace that Reuerend Name of Lord,</L>
<L>So loathsomly to buy Adulterie?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<L>We may make meanes to knowe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phae.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take courage man, weele beget some defence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am bound by nature.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phae.</SPEAKER>
<P>I by Conscience — To sell his Lady: indeed she was a Beast to marrie him, and so he makes of her, come, ile thorowe now 'ime entred.</P>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Iewellers wife with a Boy.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>I<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="missing" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>w.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Is my sweete Knight comming, are you cer∣taine hee's comming?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>Certaine for sooth, I am sure I saw him out of
<PB REF="12"/>
the Barbers shop, ere I would come away.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>A Barbers shop, O hee's a trim Knight, would hee venture his body into a Barbers shop, when hee knowes tis as dangerous as a peece of Ireland: O yonder, yonder, hee comes, get you backe agen, and looke you say as I aduiz'de you.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Knight.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<L>You know me mistris?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<L>My maske, my maske.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Knig.</SPEAKER>
<L>My sweete Reuenewe!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>My pleasure welcome: I haue got single, none but you shall accompany mee to the Iustice of peace my Fathers.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Knight.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, is thy Father Iustice of Peace, and I not knowe it?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iewe.</SPEAKER>
<P>My father! yfaith sir I, simply tho I stand heere a Cittizens wife: I am a Iustice of Peaces Daughter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Knight.</SPEAKER>
<L>I loue thee the better for thy birth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Knight.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hee's at thy seruice my sweete Reuenewe, for thy money paide for e'm.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iewe.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why then let him run a little before I beseech thee, for a my troth he will discouer vs else.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Knight.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hee shall obey thee, before sirrha▪ trudge: but doe you meane to lye at your Fathers all night?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iewel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why should I desire your company else?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Knight.</SPEAKER>
<P>S'foot where shall I lye then.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iewel.</SPEAKER>
<P>What an idle question's that? why doe you hinke I cannot make roome for you in my Fathers house, as well as in my husbands, th'are both good for nothing else?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Knight.</SPEAKER>
<P>A man so resolute in valour as a Woman in de∣sire, were an absolute Leader.</P>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter two suters with the Iustice Falso.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<P>May it plese your good worship maister Iustice.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="12"/>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<L>Please me and please are your selfe,</L>
<L>Thats my word.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<P>The partie your worship sent for, will by no means be brought to appeare.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hee will not, then what would you aduize me to doe therein?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<P>Onely to graunt your worships warrant, which is of sufficient force to compell him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<P>No by my faith: you shall not haue me in that Trap: am I sworne Iustice of Peace, and shall I giue my warrant to fetch a man against his will? why there the peace is Broken, wee must doe all quietly, if hee come hee's wel∣come, and as far as I can seeyet, hees a foole to bee absent, I by this golde is hee (which hee gaue me this morning)</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, but may it please your good wor∣shippe.—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<P>I say agen please me and please your selfe, thats my word still.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, the world esteemes it a Common fauour, vpon the Contempt of the partie, the justice to graunt his war∣rant.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, tis so common, tis the worse agen, twere the bet∣ter for me twere otherwise.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<P>I protest sir, and this Gentleman can say as much, it lyes vpon my halfe vndooing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<P>I cannot see yet, that it should be so— I see not a crosse yet.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<P>I beseech your worship showe me your immediate fa∣uour, and accept this small trifle but as a remembrance to my succeeding Thankfulnes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<P>Angels? ile not meddle with them, you giue e'm to my wife not to me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<P>I, I sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<P>But I pray tell mee nowe, did the partie <HI>Ʋina Voce,</HI> with his owne mouth deliuer that contempt, that
<PB REF="13"/>
that he would not appeare, or did you but iestint?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<L>Iest<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> no a my troth sir, such was his insolent answer</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<P>And do you thinke it stood with my credite to put vp such an abuse? will he not appeare sayes he? Ile make him appeare with a Vengeance <HI>Latronello.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Latr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Do's your worship call?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<P>Draw me a strong limbd warrant for the Gen∣tleman speedily, he will be bountifull to thee: goe and thanke him within.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<P>I shall know your worship hereafter.</P>
<STAGE>Exeunt,</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, I prethee doe. Two Angels one partie, foure another: and I thinke it a great sparke of wisdome and policie (if a man come to me for Iustice) first to knowe his greefes by his fees, which bee light and which bee he <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ie: he may coūterfet els, &amp; make me do Iustice for nothing: I like not that▪ for when I meane to be iust, let me be paide wel for't: the deed so rare, purges the bribe: how now, what's the newes thou art come so hastily? how fares my Knightly Brother?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Furt.</SPEAKER>
<P>Troth he nere farde worse in his life sir: he nere had lesse stomack to his meate since I knew him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Furt.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeede hee's dead sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fal.</SPEAKER>
<P>How sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Furt.</SPEAKER>
<P>Newly deceasd I can assure your Worship: the Tabacco-pipe new dropt out of his mouth before I tooke horse, a shrewd signe: I knew then there was no way but one with him, the poore pipe was the last man he took leaue off in this world, who sel in three peeces before him, &amp; seem'd to mourne inwardly, for it lookt as blacke'th mouth as my maister.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Would hee die so like a Polititian, &amp; not once write his minde to me?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fur.</SPEAKER>
<P>No Ile say that for him sir: he dyed in the perfect state of memorie, made your worship his ful and whole executor: bequeathing his Daughter, and with her all
<PB REF="13"/>
his wealth, onely to your disposition.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<P>Did he make such a godly end saist thou? did he die so comfortably, and bequeath all to me?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your neece is at hand sir, the will, &amp; the witnesses.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<P>What a precious ioy and comfort's this, that a Iustices brother can die so wel, nay in such a good and happie memorie, to make me full executor. Wel he was too honest to liue, and that made him die so soone: now I beshrew my heart, I am glad hee's in heauen, has left all his cares and troubles with me, and that great vexa∣tion of telling of Money, yet I hope hee had so much grace before he died to turn his white mony into gold, a great ease to his Executor.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Furt.</SPEAKER>
<L>See here comes your Neece my yong mistris sir,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ah my sweete Neece, let me kisse thee, &amp; drop a teare betweene thy lips: one teare from an old man is a great matter, the cockes of age are drie, thou hast lost a vertuous father, to gaine a notable vncle.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neece.</SPEAKER>
<L>My hopes now rest in you next vnder heauē</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let 'em rest, let 'em rest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gent.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'are most welcome ere ye begin sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are both led by oath and dreadfull promise,</L>
<L>Made to the dying man at his last sence,</L>
<L>First to deliuer these into your hands,</L>
<L>The suerties and reuealers of his state.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<L>With this his onely daughter and your Neece,</L>
<L>Whose fortunes are at your disposing set,</L>
<L>Vncle and father are in you both met.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good yfaith, a well spoken Gentleman, y'are not an Esquire sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gent.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not sir? more's the pitie: by my faith better men then you are, but a great many worse: you see I haue beene a Scholler in my time, tho I'me a Iustice nowe: Neece y'are most happily welcom, the charge of you is
<PB REF="14"/>
wholy and soly mine owne: and since you are so for∣tunately come Neece, Ile rest a perpetuall widower.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neece.</SPEAKER>
<L>I take the meaning chaster then the words:</L>
<L>Yet I hope well of both, since it is thus,</L>
<L>His phraise off ends least that's knowne humourous.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fal.</SPEAKER>
<P>I make my brother (saies he) full and whole Ex∣ecutor, honestly done of him yfaith, seldome can a man get such a brother: and here again saies he, very vertu∣ously, I bequeath all to him and his disposing: an excel∣lent fellow a my troth, would you might all die no worse, Gentlemen.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Knight with Iewellers wife.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<L>But as much better as might be.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<L>Blesse your vprightnesse maister Iustice,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<P>You'r most soberly welcome sir: daughter y'aue that ye kneele for, rise, salute your weeping coozen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Weeping coozen?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neece.</SPEAKER>
<L>I coozen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Eye to weeping is verie proper, and so is the partie that spake it beleeue me, a prettie, fine, slender, streight, delicate knit bodie.</P>
<L>Oh how it moues a pleasure through our senses!</L>
<L>How small are womens wastes to their expences?</L>
<L>I cannot see her face, that's vnder water yet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>Newes as cold to the heart as an old mans kind∣nesse: my vncle dead?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neece.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue lost the deerest Father.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fal.</SPEAKER>
<P>If she marry by your consent, choyce and liking make her dowrie fiue thousand crowns: hum, fiue thou∣sand crownes? therefore by my consent shee shall nere marry, I will neither chuse for her, like of it, nor con∣sent too't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now by the pleasure of my blood a pretty coo∣zen: I would not care, if I were as nere kin to her, as I haue beene to her kinswoman.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<L>Daughter, what Gentleman might this be?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<L>No Gentleman sir, hee's a Knight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="14"/>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is he but a knight? troth, I would a sworne had beene a Gentleman, to see, to see, to see.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee's my husbands owne brother, I can tel you (sir:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy husbands brother: speak certainly prethee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>I can assure you father, my husband and hee has laine both in one bellie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile swear then he is his brother indeed, &amp; by the surer side: I craue heartie pardon sweete kinsman that thou hast stood so long vnsaluted in the way of kinred.</P>
<L>Welcome to my boord: I haue a bed for thee,</L>
<L>My daughters husbands brother shall commaund,</L>
<P>Keyes of my Chests and Chambers.— I haue stable for thy horse, chamber for thy selfe, and a loft abou for thy lowzie lackie, all fit, away with handkirchers, drie vp eies, at funeral we must cry: now let's be wise.</P>
<STAGE>Exeūt.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<L>I told you his affection.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fal.</SPEAKER>
<L>It fals sweetly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<L>But here I bar you from all plots to night,</L>
<L>The time is yet too heauie to be light.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, I'me còntent, ile sleepe as chast as you,</L>
<L>And wager night by night who keepes most true.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well we shall see your temper.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Phoenix and Fidelio.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Feare not me Fidelio: become you that inuisible Rope-maker the Scriuener, that binds a mā as he walks yet all his ioynts at libertie, aswell as ile fit that com∣mon folly of Gentry, the easie-affecting venturer, and no doubt our purpose will arriue most happily.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<P>Chast dutie my Lord works powerfully in mee, and rather then the poore Ladie my mother should fall vpon the common side of rumour to begger her name, I would not only vndergoe all habits, offices, disguiz'd professions, tho ee'n opposite to the temper my blood holds: but in the stainlesse quarrell of her reputation, alter my shape for euer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<P>I loue thee wealthier, thou hast a noble touch, &amp; by this means which is the only safe means to preserve
<PB REF="15"/>
thy mother from such an vgly land and sea monster as a counterfeit Captain is, he resigning and basely selling all his estate, title, right, and interest in his Ladie, as the forme of the writing shall testifie.</P>
<L>What otherwise can follow but to haue,</L>
<L>A Ladie safe deliuered of a knaue?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am in debt my life, to the free goodnes of your inuentions.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh they must euer striue to be so good,</L>
<L>"Who sels his vow is stampt the slaue of blood.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Captaine his Ladie following him.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Captaine, my husband.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hence, we're at a price for thee, at a price, wants but the telling, and the sealing, then —</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladie.</SPEAKER>
<P>Haue you no sence, neither of my good name or your owne credit?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Credit? pox of credit, that makes me owe so much: it had bine better for me by a thousand Royals I had lost my credite, seauen yeare ago, t'as vndone me, that's it that makes me flie: what neede I to sea else, in the Spring time, when Woods haue leaues, to looke vpon balde Oake.</P>
<L>Happier that man say I, whom no man trusts,</L>
<L>It makes him valiant, dares outface the prisons,</L>
<L>Vpon whose carkasse no Gownde Rauen iets,</L>
<L>Oh he that has no credite owes no debts.</L>
<L>Tis time I were rid on't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladie.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh why do you so wilfully cherrish your own poyson? and breath against the best of life, chast credit.</P>
<L>Well may I call it chast, for like a Maide</L>
<L>Once falsly broke it euer liues decaide.</L>
<L>O Captaine, husband, you name that Dishonest,</L>
<L>By whose good power all that are honest liue,</L>
<L>What madnesse is it to speake ill of that,</L>
<L>Which makes all men speake well, take away credite</L>
<L>By which men amongst men, are well reputed,</L>
<L><PB REF="15"/>That man may liue, but still liues executed.</L>
<L>Oh then shewe pittie to that noble Title</L>
<L>Which else you doe Vsurpe: you'r no true Captaine,</L>
<L>To let your enemies leade you, foule disdaine,</L>
<L>And euerlasting Scandall, Oh beleeue it!</L>
<L>The money you receive for my good name</L>
<L>Will not be halfe enough to pay your shame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, ile sell thee then to the Smocke: see heere comes my honourable Chapman.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Proditor.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh my poyson!</L>
<L>Him, whome mine honour and mine eye abhors.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lady, what so vniouially departed?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fine shee pollicie? she makes my backe her Bol∣ster, but before my face, she not indures him, Tricks.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Captaine, how haps it she remou'd so strangely?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh for Modesties cause awhile my Lord: shee must restraine her selfe, shee's not yours yet:</P>
<L>Beside, it weare not wisdome to appeare,</L>
<P>Easie before my sight, fah, wherefore serues modestie but to pleasure a Lady now and then, and help her from sus∣spect, that's the best vse tis put too.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well obseru'd of a Captaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>No doubt youle be soone friendes my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thinke no lesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>And make what hast I can to my ship, I durst wa∣ger you'l be vnder saile before me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>A pleasant voyage Captaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, a verie pleasant voyage as can be: I see the houre is Ripe, heere comes the Prisons Bawde the bond-maker, one that bindes heires before they are begot.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>And here are the Crownes Captaine, goe? attend,</L>
<L>Let our bay Courser waite.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Phoenix and Fidelio both disguized.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lackey.</SPEAKER>
<L>It shall be obeyed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Farmers sonne, ist true?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="16"/>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Has crownes to scatter?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>I giue you your salute sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoen.</SPEAKER>
<L>I take it not vnthankfully sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>I heare a good report of you sir—y'aue money.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoen.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue so, true.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>An excellent vertue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, to keeep from you—heare you me Captaine?</L>
<P>I haue a certaine generous itch sir, to loose a fewe An∣gels in the way of profit: tis but a game at Tennis,</P>
<L>Where if the ship keepe aboue line, tis three to one:</L>
<L>If not, there's but three hundred Angels gone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is your venture three hundred? y'are verie pre∣tiously welcome: heere's a voyage towarde will make vs all.—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Beggerly fooles, and swarming knaues.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Captaine, whats he?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Feare him not my Lord, hee's a Gull', hee ven∣tures with me, some filthy Farmers sonne, the father's a Iew, and the sonne a Gentleman:pha.—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yet he should be a Iew too, for he is new come from giuing ouer swine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, that in our Countrey makes him a Gen∣tleman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe to, tell your money Captaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capi</SPEAKER>
<L>Read aloft Scriuener. 1.2.—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<P>To all good and honest Christian people, to whō this present writing shal come: know you for a certain, that I Captaine, for and in the consideration of the sum of fiue hundred crownes, haue clearly bargained, solde, giuen, graunted, assigned and set ouer, and by these pre∣sents doe cleerly bargaine, sell, giue, graunt, assigne and set ouer, al the right, estate, title, interest, demaund, pos∣session, and tearme of yeares to come, which I the saide Captaine haue, or ought to haue.—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoen.</SPEAKER>
<L>If I were as good as I should be,—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<P>In and to Madona Castiza, my most vertuous,
<PB REF="16"/>
modest, louing, and obedient wife.—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>By my troth my Lord and so she is.— 3.4.5.6.7.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>The more Slaue he that sayes it, and not sees it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<P>Togither, with all and singular those admirable qualities with which her noble brest is furnisht.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well said Scriuener, hast put'em all in: you shal heare now my L.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>In primis,</HI> the beuties of her minde, chastitie, tem∣perance, and aboue all, pacience:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>You haue bought a Iewell yfaith, my L, nine and thirtie, fortie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<P>Excellent in the best of Musicke, in voice deli∣cious: in conference wise and pleasing: of age content∣ful: neither too yōg to be a pish, nor too old to be sottish</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>You haue bought as louely a penny-woorth my Lord, as ere you bought in your life.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro</SPEAKER>
<L>Why should I buy her else Captaine?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<P>And which is the best, of a wife a most comfor∣table sweete companion.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>I could not affoord her so y faith, but that I am-going to sea and haue need of money.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<L>A most comfortable sweete companion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>What agen? the Scriuener reades in passion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<P>I read as the words moue me: yet if that be a faul it shall be seen no more,—which said <HI>Madona Casti<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>a</HI> lying, &amp; yet being in the occupatiō of the said captain</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ninteene—occupation? Pox out, out with oc∣cupation, a Captaine is of no occupation, man.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor thou of no religion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now I come to the <HI>Habendum,</HI> to haue and to holde, vse and—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vse? put out vse too for shame.</L>
<L>Till we are all gone, I prethee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<P>And to be acquited of and from all former bar∣gaines, former sales:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Former sailes, nine &amp; twenty thirty, by my troth
<PB REF="17"/>
my Lord, this is the first time that euer I solde her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet the writing must run so Captaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let it run on then, nine and fortie, fiftie, —</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Former sales, Guiftes, Grants, Surrenders. Reen∣tryes. —</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>For Reentryes, I will not sweare for her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<P>And furdermore (I the said) of and for the consi∣deration of the somme of fiue hundred Crownes to set me a boord before these presents vtterly disclaime for euer, any Title, estate, right, interest, demaund, or posses∣sion, in or to the said Madona Castiza, my late vertuous, and vnfortunate wife.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vnfortunate indeede, that was wel plac'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<P>As also neither to touch, attempt, molest, or in∣cumber any parte, or partes whatsoeuer: either to bee namde or not to be namde: eyther hidden or vnhid∣den, eyther those that boldly looke abroad, or those that dare not show their face.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faces: I knowe what you meane by faces: Scriuener, there's a great figure in faces.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<P>In witnesse wherof, I the said Captaine haue in∣terchangeably set to my hand and seale: in presence of all these, the day and date aboue written.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Verie good sir, Ile bee ready for you presently, foure hundred and twentie. 1.2.3.4.5.—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Of all deedes, yet this strikes the deepest wound</L>
<L>Into my apprehension,</L>
<L>Reuerend, and honourable Matrimony,</L>
<L>Mother of lawfull sweetes, vnshamed mornings:</L>
<L>Dangerlesse pleasures, thou that mak'st the bed,</L>
<L>Both pleasant, and legitimately fruitfull: without thee,</L>
<L>All the whole world were soyled Bastardy.</L>
<L>Thou art the onely and the greatest forme.</L>
<L>That put'st a difference betweene our desires</L>
<L>And the disordered appetites of Beastes,</L>
<L>Making their mates, those that stand next their lusts.</L>
<L><PB REF="17"/>Then,—with what base iniurie is thy goodnes paide</L>
<L>First, rare to haue a Bride commence a Maide,</L>
<L>But do's beguile ioy of the puritie:</L>
<L>And is made strickt by power of Drugs and Art,</L>
<L>An Artificall Maide, a Doctord Virgin,</L>
<L>And so deiceues the glorie of his bod:</L>
<L>A foule contempt, against the spotlesse power</L>
<L>Of sacred wedlocke, but if chast and honest,</L>
<L>There is another Deuill hauntes marriage,</L>
<L>(None fondly loues but knowes it) Iealousie,</L>
<L>That Wedlocks yellow sicknes, that whispering sepe∣ration euerie minute.</L>
<L>And thus the cursse takes his effect or progresse,</L>
<L>The moste of men in their first suddaine furyes,</L>
<L>Rayle at the narrow boundes of marriage,</L>
<L>And cal't a prison then it is moste iust,</L>
<L>That the disease'ath prison, Ielousie</L>
<L>Should still affect a'm, but oh! here I am fixt,</L>
<L>To make sale of a wife, monstrous and foule,</L>
<L>An act abhord in nature, could in soule:</L>
<L>Who that ha's man in him, could so resigne,</L>
<L>To make his shame, the poesye to the Coyne?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Right yfaith, my Lord fully fiue hundred,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<P>I saide how you should finde it Captaine, and with this competent summe you rest amplye conten∣ted.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Amply contented.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heere's the Pen Captaine: your name to the sale.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>S'foote doost take me to be a pen-man? I protest I could nere write more then A, B, C, those three letters in my life.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid</SPEAKER>
<L>Why those will serue Captaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>I could nere get furder.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<P>Would you haue got furder then A B C? ah Base Captaine, that's far ynough yfaith.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="18"/>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take the Seale off Captaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>It goes on hardly, and comes off easily.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>I iust like a Coward.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you write witnesse Gentleman?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hee? he shall, prethe come and set thy hand for witnesse Rogue, thou shall venture with me?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, then I ha reason Captaine that com∣maunds me?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>What a faire fist the pretty whorsone writes, as if he had had manners and bringing vp, a farmers Sonne: his Father dam's himselfe to sell mustie Corne, while hee ventures the Money, twill prosper well at Sea no doubt he shall nere see't agein</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<L>So, Captaine you deliuer this as your deede.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>As my deede, what else sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>The ouglyest deed that ere mine eye did witnes</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>So my Lord, you haue her, clip her, enioy her, shee's your owne, and let me be proud to tell you now my Lord, shee's as good a soule if a man had a minde to liue honest, and keepe a wench, the Kindest, sweetest, comfortablest Rogue.—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Harke in thine eare,</L>
<L>The Baser slaue art thou: and so ile tell her,</L>
<L>I loue the Pearle, thou soldst, hate thee the Seller—</L>
<L>Goe, to Sea, the end of thee—is Lowsie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Cap</HI>:</SPEAKER>
<L>This fine worke: a verie braue end, hum—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wel thought vpon, this Scriuener may furnish me</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why should this fellowe be a Lord by birth?</L>
<L>Being by bloud a Knaue, one that would sell</L>
<L>His Lordship if he likt her Ladyship.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Phoe</HI>:</SPEAKER>
<L>What's here Now?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Prod</HI>:</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue imployment for a trustie fellow, bould, sure—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<L>What if he be a Knaue my Lord?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<P>There thou comst to me, why he should be so,
<PB REF="18"/>
and men of your quill are not vnacquainted.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeed al our chiefe liuing my Lord, is by fooles and knaues, we could not keepe open shop else▪ Fooles that enter into bonds, and Knaues that binde e'm.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why now we meete.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<P>And as my memorie happily leades me: I know a fellowe of a standing estate, neuer flowing: I durst conuey treason into his bosome,</P>
<L>And keepe it safe nine yeares.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>A goodly Time.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<L>And if neede were would presse to an attempt,</L>
<L>And cleaue to Desperate action.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>That Last fits mee.</L>
<L>Thou hast the measure right, looke I heare from thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<L>With duteous speede.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Expect a large reward:</L>
<L>I will finde time of her to finde regard.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>The end of me is lowzie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh my Lord! I haue strange wordes to tell you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<P>Stranger yet? ile chuse some other hower to list∣en to thee, I am yet sicke of this, discouer quickly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, wil you make yourselfe knowne my Lord</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>I.</L>
<L>Who scourgeth sinne let him doo't dreadfully.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pox of his dissemblance: I will to s<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, you shall to sea, thou wouldst poyson the whole land else—why how now Captaine?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>In health.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<L>What, drooping?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or a shamde of the sale of thine owne wife?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>You might count me an asse then yfaith.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>If not a sham'd of that, what can you be a shamd ofthen?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prethe ha done, I am asham'd of nothing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>I easily beleeue that.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>This Lord stickes in my stomacke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="19"/>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>How? take one of thy fethers downe, and fetch him vp.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ide make him come.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>But what if the Duke should heare of this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, or your Sonne in Law, Fidelio knowes of the sale of his mother.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>What and they did, I sell none but mine owne: as for the Duke, hee's abroad by this time, and for Fide∣lio hee's in labour.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee, in labour?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Cap</HI>:</SPEAKER>
<L>What call you Trauelling?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<P>That's true:— but let me tell you Captain: whether the Duke heare on't, or Fidelio know on't: or both, or neither, twa's a moste filthie loathsome part.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid</SPEAKER>
<L>A base vnnaturall deede—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Cap</HI>:</SPEAKER>
<L>Slaue and foole: —ha, who? oh—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou hatefull villaine: thou shouldst chuse (to sincke</L>
<L>To keepe thy basenes shrouded.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter his Lady.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ougly wretch.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La:</SPEAKER>
<L>Who hath laid violence vpon my husband?</L>
<L>My deare sweet Captaine, helpe—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lady you wrong your value,</L>
<L>Call you him deere that has solde you so cheape?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady</SPEAKER>
<L>I do beseech your pardon good my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<L>My abused Mother:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<L>My kinde Sonne,</L>
<L>Whose liking I neglected in this match.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not that alone, but you far happyer fortunes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap</SPEAKER>
<L>Is this the Scriuener and the Farmers Sonne,</L>
<L>Fire on his Lordship he tolde me they Trauaild.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>And see the summe tolde out to buy that Iewel</L>
<L>More pretious in a Woman then her eye, her honour:</L>
<L>Nay take it to you Lady, and liudge it,</L>
<P>Too slight a recōpence, for your great wrong, but that
<PB REF="19"/>
his riddance helpes it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap:</SPEAKER>
<L>S'foot he vndoes me, I am a Rogue &amp; a Beggar,</L>
<L>The Aegiptian plague creepes ouer me alreadie,</L>
<L>I begin to be lowsie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe:</SPEAKER>
<L>Thus happily preuented, y'are set free,</L>
<L>Or else made ouer to adulterie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lad.</SPEAKER>
<L>To heauen and to you my modest thankes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Monster, to sea, spit thy al herred foame,</L>
<L>Where it may doe least harme, ther's ayre and roeme.</L>
<L>Thour't Dangerous in a Chamber, <HI>Ʋirulext Ʋenem,</HI></L>
<L>Vnto a Ladies name, and her chast breath</L>
<L>If past this euenings verge, the Dukedome hold thee,</L>
<L>Thou art reseru'd for abiect punishment.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Cap</HI>:</SPEAKER>
<P>I doe beseech your good Lordship consider the state of a poore downe-cast Captaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<P>Captaine, off with that noble title thou becomst it vildely, I nere saw the name fit worse, ile sooner al∣lowe a Pandar a Captaine then thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>More's the pittie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sue to thy Lady for pardon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lad.</SPEAKER>
<L>I giue it without suite.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>I do beseech your Ladiship not so much for par∣don, as to bestow a few of those Crownes vpon a poore vnfethered Rouer that will as truely pray for you, and wish you hangd, as any man breathing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>I giue it freely all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay by your fauour:</L>
<L>I will containe you Lady, here▪ be gone:</L>
<L>Vse slaues like slaues—wealth keepes their faults vnkowne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well 'ime yet glad, i'ue libertie and these:</L>
<L>The Land has plagu'd me, and ile plague the seas.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Sceane is cleer'd, the bane of brightnes fled</L>
<L>Who sought the death of honour, is strucke dead.</L>
<L>Come modest Lady:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid:</SPEAKER>
<L>My moste honest mother.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="20"/>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy vertue shall liue safe from reach of shames,</L>
<L>That Act endes nobly, preserues Ladies fames.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Iustice, Knight, Iewel.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why this is but the second time of your com∣ming Kinsman, visit me oftner, Daughter, I charge you bring this Gentleman along with you: Gentleman, I I crie yee mercy sir, I call you Gentleman still: I for∣get y'are but a Knight, you must pardon me sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Knight.</SPEAKER>
<P>For your worships kindenes—worship I crie you mercie sir, I call you worshipfull still, I forget, y'are but a Iustice.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am no more yfaith.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Knig.</SPEAKER>
<L>You must pardon me sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis quickly done sir, you see I make bould with you Kinsman, thrust my Daughter and you into one Chamber.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Knight.</SPEAKER>
<L>Best of all sir: Kinred you knowe may lye a∣nye where.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals</SPEAKER>
<P>True, true sir, Daughter receiue your blessing— take heed the Coach iopper not to much▪ haue a care to the fruits of your bodye—looke to her Kinsman.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Knight.</SPEAKER>
<L>Feare it not sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iewel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay Father though I say it, that should not say it, hee lookes to me more like a husband then a Kins∣man.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<L>I heare good commendations of you sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Knig.</SPEAKER>
<L>You heare the worst of me I hope sir,—I salute my leaue sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<P>Y'are welcome all ouer your body sir: nay, I can behaue my selfe courtly, though I keepe house 'ith Countrie: what, does my Neece hide herselfe, not pre∣sent, ha? Latronello.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Latr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<L>Call my Neece to mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Latr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<P>A foolish, coy, bashfull thing it is, shee's afraid
<PB REF="20"/>
to lie with her owne Vncle: ide do her no harme yfaith, I keepe my selfe a widdower a purpose, yet the foolish Girle will not looke into't, shee should haue all y∣faith, shee knowes I haue but a time, cannot holde long, see where she comes, pray whome am I Neece?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neece.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hope y'are your selfe.</L>
<L>Vncle to me, and Brother to my Father.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh am I so, it do's not appeare so,—for surely you would loue your Fathers Brother for your Fathers sake, your Vncle for your owne sake.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neece.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay you doe nothing Neece.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neece.</SPEAKER>
<L>In that loue which becomes you best I loue (you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<L>How should I know that loue becomes me best?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neece.</SPEAKER>
<L>Because tis chast, and honorable.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<L>Honorable! it cannot become me then <HI>Neece.</HI></L>
<L>For'ime scarce worshipfull: Is this an age,</L>
<L>To entertaine bare loue without the fruites</L>
<L>When I receiu'd thee first, I look't</L>
<L>Thou shouldst haue beene a wife vnto my house</L>
<L>And sau'd me from the charge of marriage.</L>
<P>Do you thinke your Fathers fiue thousand pound wold ha made me take you else? no, you should neere a ha beene a charge to me.</P>
<L>As far as I can perceiue yet by you,</L>
<P>I'ue as much neede to marrie as ere I had: would not this be a greate griefe to your friendes thinke you, if they were aliue agen?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Neece</HI>:</SPEAKER>
<L>Twould be a griefe indeede.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'aue confest</L>
<L>All about house, that young Fidelio</L>
<L>Who in his Trauailes does attend the Prince,</L>
<L>Is your vowde loue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neece.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most true, hee's my vow'd Husband.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<P>And what's a Husband is not a Husband a strāger at first, and wil you lye with a stranger before
<PB REF="21"/>
you lie with your owne Vncle? take heede what yee doe <HI>Neece,</HI> I counsell you for the best: strangers are drunken fellowes I can tell you, they will come home late a nights, beate their wiues, and get nothing but Girles: look too't, if you marry, your stubbernes is your Dowrie: fiue thousand Crownes were bequeathed to you, true, if you marry with my consent: but if ere you goe to marrying by my consent, ile goe to hanging by your's: goe too▪ be wise and loue your Vncle.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neece.</SPEAKER>
<L>I should haue cause then to repent indeede.</L>
<L>Do you so far forget the Offices</L>
<L>Of blushing modestie? Vncles are halfe Fathers,</L>
<L>Why they come so neare our bloods th'are ene part of it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why now you come to mee Neece: if your Vn∣cle be part of your owne flesh and blood, is it not then fit your owne flesh and bloud should come neerest to you? answere me to that Neece.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neece.</SPEAKER>
<L>You doe allude all to incestuous will,</L>
<L>Nothing to modest purpose: turne me foorth,</L>
<L>Be like an Vncle of these latter daies,</L>
<L>Periurde ynough, ynough vnnaturall,</L>
<L>Play your Executorship, in Tyranny,</L>
<L>Restraine my fortunes, keepe me poore, I care not,</L>
<L>In this alone moste women ile excell,</L>
<L>Ile rather yelde to beggery then to hell.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<P>Very good, a my troth my Neece is Valiant, sha's made me ritcher by fiue thousand Crownes, the price of her Dowrie: are you so honest, I doe not feare but I shall haue the Conscience to keepe you poore y∣nough Neece, or else I am quite altered a late—The Newes, may it please you sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Latron.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, theres an olde fellowe, a kinde of Law-driuer, entreates conference with your worship.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<P>A Law-driuer, prethee driue him hither.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="21"/><HI>Enter Tangle.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tan.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, no I say if it bee for defect of Apparance, take me out a speciall <HI>Significauit.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Verie good sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then if he purchase an <HI>Alias</HI> or <HI>Capias,</HI> which are Writs of custome, onely to delay time, your <HI>Proce∣dendo</HI> do's you Knights seruice—that's nothing at all, get your <HI>Distringas</HI> out as soone as you can for a Iurie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile attend your god worships comming out.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do I prethee, attend me, ile take it kindly, <HI>a Vo∣luntate.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<L>What, old Seigneur Tangle!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tan.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am in debt to your worships remembrance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<P>My old master of Fence: come, come, come, I haue not exerciz'd this twelue Moones, I haue almost forgot all my Law-weapons.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tan.</SPEAKER>
<P>They are vnder fine and Recouerie, your wor∣ship shall easily recouer them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hope so: when there?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Latron.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Rapler and Dagger foyles instantly: and whats thy suite to mee olde Tangle, ile graunt it pre∣sently.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nothing but this sir, to set your worships hand to the commendation of a Knaue whome no bodye speakes well on.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<L>The more shame for e'm, what was his offence I pray?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tang.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Vestras Deducite Culpas</HI>—nothing but robbing a Vestrie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<P>What, what! alasse poore Knaue, giue me the Pa∣per, he did but saue the Churchwardens a labour: come, come, he has done a better deed in't then the parish is a aware off, to preuent the Knaues, hee robs but seldome, they once a quarter: me thinks twere a part of good iust∣ice, to hang e'm at yeares end, wen they come out of
<PB REF="22"/>
their office, to the true terrifying of all Collectors and Sidemen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your worship would make a fruitefull Com∣mon-wealths man, the Constable lets e'm alone, looks on, and sayes nothing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<P>A lasse good man, he lets e'm alone for quietnes sake, and takes halfe a share with e'm: they know wel enough too, he ha's an impediment in his tongue, hee's alwaies drunke when he should speake.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeede your worship speakes true in that sir: they blinde him with beere, and make him so narrowe eyde, that he wincks naturallye at all their Knaueries,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<L>So, so, heeres my hand to his commendations.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tangle.</SPEAKER>
<L>A <HI>Charitate,</HI> you doe a charitable deede in't sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, if it be but a Vestrie matter, visit me at anye time, olde Signeor Law-thistle! O well done, heere are the Foiles, come, come sir, ile trie a Law-bout with you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tan.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am affraide I shall ouerthrowe you sir yfaith.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis but for want of vse then sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeed that same odde word Vse, makes a man a good Lawyer, and a woman an arrant—tuh tuh, tuh, tuh, tuh, now am I for you sir: but first to bring you into forme, can your worship name all your weapons?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<P>That I can I hope, let me see, <HI>Longswoord,</HI> what's Longsword? I am so duld with dooing justice, that I haue forgot all yfaith.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your long sword, thats a writ of delay.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<P>Masse that swords long enough indeede, I ha knowne it reach the length of fifteene Tearmes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tang</SPEAKER>
<L>Fifteene Tearmes, that's but a short sword.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<L>Me thinkes tis long enough, proceede sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tang.</SPEAKER>
<L>A <HI>Writ</HI> of <HI>Delay, Long-sword.</HI></L>
<L><HI>Scandala Magnatum,</HI> Backesword.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<L>Scandals are back-swords indeede</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tang.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Capias cominus,</HI> Case of Rapyers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="22"/>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh Desperate!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tang.</SPEAKER>
<L>A <HI>Latitat,</HI> sword and Dagger.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<L>A writ of Execution, Rapier and Dagger.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou art come to our present weapon, but what call you sword and Buckler then?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh! that's out of vse now, sword and Buckler was cal'd a good conscience, but that weapons left long agoe, that was too manly a fight, too sound a weapon for these our daies, sl'id wee are scarce able to lift vp a Buckler now, our armes are so bound to the Poxe: one good bang vppon a Buckler would make moste of our Gentlemen flye a peeces, tis not for these lintie times, our Lawyers are good Rapyer and Dagger men, theile quickly dispatch your—money.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeede since sword and buckler time, I haue obseru'd, there ha's beene nothing so much fighting: where bee all our gallant Swaggerers? there are no good frayes alate.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh sir, the properties altred, you shall see lesse fighting euerie day then other, for euerie one gets him a Mistris, and she giues him woundes enowe, and you knowe, the Surgeons cannot beehere and there too, if there were red woundes too, what wold become of the Reinish woundes?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou saist true yfaith, they would bee but il fa∣vouredly lookt to then.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tang.</SPEAKER>
<L>Verie well sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<L>I expect you sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tang.</SPEAKER>
<P>I lye in this court for you sir, my Rapyer is my Atturney, and my Dagger his Clarke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your Atturney wants a little oyling, me thinkes, he lookes very Rustily.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis but his proper colour sir, his Father was an Iremonger, he will nere look brighter, the rust ha's so eat into him, ha's neuer any leasure to be made cleane.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not in the vacation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="23"/>
<SPEAKER>Tang.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Non Vacat exiguis rebus adesse Ioui.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then Ioue will not be at leysure to scoure him, because he <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="broken" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ere came to him before.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Y'are excellent at it sir—and now you least thinke on't, I arrest you sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<L>Very good sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay very bad sir by my faith—I followe you still, as the Officers wil followe you as long as you haue a penny.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<P>You speake sentences sir—by this time haue I tryed my friendes, and now I thrust in baile—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Tang</HI>:</SPEAKER>
<P>This baile will not be taken sir, they must be two Cittizens that are no Cuckolds.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<P>Berlady then 'ime like to lye by it, I had rather twere a hundred that were.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tang.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take heede I bring you not to an <HI>Nisiprius</HI> sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must ward my selfe as well as I may sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis Court day now, <HI>Declarat Atturnatus,</HI> my Atturney gapes for money.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall haue no Aduantage yet, I put in my Answere.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<L>I follow the sute still sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<P>I like not this Court birlady—I: take me out a writ of Remoue, a writ of Remoue, doe you see sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tang:</SPEAKER>
<L>Very well sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<L>And place my cause higher.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tang,</SPEAKER>
<P>There you started me sir—yet for all your <HI>Demurres, Plures,</HI> and <HI>Sursurarers,</HI> which are all Long∣swords: that's Delaies: al the comfort is, in nine yeares a man may ouerthrowe you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fal.</SPEAKER>
<L>You must thanke your good friendes then sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let nine yeares passe, fiue hundred crownes cast away a both sides, and the suite not twentie, my Counsellors wife must haue another hood you knowe, and my Atturneyes wife wil haue a new forepart, yet
<PB REF="23"/>
see at length law, I shal haue law: now beware, I bring you to a narrowe exigent, and by no meanes can you auoide the Proclamation—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now followes a writ of execution, a <HI>Capias, vt Legatum,</HI> giues you a wound mortall, trippes vp your heeles, and layes you ith Counter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<L>O Villaine!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tang.</SPEAKER>
<P>I crie your worship heartily mercie sir, I thought we had beene in Lawe together, <HI>Aduersarius contra aduersarium</HI> by my troth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh! reach me thy hand, I nere had such an o∣uerthrowe in my life.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Twa's long of your Atturney there, hee might a staide the execution of <HI>Capias vt Legatum,</HI> and re∣mou'd you with a Supersedeas <HI>non molestandum</HI> into the Court of Equitie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pox on him, he fell out of my hand when I had most neede of him,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tan.</SPEAKER>
<L>I was bound to follow the suite sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou couldst doe no lesse then ouerthrowe me,</L>
<L>I must needes say so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tang.</SPEAKER>
<L>You had recouered cost else sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<P>And now by'th masse I thinke I shal hardly recouer without cost.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, that's <HI>Certoscio,</HI> an execution is very chargeable.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, it shall teach mee witte as long as I am a Iustice: I perceiue by this tryall, if a man haue a sound fall in Law, hee shall feele it in his bones all his life after.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, that's <HI>Recto</HI> vpon Record, for I my selfe was ouerthrowne in eighty eight by a Taylor, and I haue had a Stitch in my side euer since, oh!</P>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Toward the close of the musick, the Iustices three men prepare for a robberie.</STAGE>
<STAGE><PB REF="24"/><HI>Enter Iustice Falso, vntrust.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why Latronello, Furtiuo, Fucato, where be these lazie knaues that should trusse me, not one stirring yet?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>A crie within.</SPEAKER>
<P>Followe, followe, followe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<L>What newes there?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>A cry.</SPEAKER>
<L>This way, this way, follow, follow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hark you sluggish Soporiferous villaines, ther's knaues abroad when you are a bed, are ye not a sham'd on't, a Iustices men should be vp first, and giue example all knaues.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter two of his men tumbling in, in False beards.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Latro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh I beseech your good worship.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fuca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your worshipfull worship.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Theeues, my two hand sword, ime rob'd 'ith Hal, Latronello, Knaues, come down, my two hand sword I</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Latron.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am Latronello, I beseech your worship, (say.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou Latronello, thou lyest, my men scorne to haue beardes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Latr.</SPEAKER>
<P>We forget our beards, now I beseech your wor∣ship quickly remember vs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fuc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay theres no time to talke of how now, tis don.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>A cry.</SPEAKER>
<L>Follow, follow, follow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Latro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Foure marke and a Liuerie is not able to keepe life and soule together, wee must flye out once a quar∣te, tis for your worships credit to haue moneye in our pursse, our Fellow Furtiuo is taken in the Action.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fal.</SPEAKER>
<L>A pox on him for a lazie knaue, would hee bee taken?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>They bring him along to your worship, your the next Iustice, now or neuer show your selfe a good mai∣ster, an vpright Magistrate, and deliuer him out of their hands.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, he shal finde me—apt enough to doe him good I warrant him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Latr:</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee comes in a false beard sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="24"/>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<P>S'foot what, should hee doe here else? there's no comming to me in a true on: if he had one,—the slaue to be taken: doe not I keepe Geldings swift enough?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Latron.</SPEAKER>
<P>The goodlyest Geldings of any Gentleman in the shire.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<P>Which did the whorson knaue ride vpon?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Enter.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vpon one of your best sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fucat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stand and deliuer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<P>Vpon Stand and Deliuer: the verie Gelding I chuse for mine owne riding, as nimble as Pegasus the flying horse yonder: goe shift your selues into your coates, bring hither a great chaire, and a little table.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fucat.</SPEAKER>
<L>With all present speede sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<L>And Latronello.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Latron.</SPEAKER>
<L>I sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sit you downe, &amp; very soberly take the examna∣tion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Latro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile drawe a few horse heades in a paper, make a shew: I hope I shall keepe my countenence.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pox on him agen, would he be taken? hee frets me: I haue beene a youth my selfe, I ha seene the day I could haue told money out of other mens purses (Masse so I can doe now) nor will I keepe that fellow about me that dares not bid a man stand: for as long as drunken∣nesse is a vice, stand is a vertue: but I would not haue 'em taken. I remember now betimes in a morning I would haue peept through the greene boughs, &amp; haue had the partie presently, and then to ride away sinelye in feare, twas e'en Venerie to me yfaith, the pleasantst course of life, one would thinke euery Woodcok a Con∣stable, and euery Owle an officer, but those dayes are past with mee: and a my troth I thinke I am a greater theefe now, and in no danger: I can take my ease, sit in my Chaire, look in your faces now, and rob you, make you bring your money by authoritie put off your hat, and thanke me for robbing of you, O there is nothing to a theefe vnder Couert Barne.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="25"/><HI>Enter Phoenix, Fidelio being robd, Constable, Officers and the Theefe Furtino.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Const.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come Officers bring him away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, I see thee through thy false beard, thou mid-winde chinde Rascall,</P>
<L>How now my Maisters, whats he? ha?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your worship knowes, I neuer come but I bring a theefe with me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou hast left thy wont else Constable.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, we vnderstand you to be the onely vp right∣nes of this place.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<L>But I scare vnderstand you sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why then you vnderstand not your selfe sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<P>Such another word, and you shal change places with the Theefe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>A maintayner of equall causes I meane.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now I haue you, proceede sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<P>This Gentleman and my selfe, being led hea∣ther by occasion of businesse, haue beene offered the discurtesie of the Country, set vppon by three theeues and rob'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<L>What are become of the other two, <HI>Latronello,</HI> and Fuca?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Latro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heere sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<P>They both made away from vs, the crie pursues e'm, but as yet none but this taken.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Latronello.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Latron.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take his examination.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Latro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let the Knaue stand single.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Furt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thanke your good worship.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha's beene a suter at Court sure, hee thankes me for nothing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee's a Theefe now sure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<L>That we must know of him, what are you sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Furt.</SPEAKER>
<L>A peece next to the Taile sir—a Seruingman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<P>By my troth a prettie phrase and verye
<PB REF="25"/>
cleanly handled, put it downe Latronello: thou mayst make vse on't. Is hee of honour or worship whom thou seruest?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fur.</SPEAKER>
<P>Of both deere sir, honourable in minde, and wor∣shipfull in bodie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why would one wish a man to speake better?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoen</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh sir, they most commonly speake best, that doe worst.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<P>Say you so sir, then weele trie him farther, — Do's your right worshipfull maister, goe before you, as an ensample of Vice, and so encourage you to this slin∣king iniquitie? hee is not a Lawer, is he?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Furt.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha's the more wrong sir, both for his conscience, and honestie, he deserues to be one.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pittie hee's theefe yfaith, I should entertaine him else.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoen.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, if he were not as he is, hee would be better then himselfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Furt.</SPEAKER>
<P>No tis well knowne sir, I haue a maister, the ve∣rie picture of wisdome,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>For indeed he speakes not one wise worde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Furt.</SPEAKER>
<L>And no man but will admire to heare of his Vertues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Because he nere had any in all his life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<L>You write all downe Latronello.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Latr.</SPEAKER>
<L>I warrant you sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Furt.</SPEAKER>
<L>So sober, so discrete, so iudicious:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hum.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Furt.</SPEAKER>
<L>And aboue all, of most reuerend grauitie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<P>I like him for one qualitie, hee speakes well of his maister, he will fare the better:—Now sir, let mee touch you,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fur.</SPEAKER>
<L>I sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, seruing a Gentleman of such worship and wisdome, such sobrietie and vertue, such discretion and iudgement as your master is, doe you take such a beastly
<PB REF="26"/>
course, to stop horses, hinder Gentlewomen from their meetings, and make Citizens neuer ride but a Sundaies, onely to auoyd Morning praier and you: is it because your worshipfull Ma. feeds you with leane spits, paies you with Irish mony, or clothes you in northern dozēs?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Furt.</SPEAKER>
<P>Farre be it from his mind, or my report, Tis well knowne he kept worshipful cheer the day of his wiues burial, payes our foure marks a yeare as duly by twelue pence a quarter as can be.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>His wisdome swallowes it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Furt.</SPEAKER>
<L>And for Northren dozens, fie, fie, wee were nere troubled with so many.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<P>Receiuing then such plenteous blessings from your vertuous and bountiful master, what cause haue you to be theefe now? answer me to that geere:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Furt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis ee'n as a man giues his mind too't sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<L>How sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Furt.</SPEAKER>
<P>For alas, if the whole worlde were but of one trade; traffique were nothing: if wee were all true∣men, wee should bee of no trade: what a pittifull world would heere bee, heauen forbid we should bee all true∣men: then howe should your worships next suite bee made? not a Tayler left in the lande: of what stuffe would you haue it made? not a Merchant left to deli∣uer it, would your worship goe in that sute still? You would ha more theeues about you then those you haue banisht, and be glad to call the great ones home agen, to destroy the little.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>A notable Rogue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fal.</SPEAKER>
<P>A my troth, a fine knaue, &amp; ha's answered me glo∣riously, what wages wilt thou take after thou art hāg'd?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Furt.</SPEAKER>
<P>More then your worship's able to giue, I would thinke foule scorne to be a Iustice then.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fal.</SPEAKER>
<P>He sayes true too yfayth, for we are all full of cor∣ruption here,—hearke you my friends.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="26"/>
<SPEAKER>Fal.</SPEAKER>
<P>By my troth if you were no crueller then I, I could find in my hart to let him goe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Could you so sir, the more pittiful Iustice you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay I did but to trie you, if you haue no pittie, Ile ha none, away hee's a Theefe, to prison with him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Furt.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am content sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Are you content, bring him backe, nay then you shall not goe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile be as cruel as you can wish: y'are content, be∣like you haue a tricke to breake prison, or a bribe for the Officers.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Const.</SPEAKER>
<L>For vs sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fal.</SPEAKER>
<P>For you sir? what colour's siluer I pray, you nere saw mony in your life:—Ile not trust you with him, La∣tronello and Fucato, lay hold vpon him, to your charge I commit him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Furt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, I beseech you sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay if I must be cruell, I will be cruell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Furt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good sir, let me rather goe to prison.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fal.</SPEAKER>
<P>You desire that▪—Ile trust no prison with you, Ile make you lye in mine own house, or Ile know why I shal not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Furt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mercifull sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<L>Since you haue no pittie I will be cruell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Verie good sir, you please vs well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall appeare to morrow sirs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Furt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vpon my kees sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fal.</SPEAKER>
<P>You shall be hang'd out a'th way, away with him Latronello, and Fucato,—Officers I discharge you my house, I like not your companie.</P>
<L>Report me as you see me, fire and fuell,</L>
<L>If men be Iewes, Iustices must be cruell.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>So sir, Extreames set of all Actions thus,</L>
<L>Eyther too tame, or else too tyranous:</L>
<L>He being bent to furie, I doubt now</L>
<L><PB REF="27"/>We shall not gaine accesse vnto your loue or she to vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most wishfully here she comes.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Neece.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is that shee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is she my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoen.</SPEAKER>
<L>A modest presence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vertue blesse you Ladie,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neece.</SPEAKER>
<L>You wish me well sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'de first in charge this kisse, and next this paper,</L>
<L>You'le know the language, tis Fidelios.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neece.</SPEAKER>
<L>My euer vowed loue, how is his health?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<L>As faire as is his fauour with the Prince.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nee.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'me sick with ioy, do's the Prince loue him so?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<L>His life cannot requite it,</L>
<L>Not to wrong the remembrance of his loue,</L>
<L>I had a token for you, kept it safe,</L>
<L>Till by misfortune of the way this morning,</L>
<L>Theeues set vpon this Gentleman and my selfe,</L>
<L>And with the rest robd that.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neece.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh me, I'me deerly sorie for your chance, was it your losse?</L>
<L>They boldly looke you in the face that rob'd you,</L>
<L>No farther villaines then my vncles men.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoen.</SPEAKER>
<L>What Ladie?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neece.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis my griefe I speake so true.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why my Lord?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoen.</SPEAKER>
<L>But giue me pawsing Lady: was hee one that tooke the examination?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neece.</SPEAKER>
<L>One and the chiefe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hence-forth hang him that is no way a theefe,</L>
<P>Then I hope few will suffer,—nay all the iest was, hee committed him to the charge of his fellowes, and the rogue made it lamentable, cryed to leaue'em.</P>
<L>None liue so wise but fooles may once deceiue em?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<L>An vncle so insaciate?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="27"/>
<SPEAKER>Phoen.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, Ist not strange too,</L>
<L>That al should be by Nature vicious, and he bad against</L>
<L>Nature?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neece.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then you haue heard the sum of al my wrongs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lady, we haue, and desire rather now</L>
<L>To heale 'em, then to heare 'em:</L>
<L>For by a letter from Fidelio</L>
<L>Direct to vs, we are entreated ioyntly,</L>
<L>To hasten your remoue▪ from this foule den,</L>
<L>Of theft and purpos'd incest:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neece.</SPEAKER>
<L>I reioyce in his chast care of mee, Ile soone bee furnisht.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<L>He writes that his returne cannot be long.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neece.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'me chiefly glad,—but whither is the place?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoen.</SPEAKER>
<L>To the safe seate of his late wronged mother.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neece.</SPEAKER>
<L>I desire it,—</L>
<L>Her conference will fit mine, well you preuaile,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoen.</SPEAKER>
<L>At next groue weele expect you:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neece.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile not faile.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Knight, and Iewella.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Knig.</SPEAKER>
<L>It stands vpon the frame of my reputation I pro∣test Ladie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iewel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ladie, that worde is worth an hundred Angels at all times, for it cost more: if I liue til tomorrow night, my sweete pleasure thou shalt haue them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<L>Could you not make 'em a hundred and fiftie thinke you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile do my best endeuour to multiply, I assure you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<L>Could you not make 'em two hundred?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<L>No by my faith.—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace, ile rather be confin'd in the hundred &amp; fifty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iewel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come ee'n much about this time, when Ta∣uerns giue vp their Ghosts, and Gentlemen are in their first cast.—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Knig.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile obserue the season.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>And doe but whirle the Ring a'th doore once a∣bout,
<PB REF="28"/>
my maid-seruant shal be taught to vnderstand the language.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<L>Inough my sweet Reuenew.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good rest my effectuall pleasure.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Proditor, and Phoenix.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come hither Phoenix.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>What makes your honour breake so earely?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>A toy, I haue a toy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>A toy my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Prod</HI>:</SPEAKER>
<L>Before thou layest thy wrath vpon the duke,— be aduiz'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Phoe</HI>:</SPEAKER>
<L>I, I, I warran you my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, giue my words honour, heare me,</L>
<L>Ile striue to bring this Act into such forme,</L>
<L>And credite amongst men, they shall suppose.</L>
<L>Nay verily beleeue the Prince his sonne,</L>
<L>To be the plotter of his Fathers murther.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Phoe</HI>:</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh that were infinitely admirable!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wert not, it pleaseth me beyond my blisse:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then if his sonne meet death as he returnes,</L>
<L>Or by my hired Instruments turne vp,</L>
<L>The generall voice will crie—O happy vengeance!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>O blessed vengeance!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, ile turn my braine</L>
<L>Into a thousand vses, Tire my inuentions,</L>
<L>Make my blood sicke with studie, and mine eye</L>
<L>More hollow then my heart, but I will fashion,</L>
<L>Nay I will fashion it,—Canst counterfet?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Princes hand, more truly, most direct,</L>
<L>You shall admire it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Necessarie mischiefe.</L>
<L>Next to a woman, but more close in secrets</L>
<L>Thou'rt all the kinred that my breast vouch safes,</L>
<L>Looke into me anon,—I must frame, and muse, and</L>
<L>fashion—</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Twas time to looke into thee, in whose heart</L>
<L>Treason growes ripe, and therefore fit to fall,</L>
<L>That slaue first sinkes, whose enuie threatens all,</L>
<L>Now is his Venom at full height.</L>
<STAGE>Voices within.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Voic.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Lying, or being in the said Countie in the Te∣nor and occupation aforesaide.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="28"/>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Voyce.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>No more then, a writ of course vpon the mat∣ter of—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3. <HI>Ʋoice.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Silence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>4. <HI>Voice.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Oh o-o-o-yes <HI>Carlo Turbulenzo,</HI> appeare or loose twentie marke in the suites.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Phoe</HI>:</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha? whether haue my thoughts conueyed me? I am now within the Dizzie murmur of the law.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Ʋoyce.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>So that then, the cause being found cleere, vpon the last Scitation.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>4 <HI>Voice.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Carlo turbulenzo,</HI> Come into the Court.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Tangle w̄ith two after him.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now, now, now, now, now, vpon my knees I praise Mercury the God of law, I haue two suits at issue, two suites at issue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe you heare sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tang.</SPEAKER>
<L>I wil not heare, i'ue other busines.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<L>I beseech you my learned Counsell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Beseech not me, beseech not me, I am a mortall man, a Clyent as you are, beseech not me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<P>I would doe all by your worships direction.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tang.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then hang thy selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall I take out a speciall <HI>supplycauit.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mad me not, torment me not, teare me not, youle giue me leaue to heare mine own cause, mine owne cause</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Ʋoice.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Nay moreouer, and farder—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tang.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well said my Lawyer, well saide, well saide.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Ʋoice.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>All the opprobious speeches that man could in∣uent all malicious inuectiues, called Wittoll to his face.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thats I, thats I, thank you my learned counsell for your good remembrance: I hope I shall ouerthrowe him horse and foote.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay but good sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tang:</SPEAKER>
<P>No more sir, he that brings me happy newes first ile releeue first.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Both.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sound executions rot thy cause and thee.</L>
<STAGE><HI>Exeunt</HI>:</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ta:</SPEAKER>
<P>I, I, I, pray so still, pray so still, theile thriue the better</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>I wonder how this fellow keepes out madnes?</L>
<L>What stuffe his braines are made on?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tan.</SPEAKER>
<L>I suffer, I suffer,—till I here a iudgement.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>What old Signior?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="29"/>
<SPEAKER>Tan</SPEAKER>
<P>Prethee I will not knowe thee nowe, tis a busie time, a busie time with me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>What not me Signeur?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh crie thee mercie, giue me thy hande,—fare thee well,—ha's no reliefe agen mee then,—his demurs will not help him, his <HI>Sursararaes</HI> wil but play the knaues with him.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Iustice Falso.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoen.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Iustice: tis hee</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<P>Haue I found thee yfaith? I thought where I should smell thee out old Tangle.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tan.</SPEAKER>
<P>What old Signeur Iusticer,—embrace me another time and you can possible: how do's all thy wiues chil∣dren,—well? that's well said yfayth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heare me olde Tangle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prethee doe not rauish me, let me goe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must vse some of thy counsaile first.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sirrah, I ha brought him to an Exigent▪ hark that's my cause, thats my cause yōder, I twind'g him, I twind'g him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Neece is stolne away.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ah, get mee a <HI>ne exeat Regno</HI> quickly, nay you must not stay vppo'nt, ide faine haue you gone.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<L>A <HI>ne exeat Regno,</HI> ile about it presently,—adue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>You seeke to catch her Iustice, sheele catch you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<L>A iudgement, a iudgement.</L>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> 1.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tang.</SPEAKER>
<L>What, what, what?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<L>Ouerthrowne, ouerthrowne, ouerthrowne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, a, a.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2</SPEAKER>
<L>Newes, newes, newes.</L>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> 2.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tan.</SPEAKER>
<L>The diuell, the diuell, the diuell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2</SPEAKER>
<L>Twice Tangle's ouerthrowne, twice Tangles ouer∣throwne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tang.</SPEAKER>
<L>Holde:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now olde cheater of the Law,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tang.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray giue me leaue to bee madde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou that hast found such sweete pleasure in
<PB REF="29"/>
the vexation of others.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tang.</SPEAKER>
<L>May I not be mad in quiet?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Very Marrow, very manna to thee to be in law.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tang.</SPEAKER>
<L>Very sirrop of Toades, and perseru'd Adders.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou that hast vext, and beggerd the whole</L>
<L>Parrish, and made the honest Church wardens goe to</L>
<L>Lawe with the poores money.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heare me, doe but heare me, I pronounce a terrible, horrible cursse vpon you al—and wish you to my Atturney: see where a <HI>Praemunire</HI> comes a <HI>Dedimus potestatem,</HI> and that moste Dreadful Execution, <HI>Excom∣municato Capiendo,</HI> there's no baile to be taken, I shal rot in fifteene Iayles: make Dice of my bones, and let my Counsellors Sonne play away his Fathers money with e'm; may my bones reuenge my quarrell!— <HI>A Capias Cominus</HI>? heere, heere, heere, heere: quicklye dip your Quilles in my blood, off with my skin and write four∣teen lines of a side—there's an honest conscionable fellowe, he takes but ten shillinges of a Bellowes-men∣der—heere's another deales all with charitie, you shall giue him nothing, onely his wife an embrodered Petty∣coate, a golde frindge for her taile, or a border for her head, ah sirrha! you shall catch mee no more in the sprindge of your Knaueries.</P>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<P>Follow, follow him still, a little thing now sets him forward.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>None can except against him, the mans mad,</L>
<L>And priuiledgd by the Moone, if he say true:</L>
<L>Lesse madnes tis to speake sinne, then to doe.</L>
<L>This wretch that lou'd before, his foode, his strife,</L>
<L>This punishment falles euen with his life.</L>
<L>His pleasure was vexation, all his blisse</L>
<L>The torment of another.</L>
<L>Their heart, his health: their starued hopes his store,</L>
<L>Who so loues Law, dies either mad or poore.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="30"/><HI>Enter Fidelio.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<L>A miracle, a miracle!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now <HI>Fidelio?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord a miracle!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>What ist?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue found</L>
<L>One quiet, suffering, and vnlawyer'd man.</L>
<L>An opposite, a very Contrarie</L>
<L>To the olde turbulent fellowe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why hee's mad.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mad, why he is in his right wits, could he be mad∣der then he was, if he be any way altered from what hee was, tis for the better, my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, but where's this wonder?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis comming my Lord: A man so truely a man, so indifferently a creature, vsing the world in his right nature but to tread vppon, one that would not bruse, the cowardly est enemy to man, the worme, that dares not show his malice till we are dead: nay my Lord, you will admire his temper! see where he comes, I promisd your acquaintance, sir</P>
<STAGE>Enter Quieto.</STAGE>
<L>Yon is the Gentleman I did commend for Temper.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qui.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me embrace you simply.</L>
<L>That's perfectly, and more in heart then hand:</L>
<L>Let affectation keepe at Court.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, let it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis told me you loue quiet</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Aboue wealth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>I aboue life: I haue been wilde and rash</L>
<L>Committed many and vnnaturall crimes,</L>
<L>Which I haue since repented.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Twa's well spent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qui.</SPEAKER>
<L>I was mad, starke mad, nine yeares together.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>I pray! as how?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qui.</SPEAKER>
<L>Going to law, yfaith it made me mad.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="30"/>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>With the like frenzie not an houre since</L>
<L>An aged man was strucke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qui.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alasse I pittie him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hee's not worth pittying, for twa's stil his glad∣nes to be at variance.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qui.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet a mans worth pittie,</L>
<L>My quiet blood ha's blest me with this guift,</L>
<L>I haue cur'd some, and if his wits be not</L>
<L>Too deepely cut, I will assay to helpe e'm.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sufferance does teach you pittie.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter his Boy.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>O Maister, Maister, your abhominable next neighbor came into the house, being halfe in drink, and tooke away your best Carpet.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qui.</SPEAKER>
<L>Has hee it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alasse sir:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qui.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let him goe, trouble him not, lock the doore qui∣etly after him, and haue a safer care who comes in next.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<P>But sir, might I aduize you, in such a cause as this, a man might bouldlye, nay▪ with conscience goe to Law.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qui.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh, ile giue him the table too first. Better indure a fist then a sharpe sword: I had rather they should pull off my cloathes then flea of my skin, and hang that on mine enemies hedge.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, for such good causes was the law ordaind:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qui.</SPEAKER>
<L>True, and in it selfe tis glorious and deuine,</L>
<L>Law is the verie Maister peece of heauen:</L>
<L>But see yonder.</L>
<L>Ther's many Clowdes betweene the sunne and vs,</L>
<L>There's too much cloath before we see the Law:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'me content with that answere, be milde still,</L>
<L>Tis honour to forgiue those you could kill.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quie.</SPEAKER>
<L>There doe I keepe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Reach me your hand, I loue you,</L>
<L>And you shall knowe me better.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis my sute.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="31"/>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>The night growes deepe—and—</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter two Officers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Off</HI>:</SPEAKER>
<L>Come away, this way, this way.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who be those? stand close a little.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Iars the Ring of the Doore, the Maide enters catches him.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Maid.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh, y'are come as well as ere you came in your life, my Maister's new gone to bed, giue me your Knightly hand, I must leade you into the blind Parlor, my mistris will be downe to you presentlye.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Takes in Phoenix, amazde.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Off.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>I tell you our safest course will bee to arrest him when hee comes out a'th Tauerne: for then he will bee halfe drunke, and will not stand vppon his weapon.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2</SPEAKER>
<L>Our safest course indeede, for hee will drawe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<P>That he will, though he put it vp agen, which is more of his courtesie, then of our deseruing.</P>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qui.</SPEAKER>
<L>The world is nothing but vexation,</L>
<L>Spite and vncharitable Action.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did you see the Gentleman?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qui.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where should he be, it may be hee's past by,</L>
<L>Good sir, lets ouertake him.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Phoenix with the Maide.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Maid.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here sir, now you are there sir, sheele come downe to you instantlye, I must not stay with you, my Mistris would be iealous, you must doe nothing to me, my mistris would finde it quickly.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<P>S'foot whether am I led? brought in byth hand? I hope it can bee no harme to stay for a woman, tho in∣deede they were neuer more dangerous, I haue ventu∣red heatherto and safe, and I must venture to stay now, this should be a faire Rome, but I see it not, the blinde Parlor cal's shee it?</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Iewell.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where art thou, O my Knight!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="31"/>
<SPEAKER><HI>Phoe</HI>:</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Knight, I am the Dukes knight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<L>I say you'r my knight, for I'me sure I paid for you</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Paid for you hum,—S'foot a light.—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now out vpon the Marmoset, hast thou seru'd me so long, and offer to bring in a Candle?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Phoe</HI>:</SPEAKER>
<P>Faire Roome, villanous face, and worse woman, I ha learnt something by a glimpse ath Candle:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>How hapned it you came so soone, I lookt not for you these two howers: yet as the sweete chance is, you came as well as a thing coulde come, for my hus: band's newly brought a bed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>And what ha's Ioue sent him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hee nere sent him any thing since I knewe him, hee's a man of a bad nature to his wife, none but his Maides can thriue vnder him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Out vpon him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, iudge whether I haue a cause to be a Curtezan or no? to doe as I doe, an elderly fellow as hee is, if hee were marryed to a young Virgin, hee were able to breake her heart, tho he could breake nothing else: here, here, there's iust a hundred and fiftie, but I stole e'm so hardlye from him, twold ee'ne haue grieud you to haue seene it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe</SPEAKER>
<L>So twould yfaith.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>Therefore prethee my sweete pleasure, doe not keepe company so much, how doe you thinke I am a∣ble to maintaine you? though I bee a Iewellers wife, Iewells are like women, they rise &amp; fal, we must be con∣tent to loose sometimes, to gaine often, but you'r content alwaies to loose, and neuer to gaine: what need you ride with a Footeman before you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe:</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh thats the grace,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iewe.</SPEAKER>
<P>The grace? tis sufficient grace that y'aue a Horse to ride vpon, you should thinke thus with your selfe e∣uery time you goe to bed if my head were laide, what would become of that horse? he would runne a bad race then as well as his Maister.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="32"/>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, and you giue me money to chide me:—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iewel.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, if it were as much more, I would thinke it foule scorne to chide you, I aduise you to be thrifty, to take the time now, while you haue it, you shall sildome get such an other foole as I am, I warrant you: why there's Mettrezza Auriola keepes her loue with halfe the cost that I am at, her friend can goe a foote like a good Husband, walke in wosted Stockings, and enquire for the Six-penny ordinarie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pox on't, and would you haue me so base?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, I would not haue you so base neither: but now and then, when you keep your Chamber, you might let your Footeman out for eighteen pence a day, a great releefe at yeares end I can tell you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ph.</SPEAKER>
<L>The age must needs be foule when vice reformes it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, I'ue a greater quarrell to you yet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yfaith, what ist?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iewe.</SPEAKER>
<P>You made me beleeue at first the Prince had you in great estimation, and would not offer to Trauaile without you, nay, that he could not trauaile without your Direction and intelligence.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<P>I'me sorrie I saide so yfaith, but sure I was ouer∣flowen when I spoke it, I could nere ha saide it else.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay more, you swore to me, that you were the first that taught him to ride a greate horse, and tread the Ring with agilitie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<P>By my troth I must needes confesse I swore a great lye in that, &amp; I was a villain to doe it, for I could nere ride greate horse in my life.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iewl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why loe, who would loue you now but a Citti∣zens wife? so inconstant, so for sworne: you say women are false Creatures, but take away men, and thei'd bee honester then you—Nay last of all, which offends me moste of all, you tolde me you covld countenance me at Court, and you knowe wee esteeme a friend there, more
<PB REF="32"/>
worth then a Husband heere.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>What I spake of that. Lady, ile maintaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew:</SPEAKER>
<L>You maintaine? you seene it court?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why by this Diamond—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh take heede, you cannot haue that, tis alwaies in the eye of my husband.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<P>I protest I will not keepe it, but onely vse it for th is vertue, as a token to fetch you,&amp; approue my pow∣er, where you shall not onely ye bee receiued, but made knowne to the best and chiefest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iewel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh are you true?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me loose my Reuenewe else.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iewl.</SPEAKER>
<P>That's your word indeede, and vppon that con∣dition take it this kisse and my loue for euer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ynough.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Giue me thy hand, ile leade thee foorth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'me sicke of al professions, my thoughts burne:</L>
<L>He trauailes best, that knowes when to returne.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Knight, two Officers after him.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Adue, farwell, to bed you, I to my sweete Citty∣bird, my precious Reuennew, the verie thought of a hundred &amp; fiftie Angels, encreases Oyle and Spirit, ho:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Off.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>I arrest you sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Knig.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Off.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>You haue made vs wayte a goodly time for you, haue you not thinke you? you are in your Rowses &amp; Mulwines a poxe on you: and haue no care of poore Officers staying for you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>I drunk but one health I protest, but I could void it now: at whose sute I pra'y?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Off.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>At the sute of him that makes suits, your Taylor,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, he made me the last, this, this that I weare</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.<HI>Off.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Argo,</HI> nay, we haue bene Schollars I can tell you, wee could not haue beene knaues so soone else, for as in that notable Cittie cald London, stand two most famous Vniuersities, <HI>Poultrie</HI> and <HI>Woodstreet,</HI> where some are of
<PB REF="33"/>
twentie yeares standing, and haue tooke all their de∣grees from the Maisters side, downe to the Mistris side, the Hole, so in like manner—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Knig.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come, come, come, I had quite forgot the hun∣dred and fiftie Angells.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Off.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>S'lid where be they?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Knight.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile bring you to the sight of e'm presently.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Off.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>A notable Lad, and worthy to be arrested: weele haue but ten for wayting, and then thou shalt chuse whether thou wilt runne away from vs, or wee from thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Knight.</SPEAKER>
<L>A match at running, come, come, followe me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Off.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, feare not that.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Knig.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace, you may happen to see toyes, but doe not see e'm.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Off.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Pah.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Knig.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thats the Doore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Off.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>This?—<HI>knockes.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Knight.</SPEAKER>
<L>S foote Officer you haue spoilde all already?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Off.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Why?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Knig.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why? you shall see, you should haue but whirld the ring once about, and there's a Maid seruant brought vp to vnderstand it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Maide.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whose at doore?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Knig.</SPEAKER>
<L>Als well againe: phist, tis I, tis I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Maid.</SPEAKER>
<L>You, what are you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<L>Puh, where's thy mistris?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Maid.</SPEAKER>
<L>What of her?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Knigh.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tell her One, she knowes who, her <HI>Pleasure's</HI> heere, say.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Maid.</SPEAKER>
<P>Her <HI>Pleasure</HI>? my mistris scornes to be without her pleasure at this time of night: is shee so voide of friendes thinke you? take that for thinking so: <HI>a Boxe</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Off.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>The hundred and fifty Angells are lockt vp in a Boxe, we shall not see e'm tonight.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Knig.</SPEAKER>
<P>Howe's this? am I vsde like a hundred pound
<PB REF="33"/>
Gentleman? Do's my Reuennew forsake me? Dam me if euer I bee her pleasure agen.— Well I must to prison.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Off.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Goe prepare his roome, there's no remedie, ile bring him along, hee's tame enough now.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dare my Tailor presume to vse me in this sort?</L>
<L>He steales and I must lie in prison for't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Off.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Come, come away sir.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter a Gentleman with a Drawer.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gent.</SPEAKER>
<L>Art sure thou sawest him arested Drawer?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Draw.</SPEAKER>
<L>If mine eyes be sober.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gent.</SPEAKER>
<P>And that's a question, Masse here he goes, hee shall not goe to prison, I haue a tricke shall baile him— away.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Off.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Oh!</L>
<STAGE>Blinds the officer.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gent.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gesse, gesse, who am I? who am I?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Off.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Who the Diuell are you? let goe, — a Poxe on you, who are you? I haue lost my prisoner.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gentle.</SPEAKER>
<P>Prisoner: I'ue mistooke, I crie you hear∣tily mercie, I haue done you infinite iniurie, a my troth I tooke you to be an honest man.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Off.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Where were your eyes? could you not see I was an Officer, stop, stop, stop, stop.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gent.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hah, hah, hah, ha.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Proditor and Phoenix.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now Phoenix.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let princely blood</L>
<L>Nourish our hopes, we being confusion now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoen.</SPEAKER>
<L>A terrible suddaine blow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>I:what day is this hangs ouer vs?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bith Masse Monday.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>As I could wish my purpose will thriue best.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="34"/>
<L>Twa's first my birthday, now my fortunes daie,</L>
<L>I see whome fate will raise needes neuer pray.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Neuer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>How is the ayre?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh full of trouble.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Prod</HI>:</SPEAKER>
<L>Do's not the skie looke pittiously blacke</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>As if twere hung with Rich mens Consciences.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ah, Stucke not a Comet like a Carbuckle</L>
<L>Vpon the dreadfull browe of Twelue last night?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Twelue, no twa's about one.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>About one most proper, for thats the Duke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well shifted from thy selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>I could haue wisht it betweene one and two</L>
<L>His sonne and him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile giue you comfort then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod,</SPEAKER>
<L>Prethee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>There was a villanous Rauen seene last night,</L>
<L>Ouer the presence chamber in hard Iustle</L>
<L>With a yong Eglet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Rauen! that was I, what did the Rauen?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mary my Lord the Rauen—to say truth,</L>
<L>I left the combat doubtfull.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>So tis still,</L>
<L>For all is doubt, till the deed crowne the will,</L>
<L>Now blesse thy loynes with Freedome, wealth and honour,</L>
<L>Think all thy seede young Lords, and by this Acte.</L>
<L>Make a foote-cloathd posteritie: now imagine</L>
<L>Thou seest thy Daughters with their traines borne vp,</L>
<L>Whome else despised want, may cursse to whoredome,</L>
<L>And publike shames, which our state neuer threate,</L>
<L>Shee's neuer lew'd, that is accounted great.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile alter that Court-Axiom▪ thus renewd,</L>
<L>Shee's neuer great, that is accounted lewde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stand close, the presence fils, heere, heere the place</L>
<L>And at his rizing, let his fall be base,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="34"/>
<L>Beneath thy foote.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>How for his Guard my Lord?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>My golde and feare keepes with the chiefe of them</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's rarely well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Bould heedlesse slaue, that dares attempt a deede which shall in peeces rend him my Lords both.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Lussurioso, and Infesto two Lords.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lus.</SPEAKER>
<L>The happinesse of the day.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Time my returning,</L>
<L>Treasons haue still the worst, yet still are spurning.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Duke!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>I nere was gladder to beholde him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>All.</HI> Long liue your Grace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>I do not like that straine,</L>
<L>You know my age affoords not to liue long.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Spoke truer then you thinke for.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bestow that wish vpon the Prince our Sonne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe,</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, hee's not to liue long neither.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Him as the wealthie Treasure of our hopes,</L>
<L>You as posession of our present Comfort,</L>
<L>Both in one heart, we reuerence in one.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh Treason of a good cōplexion.</L>
<STAGE>Horn winded.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Fidelio.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now, what fresher newes fils the Courts eare?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod,</SPEAKER>
<L>Fidelio!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Glad Tydings to your Grace,</L>
<L>The prince is safe return'd, and in your Court.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our ioy breakes at our eyes, the Prince is come!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Soule qucking newes—pale vengeance to my blood.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<L>By me presenting to your serious view,</L>
<L>A briefe of all his Trauailes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis most welcome.</L>
<L>It shall be Deere and pretious to our Eye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="35"/>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee Reades, i'me glad her reades.</L>
<L>Now take thyopportunitie, leaue that place.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>At hys first rising let his fall be base.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>That must be altered now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Which? his rising or his fall?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>rod.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Art thou dull now?</L>
<L>Thou hear'st the Prince is come.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's heere my Lord?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<P>I have got such a large portion of knowledge, most worthy father, by the benefit of my Trauaile,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>And so he has no doubt my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>That I am bolde now to warne you of Lord</L>
<P>Proditors insolent Treason, who has irreligiouslye se∣duc'd a fellow, and closely conuaide him ee'n in the pre∣sence-chaire to murder you:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh guiltie, guiltie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>What was that fell? whats hee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoen.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am the man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>O slaue!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue no power to strike,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'me gone, i'me gone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me admire heauen's wisdome in my Sonne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>I confesse it, he hyred me—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is slaue,</L>
<L>Tis forg'd against mine honour and my life,</L>
<L>For in what part of reason can't appeare,</L>
<L>The Prince being Trauaild should know Treasons heere</L>
<L>Plaine counterfet—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doost thou make false our Sonne?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know the prince will not affirme it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<L>He can and will my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most iust, he may:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>A guard.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luss.</SPEAKER>
<L>We cannot but in loyall zeale our selues,</L>
<L>Lay hands on such a Villaine.—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay you, I finde you heere too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="35"/>
<SPEAKER>Lus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vs my Lord?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<P>Against <HI>Lussurioso</HI> and <HI>Infesto,</HI> who not onelye moste ryotouslye consume their houses in vicious ga∣ming, morgaging their liuings to the Merchant, wher∣by he with his heires enter vppon their lands, from whence this abuse comes, that in short time the Sonne of the Marchant has more Lordships then the Sonne of the Nobleman(which else was neuer borne to inheri∣tance) but that which is more impious, they most adul∣terously traine out young Ladyes to Mid-night ban∣quets, to the vtter defamation of their owne honors, &amp; ridiculous abuse of their Husbands.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lus.</SPEAKER>
<L>How could the Prince heare that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most true my Lord.</L>
<L>My Conscience is a witnesse gainst it selfe,</L>
<L>For to that execution of chast honour,</L>
<L>I was both hyr'd and led.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lus.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hope the Prince out of his plentious wisdome</L>
<L>Will not giue wrong to vs: as for this fellowe</L>
<L>Hee's poore, and cares not to be desperate.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Iustice Falso.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Iustice my Lord, I haue my Neece stolne from me</L>
<L>Sh'as left her Dowrie with me, but shee's gone,</L>
<L>Ide rather haue had her loue then her money I,</L>
<L>This, this, is one of them, Iustice my Lord:</L>
<L>I know him by his face, this is the Theefe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your grace may now in milder sence perceiue</L>
<L>The wrong done to vs by this impudent wretch,</L>
<L>Who ha's his hand fixt at the throate of lawe,</L>
<L>And therefore durst be desperate of his life,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duk.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace, you'r too foule, your crime is in excesse:</L>
<L>One spot of him, makes not your Vlcers lesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duk</SPEAKER>
<L>Did your Violence force away his <HI>Neece?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>No my good Lord; ilestil confesse whats truth.</L>
<L><PB REF="36"/>I did remoue her from her many wrongs,</L>
<L>Which shee was pleasd to leaue, they were so vilde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>What are you nam'd?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<L>Falso my Lord, Iustice Falso, i'me knowne by that name.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Falso, you came fitly,</L>
<L>You are the verie next that followes here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hope so my Lord, my name is in all the Records</L>
<L>I can assure your good grace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Against Iustice Falso.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ah.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who hauing had the honest charge of his Neece committed to his trust, by the last will and Test∣ament of her deceased father, and with her all the pow∣er of his wealth, not onely against faith and conscience detaines her Dowrie, but against Nature and humanity assaies to abuse her body.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neece.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'me present to affirme it my lou'd Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<L>How? what make I heere?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neece.</SPEAKER>
<L>Eyther I must agree.</L>
<L>To loathed lust, or despisde beggery.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you the plaintiue here?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<L>I my good Lord,</L>
<L>For fault of a better.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sildome comes a worse—and moreouer not containde in this vice onelye, which is odious to much, but against the sacred vse of Iustice, maintaines three threeues to his men.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cuds me!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who onely take Pursses in their Maisters liber∣tie, where if any one chance to be taken, he appeares be∣fore him in a false Beard, and owne of his owne fellows takes his examination.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<L>By my troth as true as can be, but hee shall not knowe on't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<P>And in the end will execute Iustice so cruellye vpon him, that hee will not trust him in a prison, but
<PB REF="36"/>
commit him to his fellowes chamber.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<P>Can a man doe nothing i'the Countrey but tis told at Court? there's some busie informing knaue a∣broad, a my life.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>That this is true, and these, and more my Lord.</L>
<L>(Be it vnder pardon spoken for mine owne)</L>
<L>Hee the disease of Iustice, these of honour,</L>
<L>And This of Loyaltie and Reuerence:</L>
<L>The vnswept venome of the Pallace,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Slaue!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Behold the Prince to approoue it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, where?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Eyes keep with your Actions, both looke wrong.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>An infernall to my spirit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord the Prince:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tread me to dust, thou in whō wonder keepes,</L>
<L>Behold the Serpent on his bellie creepes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ranckle not my foote, away.</L>
<L>Treason, we laugh at thy vain-labouring strings,</L>
<L>Aboue the foote thou hast no power ore Kings</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>I cannot with sufficient ioy receiue thee,</L>
<L>And yet my ioye's too much,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoen.</SPEAKER>
<L>My royall Father,</L>
<L>To whose vnnaturall murther I was hir'd,</L>
<L>I thought it a more naturall course of trauaile,</L>
<L>And answering future expectation,</L>
<L>To leaue farre Countryes, and enquire mine owne,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duk.</SPEAKER>
<L>To thee let Reuerence all her powers en∣gage,</L>
<L>That art in youth a myracle to age.</L>
<L>State is but blindness, ethou hadst piercing Art,</L>
<L>We onely saw the knee; but thou the heart.</L>
<L>To thee then power and Dukedome we resigne,</L>
<L>▪Hee's fit to raign, whose knowledge can refine:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Forbid it my obedience.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="37"/>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our word's not vaine,</L>
<L>I know thee wise can'st both obey and raigne,</L>
<L>The rest of life we dedicate to heauen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<L>A happy and safe raigne to our new Duke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Without your praiers safer, &amp; happier: Fidelio.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<L>My royall Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here take this Diamond:</L>
<L>You know the vertue on't, it can fetch vice:</L>
<L>Madam Castiza:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Fid</HI>:</SPEAKER>
<L>She attends my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Place a guard neare vs.</L>
<L>Know you you fellow Ladie?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lad.</SPEAKER>
<L>My honours euill.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Torment agen?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoen.</SPEAKER>
<L>So vgly are thy crimes,</L>
<L>Thine eye cannot endure 'em.</L>
<L>And that thy face may stand perpetually</L>
<L>Turn'd so from ours, and thy abhorred selfe,</L>
<L>Neither to threaten wracke of state or credite,</L>
<L>An euerlasting banishment ceaze on thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh Fiend!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy life is such it is too bad to end.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>May thy Rule, life, and all that's in thee glad,</L>
<L>Haue as short time—as thy begetting had.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Away, thy curse is idle, the rest are vnder refor∣mation, and therefore vnder pardon.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<P>Our duties shall turne edge vpon our crimes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fals.</SPEAKER>
<P>S'lid I was afraid of nothing, but that for my thee∣uerie, and bawderie I should haue beene turnd to an In∣keeper: my daughter, I am asham'd her worship should see mee.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Iewell: with Fidelio..</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who would not loue a friend at Court? what fine Galleries and roomes am I brought through? I had thoght my knight durst not haue shown his face here, I.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now mother of pride, and daughter of lust, which is your friend now?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ah me!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="37"/>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<P>I'me sure you are not so vnprouided to be with∣out a friend here, you'le pay enough for him first.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is the worst roome that euer I came in.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoen.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am your seruant Mistris, know you not me!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your worship is to great for me to know: I'me but a small timbred-woman when I'me out of my apparell, and dare not venture vpon greatnes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe you denie me then? know you this purse?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>That purse? O death has the Knight seru'd me so? giuen away my Fauours?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stand forth—thou one of those, for whose close lusts the plague neuer leaues the Citie.</L>
<L>Thou worse then common: priuate, subtill harlot,</L>
<L>That dost deceiue Three with one faigned lip,</L>
<L>Thy husband, the worlds eye, and the lawes whip.</L>
<L>Thy zeale is hot, for tis to lust and frawde,</L>
<L>And dost not dread to make thy booke thy Bawde,</L>
<L>Thou'rt cursse enough to husbands il-got gaines,</L>
<L>For whom the Court reiects, his gold maintaines:</L>
<L>How deere and rare was Freedome wont to be,</L>
<L>Now few but are by their wiues copies free,</L>
<L>And brought to such a head that now we see,</L>
<L>Citie and Suburbs weare one liuerie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis long of those, an't like your grace, that come in vpon vs, &amp; wil neuer leaue marrying of our widdows till they make 'em all as free as their first husbands.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoen.</SPEAKER>
<L>I perceiue you can shift a point well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let me haue pardon I beseech your grace, and Ile peach 'em all, all the close women that are, and vpon my knowledge there's aboue fiue thousand within the walls and the liberties.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoen.</SPEAKER>
<P>A band▪ they shall be sent against the Turke, Infidels against Infidels.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will hereafter liue so modestly, I will not lie with mine owne husband, nor come neere a man in the way of honestie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="38"/>
<SPEAKER>Fal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile be her warrant my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoen.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are deceiu'd, you thinke y' are stil a Iustice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fal.</SPEAKER>
<P>S'foot, worse then I was before I kneeld, I am no Iustice now, I know I shall be some Inne-keeper at last.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<L>My father! tis mine owne father.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoen.</SPEAKER>
<L>I should haue wondred else, lust being so like.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neece</SPEAKER>
<P>Her birth was kin to mine, she may proue mo∣dest, for my sake I beseech you pardon her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoen.</SPEAKER>
<L>For thy sake Ile doe more, Fidelio hand her,</L>
<L>My fauours on you both, next all that wealth</L>
<L>Which was committed to that Periur'ds trust.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fal.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'me a begger now, worse then an Inne-keeper.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Tangle madde.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your <HI>Mittimus</HI> shall not serue, Ile set my selfe free with a <HI>Deliberandum,</HI> with a <HI>Deliberandum,</HI> marke you:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's he? a guard!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vnder your sufferance, worthy Father,</L>
<L>His harme is to himselfe,</L>
<L>One that ha's lou'd vexation so much,</L>
<L>He cannot now be rid on't,</L>
<L>Has beene so long in suits that hee's Law-mad.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tang.</SPEAKER>
<P>A iudgement, I craue a iudgement, yea! <HI>Nunc pro tunc, Corruptione alicuius,</HI> I peept me a Rauen in the face, and I thought it had beene my Solister: oh the pens pricke me.</P>
<STAGE>Enter Quieto.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoen.</SPEAKER>
<L>And here comes he (wonder for temperance:)</L>
<L>Will take the cure vpon him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quie.</SPEAKER>
<L>A blessing to this faire assembly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Awa, yile haue none ont, giue me an <HI>Audita que∣rela,</HI> or a <HI>Testificandum,</HI> or a dispatch in twelue Tearms, there's a blessing, there's a blessing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoen.</SPEAKER>
<L>You see the vnbounded rage of his disease,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quie.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis the foule fiend my Lord ha's got within him the rest are faire to this, this breeds in Inke,</P>
<L>And to that colour turnes the blood possest,</L>
<L>For instance, now your grace shall see him drest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="38"/>
<SPEAKER>Tan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ah hah I reioice then hee's puzled▪ &amp; muzled too Ist come to a <HI>Soepe corpus?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ah, good sir, this is for want of patience.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tang.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's a foole.</L>
<L>She neuer saw the Dogs and the Beares fight,</L>
<L>A Countrey thing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quie.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is for lacke of grace,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tan.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'ue other businesse, not so much idle time.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quie.</SPEAKER>
<L>You neuer say your prayers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tan.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'me, aduizde by my learned counsel,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quie.</SPEAKER>
<L>The power of my charme come o're thee,</L>
<L>Place by degrees thy wits before thee,</L>
<L>With silk en patience here I binde thee,</L>
<L>Not to moue till I vnwinde thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yea! is my cause so muddy? do I sticke, do I sticke (fast?</L>
<L>Aduocate heer's my hand, pull, art made of flint?</L>
<L>Wilt not helpe out?—alas there's nothing in't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh doe you sluce the Veyne now?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes my honoured Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray let me see the issue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quie.</SPEAKER>
<L>I therefore seeke to keepe it,—now burst out</L>
<L>Thou filthy streame of trouble, spite and doubt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh an extent, a <HI>Proclamation,</HI> a <HI>Summons,</HI> a <HI>Re∣cognisance,</HI> a <HI>Tachment.</HI> and <HI>Iniunction,</HI> a <HI>Writ,</HI> a <HI>Seysure, a Writ of praeisement,</HI> an <HI>Absolution,</HI> a <HI>Quietus est.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qui.</SPEAKER>
<L>You'r quieter I hope by so much Dreggs.</L>
<L>Beholde my Lord:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoen.</SPEAKER>
<L>This, why it out frownes Inke:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quie.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis the diseases Nature, the Fiends drinke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh sicke, sick, Signior Ply-fee, sicke: lend me thy Nightcap, oh!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quie.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Balsum of a temperate braine,</L>
<L>I poure into this thirstie veine,</L>
<L>And with this blessed oyle of quiet,</L>
<L>Which is so cheape, that few men buy it,</L>
<L>Thy stormie Temples I allay,</L>
<L><PB REF="39"/>Thou shalt giue vp the Diuell and pray,</L>
<L>Forsake his works, the'yre foule and black,</L>
<L>And keepe thee bare in pursse and backe.</L>
<L>No more shalt thou in paper quarrell,</L>
<L>To dresse vp Apes in good apparell.</L>
<L>He throwes his stocke, and all his flocke,</L>
<L>Into a swallowing gulfe,</L>
<L>That sendes his Goose vnto his Foxe,</L>
<L>His Lambe vnto his Wolfe.</L>
<L>Keepe thy encrease,</L>
<L>And liue at peace,</L>
<L>For war's not equall to this battaile,</L>
<L>That eates but men this men and cattaile,</L>
<L>Therefore no more this combate choose:</L>
<L>Where he that wins, do's alwayes loose,</L>
<L>And those that gaine all, with this cursse receiue it,</L>
<L>From fooles they get it, to their sonnes they leaue it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Haile sacred patience, I begin to feele</L>
<P>I haue a Conscience now, Truth in my words, Compas∣sion in my hart, &amp; aboue al, in my blood peaces musick,</P>
<L>Vse me how you can,</L>
<L>You shall find me an honest-quiet man.</L>
<L>Oh, pardon, that I dare behold that face,</L>
<L>"Now I'ue least law, I hope haue most grace,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoen.</SPEAKER>
<L>We both admire the work-man and his peece:</L>
<L>Thus when all hearts are tunde to Honors strings,</L>
<L>There is no musicke to the Quire of Kings.</L>
</SP>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
<BACK>
<DIV1 TYPE="prologue">
<PB REF="39"/>
<HEAD>Prologus</HEAD>
<L>THe markes and notions extant in each spirit,</L>
<L>Seald by th'industrious hand of art &amp; merit,</L>
<L>Me thinkes appeare transparant (as the minde</L>
<L>By fence were bounded and might seeme confind</L>
<L>In th' externall eye) nor shall our tragicke muse,</L>
<L>(If strong hope faile not) need a coynd excuse</L>
<L>But to those marginall noates of yours do bring</L>
<L>(In following nombers from the learned spring)</L>
<L>Matter instructiue to inrich their parts</L>
<L>Where knowledge raignes crownd with it own desarts,</L>
<L>Let such with serious and impartiall hearing</L>
<L>Sound sence, quicke sight and iudgement neuer erring:</L>
<L>Suruay and censure the mineruall frame</L>
<L>Of his elaborate worke: and if his name</L>
<L>Merrit regard, and you vouchsafe to grace him</L>
<L>With eminent loue, or mongstthose lawreats place him,</L>
<L>That with the magicke of sweet poesie,</L>
<L>Transfer <HI>Pernassus</HI> into Brittany,</L>
<L>He shall digest the Chaos of his braine,</L>
<L>To tunefull order and acquire a straine,</L>
<L>Neere to the musicke of the heauenly spheres,</L>
<L>To fit Times guard and rauish choysest eares.</L>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="epilogue">
<PB REF="40"/>
<HEAD>Epilogus.</HEAD>
<L>FAme and Opinion like the two vvingd cap</L>
<L>On <HI>Hermes</HI> head, do lift all Poets vp:</L>
<L>Some, though deseruing, yet aboue the Sphere</L>
<L>Of true impartiall censure, vvhose tun'd eare</L>
<L>Listens to all and can vvith iudgement say,</L>
<L>Others sing vvell, though <HI>Thracian Orpheus</HI> play.</L>
<L>Our Muse affects no excellence: if Fame tell</L>
<L>And through her shrill trompe at the Muses well</L>
<L>(Where the thrice trebled bench of learning sits</L>
<L>In strict examination of others wits)</L>
<L>Sound ours, thogh humbly straines, whose infant growth</L>
<L>Nor dares, nor will, with times hugd darlings quarrell,</L>
<L>Nor stand the lightning with the sacred Lawrell)</L>
<L>We rest content: yet thus farre may conceipt</L>
<L>Carry each labouring Artist, where the weight</L>
<L>Of his oyld taske is ouer, that his tongue</L>
<L>May like a father of his tender young</L>
<L>Speak natures language and not be withstood,</L>
<L>When with our Muse he saith, that <HI>This is good.</HI></L>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="note">
<P>This <HI>Epilogue</HI> should haue bene printed at the end of the booke, but there was no spare place for it.</P>
<PB REF="40"/>
</DIV1>
</BACK>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

