<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2004-08-06</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Rachel Losh</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Checked for N=""s. Checked for GROUP tags. Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, CLOSER, OPENER, ARGUMENT, EPIGRAPH, SIGNED, BYLINE, etc.). Checked for signatures. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, and UNCLEARs. Corrected ** $s and $word$s etc. of **. Converted __ $$s to GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="[vendor name]". Checked spacing of foreign GAPs. Checked for LBs. Checked for startqs, endqs, oes, q;s, and Qs. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Checked for FIGUREs and decorated initials. Checked for missing-page GAPs. Revalidated. </ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A07528">
<STC T="S">17911A</STC>
<BIBNO T="oclc">24785945</BIBNO>
<VID>27874</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>A Faire Quarrell.</P>
<P>With new Additions of M<SUP>r</SUP>. <HI>Chaughs</HI> and <HI>Trimtrams</HI> Roaring, and the Bauds Song. Neuer before Printed.</P>
<P>As it was Acted before the King, by the Prince his Highnesse Seruants.</P>
<P>Written by <HI>Thomas Midleton,</HI> and <HI>William Rowley.</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Gent.</NOTE></P>
<P><FIGURE>
</FIGURE></P>
<P>Printed at London for <HI>I. T.</HI> and are to be sold at Christ Church Gate. 1617.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="2" MS="y"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>TO THE NOBLY DIS∣posed, vertuous, and faithfull-brest∣ed <HI>Robert Grey</HI> Esquire, one of the Grooms of his Highnesse Bed-Chamber, his poore Well-willer, wisheth his best wishes. Hic es Supra.</HEAD>
<LETTER>
<OPENER><SALUTE>Worthy Sir,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">T</SEG>Is but a Play, and a Play is but a Butt, against which ma∣ny shoote many Arrowes of Enuy, 'tis the weaker Part, and how much more noble shall it be in you to defend it, yet if it be (as some Philosophers haue left behind'um) that this Megac<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sme, this great world, is no more then a Stage, where euery one must act his part, you shall of necessity haue many part∣takers, some long, some short, some indifferent, all some, whilst indeed the Players themselues haue


<PB REF="3"/>
the least part of it, for I know few that haue lands, (which are a part of the World) and therefore no grounded men, but how soeuer they serue for mutes, happily they must weare good cloathes for atten∣dance, yet all haue exits and must all be stript in the Tyring-house (<HI>viz,</HI> the graue) for none must carry anything out of the stocke, you see Sir, I write as I speak, &amp; I speak as I am, &amp; thats excuse enough for me. I did not meane to write an Epistle of praise to you, it lookes so like a thing, (I know) you loue not <HI>Flattery,</HI> which you exceedingly hate actiuely, and vnpleasingly accept passiuely: indeed I meant to tell you your owne, that is, that this child of the Mu∣ses is yours, who euer begat it, tis laid to your charge and (for ought I know) you must father and keep it too, if it please you, I hope you shall not bee asham'd of it neither for it has beene seene (though I say it) in good companies, and many haue said it is a hand∣some pretty spoken infant, now be your owne iudge, at your leasure looke on it, at your pleasure laugh at it, and if you be sorry it is no better you may be glad it is no bigger.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED><HI>Yours euer.</HI> William Rowley.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</LETTER>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="play">
<PB REF="3"/>
<HEAD>A Faire Quarrell.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus primus, Scaena prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Master Russell Solus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Russell</HI>:</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>IT must be all my eare; theres all my loue,</L>
<L>And that pulls on the tother, had I beene left</L>
<L>In a sonne behind me, while I had beene here</L>
<L>He should haue shifted as I did before him;</L>
<L>Liu'd on the freeborne portion of his wit:</L>
<L>But a daughter, and that an onely one, oh▪</L>
<L>We cannot be to carefull ore, to tender,</L>
<L>Tis such a brittle nicenes: a meere cubbord of glasses,</L>
<L>The least shake breakes, or crakes em; all my aime is</L>
<L>To cast her vpon riches: thats the thing</L>
<L>We richmen call perfection, for the world</L>
<L>Can perfect nought without it, 'tis not neatnesse</L>
<L>Either in handsome wit; or handsome outside</L>
<L>With which one gentleman (far indebt) has courted her</L>
<L>Which boldnes he shall rue. He thinkes me blind,</L>
<L>And ignorant, I haue let him play along time,</L>
<L>Seem'd to beleiue his worth; which I know nothing.</L>
<L>He may perhaps laugh at my easie confidence</L>
<L>Which closely I requite vpon his fondnesse.</L>
<L>For this houre, snaps him; and before his Mistris</L>
<L>His Saint forsooth, which he inscribes my girle,</L>
<L>He shall be rudely taken and disgract,</L>
<L>The trick will proue an euerlasting Scarcrow,</L>
<L>To fright poore gallants from our rich-mens daughters,</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Enter the Lady Ager, with two seruants.</STAGE>
<LG>
<L>Sister? Iue such a ioy to make you a well-come of,</L>
<L>Better you neuer tasted.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady,</SPEAKER>
<L>Good sir spare it not,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="4"/>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Colonells</HI> come, &amp; your son Captaine <HI>Ager</HI>;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>My sonne! <STAGE>— <HI>she weepes</HI>:</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I know your eye would be first seru'd,</L>
<L>Thats the soules taster still for griefe, or ioy,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Oh if a mothers deare suit may preuaile with him,</L>
<L>From England; he shall neuer partagen,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<L>No question he'le be ruld, and grant you that,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile bring all my desires to that request.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Lady and her Seruants.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Affectionate sister, she ha's no daughter now</L>
<L>It followes all the loue must come to him,</L>
<L>And he has a worth deserues it, were it dearer.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter a friend of the Colonells, and another of Captaine Agers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colo. Frien.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must not giue way too't,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whats here to question,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col. Frie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Compare young Captaine <HI>Ager,</HI> with the <HI>Colonel,</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap. Fri.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yong? why, doe you make youth stand for an im∣putation: that which you now produce for his disgrace,</L>
<L>Infers his noblenes, that being young</L>
<L>Should haue an anger more enclind to courage</L>
<L>And moderation then the <HI>Colonell:</HI></L>
<L>A vertue as rare as chastety in youth.</L>
<L>And let the cause be good; (conscience in him</L>
<L>Which euer crownes his acts, and is indeed,</L>
<L>Valours prosperity) he dares then as much,</L>
<L>As euer mad him famous that you pleade for;</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col: Frien.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then I forbeare to long.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap: Frien.</SPEAKER>
<L>His worth for me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heres noble youths, belike some wench has croft'em, and now they know not what to doe with their blood.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter the Colonell and Captaine Agar.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colo.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold, hold, whats the incitement,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colo.</SPEAKER>
<L>So serious at your game, come, come, the quarrell,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colo. frie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nothing good faith sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nothing, and you bleed,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="4"/>
<SPEAKER>Col. fri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bleed, where, pish, a little scratch by chance sir,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col:</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What need this nicenes, when you know so wel</L>
<L>That I must know these things, and truly know 'em,</L>
<L>Your daintines makes me but more impatient,</L>
<L>This strange concealement frets me.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col. fri.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Words did passe</L>
<L>Which I was bound to answer, as my opinion</L>
<L>And loue instructed me, and should I take in generall fame,</L>
<L>Into 'em, I thinke I should commit no error in't,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colo.</SPEAKER>
<L>What words sir, and of whom,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col. fri.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>This gentleman.</L>
<L>Paralelld Captaine <HI>Agers</HI> worth with yours,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colo.</SPEAKER>
<L>With mine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col. fai.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>It was a thing I could nor listen to</L>
<L>With any patience.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What should aile you sir,</L>
<L>There was little wrong done to your friend i'that,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colo.</SPEAKER>
<L>How<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> little wrong, to me,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I said so, friend.</L>
<L>And I suppose that you'le esteeme it so;</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Compatisons?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Why sis? twixt friend, and friend,</L>
<L>There is so euen and leuell a degree</L>
<L>It will admit of no superlatiue.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Col</HI>:</SPEAKER>
<L>Not in termes of man-hood?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay gentlemen,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Good sir giue mee leaue, in termes of manhood?</L>
<L>What can you dispute more questionable▪</L>
<L>You are a captaine sir, I giue you all your due,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And you are a Colonell, a title</L>
<L>Which may include within it many captaines,</L>
<L>Yet sir, but throwing by those titular shaddows,</L>
<L>Which ad ne substance to the men themselues;</L>
<L>And take them vncompounded, man and man;</L>
<L>They may be so with faire equallity,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'are a boy sir,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And you haue a Beard sir.</L>
<L>Virginity and marriage are both worthy,</L>
<L>And the positiue puritie there are some</L>
<L>

<PB REF="5"/>Haue made the nobler.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colo.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay good sir,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I shrinke not, he that goes the formost,</L>
<L>May be oretaken.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Colo</HI>:</SPEAKER>
<L>Death, how am I weighd?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>In an euen ballance sir, a beard put in</L>
<L>Giues but a small aduantage: man and man</L>
<L>And lift the scales,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colo.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Patience shalbe my curse</L>
<L>If it tide me further;</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>How now Gallants?</L>
<L>Beleeue me then, I must giue aime no longer,</L>
<L>Can words beget swords and bring um forth, ha?</L>
<L>Come they are abortiue propagations;</L>
<L>Hide 'um for shame, I had thought Souldiers</L>
<L>Had bin musicall; would not strike out of time,</L>
<L>But to the consort of Drum, Trumps and Fife.</L>
<L>Tis madman-like to daunce without musique.</L>
<L>And most vnpleasing showes to the beholders,</L>
<L>A Lydian ditty to a Dorick note</L>
<L>Friends embrace with steele hands? fie, it meets to hard,</L>
<L>I must haue those encounters heere debar'd,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colo.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Shall I loose heere what I haue safe broughthome</L>
<L>Through many dangers?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whats that sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colo.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My fame,</L>
<L>Life of the life, my reputation,</L>
<L>Death? I am squar'd and measur'd out, my heights</L>
<L>Depths, breadth, all my dimensions taken,</L>
<L>Sure I haue yet beyond your Astralobe</L>
<L>A spirit vnbounded;</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, you might weigh,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Tush, all this is weighing fire, vaine &amp; fruitles,</L>
<L>The further it runnes into argument</L>
<L>The further plung'd, beseech you no more on't,</L>
<L>I haue a little claime, sir, in your blood</L>
<L>As neare as the brother to your mother,</L>
<L>If that may serue for power to moue your quiet</L>
<L>The rest I shall make vp with curtesie</L>
<L>

<PB REF="5"/>And an Vncles loue.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue done sir, but</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<L>But! Ile haue no more shooting at these buts,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Colo</HI>:</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee'le to pricks, when he please,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You roue all still</L>
<L>Sir, I haue no motiue proofe to disgest</L>
<L>Your raisd choller ba<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>k into temperate blood,</L>
<L>But if you'le make mine age a counsellor</L>
<L>(As all ages haue hitherto allow'd it)</L>
<L>Wisdome in men growes vp as yeares encrease,</L>
<L>You shall make me blessed in making peace,</L>
<L>And doe your iudgement right,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colo.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>In peace at home</L>
<L>Gray hayres are Senators: but to determine</L>
<L>Soldiers and their actions;</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Fitzallen and Iane.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Tis peace heere sir,</L>
<L>And see, heere comes a happy Interim,</L>
<L>Here enters now a Sceane of louing armes;</L>
<L>This couple will not quarrell so;</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colo. Fri.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Be aduisd Sir,</L>
<L>This gentleman <HI>Fitzallen</HI> is your kinsman,</L>
<L>You may'orethrow his long labord fortunes</L>
<L>With one angry minut, tis a rich churle</L>
<L>And this his sole inheritrix, blast not</L>
<L>His hopes with this tempest,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colo.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>It shall calme me,</L>
<L>All the townes coniurers and their <HI>Daemons</HI></L>
<L>Could not haue layd my spirit so,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Worthy Cuz</L>
<L>I gratulate your faire returne to peace</L>
<L>Your swift fame was at home long before you;</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colo</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>It meetes (I hope) your hapy fortunes heere</L>
<L>And I am glad int, I must salute your ioyes, cuz,</L>
<L>With a soulders encounter
<STAGE>Kisses her.</STAGE></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Worthy Captaine <HI>Ager,</HI></L>
<L>I hope my kinsman shortly, —</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You must come short indeed,</L>
<L>

<PB REF="6"/>Or the length of my deuise will be ill shrunke,</L>
<L>Why now it showes finely, Ile tell you, sir,</L>
<L>Sir, nay sonne, I know i'th end, twill be so,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hope so, sir,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Hope? nay tis past all hope, sonne,</L>
<L>Heere has beene such a stormy incounter,</L>
<L>Betwixt my cozen Captaine and this braue Colonell</L>
<L>About I know not what, nothing indeed,</L>
<L>Competitions, degrees and comparatiues</L>
<L>Of Soldiership: but this smooth passage</L>
<L>Of loue has calm'd it all, come Ile hau't found,</L>
<L>Let me see your hearts combined in your hands,</L>
<L>And then I will beleeue the league is good,</L>
<L>It shall be the grapes if we drinke any blood.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue no anger sir,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I haue had none,</L>
<L>My blood has not yet rose to a quarrell,</L>
<L>Nor haue you had cause,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colo.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No cause of quarrell?</L>
<L>death? if my father should tell me so:</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<L>agen?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good sir, for my sake,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colo.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Faith, I haue done, Cuz,</L>
<L>You doe too hastily beleeue mine anger,</L>
<L>And yet to say, deminiting vallour</L>
<L>In a soldier is no cause of quarrell.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Nay then Ile remoue the cause to kil th'effect,</L>
<L>Kinsman, Ile presse you too't, if either loue</L>
<L>Or consanguinity may moue you too't,</L>
<L>I must disarme you, though yeare a soldier,</L>
<L>Pray grant me your weapon, it shall be safe</L>
<L>At your regresse from my house, now I know</L>
<L>No words can moue this noble soldiers sword</L>
<L>To a man vndefenc't so, we shall parle,</L>
<L>And safely make all perfect friends agen,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colo.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>To shew my will sir, accept mine to you,</L>
<L>As good not weare it as not dare to vse it.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colo friend.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Nay then sir, we will be all exampled.</L>
<L>Wee'le haue no Armes heere now but louers armes.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="6"/>
<SPEAKER>Capt. friend.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No seconds must begin a quarrell,</L>
<L>Take mine sir.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Why Law, what a fine Sun shines heere? these</L>
<L>clouds my breath has blowne into another Climate,</L>
<L>Ile be your armourers, they are not paun'd,</L>
<L>These were the fish that I did angle for,</L>
<L>I haue caught 'vm finely, now for my trick,</L>
<L>My proiect's lusty, and will hit the nick.
<STAGE>Exit with weapons.</STAGE></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colo.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What ist a match beauty? I would now haue,</L>
<L>Aliance with my worthy Captaine <HI>Ager,</HI></L>
<L>To knit our loues the faster; heeres witnes</L>
<L>Enough if you confirme it now.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sir my voyce,</L>
<L>Was long since giuen, since that I gaue my hand,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would you had seald too,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>That wish comes too late,</L>
<L>For I too soone feare my deliuery:
<STAGE>(<HI>aside.</HI>)</STAGE></L>
<L>My fathers hand stickes yet sir, you may now</L>
<L>Challenge a lawfull interest in his,</L>
<L>Hee tooke your hand from your enraged blood,</L>
<L>And gaue it freely to your opposite</L>
<L>My Cozen <HI>Ager,</HI> me thinks you should claime from him,</L>
<L>In the lesse quality of calmer blood,</L>
<L>To ioyne the hands of two diuided friends,</L>
<L>Euen these two that would offer willingly</L>
<L>Their owne embrace.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt. friend.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Troth, she instructs you well</L>
<L><HI>Colonell:</HI> and you shall doe a louers part</L>
<L>worth one braue act of vallour.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colo.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>VVhy, I did</L>
<L>misdoubt no scruple, is there doubt in it?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Faith sir, delaies, which at the least are doubts,</L>
<L>But heeres a constant resolution fixt,</L>
<L>VVhich we wish willingly he would accord to,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colo.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Tush he shall doo't, I will not be denyed,</L>
<L>Hee owes me so much in the recompence</L>
<L>of my reconcilement, Captaine <HI>Ager</HI></L>
<L>You will take our parts aganst your vncle</L>
<L>

<PB REF="7"/>In this quarrell?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ager.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I shall doe my best, sir,</L>
<L>Two denialls shall not repulse me, I loue</L>
<L>Your worthy kinsman and wish him mine, I know</L>
<L>He doubts it not.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colo.</SPEAKER>
<L>See, hees returnd.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Russell and a Seruant.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Your qu.</L>
<L>Be sure you keep it, 'twill be spoken quickly.</L>
<L>Therefore watch it.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lets set on him all at once.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes,</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, we haue a sute to you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<L>What! all at once.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<L>All, all, i faith, sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>On speaker may yet deliver, say, say,</L>
<L>I shall not dare to stand out against so many,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colo.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Faith sir heeres a brabling matter hangs on demurre,</L>
<L>I make the motion for all, without a fee</L>
<L>Pray you let it be ended this terme,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Ha, ha, ha.</L>
<L>Thats the rascalls qu, and he has mist it. <STAGE>a side.</STAGE></L>
<L>What is it? what is it sir?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colo.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Why sir, here's a man;</L>
<L>And heer's a woman; y'are scholler good enough,</L>
<L>Put 'am togither; and tell me what it spells,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, ha, ha, theres his qu once agen,</L>
<STAGE>Enter Seruant.</STAGE>
<L>Oh hee's come, humh:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seru.</SPEAKER>
<L>My maister laughes, that's his qu to mischiefe,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<L>What say you, sir</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha? what say you sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, theres a couple desire speedily to speake with you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<L>A couple sir, of what, hounds, or horses?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seru.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Men sir, gentlemen or yeomen, I know not which;</L>
<L>But the one sure they are</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hast thou no other description of them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seru.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>They come with commission, they say, sir to</L>
<L>tast of your earth: if they like it, they'le turne it into gunpouder.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Oh, they are Salt-peetermen, before mee</L>
<L>And they bring commission: the kings power indeed,</L>
<L>

<PB REF="7"/>They must haue entrance, but the knaues will be brib'd,</L>
<L>Theres all the hope we haue in Officers,</L>
<L>They were too dangerous in a common wealth,</L>
<L>But that they will be very, well corrupted, necessary varlets,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seru:</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall I enter in sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>By all faire meanes sir.</L>
<L>And with all speed sir giue vm very good words,</L>
<L>To saue my ground vnrauisht, vnbroke vp,</L>
<L>Mines yet a virgin earth: the worme hath not beene seene,</L>
<L>To wriggle in her chast bowells: and Ide be loth</L>
<L>A Gunpowder fellow should defloure her now.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our suit is yet delayd by this meanes sir,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Alas I cannot help it, these fellowes gone</L>
<L>(As I hope I shall dispatch vm quickly)</L>
<L>A few Articles shall conclude your suite,</L>
<L>Who? M<SUP>r</SUP>. <HI>Fitzallen</HI>: the onely man</L>
<L>That my adoption aymes at.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Theres good hope then.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter two Sergeants in disguise.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Ser.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Saue you, sir,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are welcome sir for ought I know yet,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Ser.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>We come to take a view and tast of your ground, sir,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I had rather feed you with better meat, Gentlemen,</L>
<L>But doe your pleasures, pray:</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is our pleasures, we arrest you, sir, in the Kings name</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha! at whose suite?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<L>Howe's that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our weapons, good sir furnish vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>Aye me,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Stay stay, Gentlemen, lets enquire the cause,</L>
<L>It may be but a trift; a small debt,</L>
<L>Shall need no rescew heere.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir betwixt three Creditors: M<SUP>r</SUP>. <HI>Leach,</HI> M<SUP>r</SUP>. <HI>Swallow,</HI> and M<SUP>r</SUP>. <HI>Bonesuck,</HI> the debts are a thousand pvunds.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>A thousand pounds?</L>
<L>Beshrow me a good mans substance.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good sir our weapons weele teach these var∣lets to walke in their owne parti-coulour'd Coates, that they may be distinguish't from honest men.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Ser.</HI></SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sir, attempt no rescue, hee's our prisoner,</L>
<L>you'le make the danger worse by violence.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="8"/>
<SPEAKER>Colo.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>A plague vpon your Gunpowder treason;</L>
<L>Yee quicke damb'd Varlets, is this your salt peter proouing,</L>
<L>Your tasting earth, would you might neuer feede better,</L>
<L>Nor none of your Catchpole tribe:</L>
<L>Our weapons good sir, weele yet deliuer him.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Pardon me sir,</L>
<L>I dare not suffer rescue heere,</L>
<L>At least not by so great an accessarie</L>
<L>As to furnish you; had you had your weapons,</L>
<L>But to see the Ill fate on't, my fine tricke Ifaith,</L>
<L>Let Beggers beware to loue Richmens Daughters,</L>
<L>I'le teach 'um the new morrice, I learn't it</L>
<L>My selfe of another carefull Father.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>May <HI>I</HI> not be bayld?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Ser.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, but not with swords,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Slaues, heere are sufficent men;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Ser.</HI></SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L><HI>I</HI> ith field,</L>
<L>But not in the Citty, sir, if this Gentleman</L>
<L>Will be one, wee'le easily admit the second.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Who <HI>I</HI>? sir, pray pardon me, <HI>I</HI> am wrongd,</L>
<L>Very much wrongd in this, <HI>I</HI> must needs speake it,</L>
<L>Sir, you haue not dealt like an honest Louer,</L>
<L>With me nor my child, heere you boaste to mee</L>
<L>Of a great reuenew, a large substance</L>
<L>Wherein you would endow &amp; state my daughter,</L>
<L>Had <HI>I</HI> mist this, my opinion yet</L>
<L>Thought you a frugall man, to vnderstand,</L>
<L>The sure wardes against all necessities,</L>
<L>Boldly to defend your wife and Family,</L>
<L>To walke vnmuffled, dreadlesse of these fleshhookes,</L>
<L>Euen in the daring'st streets through all the Citty,</L>
<L>But now <HI>I</HI> find you a loose Prodigall,</L>
<L>A large vnthrift, a whole thousand pound?</L>
<L>Come from him girle, his inside is not found?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sir <HI>I</HI> am wrongd,</L>
<L>These are malitious plots,</L>
<L>Of some obscure enemies that <HI>I</HI> haue,</L>
<L>These debts are none of mine.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L><HI>I</HI> all say so,</L>
<L>

<PB REF="8"/>Perhaps you stand ingag'd for other men,</L>
<L>If so you doe, you must then cal't your owne,</L>
<L>The like arrerage doe I run into</L>
<L>Should I batle you; But I haue vow'd against it,</L>
<L>And I will keepe my vowes: that's religious.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>All this is nothing so sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Nothing so?</L>
<L>By my faith it is sir, my vowes are firme,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I neither owe these debts,</L>
<L>Nor engag'd for others.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The easier is your liberty regain'd,</L>
<L>These appeare proofes to me,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colo.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Liberty sir?</L>
<L>I hope youle not see him goe to Prison,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I do not meane to beare him company</L>
<L>So far: but Ile see him out of my doores,</L>
<L>Oh sir, let him goe to Prison, 'tis a Schoole</L>
<L>To tame wild bioods, heele be much better fort,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Better for lying in Prison,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>In prison,</L>
<L>Beleeue it many an honest man lies in prison,</L>
<L>Else all the keepers are knaues,</L>
<L>They told me so themselues.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sir, I doe now suspect you haue betraid him,</L>
<L>And vs to cause vs to be weaponlesse,</L>
<L>If it be so y'are a blood suckng Churle,</L>
<L>One that was born in a great frost, when charity</L>
<L>Could not stir a finger, and you shall dye</L>
<L>In heate of a burning feauer i'th Dog▪ dayes,</L>
<L>To begin your hell to you, I haue said your grace for you,</L>
<L>Now get you to supper as soone as you can,</L>
<L><HI>Pluto</HI> the Maister of the house is set already,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir you doe wrong mine Vncle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colo</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Poxe on your Vncle,</L>
<L>And all his kin, if my Kinsman mingle</L>
<L>No blood with him.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'are a foule mouthd fellow,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Foule mouth'd I will be, th'art the son of a whore,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="9"/>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Ha! Whore! plagues and furies Ile thrust that backe,</L>
<L>Or pluck thy heart out after, sonne of a whore?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colo.</SPEAKER>
<L>On thy life Ile proue it,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Death I am naked,</L>
<L>Vncle, Ile giue you my left hand, for my sword,</L>
<L>To arme my right with; Oh this fire wil flame me</L>
<L>Into prsent ashes,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colo.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sir, giue vs Weapons,</L>
<L>We aske our owne, you will not rob vs of them?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No sir, but still restraine your furies heere,</L>
<L>At my dore Ile giue you them, nor, at this time</L>
<L>My Nephewes, a time will better suit you,</L>
<L>And I must tell you sir, you haue spoke swordes,</L>
<L>And'gainst the law of armes poyson'd the blades</L>
<L>And with them wounded the reputation</L>
<L>Of an vnblemisht woman: would you 'were out of my dores.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colo.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Poxe on your dores, and let it run all your house ore,</L>
<L>Giue me my sword.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>We shall meet <HI>Colonel</HI>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colo.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yes better prouided, to spur thee more,</L>
<L>I do repeat my words Son of a Whore.
<STAGE>Exit with his friend.</STAGE></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt. fr.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Come sir, 'tis no worse then 'twas:</L>
<L>You can doe nothing now.
<STAGE>Exit Capt. and his friend.</STAGE></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, Ile bar him now, away with that begger,
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Good sir, let this perswade you for two minutes stay,</L>
<L>At this prise (I know) you can wait all day.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Ser.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>You know the Remora that stayes our ship alwaies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Your ship sinkes many when this hold lets goe,</L>
<L>Oh my <HI>Fitzallen</HI> what is to be done,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>To be still thine is all my part to be,</L>
<L>Whether in freedome or captiuity,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>But art thou so ingag'd as this pretends?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>By heau'n, sweet <HI>Iane</HI> 'tis all a hellish plot</L>
<L>Your cruell smiling father all this while,</L>
<L>Has candied o're a bitter pill for me,</L>
<L>Thinking by my remoue to plant some other,</L>
<L>And then let goe his fangs.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="9"/>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Plant some other?</L>
<L>Thou hast too firmely stampt me for thine owne,</L>
<L>Euer to be rast out, I am not currant</L>
<L>In any others hand; I feare too soone</L>
<L>I shall discouer it.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Let come the worst,</L>
<L>Binde but this knot with an vnloosed line,</L>
<L>I will be still thine owne..</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>And Ile be thine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Ser.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>My watch has gone two minutes M.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz</SPEAKER>
<L>It shall not be renew'd, I goe sir, farewell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ia.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Farewell, wee both are prison'd, though not togeither:</L>
<L>But heers the difference in our luckelesse chance.</L>
<L>I feare mine owne, wish thy deliuerance.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Our hearts shall hourely visit, ile send to thee,
<STAGE>Exit Fitz, with Officers</STAGE></L>
<L>Then tis no prison where the mind is free.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Russell.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>So, let him goe, now wench <HI>I</HI> bring thee ioyes,</L>
<L>A faire sun-shine after this angry storme:</L>
<L>It was my pollicie to remoue this begger:</L>
<L>What shall rich men wed their onely daughters</L>
<L>To two faire suites of cloathes? and perhaps yet</L>
<L>The poore Taylor is vnpaid; no, no my gitle,</L>
<L><HI>I</HI> haue a lad of thousands comming in;</L>
<L>Suppose he haue more wealth then wit to guid it▪</L>
<L>Why, theres thy gaines, thou kep'st the keies of all</L>
<L>Disposest all: and for generation,</L>
<L>Man does most sildome stampe 'um from the braine,</L>
<L>Wisemen begets fooles, and fooles are the fathers</L>
<L>To many wise Children. <HI>Histeron, Proteron,</HI></L>
<L>A great scholler may be get an Ideot,</L>
<L>And from the plow tayle may come a great scholler:</L>
<L>Nay, they are frequent propogations.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am not well, sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Ha? not well my girle?</L>
<L>Thou shalt haue a Physitian then,</L>
<L>The best that gold can fetch vpon his footecloath,</L>
<L>Thou knowest my tender pitty to thee euer,</L>
<L>

<PB REF="10"/>VVant nothing that thy wishes can instruct thee</L>
<L>To call for, 'fore mee, and thou look'st halfe ill indeed,</L>
<L>But Ile bring one within a day to thee</L>
<L>Shall rouse thee vp: for hees come vp already,</L>
<L>One M. <HI>Chaugh</HI> a Cornish Gentleman:</L>
<L>Ha's as much land of his owne fee-simple,</L>
<L>As a Crow can flie ouer in halfe a day:</L>
<L>And now <HI>I</HI> thinke on't, at the Crow at Algate</L>
<L>His lodging is, He shall so stir thee vp,</L>
<L>Come, come, be cheard, thinke of thy preserment,</L>
<L>Honour and attendance, these wil bring thee health</L>
<L>And the way to 'um is to clime by wealth.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</LG>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus Secundus, Scaena primae.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter Captaine</HI> Ager.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The Sonne of a VVhore?</L>
<L>There is not such another murdring piece</L>
<L>In all the stocke of Calumny: it kils</L>
<L>At one report two reputations,</L>
<L>A mothers and a Sonnes: if it were possible</L>
<L>That soules could fight after the bodies fell,</L>
<L>This were a quarrell for 'em; he should be one indeed</L>
<L>That neuer heard of heauens ioyes or hels torments</L>
<L>To fight this out: <HI>I</HI> am too full of conscience,</L>
<L>Knowledge and patience, to giue Iustice too't,</L>
<L>So carefull of my Eternity, which consists</L>
<L>Of vpright actions: that vnlesse I knew</L>
<L>It were a truth <HI>I</HI> stood for, any Coward</L>
<L>Might make my breast his footepace, &amp; who liues</L>
<L>That can assure the truth of his conception,</L>
<L>More then a mothers carriage makes it hopefull.</L>
<L>And i'st not miserable valour then,</L>
<L>That man should hazard all vpon things doubtfull</L>
<L>Oh ther's the cruelty of my foes aduantage,</L>
<L>

<PB REF="10"/>Could but my soule resolue my cause were iust,</L>
<L>Earth's mountaine, nor seas surge should hide him from mee,</L>
<L>Ee'ne to hells threshold would <HI>I</HI> follow him,</L>
<L>And see the slanderer in before <HI>I</HI> left him,</L>
<L>But as it is it feares me, and <HI>I</HI> neuer</L>
<L>Appeard too conscionably iust till now:</L>
<L>My good oppinion of her life and Vertues,</L>
<L>Bids me goe on: and faine would I be ruld by't,</L>
<L>But when my iudgement tels me shees but woman,</L>
<L>Whose fraile to let in death to all mankinde,</L>
<L>My valour shrinkes at that, certaine shees good,</L>
<L>There onely wants but my assurance in't,</L>
<L>And al things thē were perfect how I thirst for't,</L>
<L>Heere comes the onely shee that could resolue,</L>
<L>But 'tis too vild a question to demand indeed.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter the Lady</HI> Ager.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sonne l'ue a suite to you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>That may doe well.</L>
<L>To me good Madame, you're most sure to speed in't.</L>
<L>Beet i'my power to grant it,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Tis my loue</L>
<L>Makes the request, that you would neuer parte</L>
<L>From England more,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Capt</HI>:</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>With all my heart tis graunted,</L>
<L>I'me sure Ime i'th way neuer to part from't,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where left you your deare friend the <HI>Colonel?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh the deare <HI>Colonel,</HI> I should meete him soone,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Oh faile him not then, hees a Gentleman</L>
<L>The same and reputation of your time</L>
<L>Is much engadg'de to.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, and you knew all mother.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I thought I'de knowne so much of his faire goodnes,</L>
<L>More could not haue bin look't for.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O yes, yes Madam.</L>
<L>And this his last exceeded all the rest.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<L>For gratitudes sake let me know this, I pre thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Then thus, and I desire your censure freely,</L>
<L>Whether it appeard not a strange noble kindnes in him.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="11"/>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>Trust me I long to hear't,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You know hees hasty,</L>
<L>That by the way.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>So are the best conditions</L>
<L>Your Father was the like.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I begin now</L>
<L>To doubt me more, why am not I so too then,</L>
<L>Blood followes blood through forty generations,</L>
<L>And I'ue a flow pac't wrath, a shrewd <HI>Dilemma,</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, as you were saying sir,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Marry thus good Madame,</L>
<L>There was in company a foule mouth'd villaine, stay, stay,</L>
<L>Who should I liken him to, that you haue seene,</L>
<L>He comes so neere one that I would not match him with,</L>
<L>Faith iust a'th Colonels pitch, hees nere the worse man,</L>
<L>Vserers haue bin compard to Magistrates,</L>
<L>Extortiners to Lawyers, and the like,</L>
<L>But they all proue nere the worse men for that,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> hats bad enough, they need not,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>This rude fellow,</L>
<L>A shame to all humanity or manners,</L>
<L>Breaths from the rottenes of his gall and mallice,</L>
<L>The foulest staine that euer mans same blemisht,</L>
<L>Part of which fell vpon your honor Madame,</L>
<L>VVhich heighthend my affliction.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lad.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mine? my honor sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The Colonel soone inrag'd,</L>
<L>(As hee's all touch-wood)</L>
<L>Takes fire before me, makes the quarrell his,</L>
<L>Appoynts the Field, my wrath could not be heard</L>
<L>His was so high pitcht, so gloriously mounted,</L>
<L>Now whats the friendly feare, that fights within mee,</L>
<L>Should his braue noble Fury vndertake,</L>
<L>A cause that were vniust in our defence,</L>
<L>And so to loose him euerlastingly,</L>
<L>In that darke depth where all bad quarrells sinke,</L>
<L>Neuer to rise againe, what pitty twere,</L>
<L>First to dye heere and neuer to dye there.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="11"/>
<SPEAKER>Lady,</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Why whats the quarrel, speake sir: that should raise</L>
<L>Such fearefull doubt, my honour bearing part ou't:</L>
<L>The words what ere they were:</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Son of a whore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La..</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Thou lyest, &amp; were my loue ten thousand times more to thee,</L>
<L>Which is as much now, as ere mothers was,</L>
<L>So thou shouldst feele my anger. Do'st thou call</L>
<L>That quarrel doubtfull; where are all my merites,
<STAGE>Strikes him.</STAGE></L>
<L>Not one stand vp to tell this man his error.</L>
<L>Thou might'st as well bring the Sun's truth in question,</L>
<L>As thy birth or my honour.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Now blessings crown you for't,</L>
<L>It is the ioyful'st blow that ere flesh felt.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Nay stay, stay sir, thou art not left so soone,</L>
<L>This is no question to be slighted of,</L>
<L>And at your pleasure closde vp fayre agen,</L>
<L>As though you'de neuer toucht it, no honour doubted,</L>
<L>Is honour deepely wounded, and it rages</L>
<L>More then a common smart, being of thy making.</L>
<L>For thee to feare my truth, it kils my comfort,</L>
<L>Where should fame seeke for her reward, when he</L>
<L>That is her owne by the great tye of bloud,</L>
<L>Is fardest of in bounty, O poore goodnes!</L>
<L>That onely pay'st thy selfe with thy owne works,</L>
<L>For nothing else looks towards thee. Tell me pray,</L>
<L>Which of my louing cares dost thou requite</L>
<L>With this vilde thought? which of my prayers or wishes?</L>
<L>Many thou owest me for, this seauen year hast thou known me</L>
<L>A widdow, onely married to my vow:</L>
<L>Thats no small witnesse of my faith and loue</L>
<L>To him that in life was thy honord Father,</L>
<L>And liue I now to know that good mistrusted.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No, t'shall appeare that my beliefe is cherefull,</L>
<L>For neuer was a mothers reputation</L>
<L>Noblyer defended, tis my ioy and pride,</L>
<L>I haue a firme to bestow vpon it.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whats that you said sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>'Twere too bold, and soone yet</L>
<L>

<PB REF="12"/>To craue for giuenesse of you. I will earne it first,</L>
<L>Dead or aliue, I know I shall enioy it.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whats all this sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My ioyes beyond expression:</L>
<L>I do but thinke how wretched I had been,</L>
<L>Were this anothers quarrell, and not mine.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, is it yours?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Mine! Thinke me not so miserable,</L>
<L>Not to be mine: then were I worse then abiect,</L>
<L>More to be loathde then villnes; or sins dunghill:</L>
<L>Nor did I feare your goodnes (faithfull Madame)</L>
<L>But came with greedy ioy to be confirmde in't,</L>
<L>To giue the nobler onset, then shines valour,</L>
<L>And admiration from her fix't Sphere drawes,</L>
<L>When it comes burnisht with a righteous cause,</L>
<L>Without which I'me ten sadomes vnder coward,</L>
<L>That now am ten degrees aboue a man,</L>
<L>VVhich is but one of vertues easiest wonders.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But pray stay; all this while I vnderstood you,</L>
<L>The Colonel was the man</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yes, hee's the man,</L>
<L>The man of iniury, reproach and slander,</L>
<L>Which I must turne into his soule again.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Colonell doo't, thats strange</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The villaine did it:</L>
<L>Thats not so strange; — your blessing and your leaue</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, come, you shall not goe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Not goe; were death</L>
<L>Sent now to summon me to my Eternity,</L>
<L>I'de put him off an howre: why the whole world</L>
<L>Ha's not chains strong inough to bind me from't:</L>
<L>The strongest is my Reuerence to you,</L>
<L>VVhich if you force vpon me in this case;</L>
<L>I must be forc'st to breake it.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay I say.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>In any thing commaund me but in this Madame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lasse, I shall loose him, you'le heare me first.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="12"/>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>At my returne I will.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>Youl'e neuer heare me more then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>How?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Come backe I say:</L>
<L>You may well thinke theres cause I call so often.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hah, cause! what cause?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>So much, you must not goe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>How?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>You must not goe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Must not, why?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I know a reason for't,</L>
<L>VVhich I could wish you'd yeeld to, &amp; not know</L>
<L>If not, it must come forth. Faith, do not know,</L>
<L>And yet obey my will.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Why I desire</L>
<L>To know no other then the cause I haue,</L>
<L>Nor should you wish it, if you take your iniury</L>
<L>For one more great, I know the world includes not.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yes, one that makes this nothing,—yet be rulde,</L>
<L>And if you vnderstand not, seeke no further.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must, for this is nothing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Then take all,</L>
<L>And if amongst it you receiue that secret</L>
<L>That will offend you, though you condemn mee,</L>
<L>Yet blame your selfe a little, for perhaps</L>
<L>I would haue made my reputation sound</L>
<L>Vpon an others hazards with lesse pitty;</L>
<L>But vpon yours I dare not.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>How?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I dare not,</L>
<L>'T was your owne seeking; this,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If you meane euilly</L>
<L>I cannot vnderstand you, nor for all the riches</L>
<L>This life has, would I.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<L>would you neuer might.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, your goodnes, that I ioy to fight for.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>In that you neither right your ioy nor me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>What an ill Orator has vertue got here?</L>
<L>

<PB REF="13"/>Why, shal I dare to thinke it a thing possible</L>
<L>That you were euer false?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Oh fearefully!</L>
<L>As much as you come to.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Oh silence, couer me.</L>
<L>Iue felt a deadlier wound then man can giue me, false?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>I was betraide to a most sinfull howre.</L>
<L>By a corrupted soule I put in trust once.</L>
<L>A Kinswoman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where is shee? let me pay her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, dead long since.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Nay then sh'as all her wages:</L>
<L>False, do not say't, for honors goodnes doe not,</L>
<L>You neuer could be so, he I calde Father,</L>
<L>Deserud you at your best, when youth &amp; merit</L>
<L>Could boast at highest in you, y'ade no grace,</L>
<L>Or vertue that he matcht not, no delight</L>
<L>That you inuented but he sent it crownde</L>
<L>To your full wishing soule.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>That heapes my guiltinesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Oh, were you so vnhappy to be false,</L>
<L>Both to your selfe and me, but to me chiefly,</L>
<L>What a dayes hope is here lost, and with it</L>
<L>The ioyes of a iust cause. Had you but thought</L>
<L>On such a noble quarrell, you'd ha dyed</L>
<L>Ere you'd ha yeelded, for the sins hate first,</L>
<L>Next for the shame of this howres cowardize:</L>
<L>Curst be the heate that lost me such a cause,</L>
<L>A worke that I was made for. Quench my spirit,</L>
<L>And out with honors flaming lights within thee:</L>
<L>Be darke and dead to all respects of manhood,</L>
<L>I neuer shall haue vse of valour more:</L>
<L>Put off your vow for shame, why should you hoarde vp</L>
<L>Such Iustice for a barren widdowhood,</L>
<L>That was so iniurious to the faith of wedlocke.
<STAGE>Exit Lady.</STAGE></L>
<L>I sheuld be dead, for all my lifes works ended,</L>
<L>I dare not sight a stroke now, nor engadge</L>
<L>

<PB REF="13"/>The noble resolution of my friends,</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Enter two friends of Captaine Agers.</STAGE>
<LG>
<L>That were more vilde. Their here, kill me my shame,</L>
<L>I am not for the fellowship of honour.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Friend.</HI></SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Captaine, fie come sir, we haue been seeking for you</L>
<L>very late to day, this was not wout to be,</L>
<L>Your enemies ith field,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Truth enters cheerefully.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Friend.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Good faith sir y'aue a royall quarrell on't,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yes, in some other Country, <HI>Spaine</HI> or <HI>Italy.</HI></L>
<L>It would be held so.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Friend.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>How, and ist not hereso?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Tis not so contumeliously receiude</L>
<L>In these parts, and you marke it.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Friend.</HI></SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Not in these?</L>
<L>Why prithee what is more, or can be?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt,</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yes,</L>
<L>That ordinary Commotioner the lye</L>
<L>Is Father of most quarrels in this Clymate,</L>
<L>And held here capitall, and you go to that.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Fr.</HI></SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But sir, I hope you will not go to that,</L>
<L>Or change your owne for it, <HI>Sonne of a Whore,</HI></L>
<L>Why theres the Lye downe to posterity.</L>
<L>The lye to brithe, the lye to honesty,</L>
<L>Why would you cussen you selfe so, and beguile</L>
<L>So braue a cause, Manhoods best Master peece,</L>
<L>Doe you euer hope for one so braue agen.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Consider then the man Colonell,</L>
<L>Exactly worthy, absolutely noble,</L>
<L>How euer spleene and rage abuses him:</L>
<L>And tis not wel, nor manly to pursue</L>
<L>A mans infirmity.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Friend.</HI></SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O miracle!</L>
<L>So hopefull, valiant and compleate a Captaine,</L>
<L>Possest with a tame deuill, come out, thou spoilest</L>
<L>The most improude yong souldier of seuen kingdoms,</L>
<L>Made Captaine at nineteene, which was deserude</L>
<L>

<PB REF="14"/>The yeare before, but honor comes behind still,</L>
<L>Come out I say, this was not wont to be,</L>
<L>That spirit neuer stood in need of prouocation,</L>
<L>Nor shall it now. Away sir.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vrge me not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>F.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>By Manhoods reuerend honor but we must.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will not fight a stroake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Friend.</HI></SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O blasphemy</L>
<L>To sacred valour!</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Leade me where you lift.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Friend.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Pardon this trayterous slumber, clogd with e∣uils.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Giue Captaines rather wiues then such tame diuels.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Physitian and Iane.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ph.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Nay Master, you must not be couer'd to me,</L>
<L>The Patient must ope to the Physitian</L>
<L>All her dearest sorrowes: Art is blinded else,</L>
<L>And cannot shew her misticall effects.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Can Art be so dimsighted, learned sir?</L>
<L>I did not thinke her so in capacious:</L>
<L>You traine me (as I guesse) like a Coniurer,</L>
<L>One of our fiue Oraculous wizards,</L>
<L>who from the helpe of his Examinant,</L>
<L>By the neare guesse of his suspition</L>
<L>Appoints out the thiefe by the marks he tels him:</L>
<L>Haue you no skill in Phisiognomie?</L>
<L>what colour (sayes your coat) is my disease?</L>
<L>I am vnmarried, and it cannot be yellow,</L>
<L>If it be Mayden greene, you cannot misse it.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phis.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I cannot see that <HI>vacuum</HI> in your bloud:</L>
<L>But Gentlewoman, if you loue yourselfe,</L>
<L>Loue my aduise, be free and plaine with me,</L>
<L>where lyes your griefe?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Where lyes my griefe indeed?</L>
<L>I cannot tell the truth where my griefe lyes,</L>
<L>But my Ioy's imprison'd.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phis.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is misticall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ian.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Lord, what plaine questions you make problemes of,</L>
<L>

<PB REF="14"/>Your Artis such a regular high way</L>
<L>That put you out of it, and you are lost:</L>
<L>My heart is imprison'd in my body, sir:</L>
<L>Theres all my ioy, and my sorrow too</L>
<L>Lyes very neere it.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phys.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>They are bad adiuncts,</L>
<L>Your ioy and griefe lying so neare together,</L>
<L>Can propagate no happy issue, remoue</L>
<L>The one (and let it be the worst) your griefe,</L>
<L>If youl'e propose the best vnto your ioy.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>why, now comes your skill: what physicke for it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now I haue found you out, you are in loue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I thinke I am, what your appliance now?</L>
<L>Can all your Paracelsian mixtures cure it,</L>
<L>'T must be a Surgeon of the Ciuill Law,</L>
<L>I feare that must cure me.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Gentlewoman,</L>
<L>If you knew well my heart, you would not bee</L>
<L>So circuler, the very common name</L>
<L>Of Physitian might reproue your nicenesse,</L>
<L>wee are as secret as your Confessors,</L>
<L>And as firme oblig'd, tis a fine like death</L>
<L>For vs to blab.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I will trust you, yet sir,</L>
<L>I had rather doe it by Atturney to you,</L>
<L>I else haue blushes that will stop my tongue</L>
<L>Haue you no friend so friendly as your selfe</L>
<L>Of mine owne Sexe, to whom I might impart</L>
<L>My sorrowes to you at the second hand.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>why law, there I hit you, &amp; be confirmde,</L>
<L>Ile giue you such a bosome counsellonr,</L>
<L>That your own tong shall be sooner false to you,</L>
<L>Make your selfe vnready, and be naked to her:</L>
<L>Ile fetch her presently.
<STAGE>Exit Physitian.</STAGE></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I must reueale</L>
<L>My shame will else take tongue, &amp; speake before</L>
<L>Tis a necessity impulsiue driues me: me,</L>
<L>

<PB REF="15"/>Oh my hard fate, but my more hard father,</L>
<L>That Father of my fate, a father said I?</L>
<L>What a strange Paradoxe I run into,</L>
<L>I must accuse two fathers of my fate</L>
<L>And fault, a reciprocall generation,</L>
<L>The father of my fault would haue repairde,</L>
<L>His faulty issue, but my Fates Father hinders it:</L>
<L>Then Fate and fault, where euer I begin,</L>
<L>I must blame both, and yet 'twas loue did sinne.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Physician, and Anne his sister.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Looke you Mistres, heres's your closer put in,</L>
<L>What you please, you euer keep the key of it,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me speake priuate, sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>With all my heart,</L>
<L>I will be more then mine eares length from you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>You hold some indeared place with this Gent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>An.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Hee's my brother forsooth, I his creature,</L>
<L>He does command me any lawfull office</L>
<L>Eyther in act or counsell.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I must not doubt you,</L>
<L>Your brother ha's protested secresic,</L>
<L>And strengthned me in you: I must lay ope</L>
<L>A guilty sorrow to you: I am with child,</L>
<L>Tis no blacke Swan I show you, these spots sticke</L>
<L>Vpon the face of many goe for maides,</L>
<L>I that had face ynough to do the deed,</L>
<L>Cannot want tongue to speake it: but tis to you,</L>
<L>Whom I accept my helper.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anne.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Mistris, tis lock't</L>
<L>Within a Castle that's inuincible,</L>
<L>It is too late to wish it were vndone.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ia.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I haue scarce wish within my selfe so strong</L>
<L>For vnderstand me, tis not all so ill,</L>
<L>As you may yet conceit it: this deed was done</L>
<L>VVhen heauen had witness to the Iugall knot,</L>
<L>

<PB REF="15"/>Onely the barren ceremonie wants.</L>
<L>Which by an aduerse Father is abridged.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anne.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would my pitty could helpe you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Your counsell may.</L>
<L>My Father yet shootes widest from my sorrow,</L>
<L>And with a care indulgent seeing me chang'd</L>
<L>From what <HI>I</HI> was, sends for your good brother</L>
<L>To finde my griefe, and practise remedy:</L>
<L>You know it, giue it him, but if a fourth</L>
<L>Be added to this counsell: <HI>I</HI> will say</L>
<L>Ye' are worse then you can call me at the worst.</L>
<L>At this aduantage of my reputation.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anne.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L><HI>I</HI> will reuiue a reputation,</L>
<L>That women long has lost, ile keepe counsell.</L>
<L>Ile onely now oblige my teeth to you,</L>
<L>And they shall bite the blabber if it offer</L>
<L>To breath on an offending syllable.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>I trust you, go, whisper, here comes my Father.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Russell, Chawgh, and Trimtram.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sir. you are welcome, more and most welcome,</L>
<L>All the degrees of welcome: thrice welcome sir.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chaw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is this your daughter, sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mine onely ioy, sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chaw.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile shew her the Cornish hug, sir, — <HI>I</HI> haue kist you now sweet heart, and <HI>I</HI> neuer doe any kindnesse to my friendes, but I vse to hitte'am in the teeth with it pre∣sently.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<P>My name is <HI>Trimtram</HI> forsooth, looke what my ma∣ster does, <HI>I</HI> vse to doe the like.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anne.</SPEAKER>
<P>You are deceiu'd, sir, I am not this Gentlewo∣mans seruant, to make your courtesie equall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chaw.</SPEAKER>
<P>You doe not know me Mistresse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<P>No indeed, I doubt I shall learne too soone.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chaw.</SPEAKER>
<P>My name is <HI>Chawgh,</HI> a Cornish Gentleman, my mans mine owne countriman too yfaith: I warrant, you tooke vs for some of the small <HI>Islanders.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>I</HI> did indeed, betweene the <HI>Scotch</HI> and <HI>Irish.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="16"/>
<SPEAKER>Chaw.</SPEAKER>
<P>Red-shankes: I thought so by my truth, no truely, we are right Cornish Diamonds.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, we cut out quarrels, and breake glasses, where wee goe,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phis.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If it be hidden from her Father, yet</L>
<L>His ignorance vnderstands well his knowledge,</L>
<L>For this (I guesse) to be some rich coxcombe</L>
<L>Hee'de put vpon his daughter,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>An.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thats plainely so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phys.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Then only shee's beholding to out helpe</L>
<L>For the close deliuery of her burden,</L>
<L>Else all's ouerthrowne.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>An.</SPEAKER>
<L>And pray be faithfull in that. sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phys.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Tush, we Physitians are the truest</L>
<L>Alchymists, that from the <HI>ore</HI> and <HI>drosse</HI> of sinne,</L>
<L>Can new distill a Maydenhead agen.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<L>How doe you like her sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chaw.</SPEAKER>
<P>Troth I doe like her sir in the way of comparison to any thing that a man would desire. I am as high as the Mount in loue with her already, and thats as far as I can go by land, but I hope to goe further by water with her one day.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I tell you sir, she has lost some colour,</L>
<L>By wrastling with a peeuish sicknes now of late.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chaw.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wrastle? nay and she loue wrastling, Ile teach her a tricke to ouerthrow any peeuish sicknes in <HI>London,</HI> what ere it be.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Well, she had a rich beauty though I say't,</L>
<L>Nor is it lost: a little thing repayres it.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chaw.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shee shall commaund the best thing that I haue in <HI>Middlesex,</HI> yfaith.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kuss.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Well sir, talke with her, giue her a relish</L>
<L>Of your good liking to her, you shall haue time</L>
<L>And free accesse to finish what you now begin,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What meanes my father? my loues vniust restraint,</L>
<L>My shame were it publisht, both together</L>
<L>Could not afflict me like this odious foole:</L>
<L>Now I see why he hated my <HI>Fitz-Allen.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chaw.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sweet Lady, your father sayes you are a wrastler,


<PB REF="16"/>
if you loue that sport, I loue you the better. I faith I loue it as well as I loue my meate after supper, tis indeed meate, drinke and cloth to me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>Me thinkes it should teare your clothes, sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chaw.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not a rag yfaith: <HI>Trimtram</HI> hold my cloake, —Ile wrastle a fall with you now, Ile show you a tricke that you neuer saw in your life.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh good sir for beare, I am no wrastler.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good sir take heed, you'le hurt the Gentlewoman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chaw.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will not catch beneath the waste belieue it, I know fayre play,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis no womans exercise in <HI>London,</HI> sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chaw.</SPEAKER>
<P>I'le nere belieue that, the hug and the locke be∣tweene man and woman, with a fayre fall, <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>is as sweete an exercise for the body, as you'l desire in a sommers euening.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, the Gentlewoman is not well,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chaw,</SPEAKER>
<L>It may be you are a Physitian, sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phys.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis so, sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chaw.</SPEAKER>
<P>I say then, and ile stand too't, three ounces of wrastling with two hippes, a yard of a greene gowne put together in the Intourne, is as good a medicine for the greene sicknesse as euer breathd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come sir, take your cloake agen, I see here wil be nere a match.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<P>A match? I'de rather bee matcht from a Muskets mouth, and shot vnto my death.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chaw,</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile wrastle with any man for a good supper.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<L>I marry sir, ile take your part there, catch that catch may.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sir, she is willing too't. There at my house,</L>
<L>She shall be priuate, and neare to my attendance,</L>
<L>I know you not mistrust my faithfull care,</L>
<L>I shall returne her soone and perfectly.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ,</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Take your charge sir, go with this gentleman (<HI>Iane</HI>)</L>
<L>But prithee looke well this way, ere thou go'st,</L>
<L>'Tis a rich Simplicity of great Estate:</L>
<L>A thing that will be rul'd, and thou shalt rule,</L>
<L>Consider of your sexes generall ayme,</L>
<L>

<PB REF="17"/>That domination is a womans heauen.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>I</HI>'le thinke on't sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<L>My daughter is retiring, sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chaw.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>I</HI> will part at <HI>Dartmouth</HI> with her, sir, Oh that thou didst but loue wrastling, <HI>I</HI> would giue any man three foiles on that condition.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<P>There's three sorts of men that would thanke you for 'um, eyther Cutlers, Fencers, or Players.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir as <HI>I</HI> began, <HI>I</HI> end, wondrous welcome.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Russ, Iane, Phys. An.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<P>What, will you go to schoole to day? you are en∣terd you know, and your quarterige runs on.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chaw.</SPEAKER>
<P>What? to the roaring schoole? pox on't, 'tis such a damnable noyse, <HI>I</HI> shall neuer attaine it neyther: <HI>I</HI> doe wonder they haue neuer a Wrastling Schoole, that were worth twenty of your fencing or dancing schooles.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wel, you must learne to roare here in <HI>London,</HI> you'le neuer proceede in the reputation of Gallantrie else.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chaw.</SPEAKER>
<P>How long ha's Roaring been an exercise, thinkest thou <HI>Trimtram.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<P>Euer since Guns came vp, the first was your roaring <HI>Meg</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Ch. Meg</HI>▪</SPEAKER>
<P>Then 'twas a woman was the first roarer:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>I,</HI> a fire of her tuch-hole, 'that cost many a proper mans life since that time: and then the Lyons they learn't it from the Guns, liuing so neare 'um, then it was heard to the Banckeside, and the Beares they beganne to roare: then the boyes got it, and so euer since there haue beene a company of roaring boyes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chaw.</SPEAKER>
<P>And how long will it last, thinkest thou?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<P>As long as the Water runs vnder <HI>London</HI> Bridge, or Watermen at <HI>Westminster</HI> stayres.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chaw.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, <HI>I</HI> will beginne to roare too, since it is in fa∣shion, Oh <HI>Corineus,</HI> this was not in thy time, <HI>I</HI> should haue heard on't by the tradition of mine Ancestors (for <HI>I</HI>' me sure there were <HI>Chawghes</HI> in thy dayes) if it had beene so, when <HI>Hercules</HI> and thou wert on the <HI>Olimpicke</HI> mount together, then was wrastling in request.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="17"/>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>I,</HI> and that Mount is now the Mount in <HI>Cornwall. Corineus</HI> brought it thither vnder one of his arms, they say.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chaw.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh <HI>Corineus</HI> my predecessor: that <HI>I</HI> had but liu'd in those dayes to see thee wrastle, on that condition <HI>I</HI> had dyed seuen yeare ago.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, it should haue been a dozen at least, yfaith, on that condition.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus Tertius. Scaena Prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Captaine Ager with his two friends.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, your wils now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Our Wils? our Loues, our Duties</L>
<L>To honord Fortitude: What wils haue we</L>
<L>But our desires to Noblenes and Merit?</L>
<L>Valours aduancement, and the sacred Rectitude</L>
<L>Due to a valourous cause.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, thats not mine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>War ha's his court of Iustice, that's the field,</L>
<L>Where all cases of Manhood are determinde,</L>
<L>And your case is no meane one.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>True, then 'twere vertuous:</L>
<L>But mine is in extreames, fowle and vniust:</L>
<L>Well, now y'aue got me hither, y'are as far</L>
<L>To seeke in your desire, as at first minute:</L>
<L>For by the strength and honour of a vow,</L>
<L><HI>I</HI> will not lift a finger in this quarrell.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>How? not in this? be not so rash a sinnen:</L>
<L>Why sir, doe you euer hope to fight agen then</L>
<L>Take heede on't, you must neuer looke for that,</L>
<L>Why the vniuersall stocke of the Worlds iniury,</L>
<L>Will bee too poore to finde a quarrell for you:</L>
<L>Giue vp your right and title to desert, sir,</L>
<L>If you fayle vertue here, shee needes you not:</L>
<L>All your time after, let her take this wrong,</L>
<L>And neuer presume then to serue her more:</L>
<L>

<PB REF="18"/>Bid farewell to the integrity of armes,</L>
<L>And let that honourable name of Souldier</L>
<L>Fall from you like a shiuered wreath of Lawrell</L>
<L>By Thunder strucke from a desertlesse forehead,</L>
<L>That weares anothers right by vsurpation.</L>
<L>Good Captaine, do not wilfully cast away</L>
<L>At one houre all the same your life ha's won:</L>
<L>This is your natiue seate, here you should seeke</L>
<L>Most to preserue it, or if you will doate</L>
<L>So much on life (poorelife) which in respect</L>
<L>Of life in honour is but death and darknesse</L>
<L>That you will proue neglectfull of your selfe,</L>
<L>Which is to me too fearefull to imagine,</L>
<L>Yet for that vertuous Ladies cause (your mother)</L>
<L>Her Reputation, deere to Noblenesse</L>
<L>As grace to penitence, whose fayre memory,</L>
<L>Ee'n crowns fame in your issue, for that blessed∣nes,</L>
<L>Giue not this ill place, but in spite of hell,</L>
<L>And all her base feates, be exactly valiant,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh—o—o</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Why, well sayd, thetes fayre hope in that,</L>
<L>Another such a one.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Came they in thousands?</L>
<L>Tis all against you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Then poore friendlesse merite,</L>
<L>Heauē be good to thee, thy professor leaues thee:</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Enter Colonell and his two friends.</STAGE>
<L>Hee's comd, do but you draw, wee'le fight it for you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know too much to grant that.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O dead manhood!</L>
<L>Had euer such a cause so faynt a seruant?</L>
<L>Shame brand me if I do not suffer for him.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colo.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Iu'e heard sir, ya'ue bin guilty of much boasting,</L>
<L>For your braue earlines at such a meeting,</L>
<L>Y'aue lost the glory of that way this morning:</L>
<L>I was the first to day.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt,</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>So were you euer.</L>
<L>

<PB REF="18"/>In my respect sir.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L>O most base <HI>Praeludium!</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I neuer thought on Victory our Mistres</L>
<L>With greater reuerence then I haue your worth,</L>
<L>Nor euer lou'd her better.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Slight, I could knocke his braines about his heeles, mee thinkes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace, prithee peace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Successe in you has beene my absolute ioy,</L>
<L>And when I haue wisht content, I haue wisht your friend∣ship.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Stay, let me but run him through the tongue a little,</L>
<L>Theres Lawyers bloud in't, you shal see foule geere streight</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come you are as mad now, as hee's cowardous.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<L>I came not hither sir for an <HI>Encomium.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No, the more Coxcombe he, that clawes the head</L>
<L>Of your vaine glory with't!</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I came prouided</L>
<L>For Stormes and Tempests, and the fowlest Season</L>
<L>That euer Rage let forth, or blew in wildnesse</L>
<L>From the incensed prison of mans bloud.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Tis otherwise with me, I come with Mildnesse,</L>
<L>Peace, constant Amity, and calme Forgiuenes,</L>
<L>The weather of a Cristian and a friend.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1,</SPEAKER>
<L>Giue me a valiant Turke, though not worth ten pence, rather.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yet sir, the world will iudge the iniury mine.</L>
<L>Insufferable mine, mine beyond iniury,</L>
<L>Thousands haue made a lesse wrong reach to hel,</L>
<L>I, and reioyc'st in his most endlesse vengeance,</L>
<L>(A miserable triumph, though a iust one)</L>
<L>But when I call to memory our long friendship</L>
<L>Me thinkes it cannot be too great a wrong.</L>
<L>That then I should not pardon, why should man,</L>
<L>Eor a poore hasty syllable or two,</L>
<L>(And vented onely in forgetfull fury)</L>
<L>Cheine all the hopes and riches of his soule</L>
<L>To the reuenge of that, dye, lost for euer:</L>
<L>For he that makes his last peace with his Maker</L>
<PB REF="19"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="19"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<L>

<PB REF="20"/>In anger, anger is his peace eternally:</L>
<L>He must expect the same returne againe,</L>
<L>Whose venture is deceitfull. Must he not sir?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L><HI>I</HI> see what <HI>I</HI> must do, fairely put vp agen:</L>
<L>For here'le be nothing done, <HI>I</HI> perceiue that,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What shall be done in such a worthlesse businesset</L>
<L>But to be sorry, and to be forgiuen.</L>
<L>You sir to bring repentance, and <HI>I</HI> pardon.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>I</HI> bring repentance sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If it be too much</L>
<L>To say Repentance: Call it what you please sir:</L>
<L>Chuse your owne world, I know you'r sorry for't, and thats as good.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I sorry? by fames honour, I am wrongd:</L>
<L>Doe you seeke for peace, and draw the quarrell larger?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then tis: I'me sorry that I thought you so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Captaine, I could gnaw his title of.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Nor is it any misbecomming vertue, sir,</L>
<L>In the best manlines to repent a wrong,</L>
<L>Which made me bold with you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L>I could cuff his head off,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay: pish.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pox on him, I could eate his buttocke bak't me thinks.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>So, once agen take thou thy peacefull rest then,</L>
<L>But as I put thee vp: I must proclaime</L>
<L>This Captaine here, both to his friends and mine,</L>
<L>That onely came to see sayre valour righted,
<STAGE>Offers to go away.</STAGE></L>
<L>A base submisiue coward; so I leaue him.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Oh, heauen has pittied my excessiue patience,</L>
<L>And sent me a cause: now I haue a cause:</L>
<L>A coward I was neuer: —Come you backe sir?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<L>How?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>You left a coward here?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes sir, with you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Tis such base mettell sir: 'twill not be taken,</L>
<L>It must home agen with you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<L>Should this be true now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L>Impossible, coward do more then bastard?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="20"/>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I prethee mocke me not, take heed you do not,</L>
<L>For if I draw once more, I shall grow terrible,</L>
<L>And rage will force me doe what will grieue honour.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, ha, ha.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>He smiles, dare it be he? what thinke you Gentlemē?</L>
<L>Your iudgements, shall I not be cussend in him?</L>
<L>This cannot be the man? why he was bookish,</L>
<L>Made an inuectiue lately against fighting,</L>
<L>A thing introth that mou'de a little with me,</L>
<L>Put vp a fowler contumely far</L>
<L>Then thousand cowards came to, &amp; grew thank∣full</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Blessed remembrance in time of need?</L>
<L>I'de lost my honour else.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do you note his ioy?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I neuer felt a more seuere necessity.</L>
<L>Then came thy excellent pitty.-.Not yet ready?</L>
<L>Haue you such confidence in my iust manhood:</L>
<L>That you dare so long trust me, and yet tempt me</L>
<L>Beyond the tolleration of mans vertue,</L>
<L>Why? would you be more cruel then your iniury?</L>
<L>Do you first take pride to wrong me, &amp; then think me</L>
<L>Not worth your fury, do not vse me so:</L>
<L>I shall deceyue you then: sir, eyther draw,</L>
<L>And that not sleightingly, but with the care</L>
<L>Of your best preseruation; with that watchfulnes,</L>
<L>As you'd defend your selfe from circuler fire,</L>
<L>Your sins rage, or her Lord, this will require it,</L>
<L>Or you'le be too soone lost for I'ue an anger</L>
<L>Has gathered mighty strength against you: mighty;</L>
<L>Yet you shall find it honest to the last,</L>
<L>Noble and Fayre.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I'le ventur'te once agen.</L>
<L>And if't be but as true, as it is wondrous,</L>
<L>I shall haue that I come for; Your leaue Gent.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If he should doo't indeed, &amp; deceiues al now:</L>
<L>Stay, by this hand he offers; fights yfaith.</L>
<L>Fights: by this light he fights sir.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="21"/>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<L>So me thinkes sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L>An absolute Punto: hey.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<L>!Twas a Passado sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Why let it passe, and 'twas, I'me sure, t'was somwhat,</L>
<L>Whats that now.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thats a Punto.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O goe to then,</L>
<L>I knew 'twas not farre off: What a worlds this?</L>
<L>Is coward a more stirring meat then bastard, my Masters?</L>
<L>Put in more egges for shame when you get children,</L>
<L>And make it true Court custard. —Ho? I honor thee:</L>
<L>Tis right and fayre, and he that breathes against it,</L>
<L>He breathes against the iustice of a man,</L>
<L>And man to cut him off: tis no iniustice.</L>
<L>Thanks, thanks, for this most vnexpected noblenes.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Truth neuer fayles her seruant, sir, nor leaues him With the dayes shame vpon him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Th'ast redeemde</L>
<L>Thy worth to the same height 'twas first esteemde.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Captaine and his friends.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Col.</HI> 1. <HI>Friend.</HI></SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Alasse, how is it sir: giue vs some hope</L>
<L>Of your stay with vs: Let your spirit bee seene</L>
<L>Aboue your fortune, the best fortitude</L>
<L>Ha's been of Fate ill friended: Now force your Empire,</L>
<L>And raigne aboue your bloud, spite of deiection,</L>
<L>Reduce the Monarchie of your abler mind,</L>
<L>Let not flesh streighten it.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Oh, iust Heauen has found me,<SUP>1</SUP></L>
<L>And turnde the strings of my too hasty Iniuries</L>
<L>Into my owne bloud, I pursude my ruine,</L>
<L>And vrgde him past the patience of an Angell.</L>
<L>Could mans reuenge extend beyond mans life:</L>
<L>This would ha' wak't it, If this flame will light me</L>
<L>But till I see my sister: tis a kinde one.</L>
<L>More I expect not from't, Noble deseruer:</L>
<L>Farewell most valiant, and most wrong'd of men,
<STAGE>Exeunt, led by them.</STAGE></L>
<L>Do but forgiue me, &amp; I am Victor then.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>

<PB REF="21"/>
<HI>Enter Physitian, Iane, Anne, Dutch Nurse with the child.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phys.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sweet Fro, to your most indulgent care,</L>
<L>Take this my hearts ioy, I must not tell you,</L>
<L>The valew of this iewell in my bosome.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dat you may vell. sir, der can niet forstoore you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ph.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Indeed I cannot tell you, you know Nurse,</L>
<L>These are aboue the quantity of prise,</L>
<L>Where is the glory of the goodliest trees</L>
<L>But in the fruit and branches? The old stocke</L>
<L>Must decay, and sprigs, syens such as these</L>
<L>Must become new stockes from vs to glory,</L>
<L>In their fruitfull issue, so we are made</L>
<L>Immortall on by other.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nur.</SPEAKER>
<P>You spreke a most lieben fader, and Ick fall do de best of tender Nurses to dis Infant, my prettie Frokin.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phys.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I know you will be louing, here sweet friend,
<STAGE>Giue. money.</STAGE></L>
<L>Heere's earnest of a large summe of loue and coyne.</L>
<L>To quit your tender care.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue some reason too,
<STAGE>Giues her money.</STAGE></L>
<L>To purchase your deare care vnto this Infant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nurs.</SPEAKER>
<P>You be de witnesse of de Baptime, dat is, as you spreken: de godimother, ick vell forstoor it so.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, I am the bad mother: If it be offence.
<STAGE>Aside.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ann.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must be a little kinde too.
<STAGE>Giues her money.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nurs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Much tankes to you all: dis child is much belouen: and Ick sall see much care ouer it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phys.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Farewell good sister: Show her the way forth,</L>
<L>I shall often visite you, kind Nurse.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nurs.</SPEAKER>
<L>You sall be velcome.
<STAGE>Exeunt Ann and Nurse.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Oh sir, what a friend haue I found in you?</L>
<L>Where my poore power shall stay in the requitall,</L>
<L>Your selfe must from your fayre condition</L>
<L>Make vp in meere acceptance of my will.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phys.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Oh, pray you vrge it not, we are not borne</L>
<L>For our selues onely, selfe loue is a sinne,</L>
<L>But in our louing donatiues to others,</L>
<L>Mans vertue best consists, loue all begets,</L>
<L>

<PB REF="22"/>Without, all are adulterate and counterfeit.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Your boundlesse loue I cannot satisfie,</L>
<L>But with a mentall memory of your vertues,</L>
<L>Yet let me not ingage your cost withall,</L>
<L>Beseech you then take restitution</L>
<L>Of paines and bounty which you haue disburst</L>
<L>For your poore debter.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phys.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You will not offer it:</L>
<L>Doe not esteeme my loue so mercenary,</L>
<L>To be the hyre of coyne? Sure, I shall thinke</L>
<L>You doe not hold so worthily of me</L>
<L>As I wish to deserue.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Not recompence!</L>
<L>Then you will begger me with too much credit,</L>
<L>If not sufficient, you preserue my name,</L>
<L>Which I had forfeyted to shame and scorne:</L>
<L>Couer my vices with a vaile of loue,</L>
<L>Defend and keepe me from a fathers rage,</L>
<L>Whose loue yet infinite (not knowing this)</L>
<L>Might (knowing) turne a hate as infinite:</L>
<L>Sure he would throw me euer from his blessings,</L>
<L>And cast his curses on me: yes, further,</L>
<L>Your secresie keepes me in the state of woman:</L>
<L>For else what husband would chuse me his wife:</L>
<L>Knowing the honour of a Bride were lost.</L>
<L>I cannot number halfe the good you doe me,</L>
<L>In the concealde retention of my sinne,</L>
<L>Then make me not worse then I was before.</L>
<L>In my ingratitude, good sir.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phys.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Agen.</L>
<L>I shall repent my loue (if you'le so call't)</L>
<L>To be made such a Hackney, giue me coyne?</L>
<L>I had as leaue you gaue me poyson (Lady)</L>
<L>For I haue Art and Antidotes gain'st that,</L>
<L>I might take that, but this <HI>I</HI> will refuse.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ian.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Well you then teach me how I may requite you,</L>
<L>In some small quantity.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="22"/>
<SPEAKER>Phys.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>'T was that I look't for.
<STAGE>Aside.</STAGE></L>
<L>Yes, I will tell you Lady a full quittance,</L>
<L>And how you may become my Creditresse.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>I beseech you do sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phys.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Indeed I will Lady,</L>
<L>Not in coyne, Mistris, for siluer though white,</L>
<L>Yet it drawes blacke lines: It shall not rule my palme</L>
<L>There to marke forth his base corruption:</L>
<L>Pay me agen in the same quality</L>
<L>That <HI>I</HI> to you tendred, thats loue for loue:</L>
<L>Can you loue me Lady? you haue confest</L>
<L>My loue to you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most amply.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Why faith then,</L>
<L>Pay me backe that way.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>How do you meane, sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phys.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Tush, our meanings are better vnderstood</L>
<L>Then shifted to the tongue, it brings along</L>
<L>A little blabbing bloud into our cheekes,</L>
<L>That shames vs when we speake.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>I vnderstand you not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Fie, you doe, make not your selfe ignorant</L>
<L>In what you know, you haue tane forth the lesson</L>
<L>That I would read to you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sure then I need not,</L>
<L>Reade it agen, sir.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yes, it makes perfect,</L>
<L>You know the way vnto <HI>Achillis</HI> speare,</L>
<L>If that hurt you, I haue the cure you see.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ian.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Come, y'are a good man, I do perceiue you:</L>
<L>You put a tryall to me, I thanke you,</L>
<L>Y'are my iust Confessor, and beleeue me,</L>
<L>I'le haue no further penance for this sinne,</L>
<L>Conuert a yeare vnto a lasting euer,</L>
<L>And call't <HI>Apollo's</HI> smile, 'twas onces then neuer.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray you mistake me not, indeed I loue you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeed, what deed?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="23"/>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<L>The deed that you haue done.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>I cannot belieue you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Belieue the deed then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Away, y'are a Blackamore, you loue me?</L>
<L>I hate you for your loue: Are you the man</L>
<L>That in your painted outside seem'd so white?</L>
<L>Oh, y'are a soule dissembling Hypocrite,</L>
<L>You sau'd me from a thiefe that your selfe might rob me,</L>
<L>Skin'd'ore a greene wound to breed an vlcer.</L>
<L>Is this the practise of your Physicke Colledge?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phys.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Haue you yet vtter'd all your nicenesse forth?</L>
<L>If you haue more, vent it, certes I thinke</L>
<L>Your first grant was not yeelded with lesse paine,</L>
<L>If'twere, you haue your prise, yeeld it againe.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Pray you, tell me sir, (I ask't it before)</L>
<L>Is it a practise 'mongst you Physitians.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Tush, thats a secret, We cast al waters.</L>
<L>Should I reueale, you would mistrust my counsell:</L>
<L>The Lawyer and Physitian here agrees</L>
<L>To women Clients they giue backe their fees,</L>
<L>And is not that kindnesse?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>This for thy loue,
<STAGE>Spits,</STAGE></L>
<L>Out, outside of a man: thou Cynamon tree,</L>
<L>That but thy bark hast nothing good about thee</L>
<L>The Vnicorne is hunted for his horne,</L>
<L>The rest is left for carion: Thou false man.</L>
<L>Tha'st fisht with siluer hookes and golden baites:</L>
<L>But I'le auoyde all thy deceiuing sleights.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phys.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Doe what you lift, I will do somthing too:</L>
<L>Remember yet what I haue done for you,</L>
<L>Y'aue a good face now, but 'twill grow rugged.</L>
<L>Ere you grow old: old men will despise you:</L>
<L>Think on your Grandam <HI>Helen</HI> the fairest Queen</L>
<L>When in a new glasse she spyed her old face:</L>
<L>Shee (smiling) wept to thinke vpon the change,</L>
<L>Take your time, y'are craz'd, y'are an apple falne</L>
<L>From the tree, if you be kept long, you'le rot.</L>
<L>

<PB REF="23"/>Study your answere well, yet I loue you.</L>
<L>If you refuse I haue a hand aboue.
<STAGE>Exit Phys.</STAGE></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Poyson thy selfe, thou soule Empoysoner:</L>
<L>Of thine owne practique drinke the <HI>Theorie.</HI></L>
<L>What, a White Diuill haue I met withall?</L>
<L>What shall I doe? What do? i'st a question?</L>
<L>Nor shame, nor hate, nor feare, nor lust, nor force</L>
<L>(Now being too bad) shall euer make mee worse,</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Enter Anne.</STAGE>
<L>What haue we here? a second spirit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anne.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Mistresse,</L>
<L>I am sent to you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is your message good?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anne.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>As you receyue it, my brother sent me,</L>
<L>And you know he loues you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane,</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I heard say so;</L>
<L>But 'twas a false report.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anne.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Pray, pardon me, I must doe my message,</L>
<L>Who liues (commanded) must obey his Keeper.</L>
<L>I must perswade you to this act of woman.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>Woman! of Strumpet</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anne.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Indeed of Strumpet,</L>
<L>He takes you at aduantage of your fall,</L>
<L>Seeing you downe before.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>Curse on his fained smiles.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>An.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Hee's my brother Mistresse, &amp; a curse on you</L>
<L>If ere you blesse him with that cursed deede,</L>
<L>Hang him, poyson him, he held out a Rose,</L>
<L>To draw the yeelding sence, which come to hand</L>
<L>He shifts, and giues a canker.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>You speake well yet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ann.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I, but Mistresse, now I consider it,</L>
<L>Your reputation lyes at his mercy,</L>
<L>Your fault dwels in his brest, say, he throw it out,</L>
<L>It will be knowne, how are you then vndone?</L>
<L>Thinke on't, your good name, and they are not to be solde▪</L>
<L>In euery market, a good name's deare,</L>
<L>And indeed more esteemed then our actions,</L>
<L>

<PB REF="24"/>By which wee should deserue it.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>Aye me most wretched.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anne.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What? doe you shrinke at that?</L>
<L>Would you not weare one spot vpon your face,</L>
<L>To keepe your whole body from a leprosie,</L>
<L>Though it were vndiscouerd euer, hang him,</L>
<L>Feare him not. Horseleeches sucke out his corrupt bloud,</L>
<L>Draw you none from him, lesse it be pure and good.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do you speake your soule?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anne.</SPEAKER>
<L>By my soule doe I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Then yet I haue a friend; but thus exhort me,</L>
<L>And I haue still a collumbe to support me.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anne.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>One fault Heauen soone forgiues, and tis on earth forgot,</L>
<L><HI>The Moone her selfe is not without one spot.</HI>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter the Lady Ager, meeting one of her seruants.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Now sir, where is he? speake, why comes he not?</L>
<L>I sent you for him; blesse this fellowes sences:</L>
<L>What has he seene? a soule nine houres entrancst,</L>
<L>Houering twixt hell and heauen, could not wake gastlier,</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Enter Seruant.</STAGE>
<LG>
<L>Not yet returne an answere? What say you sir?</L>
<L>Where is he?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Ser.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Gon?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>What sayst thou?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Ser.</HI></SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>He is gone Madame.</L>
<L>But as we heard, vnwillingly hee went</L>
<L>As euer bloud enforc't.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<L>Went, whether went he?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Ser.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, I feare, I ha said too much already.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<L>These men are both agreed, speake, whether went he?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Se.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Why to—I would you'd thinke the rest your selfe Madame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>Meeke Patience blesse me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Ser.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>To the field.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Ser.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>To fight, Madame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>To fight!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Ser.</HI></SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>There came two vrging Gentlemen,</L>
<L>That cal'd themselues his seconds, both so powerfull,</L>
<L>As tis reported they preuailde with him,</L>
<L>With little labour.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="24"/>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O hees lost, hees gone,</L>
<L>For all my paines, hee's gone; two meeting torrents</L>
<L>Are not so mercilesse as their two rages,</L>
<L>Hee neuer comes agen,—wretched affection.</L>
<L>Haue I belied my faith? iniur'd my goodnes?</L>
<L>Slaunderd my honour for his praeseruation?</L>
<L>Hauing but onely him: and yet no happier.</L>
<L>Tis then a iudgment plaine, truths angrie with mee,</L>
<L>In that I would abuse her sacred whitenesse,</L>
<L>For any wordly temporall respect:</L>
<L>Forgiue me then thou glorious womans vertue,</L>
<L>Admir'd where ere thy habitation is,</L>
<L>Especially in vs weake ones: Oh forgiue mee.</L>
<L>For tis thy vengeance this, to belie truth,</L>
<L>VVhich is so hardly ours, with such paine purchas'd</L>
<L>Fastings, and praiers, continence and care,</L>
<L>Misery must needs ensue: Let him not dye</L>
<L>In that vnchast beliefe of his false birth,</L>
<L>And my disgrace: VVhat euer Angell guides him,</L>
<L>May this request be with my teares obtaind,</L>
<L>Let his soule know, my honour is vnstaind,</L>
<L>Runne, seeke, away, if there be any hope,
<STAGE>Exeunt Seru.</STAGE></L>
<L>Let me not loose him yet; when I thinke on him,</L>
<L>His deerenes, and his worth, it earnes me more,</L>
<L>They that know riches tremble to be poore.</L>
<L>My passion is not euery womans sorrow,</L>
<L>She must be truly honest feeles my greese,</L>
<L>And onely knowne to One, if such there bee,</L>
<L>They know the sorrow that oppresseth mee.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</LG>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus quartus, Scaena prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter the Colonels Second.. Vsher &amp;c. with Chaugh and Trim.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Second.</SPEAKER>
<P>Truth sir, I must needs blame you for a Trewant, hauing but one lesson read to you and neglect so soone: fye, I must see you once a day at least.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="25"/>
<SPEAKER>Chaugh.</SPEAKER>
<P>Would I were whipt Tutor if it were not long of my man <HI>Trimtram</HI> here.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who, of mee?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cha.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tak't vpon the <HI>Trim.</HI> Ile giue the fiue shillings, 'as <HI>I</HI> am a Gentleman.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile see you whipt first: well, <HI>I</HI> will too; faith sir, <HI>I</HI> saw he was not perfect, and <HI>I</HI> was loth he should come be∣fore to shame himselfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<P>How? shame sir? is it a shame for Schollers to learne? Sir, there are great Schollers that are but slenderly read in our profession: sir, first it must be <HI>Oeconomicall,</HI> the <HI>Oecume∣nicall</HI>: shame not to practise in the house how to performe in the field: the naile that is driuen takes a little hould at the first stroke, but more at the second, and more at the third, but when tis home to the head, then tis firme.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith <HI>I</HI> haue bene driuing it home to the head this two dayes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>I</HI> helpt to hammer it in as well as <HI>I</HI> could too sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVell sir, <HI>I</HI> will heare you rehearse anon, meane time peruse the exemplary of my bills, and tell me in what lan∣guage <HI>I</HI> shall rore a Lectue to you; or ile read to you the Ma∣thematicall science of Roaring.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cha.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Is</HI> it Mathematicall?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh sir, does not the windes roare? the Sea roare? the Welkin roare? indeed, most thinges doe roare by nature, and is not the knowledge of these thinges Mathematicall?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cha.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray prooceed sir.
<STAGE>reads his bill</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<P>The names of the languages, the <HI>Sclanonian, Partha∣menian, Barmeothian, Tiburnian, Wappinganian,</HI> or the mo∣derne <HI>Londonian.</HI> Any man or woman that is desirous to roare in any of these languages, in a weeke they shall be perfect, if they will take paines; so let'um repaire into Holborne to the signe of the Cheat loafe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now your bill speakes of that, I was wondring a good while at your signe, the loafe lookes very like bread ifaith, but why is it called the cheate loafe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Second.</SPEAKER>
<P>This house was sometimes a Bakers sir, that serued the Court where the bread is called cheate.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="25"/>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, I, twas a Baker that cheated the Court with bread.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well sir, choose your languages: and your Lectures shal be read, betweene my Vsher and my selfe, for your bet∣ter instruction, prouided your conditions be performed in the premisses beforesaid.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Looke you sir, theres twenty pound in hand, and twenty more, I am to pay when I am allowed a sufficient Roarer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<P>You speake in good earnest sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes faith doe <HI>I Trimtram</HI> shall be my witnes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes indeed sir, twenty pound is very good earnest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vsher.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir one thing I must tell you belongs to my place, you are the youngest Scholler, and till another comes vnder you, there is a certaine garnish belongs to the Schoole, for in our practise we grow to a quarrell: then there must be wine ready to make all friends, for thats the end of Roaring, 'tis valiant but harmelesse, and this charge is yours.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>With all my heart ifaith and <HI>I</HI> like it the better: be∣cause no blood comes on it, who shall fetch?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Roar.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Ile be your Spanniell sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<P>Bid Vapor, bring some Tobacco too,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doe and heere's mony for't.
<STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> 2. <HI>Roarer.</HI></STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vsher.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, you shall not, let me see the mony: so, Ile keepe it, and discharge him after the Combat, for your practise sake you and your man shall roare him out on't, (for indeed you must pay your debts so: for thats one of the maine ends of Roaring) and when you haue left him in a chafe, then Ile qualifie the Rascall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Content ifaith <HI>Trim.</HI> weele Roare the rusty Rascall out of his Tobacco.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>I</HI> and he had the best Craccus in London.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<P>Obserue Sir, wee could now roare in the Slauonian Language, but this practise hath beene a little sublime: some hayres breadth or so aboue your Caput; <HI>I</HI> take it for your vse and vnderstanding both it were fitter for you to tast the mo∣derne assault, only the Londonian Roare.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ifaith sir, that's for my purpose, for I shall vse all my


<PB REF="26"/>
roaring heere in London: in Cornewall wee are all for wrast∣ling, and I doe not meane to trauell ouer sea to roare there.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<P>Obserue then sir, but it were necessary you took forth your tables, to note the most difficult poynts for the better assistance of your memory.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay sir, my man and I keep two Tables.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<P>I sir, and as many trenchers, cattes meat and dogges meate enough.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<P>Note sir, — Dost thou confront my <HI>Cyclops?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vsh.</SPEAKER>
<P>With a <HI>Briarean Brousted</HI>:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Cyclops.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Briarean.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<P>I know thee and thy lineall pedegree,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vsher.</SPEAKER>
<P>It is Collateral: as <HI>Brutus</HI> and <HI>Posthumus.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<P>Brutus.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Posthumus.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<P>False as the face of <HI>Heccate</HI>; thy sister is a —</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vsh.</SPEAKER>
<P>What is my Sister Centaure?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seco.</SPEAKER>
<P>I say thy Sister is a Bronstrops.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Vsh</HI>:</SPEAKER>
<P>A Bronstrops!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tutor, Tutor, ere you goe any further, tell mee the English of that, what is a <HI>Bronsterops</HI> pray.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Se.</SPEAKER>
<P>A <HI>Bronsterops</HI> is in English a <HI>Hippocrene.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>A <HI>Hippocrene,</HI> note it <HI>Trim.</HI> I loue to vnderstand the English as I goe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whats the English of <HI>Hippierene.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why <HI>Bronsterops?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vsh:</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou dost obtrect my flesh and blood,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<P>Agen, I denounce, thy sister is a fructifer,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>What's that Tutor?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<P>That is in English a <HI>Fucus</HI> or a <HI>Minotaure.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>A <HI>Minotaure:</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>A <HI>Fucus.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vsh.</SPEAKER>
<P>I say thy mother is a <HI>Callieut,</HI> a <HI>Panagron,</HI> a <HI>Duplar</HI> and a <HI>Sindicus.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<P>Dislocate thy <HI>Bladud.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vsh.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Bladud</HI> shall coniure, if his Daemons once appeare,</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> 2. <HI>Roarer with Wine, and</HI> Vapor <HI>with Tobacco.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<P>Aduance thy respondency.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="26"/>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay good gentleman, doe not fallout, a cup of wine quickly <HI>Trimtram.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vsh:</SPEAKER>
<P>See my steele hath a glister,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray wipe him, and put him vp againe good Vsher.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vsh.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir at your request I pull downe the Flag of defiance.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<P>Giue me a boule of Wine my fury shall bee quencht, heere Vsher.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vsh.</SPEAKER>
<P>I pledge thee in good friendship.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>I like the conclusion of Roaring very well ifaith.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<P>It has an excellent conclusion indeed, if the Wine be good, alwayes prouided.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seco.</SPEAKER>
<P>O the wine must be alwayes prouided be sure of that.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vsh.</SPEAKER>
<P>Else you spoyle the conclusion, and that you know crownes all.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis much like wrestling ifaith: for wee shake hands ere we begin: now thats to avoid the Law, for then if hee throw him a furlong into the grownd, hee cannot recouer himselfe vpon him, because twas done in cold friendship.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seco.</SPEAKER>
<P>I beleeue you sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>And then we drinke afterwards, iust in this fashion, wrestling and Roaring are as like as can bee ifaith, euen like long sword and halfe pike.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay they are reciprocall if you marke it, for as there is a great Roaring at Wrestling: so there is a kinde of wrest∣ling and contention at Roaring.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>True ifaith, for I haue heard 'um roare from the sixe windmilles to <HI>Islington</HI>: those haue beene great falls then.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come, now a briefe rehersall of your other dayes lesson, betwixt your man and you, and then for to day wee break vp schoole.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come, <HI>Trimtram</HI>; if I be out Tutor, Ile be bold to looke in my tables, because I doubt I am scarse perfect.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, well, I will not see small faults</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>The wall,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<P>The wall of mee, to thy kennell spannell,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wilt thou not yeeld precedencie?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<P>To thee, I know thee and thy broode</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Knowst thou my brood, I know thy broode to,


<PB REF="27"/>
thou art a Rooke;</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<P>The nearer a kinne to the Chaughes?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Rookes a kin to the Chaughis?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<P>Verie well maintain'd,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Dungcoer, thou liest,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<P>Lie, enucleate the kernell of thy scabberd,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now if I durst draw my sword, twere valiant yfaith:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seco.</SPEAKER>
<P>Draw, draw, howsoeuer,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Haue some wine readie to make vs frends I pray you,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<P>Chaugh, I will make thee flie and roare,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will roare if thou strik'st me,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seco.</SPEAKER>
<P>So tis ynoughe now conclude in wine, I see you will proue an excelent practitioner: wondrous well perform'd on both sides:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heere <HI>Trimtram</HI> I drinke to thee,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le pldge in good friendship,</L>
<STAGE>Enter a Seruant.</STAGE>
<L>Is there not one Maister <HI>Chauogh</HI> heere,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vsh.</SPEAKER>
<P>This is the Gentleman sir;</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seru.</SPEAKER>
<P>My maister, sir, your elected father in law, desires speedyly to speake with you:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Friend I will follow thee, I would thou hadst come a little soner, thou shouldest haue seene Roring sportysaith,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seru.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir Ile returne that you are following,
<STAGE>Exit seruant</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doe so: Ile tell thee <HI>Tutor, I</HI> am to marry shortly, but I will deferre it a while till I can roare perfectly, that I may get the vpper hand of my wife on the wedding day, 'tmust be done at first or neuer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<P>'T will serue you to good vse in that sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cha.</SPEAKER>
<P>How lik'st thou this Whister?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vap.</SPEAKER>
<P>very valiantly ifaith sir,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cha.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tush, thou shalt see more by and by.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>I</HI> can stay no longer indeed sir, who paies mee for my Tobocco?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cha.</SPEAKER>
<P>How, pay for Tobacco, away ye sootie mouth'd pi∣per: you rustie piece of Martlemas bacon, away.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let me giue him a Marke for't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>No <HI>Trimtram,</HI> doe not strike him, weele onely


<PB REF="27"/>
roare out a curse vpon him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, doe you begin then,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>May thy Roule rot, and thy pudding drop in pie∣ces, being sophisticated with filthy vrine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<P>May Serieants dwell on either side of thee, to fright away thy two penny customers.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cha.</SPEAKER>
<P>And for thy penny ones, let them sucke thee drie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhen thou art dead, maist thou haue no other sheets to be buried in but mouldie Tobacco leaues.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cha.</SPEAKER>
<P>And no strawings to sticke thy Carkas, but the bit∣ter stalkes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thy mourners, all greazie Tapsters,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cha.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVith foule Tobacco pipes in their hats in stead of rotten Rose mary: and last of all may my man and <HI>I</HI> liue to see all this perform'd and, to pisse reeking euen vpon thy graue</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<P>And last of all for mee, let this Epitaph bee remem¦bred ouer thee.</P>
</SP>
<Q><LG>
<L>Here coldly now within is laid to rot,</L>
<L>Aman that yesterbay was piping hot:</L>
<L>Some sap he died by p<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>dding, some by pricke,</L>
<L>Others by role and ball some lease, all sticke</L>
<L>Fast in censure, yet thinke it strange and rare,</L>
<L>(He liu'd by smoake, yet died for want of ayre)</L>
<L>But then the Surgeon said when he beheld him,</L>
<L>It was the burning of his Pipe that kild him.</L>
</LG></Q>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>So, are you paid now <HI>whisler?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vap.</SPEAKER>
<P>All this is but smoake out of a stinking Pipe,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>So, so, pay him now <HI>Usher.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec:</SPEAKER>
<P>Doe not henceforth neglect your schooling <HI>M. Chaugh.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cha.</SPEAKER>
<P>Call me Rooke if <HI>I</HI> doe Tutor.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<P>And me Rauen, though my name be <HI>Trimtram.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cha.</SPEAKER>
<P>Farewell Tutor.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<P>Farewell <HI>Vsher.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thus when the Drum's vnbrast, and Trumpet cease, Soldiers must get pay for to liue in peace.
<STAGE>Exeunt</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter the Colonels Sister, meeting the Surgeon.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sist.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh my most worthy brother, thy hard fate 'twas: Come hither honest <HI>Surgeon,</HI> and deale faithfully


<PB REF="28"/>
With a distressed Virgin: what hope is there?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Surg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hope, <HI>Chillis</HI> was scapt miraculously Lady.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sist.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whats that sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Surg Cava vena</HI>:</SPEAKER>
<P>I care but little for his wound'ith <HI>Orso∣phag,</HI> not thus much trust mee, but when they come to <HI>Dia∣phragma</HI> once, the small <HI>Intestines,</HI> or the <HI>Spynall Medull,</HI> or i'th Rootes of the <HI>Emunctories</HI> of the noble parts, then straight <HI>I</HI> feare a <HI>Syncops</HI>; the flankes retyring towards the backe, the <HI>Vrine</HI> bloody, the Excrements <HI>purulent,</HI> and the <HI>Dolour</HI> pricking or pungent.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sist.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alasse I'me nere the better for this answer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Surg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now I must tell you his principal <HI>Dolour</HI> lies i'th re∣gion of the Liuer, and theres both inflamation and <HI>Turma∣faction</HI> feard, marry <HI>I</HI> made him a <HI>Quadragular plumation,</HI> where <HI>I</HI> vsde <HI>Sanguis Draconis</HI>; by my faith, with powders <HI>incarnatiue,</HI> which <HI>I</HI> temperd with oyle of <HI>Hypericon,</HI> and o∣ther liquors mundificatiue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sist.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pox a your Mundies figatiues, <HI>I</HI> would they were all fired,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Surg.</SPEAKER>
<P>But <HI>I</HI> purpose Lady to make an other experiment at next dressing with a <HI>Sarcotricke medicament,</HI> made of <HI>Iris</HI> of Florence. Thus <HI>Masticke, Calaphena, Apopanax, Sacrocolla</HI>:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sist.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sacro-halter, what comfort is i'this to a poore Gen∣tlewoman; pray tell me in plaine tearmes what you thinke of him?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sur.</SPEAKER>
<P>Marry in plaine tearms I know not what to say to him, the wound <HI>I</HI> can assure you enclines to <HI>Paralisme</HI>; and I find his body <HI>Cacochimicke</HI>: being then in feare of Feuer and in∣flamation, <HI>I</HI> nourish him altogeither with <HI>Viands refrigeratine</HI> and giue for potion the iuyce of <HI>Sauicola,</HI> dissolu'd with water <HI>Cerefolium: I</HI> could doe noe more Lady, if his best <HI>Guiguimos</HI> were disseuered.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sist.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What thankelesse paines does the tongue often take,</L>
<L>To make the whole man most ridiculous:</L>
<L><HI>I</HI> come to him for comfort, and he tyres me</L>
<L>Worse then my sorrow, what a pretious good</L>
<L>May be deliuered sweetly in few words:</L>
<L>And what a mount of nothing ha's he cast forth.</L>
<L>

<PB REF="28"/>Alasse his strength decaies: how cheere you sir,</L>
<L>My honourd Brother?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colo.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>In soule neuer better.</L>
<L>I feele an excellent health there, such a stoutnes,</L>
<L>My inuisible enemy flies mee, seeing me armde</L>
<L>With penitence and forgiuenes, they fall backward,</L>
<L>VVhether through admiration, not imagining</L>
<L>There were such armory in a Souldiers soule,</L>
<L>As pardon and repentance: or through power</L>
<L>Of ghostly valour? but I haue bene Lord</L>
<L>Of a more happy conquest in nine howers now,</L>
<L>Then in nine yeares before: Oh kinde Lieftenants</L>
<L>This is the onely war we should prouide for,</L>
<L>VVhere he that forgiues largest &amp; sighes strongest,</L>
<L>Is a tride Soldier, a true man in deed,</L>
<L>And wins the best field, makes his owne heart bleed.</L>
<L>Read the last part of that <HI>Will</HI> sir.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>1 <HI>Liefetenant reads.</HI></STAGE>
<P>I also require at the hands of my most beloued Sister, whom <HI>I</HI> make full Executrix, the disposure of my body in bu∣riall at S. <HI>Martins</HI> i'th field: and to cause to be distributed to the poore of the same parish, forty Marke, and to the Hospital of maymed Souldiers a hundred: lastly I giue and be∣queath to my kinde, deare, and vertuous sister, the full pos∣session of my present estate in riches, whether it be in Lands, Leases, Money, Goods, Plate, Iewels, or what kind soeuer, vpon this condition following, that shee forthwith, tender both her selfe and all these Infeoffments, to that noble Cap∣taine my late Enemy Captaine <HI>Ager.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sist.</SPEAKER>
<L>How sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Read it againe sir, let her heare it plaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sist.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Pray spare your paines sir, tis too plaine already.</L>
<L>Good sir, how doe you, is your memory perfect?</L>
<L>This Will makes question of you: <HI>I</HI> bestowde</L>
<L>So much griefe and compassion a your wound,</L>
<L>I neuer look't into your sences <HI>Epilepsie</HI>:</L>
<L>The sickenes and infirmity of your iudgement</L>
<L>Is to be doubted now, more then your bodies,</L>
<L>

<PB REF="29"/>Why is your loue no dearer to mee sir,</L>
<L>Then to dispose me so vpon the man,</L>
<L>Whose furie is your bodies present torment?</L>
<L>The Author of your danger: one I hate</L>
<L>Beyond the bounds of malice, doe you not feele</L>
<L>His wrath vpon you? <HI>I</HI> beseech you sir,</L>
<L>Alter that cruell article.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colo.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Cruell sister? (forgiue me naturall loue)</L>
<L>I must offend thee, speaking to this woman, am I content,</L>
<L>Hauing much kindred, yet to giue thee all,</L>
<L>(Because in thee <HI>I</HI>'de raise my meanes to goodnesse)</L>
<L>And canst thou prooue so thanklesse to my bounty,</L>
<L>To grudge my soule her peace? is my intent</L>
<L>To leaue her rich, whose onely desire is</L>
<L>To send me poorer into the next world,</L>
<L>Then euer Vsurer went, or politicke Statist?</L>
<L>Is it so burdensome for thee to loue</L>
<L>VVhere <HI>I</HI> forgiue? Oh wretched is the man</L>
<L>That buildes the last hopes of his sauing comforts</L>
<L>Vpon a womans charity? hees most miserable,</L>
<L>If it were possible, her obstinate will</L>
<L>VVill pull him downe in his midway to heauen,</L>
<L>I'ue wrongd that worthy man past recompence,</L>
<L>And in my anger robd him of faire fame:</L>
<L>And thou the fairest restitution art</L>
<L>My life could yeeld him: if I knewe a fairer,</L>
<L>I'de set thee by and thy vnwilling goodnes,</L>
<L>And neuer make my sacred peace of thee:</L>
<L>But theres the cruelty of a fate debard,</L>
<L>Thou art the last, and all, and thou art hard.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sist.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Let your grieu'd heart hold better thoughts of mee,</L>
<L><HI>I</HI> will not proue so sir, but since you enforce it,</L>
<L>VVith such a strength of passion Ile performe,</L>
<L>VVhat by your will you haue inioynd me to,</L>
<L>Though the world neuer shew me ioy agen.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colo.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Oh this may be faire cunning for the time,</L>
<L>To put me off, knowing I hold not long,</L>
<L>And when I looke to haue my ioyes accomplish't,</L>
<L>

<PB REF="29"/>I shall find no such things: that were vilde cosenage,</L>
<L>And not to be repented.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sist.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>By all the blessednes,</L>
<L>Truth and a good life lookes for, I will doo'te sir,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colo.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Comforts reward you for't, when ere you grieue,</L>
<L>I know if you dare sweare I may belieue.
<STAGE>Exeunt</STAGE></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Euter Captaine Ager.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No sooner haue I entrance i'this house now,</L>
<L>But all my ioy falls from mee, which was wont</L>
<L>To be the sanctuary of my comforts:</L>
<L>Me thought I lou'd it with a reuerent gladnes,</L>
<L>As holy men doe consecrated Temples</L>
<L>For the Saints sake, which <HI>I</HI> belieu'd my mother,</L>
<L>But prou'd a false faith since, a fearefull heresie,</L>
<L>O who'de erect th'assurance of his ioyes</L>
<L>Vpon a womans goodnes? whose best vertue,</L>
<L>Is to commit vnseene, and highest secrecie,</L>
<L>To hide but her owne sin, ther's their perfection,</L>
<L>And if shee be so good, which many faile of to,</L>
<L>When these are bad, how wondrous Ill are they,</L>
<L>What comfort I'st to fight, win this dayes fame,</L>
<L>When all my after dayes, are lamps of shame,</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Enter the Lady Ager.</STAGE>
<LG>
<L>Blessings bee firme to me, hee's come tis hee,</L>
<L>A surgeon speedily;</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>A surgion? why maddam,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Perhaps you'le say tis but a little wound</L>
<L>Good to preuent a Danger: quick, a surgeon,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why maddam,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L><HI>I, I,</HI> thats all the faust of valiant men,</L>
<L>Theile not be knowne a their hurts till rhei'r past helpe,</L>
<L>And then to late they wish for't:</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you heare mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Tis no disparagement to 'confesse a wound,</L>
<L><HI>I</HI>'me glad sir tis no worse, a surgeon quickly,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Maddam,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Come, come sir, a woun'ds Honorable,</L>
<L>And neuer shames the wearer,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="30"/>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>By the Iustice</L>
<L><HI>I</HI> owe to honour, <HI>I</HI> came of vntouch't,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'de rather beleeue that;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>You beleeue truth so,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My teares preuaile then, welcome, welcome sir,</L>
<L>As peace and mercy to one new departed,</L>
<L>Why would you goe though, and deceiue me so,</L>
<L>When my aboundant loue tooke all the course</L>
<L>That might be to preuent it, <HI>I</HI> did that,</L>
<L>For my affections sake, goodnes forgiue me for't,</L>
<L>That were my owne lifes safety put vppon't,</L>
<L>Ide rather dye then doo't, thinke how you vsd me then,</L>
<L>'And yet would you goe, and hazard your selfe too,</L>
<L>Twas but vnkindly done.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whats all this Madame?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>See then how rash you were and short in wisedome,</L>
<L>Why wrong my faith <HI>I</HI> did, slanderd my constancy,</L>
<L>Belyed my truth, that which few Mothers will,</L>
<L>Or fewer can, I did, out of true feare</L>
<L>And louing care, onely to keep thee heere.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I doubt <HI>I</HI> am too quick of apprehension, now</L>
<L>And that's a generall fault, when we heere ioyfully,</L>
<L>With the desire of longing fort, <HI>I</HI> aske it:</L>
<L>Why? were you neuer false,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>May death come to me,</L>
<L>Before Repentance then?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I heard it plaine sure,</L>
<L>Not false at all?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>By the reward of truth,</L>
<L>I neuer knew that deed</L>
<L>That claimes the name on't.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>May then that glorious reward you swore by,</L>
<L>Be neuer failing to you, all the blessings</L>
<L>That you haue giuen me since obedient custome</L>
<L>Taught me to kneel &amp; aske 'um, are not valuable</L>
<L>With this immaculate blessing of your truth:</L>
<L>This is the Palme to victory.</L>
<L>The Crowne for all deserts past, and to come,</L>
<L>

<PB REF="30"/>Let 'em be numberlesse, they are rewarded,</L>
<L>Already they'r rewarded: blesse this frame</L>
<L>I feele it much too weake to beare the ioy on't.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rise Sir,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O pardon me—</L>
<L>I cannot honor you too much, too long,</L>
<L><HI>I</HI> kneele not onely to a Mother now,</L>
<L>But to a woman that was neuer false,</L>
<L>Yeare deare, and yeare good too: <HI>I</HI> thinke a that,</L>
<L>What reuerence doe's she merit tis fit such</L>
<L>Should be distinguisht from the prostrate sexe,</L>
<L>And what distinction properer can be showne,</L>
<L>Then honor done to her that keepes her owne,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come sir, Ile haue you rise,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>To doe a deed then,
<STAGE>rises.</STAGE></L>
<L>That shall for euer raise me: O my glory,</L>
<L>Why this, this is the quarrell that <HI>I</HI> lookt for,</L>
<L>The tother but a shift to hold time play,</L>
<L>You sacred ministers of preseruation,</L>
<L>For Heauens sake send him life,</L>
<L>And with it mighty health, and such a strength,</L>
<L>May equal but the cause, I wish no foule things,</L>
<L>If life but glow in him he shall know instantly</L>
<L>That I'me resolud to call him to accompt for't.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why harke you sir,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I bind you by your honor, Madame,</L>
<L>You speake no hindernce too'<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</L>
<L>Take heed, you ought not</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What an vnhappines haue I in goodnes,</L>
<L>'Tis euer my desire to intend well</L>
<L>But haue no fortunate way in't, for all this</L>
<L>deserue <HI>I</HI> yet no better of you: but to be greeud agen?</L>
<L>Are you not well with honest gaine of fame,</L>
<L>With safety purchasd, will you needs tempt a ruine,</L>
<L>That auoyds you?
<STAGE>Exit Lady.</STAGE></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No y'aue preuaild: things of this nature sprung,</L>
<L>When they vse action must vse little tongue.</L>
<L>Now sir, the newes?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>

<PB REF="31"/>
<HI>Enter a Seruant.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sir theres a gentlewoman,</L>
<L>Desires some conference with you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>How, with me?</L>
<L>A Gentlewoman? what is she?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seru.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Her attendant</L>
<L>Deliuered her to be the <HI>Colonels</HI> Sister.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Oh for a storme then,</L>
<L>'Lasse poore vertuous Gentlewoman,</L>
<L>I wil indure her violence with much pitty,</L>
<L>She comes to ease her heart good noble soule,</L>
<L>Tis ee'ne a charity to release the burden,</L>
<L>Were, not that remedy ordaind for weomen,</L>
<L>Their hearts would neuer hold three yeares together,</L>
<L>And heere she comes, <HI>I</HI> neuer markt so much of her,</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Enter the Colonels Sister.</STAGE>
<LG>
<L>That face can be the mistris of no anger</L>
<L>But <HI>I</HI> might very wel indure a month me thinks,</L>
<L><HI>I</HI> am the man speake Lady, Ile stand faire.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sist.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And Ime enioynd by vow to fall thus low,
<STAGE>She kneeles.</STAGE></L>
<L>And from the dying hand of a repentant</L>
<L>Offer for expiation of wrongs done you,</L>
<L>My selfe, and with my selfe all that was his,</L>
<L>Which vpon that condition was made mine,</L>
<L>Being his soules wish to depart absolute man,</L>
<L>In life a soldier death a Christian.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Oh Heauen has toucht him nobly, how it shames</L>
<L>My vertues slow perfection: rise deere brightnes,</L>
<L>I forget manners too, vp matchlesse sweetnesse,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sist.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L><HI>I</HI> must not sir, there is not in my vow</L>
<L>That liberty, <HI>I</HI> must be receiu'd first,</L>
<L>Or all denyed, if either, <HI>I</HI> am free,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>He must be without soule should deny thee,</L>
<L>And with that reuerence <HI>I</HI> receiue the guift,</L>
<L>As it was sent me, worthy Colonel,</L>
<L>Has such a conquering way i'th blest things,</L>
<L>Who euer ouercomes, he only wins.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>

<PB REF="31"/>
<HI>Hem, within.</HI></STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Captaine Albo, a Baud and a Whore.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Harke of these hard-hearted Blood-hounds: these Butchers are ee'ne as mercilesse as their Dogs, they knocke downe a Womans fame, ee'ne as it walkes the Streetes by 'um.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whor.</SPEAKER>
<P>And the Captaine heere that should defend vs, walkes by like Iohn of the Apple loft.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<P>What for interiections <HI>Prisse? Hem, Euax, Vah:</HI> let the Carnisexes scoure their throates: thou knowest there is a curse hangs ouer their bloudy heads, this yeare there shall be more Butchers Pricks burnt then of all trades besides.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bau.</SPEAKER>
<P>I doe wonder how thou camest to be a Captaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>As thou camest to be a Baud <HI>Meg,</HI> and <HI>Prisse</HI> to be a whore, euery one by their deserts.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Baud, and Whore? out you vnprofitable raskall, hast not thou beene at the new Play yet, to teach thee better manners: truely they say they are the finest Players, and good speakers of Gentle-women of our quality; Baud and Whore is not mention'd amongst 'um, but the handsomest narrow-mouth'd names they haue for vs, that some of them may serue as well for a Lady, as for one of our occupation.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Who.</SPEAKER>
<P>Prethee Patronesse, lets goe see a peece of that Play: if we shall haue good words for our mony, tis as much as we can deserue ifaith.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bau.</SPEAKER>
<P>I doubt 'tis too late now, but another time Seruant.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let's goe now sweet face I am acquainted with one of the <HI>Pantomimick<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</HI> the <HI>Bulchins</HI> will vse the Irish Captaine with respect, and you two shall bee boxt amongst the bet∣ter sort.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Who.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sirra Captaine <HI>Albo,</HI> I doubt you are but white∣liuer'd, looke that you defend vs valiantly, you know your pennance else: Patronesse, you remember how you vs'd him once?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bau.</SPEAKER>
<P>I seruant, and I shall neuer forget it, till I vse him so agen: doe you remember Captaine?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="32"/>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mum <HI>Meg,</HI> I will not heare on't now.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bau.</SPEAKER>
<P>How I and my <HI>Amazons</HI> stript you as naked as an Indian.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why <HI>Meg</HI>?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bau.</SPEAKER>
<P>And then how I bound you to the good behauiour, in the open fields.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Who.</SPEAKER>
<P>And then you strow'd oates vpon his hoppers.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Prethee sweet face.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Who.</SPEAKER>
<P>And then brought your Ducks to nibble vpon, him you remember?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh, the remembrance tortures me agen, no more good sweet face.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, lead on Sir: but harke a little.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Chaugh and Trim.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Didst thou bargaine for the bladders with the Butcher <HI>Trim</HI>?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<P>I sir, I haue 'um heere, I'le practise to swim too sir, and then I may roare with the water at London bridge, he that roares by land and by water both, is the the perfect Roarer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well Ile venter to swim too: if my father in Law giues me a good dowry with his daughter, I shall hold vp my head well enough.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<P>Peace, sir, heere's practise for our roaring, heer's a <HI>Centaure,</HI> and two <HI>Hippocrenes.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Offer the iustle <HI>Trim.</HI>
<STAGE>Iustle:</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha? What meanest thou by that?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<P>I meane to confront thee, <HI>Cyclops.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile tell thee what a meanes, is this thy Sister?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>How then sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why then I say shee is a <HI>Bronsterops</HI>: and this is a <HI>Fucus.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Who.</SPEAKER>
<P>No indeed sir, we are both <HI>Fucusses.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Art thou military? art thou a Soldier?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>A Soldier, no I scorne to be so poore, I am a Roarer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>A Roarer?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<P>I sir, two Roarers.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ca.</SPEAKER>
<P>Know then my fresh water friends, that I am a Capten.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>What, and haue but two to serue vnder you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am now retiring the field.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="32"/>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<P>You may see that by his Bag and Baggage.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Deliuer vp thy <HI>Panagron</HI> to me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<P>And giue me thy <HI>Sindicus.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Deliuer?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bau.</SPEAKER>
<P>I pray you Captaine bee contented, the Gentlemen seeme to giue vs very good wordes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good words? I if you could vnderstand 'um, the words cost twenty pound.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bau.</SPEAKER>
<P>What is your pleasure Gentlemen?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>I would <HI>enucleate</HI> my <HI>Fructifer.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Who.</SPEAKER>
<P>What sayes he Patronesse?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bau.</SPEAKER>
<P>He would <HI>enoculate</HI>: I vnderstand the Gentleman very pithily.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Speake, are you Gentile or Plebeyan, can you giue Armes?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Armes? I sir, you shall feele our armes presently.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sault you the Women, Ile pepper him til he stinks agen: I perceiue what Country-man hee is, let mee alone with him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Dar'st thou charge a Captaine?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, and discharge vpon him too.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Foh, tis poyson to my Country, the slaue has eaten pippins: Oh shoote no more, turne both thy Broad-sides rather then thy Poope: 'tis foule play: my Country breeds no poyson: I yeelde, the great <HI>O Toole</HI> shall yeeld on these condicions.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue giuen one of 'um a faire fall <HI>Trim.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then thus farre wee bring home Conquest: fol∣low me Captaine, the <HI>Cyclops</HI> doth command.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Follow mee <HI>Tweaks,</HI> the <HI>Centaure</HI> doth com∣mand.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Any thing sweet Gentlemen, wilt please you to lead to the Tauerne, where weele make all friends.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why now you come to the conclusion.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Stay, <HI>Trim</HI>; I haue heard your <HI>Tweakes</HI> are like your Mer maydes, they haue sweet voyces to entice the passengers: lets haue a Song, and then weele set 'um at liberty.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="33"/>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<L>In the commendation of Roaring, not else Sir,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, in the commendation of Roaring,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bau.</SPEAKER>
<L>The best we can Gentlemen.</L>
<LG TYPE="song">
<HEAD>Sing Baud.</HEAD>
<L><HI>THen heere thou shalt resigne</HI></L>
<L><HI>Both Captaine and Commander,</HI></L>
<L><HI>That name was neuer thine,</HI></L>
<L><HI>But Apple-Squire and Pander.</HI></L>
<L><HI>And henceforth will wee grant,</HI></L>
<L><HI>In pillage or in monies,</HI></L>
<L><HI>In cloathing or prouant,</HI></L>
<L><HI>What ere wee get by Conies:</HI></L>
<L>With a hone, a hone, a hone,</L>
<L>No Cheaters nor Decoyes,</L>
<L>Shall haue a share, but alone</L>
<L>The brauest Roaring Boyes.</L>
<L><HI>What are we get by Gulls,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Of Country or of Citty</HI>:</L>
<L><HI>Old Flatcaps or young Heyres,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Or Lawyers Clarkes so witty</HI>:</L>
<L><HI>By Saylers newly landed,</HI></L>
<L><HI>To put in for fresh waters</HI>:</L>
<L><HI>By wandring Gander-mooners</HI>:</L>
<L><HI>Or mufled late night-walkers.</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg">With a, &amp;c.</NOTE></L>
<L><HI>What are we get by Strangers,</HI></L>
<L><HI>The Scotch, the Dutch, or Irish:</HI></L>
<L><HI>Or to come nearer home,</HI></L>
<L><HI>By Maisters of the Parish.</HI></L>
<L><HI>It is concluded thus,</HI></L>
<L><HI>By all and euery wench,</HI></L>
<L><HI>To take of all their coynes,</HI></L>
<L><HI>And pay 'um backe in French.</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg">With a, &amp;c.</NOTE></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Melodious <HI>Minotaure.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Harmonious <HI>Hippocrene.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweet-brested <HI>Bronsterops.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most runable <HI>Tweake.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Delicious <HI>Duplar.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Putrefactious <HI>Panagron.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Calumnious <HI>Calieut.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<L>And most singular <HI>Sindicus.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bau.</SPEAKER>
<P>We shall neuer be able to deserue these good words at your hands Gentlemen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="33"/>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shake golls with the Captaine, hee shall be thy vali∣ant friend.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not yet Captaine, wee must make an end of our Roaring first.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wee'le serue 'um as we did the Tobacco-man: lay a curse vpon 'um, marry wee'le lay it on gently, because they haue vsed vs so kindly, and then wee'le shake gols together.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Who.</SPEAKER>
<P>As gently as you can, sweet Gentlemen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ch.</SPEAKER>
<P>For thee, Oh Pander: maist thou trudge till the damn'd soles of thy boots fleet into durt, but neuer rise into Ayre.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<P>Next, maist thou fleet so long from place to place, till thou beest kickt out of Fleetstreet.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>As thou hast liued by bad flesh, so rotten mutton be thy bane.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<P>When thou art dead, may twenty whores follow thee, that thou maist goe a Squire to thy graue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Enough for me sweet faces, let me sleepe in my graue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ch.</SPEAKER>
<P>For thee old <HI>Sindicus,</HI> may I see thee ride in a Caroch with two wheeles, and drawne with one horse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ten Beadles running by, in stead of foot-men.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cha.</SPEAKER>
<P>With euery one a whip, steed of an Irish dart.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<P>Forty Barbers Basons sounding before in steed of Trumpets.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bau.</SPEAKER>
<P>This will be comly indeed sweet Gentlemen Roarers.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thy Russe starch't yellow with rotten Egges.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>And maist thou then be drawne from Holborne, to Hounslow-Heath.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<P>And then be burnt to Colebrooke for destroying of Maydenhead.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bau.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will study to deserue this kindnesse at your hands Gentlemen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now for thee little <HI>Fucus,</HI> Maist thou first serue out thy time as a <HI>Tweake,</HI> and then become a <HI>Bronstrops</HI> as she is.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<P>Maist thou haue a reasonable good Spring, for thou art like to haue many dangerous soule falls.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Maist thou haue two Ruffes torne in one weeke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<P>May Spiders onely weaue thy Cobweb-lawne:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Maist thou set vp in Rogue Lane.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="34"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="34"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="35"/>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<P>Liue till thou stink'st in Garden-Allyes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>And die sweetly in Tower-Ditch.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Who.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thanke you for that good sir Roarer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ch.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come, shall we goe now <HI>Trim,</HI> my father in law stayes for me all this while.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, I'le serue 'um as wee did the Tobacco-man: Ile burie 'um altogether, and giue 'um an Epitaph.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chaugh.</SPEAKER>
<P>All together <HI>Trim,</HI> why then the Epitaph will be accessary to the sinne: alas, he has kept the doore all his life time, for pity let 'um lye together in their graues.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ca.</SPEAKER>
<P>Eene as thou wilt <HI>Trim,</HI> and I thank you too sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<Q><LG>
<L>He that the reason would know, let him harke,</L>
<L>Why these two were buried neere Maribone Parke:</L>
<L>These three were a Pander, a Band, and a Whore,</L>
<L>That suckt many dry to the bones before.</L>
<L>Well you know how they liu'd? heer't may be red,</L>
<L>The low Countries did euer finde 'um bred,</L>
<L>They liu'd by Flushing, by Sluce, and the Greyne,</L>
<L>Sickened in France, and dyed vnder the Line.</L>
<L>Three letters at last commended 'um hither,</L>
<L>But the hangman broke one in putting together.</L>
<L>P. was the first, who cryes out for a Pardon,</L>
<L>O. craues his booke, yet could not read such a hard one,</L>
<L>An X. was the last, which in coniunction</L>
<L>Was broke by Brandon, and heere's the conclusion.</L>
<L>By three trees, three letters; these three, Pander, Band, Whore:</L>
<L>Now stinke below ground, stunke long aboue before.</L>
</LG></Q>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>So, now we haue done with you, remember Roa∣ring Boyes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<P>Farewell <HI>Centaure.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Farewell <HI>Bronsterops.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<P>Farewell <HI>Fucus.</HI></P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Exeunt</HI> Chaugh <HI>and</HI> Trim.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well <HI>Meg</HI>: I will learne to Roare, and still maintaine the name of Captaine ouer these Launcepresadoes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bau.</SPEAKER>
<P>If thou do'st not, maist thou bee buried vnder the Roaring curse.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="35"/>
<HEAD>Actus Quintus, Scaena prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Phisition: Iane as a Bride.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phis.</SPEAKER>
<P>Will you be obstinate?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Torment me not,</L>
<L>Thou lingring Executioner to death,</L>
<L>Greatest disease to Nature, that striu'st by Art</L>
<L>To make men long a dying, your practise is</L>
<L>Vpon mens bodyes, as men pull Roses,</L>
<L>For their owne relish, but to kill the flower</L>
<L>So you maintaine your liues by others deaths,</L>
<L>What eat you then by carrion?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phis.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Fie bitternes,</L>
<L>Ye'ad need to candy ore your tongue a little,</L>
<L>Your wordes will hardly be digested els,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You can giue your selfe a vomit to returne 'um,</L>
<L>If they offend your stomacke,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phis.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Heere my vow</L>
<L>You are to be married to day.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>A second torment,</L>
<L>Worse then the first, cause vnauoydable,</L>
<L>I would I could as soone annihilate</L>
<L>My Fathers will in that as forbid thy lust.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phis.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If you then tender an vnwilling hand,</L>
<L>Meet it with reuenge, marry a Cuckolde.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If thou wilt marry me, Ile make that vow,</L>
<L>And giue my body for satisfaction</L>
<L>To him that should enioy me for his wife.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Go to, Ile marre your marriage.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Doe, plague me so.</L>
<L>Ile rather beare the brand of all thats past,</L>
<L>In Capitall Characters vpon my Brow,</L>
<L>Then thinke to be thy whore or marry him,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phis.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will defame thee euer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane</SPEAKER>
<L>Spare me not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="36"/>
<SPEAKER>Phis.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L><HI>I</HI> will produce thy Bastard,</L>
<L>Bring thee to publike pennance,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No matter, I care not,</L>
<L>I shall <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> haue a cleane sheet, Ile weare twenty</L>
<L>Rather then one desil'd with thee.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Looke for Reuenge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Pursue it fully then, out of his hate,</L>
<L>I shall pursue (I hope) a loathed fate.
<STAGE>Exit Iane</STAGE></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phis.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Am I reiected, all my baites nibled off,</L>
<L>And not the fish caught? Ile trouble the whole streame,</L>
<L>And choake it in the mudde, since hookes not take,</L>
<L>Ile throw in nets that shall or kill or breake.</L>
<L>This is the Bridegroomes man, harke sir, a word.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Trimtram with Rosemarie.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>'Tis a busie day sir, nor I need no phisicke,</L>
<L>You see I scoure about my busines.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phis.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray you a word sir, your Maister is to bee married to day.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Else all this Rosemaries lost.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phis.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would speake with your maister sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Maister sir, is to bee married this morning and cannot be within while soone at night.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If you will doe your maister the best seruice,</L>
<L>That ere you did him, if he shall not curse</L>
<L>Your negligence hereafter slacking it:</L>
<L>If he shall blesse mee for the dearest friend</L>
<L>That euer his acquaintance met withall,</L>
<L>Let me speake with him ere he goe to Church.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<P>A right Phisition, you would haue none goe to the Church, nor Churchyard till you send them thither; well, if death doe not spare you your selues, hee deales hardly with you, for you are better benefactors and send more to him then all diseases besides.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<STAGE>within.</STAGE>
<P>What <HI>Trimtram, Trimtram?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>I</HI> come sir. Harke you, you may heare him, hee's vp∣on the spur and would faine mount the saddle of Matrimony, but (if <HI>I</HI> can) Ile perswade him to come to you.
<STAGE>Exit Trim</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Pray you doe sir: Ile teach all peeuish nicenes</L>
<L>

<PB REF="36"/>To beware the strong aduantage of reuenge.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Chaugh.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who's that would speake with me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>None but a friend sir.</L>
<L><HI>I</HI> would speake with you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why sir, and <HI>I</HI> dare speake with any man vnder the vniuerse, can you roare sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No infaith sir.</L>
<L><HI>I</HI> come to tell you mildelie for your good,</L>
<L>If you please to heare me: you are vpon Marriages</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau</SPEAKER>
<P>No sir, <HI>I</HI> an towards it, but not vpon it yet.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doe you know what you doe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes sir, I haue practis'd what to doe before now, I would be asham'd to be married else: <HI>I</HI> haue seen a <HI>Bronstrops</HI> in my time, and a <HI>Hippocreene,</HI> and a <HI>Tweke</HI> too.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<P>Take fayre heede sir, the wife that you would marry is not fit for you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cha.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why sir, haue you tried her?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not <HI>I</HI> beleeue it sir, but belieue with all, Shee has beene tryed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhy sir, is she a Fructifer? or a Fucus?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<P>All that I speake sir, is in loue to you, Your Bride, that may be, 'has not that portion that a Bride should haue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhy sir? she has a thousand and a better penny.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>I</HI> doe not speake of rubish, drosse, and ore, But the refined Mettle, <HI>Honour</HI> sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhat she wants in honour shall be made vp in wor∣ship sir, money will purchase both.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy,</SPEAKER>
<P>To be plaine with you, she's naught.
<STAGE>drawes his sword</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>If thou canst not roare th'art a dead man, my Bride naught?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, <HI>I</HI> doe not feare you that way, what <HI>I</HI> speake, My life shall mainetaine, <HI>I</HI> say shee's naught.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Dost thou not feare me▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeed <HI>I</HI> doe not sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile neuer draw vpon the while <HI>I</HI> liue for that tricke, put vp and speake freely.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="37"/>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your intended Bride is a whore, thats freely sir,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes saith, a whor's free enough, and she hath a conscience: is snee a whore? Foote <HI>I</HI> warrant shee has the Poxe then?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVorse, the Plague, 'tis more incurable,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<L>A plaguie whore? a pox on her Ile none of her,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Mine accusation shall haue firme euidence.</L>
<L>I will produce an vnaubided witnes,</L>
<L>A bastard of her bearing.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau,</SPEAKER>
<P>A Bastard? 'snailes, ther's great suspition shee's a whore then, Ile wrastle a fall with her father for putting this tricke vpon me as <HI>I</HI> am a Gentleman.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Good sir mistake me not, <HI>I</HI> doe not speake</L>
<L>To breake the contract of vnited hearts,</L>
<L><HI>I</HI> will not pull that curse vpon my head,</L>
<L>To separate the husband and the wife,</L>
<L>But this (in loue) <HI>I</HI> thought fit to reueale,</L>
<L>(As the due office betwixt man and man)</L>
<L>That you might not be ignorant of your ills,</L>
<L>Consider now of my premonishment,</L>
<L>As your selfe shall please.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile burne all the Rose mary to sweeten the house, for in my conscience tis infected: has she drunke Bastard? if she would pisse me wine Viniger now nine times a day I'de neuer haue her, and <HI>I</HI> thanke you too.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Trimtram</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come, will you come away sir, they haue all Rose∣mary and stay for you to lead the way.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile not de married to day <HI>Trimtram,</HI> has't ere an Al∣manacke about thee? this is the nintenth of August, looke what day of the month 'tis.
<STAGE>Lookes in an Almanacke.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis tenty nine indeed sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhat's the word? what sayes <HI>Bretnor</HI>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<L>The word is sir, <HI>theres a hole in her coate.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>I</HI> thought so, the Physition agrees with him, Ile not marry to day.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<P>I pray you sir, there will be charges for new Rosema∣ry else, this will be wither'd by to morrow.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="37"/>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Make a Bon fire ont to sweeten Rosemary Lane pre∣thee <HI>Trim.</HI> entreat my father in law that might haue be<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>, to come and speake with me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Bride cries already and lookes to ther way, and you be so backward too, we shall haue a fine arseward wed∣ding on't.
<STAGE>Exit Trim.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Youle stand to your words, sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phis.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile not flye the house sir, when you haue need call me to euidence.
<STAGE>Exit Phisition.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>If youle proue she has borne a Bastard, Ile stand too't shee's a whore.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Russell and Trimtram.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why how now sonne what causeth these delayes? All stay for your leading.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Came I from the mount to be confronted?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<L>How's that sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Canst thou roare old man;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<L>Roare? how meane you sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why then Ile tell thee plainely thy daughter in a <HI>Bronstrops.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<L>A <HI>Bronsterop?</HI> Whats that sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir if she be so she is a <HI>Hippocrene.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay worse she is a fructifer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay then she is a <HI>Fucus,</HI> a <HI>Minotaure,</HI> and a <HI>Tweke.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray you speake to my vnderstanding sir,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>If thou wilt haue it in plaine termes: She is a <HI>Callicut,</HI> and a <HI>Panagron.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay then she is a <HI>Duplar</HI> and a <HI>Sindicus.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good sir, speake English to me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>All this is Cornish to thee, I say thy Daughter has drunke Bastard in her time.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bastard you doe not meane to make her a whore?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes but I doe, if shee make a foole of me, Ile nere make her my wife, till she haue her maidenhead agen?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<L>A whore? I doe defie this Callumnie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dost thou? I defie thee then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doe you sir, then I defie thee too, fight with vs both at once in this quarrell if thou darest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="38"/>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<L>I could haue had a whore at Plimouth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<L>I or at Perin.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<L>I or vnder the Mount.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or as you came, at Euill.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or at Hoc-kye hole in Somersetshire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or at the hanging stones in Wiltshire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Or at Maidenhead in Barkshire: and did I come in by Maidenhead to goe out by Staines? Oh that man wo∣man or childe, would wrastle with me for a pound of pa∣tience.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Some thiefe has put in poyson at your eares.</L>
<L>To steale the good name of my child from me:</L>
<L>Or if it be a mallice of your owne,</L>
<L>Be sure I will enforce a proofe from you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hees a goose and a woodcocke that sayes I will not proue any word that I speake.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<P>I either goose or Woodcocke he shall sir with any man.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Phi-si-ti-an, <HI>Mauz auez</HI> Phisitian.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is he the author?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phis.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sir, with much sorrow for your sorrowes sake,</L>
<L>I must deliuer this most certaine truth,</L>
<L>Your daughter is an honor stayned Bride,</L>
<L>Indeed she is the mother to a child,</L>
<L>Before the lawfull wife vnto a husband.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Law, thats worse then I told thee, I said shee had borne a Bastard, and hee sayes she was the mother ont too.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I'me yet an infidell against all this,</L>
<L>And will beleeue the Sun is made of Brasse,</L>
<L>The Starres of amber.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<L>And the moone of a holland cheese.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rather then this impossibility, oh, heere she comes,</L>
<STAGE>Enter Iane and Anne.</STAGE>
<LG>
<L>Nay come daughter, stand at the barre of shame,</L>
<L>Either now quit thy selfe, or kill me euer:</L>
<L>Your marriage day is spoyld if all bee true.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>A happy misery, whose my accuser?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phis.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am that knowes it true I speake,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="38"/>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes and Ime his witnes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I agen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And I agen too,</L>
<L>theres foure thats enough <HI>I</HI> hope.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>How can you witnes sir that nothing know,</L>
<L>But what you haue receiu'd from his report.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Must we not beleeue our Phisitians? pray you thinke</L>
<L><HI>I</HI> know as much as euery foole do's.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me be <HI>Trimtram: I</HI> pray you too sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sir if this bad man haue layd a blemish</L>
<L>On my white name: he is a most false one,</L>
<L>Defaming me for the iust denyall</L>
<L>Of his soule lust, nay now you shall be known sir.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>An</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sir Ime his sister and do better know him,</L>
<L>Then all of you giue not too much beliefe</L>
<L>To his wilde wordes, hee's oftentimes mad sir.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phis.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>I</HI> thanke you good sister.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>An.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Are you not mad to doe this Office,</L>
<L>Fie vppon your mallice.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phis.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Ile presently produce both nurse and Child,</L>
<L>Whose very eyes shall call her mother, before it speakes.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha, ha, ha, ha, by my troth Ide spend a shilling on that condition to heare that, <HI>I</HI> thinke in my conscience <HI>I</HI> shal take the Phisitian in a lye if the Childe call her mother be∣fore it can speake, Ile neuer wrastle while <HI>I</HI> liue agen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<P>It must be a shee child if it doe sir, and those speake the soonest of any liuing Creatures they say.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Baw waw, a dog will barke a Month sooner, hee's a very puppy else.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Come tell truth twixt our selues, heers none but friends</L>
<L>One spot a fathers loue will soone wipe off?</L>
<L>The truth and they trie my loue abundant,</L>
<L>Ile couer it with all the care <HI>I</HI> haue▪</L>
<L>And yet (perhaps) make vp a marriage day.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then its true sir, <HI>I</HI> haue Child.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Hast thou?</L>
<L>Well wipe thine eyes, Ime a Grandfather then,</L>
<L>

<PB REF="39"/>If all bastards were banisht, the Citty would be thinne,</L>
<L>In the thickest terme time, well now let me alone</L>
<L>Ile try my wits for thee, <HI>Richard, Francis, Andrew,</HI></L>
<L>None of my knaues within?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter his Seruant.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heeres one of'um, sir, the Guests come in apace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doe they dick? let 'um haue wine and sugar, weele befor 'um presently, but harke Dick.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cha.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>I</HI> long to heare this childe speake ifaith, <HI>Trim, I</HI> would this foolish Phisition would come once.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<P>If it calls her mother, <HI>I</HI> hope it shall neuer call you father.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, and it do Ile whip it ifaith, and giue thee leaue to whip me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<L>Run on thy best legges Dicke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile be heere in a twinkling sir.
<STAGE>Exit Ser.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Phisitian, Nurse, with the childe.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now Gentlemen, beleeue your eyes, if not my tongue Doe not you call this your childe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>C.</SPEAKER>
<P>Phew, thats not the point you promis'd vs the child should call her Mother, if it do's this month, Ile nere go to the roa∣ring schoole agen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whose childe is this Nurse?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nurse.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dis Gentlemans, so he to me readen.
<STAGE>Poynts to the Phisitian.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Snailes shees the Phisitians <HI>Bronstrops, Trim.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<L>His <HI>Fucus,</HI> his very <HI>Tweke,</HI> ifaith.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>A glister in his teeth, let him take her with a purga∣tion to him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>'Tis as your sister said: you are starke mad, sir,</L>
<L>This much confirmes it, you haue defamed</L>
<L>Mine honest daughter: Ile haue you punisht fort,</L>
<L>Besides the ciuill pennance of your sinne,</L>
<L>And keeping of your bastard.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phis.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>This is fine,</L>
<L>All your wit and wealth must not thus carry it.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir <HI>Chaugh</HI> a word with you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile not haue her ifaith, sir, if <HI>Trimtram</HI> will haue her and he will let him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="39"/>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who I, sir? I scorne it, if you'l haue her, Ile haue her too, Ile doe as you doe, and no otherwise.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L><HI>I</HI> doe not meant to either, this onely, sir,</L>
<L>That whatsoere y'aue seene, you would be silent,</L>
<L>Hinder not my child of another husband,</L>
<L>Though you forsake her.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile not speake a word, ifaith,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<L>As you are a gentleman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>By these basket hilts, as <HI>I</HI> am a youth,</L>
<L>A gentleman a Roarer.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<L>Charme your man <HI>I</HI> beseech you too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>I</HI> warrant you sir hee shall doe nothing but what <HI>I</HI> doe before him.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Seruant with Fitzallen.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L><HI>I</HI> shall most dearly thanke you, Oh are you come,</L>
<L>Welcome sonne in law: this was beyond your hope,</L>
<L>We old men haue pretty conceits sometimes,</L>
<L>Your Wedding daye's prepard, and this is it,</L>
<L>How thinke you of it?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>As of the ioyfulst</L>
<L>That euer welcomd me, you shew your selfe now</L>
<L>A patterne to all kind fathers: my sweetest <HI>Iane,</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Your captiuity <HI>I</HI> mean't but as sauce,</L>
<L>Vnto your Wedding dinner, now, I'me sure</L>
<L>'Tis far more welcome in this short restraint</L>
<L>Then had it freely come:</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>A thousand fold.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>I</HI> like this well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>I</HI> haue not the heart to see this Gentleman guld so, <HI>I</HI> will reueale, <HI>I</HI> make it mine owne case tis a foule case.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Remember you haue sworne by your hilts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile break my hilts rather then conceale, <HI>I</HI> haue a trick Doe thou follow mee, <HI>I</HI> will reueale it, and yet not speake it neither.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis my duty to follow you sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chaugh</SPEAKER>
<L><STAGE>sings.</STAGE> Take heed in time oh man vnto thy head,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<L><STAGE>Sings.</STAGE> All is not gold that glistereth in bed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why sir? why sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Looke too't <HI>I</HI> say, thy Bride's a <HI>Bronsterops,</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="40"/>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<L>And knowes the thing that men weare in their slops,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>How's this sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<L>A <HI>Hipocrene,</HI> a <HI>Tweke,</HI> for and a <HI>Fueus,</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let not fond loue with foretops so rebuke vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Behold a baby of this maids begetting,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<L>A deed of darknes after the sun-setting.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Oath sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Chau</HI>:</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>I</HI> sweare and sing thy Bride has taken Phisike,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<L>This was the Doctor curd her of that Ptisicke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you'le beleeue me <HI>I</HI> will say no more,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy Brides a <HI>Tweke</HI> as we doe say that roare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Beare witnes Gentlemen <HI>I</HI> haue not spoke a word,</L>
<L>My hilts are hole still.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>This is a sweet <HI>Epithalamium,</HI></L>
<L>Vnto the Marriage bed, a musicall</L>
<L>Harmonius <HI>Io</HI>: sir, yaue wrongd me,</L>
<L>And basely wrong'd me, was this your cunning fetch,</L>
<L>To Fetch me out of prison, for euer</L>
<L>To marry me vnto a Strumpet?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>None of those words good sir,</L>
<L>Tis but a fault, and tis a sweet one too,</L>
<L>Come sir, your meanes is short, lengthen your fortunes,</L>
<L>With a faire proffer: Ile put a thousand pieces</L>
<L>Into the scale to helpe her to weigh it vp,</L>
<L>Aboue the first dowrie.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Ha? you say, well</L>
<L>Shame may be bought out at a deere rate,</L>
<L>A thousand pieces added to her dowry.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Theres fiue hundred of 'um to make the Bargaine,</L>
<L><HI>I</HI> haue worthy guests comming and would not delude 'um,</L>
<L>Say: speake like a Sonne to me.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your blessing sir, we are both yours, witnes Gen∣tlemen these must be made vp a thousand pieces, added to a first thousand for her dowry, to father that childe,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh is it out now?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chau.</SPEAKER>
<L>For tother thousand Ile doo't my selfe yet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or <HI>I,</HI> if my Maister will.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="40"/>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The Bargaine's made, sir, I haue the tender</L>
<L>And possession both; and will keepe my purchase,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chaw.</SPEAKER>
<P>Take her eene to you with all her moueables, ile weare my batchellors buttons still.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<P>So will I ifaith; they are the best flowers in any mans garden, next to hartsease.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>This is as welcome as the other sir,</L>
<L>And both as the best blisse that ere on earth,</L>
<L>I shall enioy, sir, this is mine owne childe,</L>
<L>You could not haue found out a sitter Father</L>
<L>Nor is it basely bred as you imagine</L>
<L>For we were wedded by the hand of heauen</L>
<L>Ere this worke was begun.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chaw.</SPEAKER>
<L>At Pancridge, ile lay my life on't,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le lay my life on't too, twas there,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Some where it was, sir,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wa'st so ifaith sonne?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And that <HI>I</HI> must haue reuea'ld to you, sir,</L>
<L>Ete <HI>I</HI> had gone to Church with this faire groome,</L>
<L>But thanke this gentleman, he preuented me,</L>
<L><HI>I</HI> am much bound vnto your mallice sir.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>I</HI> am a sham'd</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shame to amendment then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Now get you together for a couple of cunning ones,</L>
<L>But sonne, a word, the latter thousand peeces</L>
<L>Is now more then bargaine.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No by my faith sir</L>
<L>Here's witnesse inough ont, must serue to pay my fees</L>
<L>Imprisonment is costly</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chaw.</SPEAKER>
<P>By my troth the old man ha's gul'd himselfe, finely, well sir, Ile bid my selfe a guest, though not a groome, Ile dine and dance, and roare at the wedding for all this.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trim.</SPEAKER>
<L>So will <HI>I</HI> sir, if my Maister does,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Well sir, you are welcome, but now, no more wordes on't,</L>
<L>Till we be set at dinner for there will mirth</L>
<L>Be the most vsefull for digestion,</L>
<L>See, my best guests are comming.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>

<PB REF="41"/>
<HI>Enter Captaine Ager, Surgeon, Lady Ager Colonells Sister, two friends.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Recouerd saist thou.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Surg.</SPEAKER>
<P>May <HI>I</HI> bee excluded quite out of Surgeons hall else, marry <HI>I</HI> must tell you the wound was faine to be twice Coro∣ded, 'twas a plaine Gastrolophe, and a deep one, but <HI>I</HI> closed the lips on't with Bandages and Sutteures, which is a kind coniunction of the parts seperated against the course of na∣ture.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well sir, he is well</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sur.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>I</HI> feard him <HI>I</HI> assure you Captaine before the Surture in the belly, it grew almost to a convulsion, and there was like to be a bloody issue from the hollow vessells of the kidnyes.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>giues him money.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<P>Theres that, to thanke thy new<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s and thy Art toge∣ther.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sur.</SPEAKER>
<P>And if your worship at any time stand in need of in∣cission, if it be your fortune to light into my hands, ile giue you the best.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Vncle, the noble <HI>Colonells</HI> recouerd,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Russ.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Recouered.</L>
<L>Then honor is not dead in all parts Cusse.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Colonell with his too friends.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Behold him yonder sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Capt</HI>:</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My much vnworthinesse is now found out,</L>
<L>Tha'st not a face to fi<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> it.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colo. frie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir yonders Captaine <HI>Ager.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colo.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O Lieftenant the wrong I haue done his same,</L>
<L>Puts me to silence, shame so confounds me,</L>
<L>That I dare not see him.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Capt</HI>:</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I neuer knew how poore my deserts were,</L>
<L>Till he appeard'; no way to giue requitall,</L>
<L>Here shame me lastingly; doo't with his owne,</L>
<L>Returne this to him, tell him I haue Riches</L>
<L>In that abundance in his sisters loue,</L>
<L>These come but to oppresse me, and confound</L>
<L>All my deseruings euerlastingly:</L>
<L>I neuer shall requite my wealth in her say,</L>
<L>

<PB REF="41"/>How soone from vertue and an honord spirit,</L>
<L>May man receiue what he may neuer merit.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colo.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>This comes most happily, to expresse me better,</L>
<L>For since this will was made there fell to me</L>
<L>The manner of <HI>Fitz-dale,</HI> giue h'um that too,</L>
<L>Hee's like to haue chardge theres faire hope</L>
<L>Of my sisters fruitfullnesse, for me</L>
<L>I neuer meane to change my mistris,</L>
<L>And warre is able to maintaine her seruant,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Read there, a faire increase sir, by my faith,</L>
<L>He hath sent it backe sir, with new additions.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>How miserable he makes me, this inforces me</L>
<L>To breake through all the passadges of shame</L>
<L>And headlong fall,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Into my armes deare worthy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You haue a goodnesse</L>
<L>Has put me past my answers, you may speake,</L>
<L>what you please now; I must be silent euer,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colo.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>This day has showen me ioyes vnualeu'd treasure,</L>
<L>I would not change this brotherhood with a monarch,</L>
<L>Into which blest aliance sacred heauen</L>
<L>H<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'s plac't my kinsman, and giuen him his ends</L>
<L>Faire be that Quarrell makes such happy friends.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Omnes.</STAGE>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

