<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2004-02</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Angela Lea</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Checked for N=""s. Checked for GROUP tags. Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, etc.). Checked for signatures. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, and UNCLEARs. Corrected ** $s and $$word$$s etc. of **. Converted __ $$s to GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex". Checked spacing of foreign GAPs. Checked for EPIGRAPHs and ARGUMENTs. Checked for &amp;cs with incorrect spacing. Checked for LBs. Checked for startqs, endqs, oes, q;s, and Qs. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Checked for CLOSERs, TRAILERs, and BYLINEs. Checked for missing page GAPs. Sample: ** minutes. Proofing: ** minutes. Tag review and corrections: ** minutes. DONE.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A07974">
<STC T="S">18341</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99848304</BIBNO>
<VID>13389</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<P><PB REF="1"/>
HANNIBAL AND SCIPIO.</P>
<P>AN HISTORICALL <HI>TRAGEDY.</HI></P>
<P>Acted in the yeare 1635. by the Queenes Majesties Servants, at their Private house in <HI>Drury Lane.</HI></P>
<P>The Author <HI>Thomas Nabbes.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Arma virosque cano.</HI></P>
<P>LONDON, Printed by <HI>Richard Oulton</HI> for <HI>Charles Greene,</HI> and are to be sold at the white Lion in <HI>Pauls</HI> Church-yard. 1637.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="letter">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD><HI>To the Ghosts of</HI> HANNIBAL <HI>and</HI> SCIPIO.</HEAD>
<L>WHere e're your thin remaines, and shaddows dwell;</L>
<L>In the Elysian blisse, or paines of Hell;</L>
<L>I, that with writing of your story new</L>
<L>Am almost worne into a ghost like you,</L>
<L>Present you with your selves: such as you were</L>
<L>When you breath'd ayre, and had your beings here.</L>
<L>Let not hells Judges damne it to the fire;</L>
<L>It past mens sentence: there's besides some hire</L>
<L>Yet undischarg'd; and where the debt was due</L>
<L>Being deny'd, I have sent the bill to you,</L>
<L>Say not for money, how shall we come by it?</L>
<L>Borrow of <HI>Pluto:</HI> he will not deny it</L>
<L>Vpon your bond. Stay: here's a great mistaking;</L>
<L>His state and riches were of Poets making:</L>
<L>And they I feare so apt are to belye him,</L>
<L>I cannot think he hath one penny by him.</L>
<L>How e're your patronage shall doe me right,</L>
<L>'Bove the prefixt name of a Lord or Knight:</L>
<L>Or other outside men: such as inherit</L>
<L>Of honour but the title, not the merit.</L>
<L>Who think that if the least state action rest</L>
<L>On their dispatch; or to a Christmas feast</L>
<L>They yearly call the neighbour-hood; or be</L>
<L>Put in commission, or the Shrivaltie</L>
<L>(The Countreys highest grace) they may dispence</L>
<L>With what belongs more to their difference,</L>
<L><PB REF="3"/>
Bounty unto desert. But you are free;</L>
<L>And if you might would rather come to me,</L>
<L>Then put me to a charge: the journey's great,</L>
<L>And ere I could return, I might want meat:</L>
<L>Vnlesse some kind poore cobler, (you know well</L>
<L>Mending of soales is no rich trade in Hell.)</L>
<L>Lend me a shilling. Loth I am 'tis true</L>
<L>At any rate of hopes to come to you.</L>
<CLOSER><SALUTE>The honourer of your memories,</SALUTE>
<SIGNED>THOMAS NABBIS.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="letter">
<PB REF="3"/>
<HEAD>The Ghosts of <HI>Hanniball</HI> and <HI>Scipio</HI> to the Authour.</HEAD>
<L>WHat charm commands us hither to repayre?</L>
<L>And once again salute the upper ayre?</L>
<L>Would <HI>Lucsan</HI> vexe our shadowes? make us tell</L>
<L>Which of us holds priority in Hell?</L>
<L>What art, that do'st with thy Poetick fire</L>
<L>A soule into each Histrio inspire</L>
<L>Like ours? and make them move with active rage</L>
<L>As we did, when the World became our Stage?</L>
<L>We know thee now: thy thinne cheeke, hollow eye,</L>
<L>And ghostlike colour speak the mystery</L>
<L>Thou wonldst, but canst not live by: for the more</L>
<L>Thou do'st enrich thy works, they make thee poore.</L>
<L>Who will by fancy and invention thrive,</L>
<L>Must practise how to flatter men alive.</L>
<L>We would have left thee provinces, hadst thou</L>
<L>Done this whilst we had being here: but now</L>
<L><HI>Pluto</HI> restraines our bounties; else wee'ld be</L>
<L>Not ayrie patrons to thy work and thee,</L>
<L>But give thee crowns of Mettall, whilst thy brows</L>
<L>Others did deck with cheap <HI>Phebean</HI> boughs.</L>
<L>The singer of the Punick warr had bayes</L>
<L>Making our acts his subject; and thy prayse</L>
<L>Should be no lesse. But we are empty things,</L>
<L>Though once we aw'd states, and commanded Kings.</L>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Hannibal.</SIGNED>
<SIGNED>Scipio.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="prologue">
<PB REF="4"/>
<HEAD>THE PROLOGUE.</HEAD>
<L>ANother Tragedy? What will become</L>
<L>Of the soft Muse? Shee'l shortly have no roome</L>
<L>On this transform'd stage. Ladies shall not blush,</L>
<L>Nor smile under their fannes: nor he in plush,</L>
<L>That from the Poets labours in the pit</L>
<L>Informes himselfe for th' exercise of wit</L>
<L>At Tavernes, gather notes. Stay, I should be</L>
<L>A Prologue, not a Satyre. You shall see</L>
<L>A piece from a rich subject drawne; but how</L>
<L>The workmanship will please, and you allow</L>
<L>Th' imperfect colours and the weake designe,</L>
<L>Let your owne judgements tell you, and not mine.</L>
<L>The Author warrants us the story's cleare;</L>
<L>Vnlesse to fit the Stage he doth transferre</L>
<L>Some actions that were ones to other men:</L>
<L>The places sometimes chang'd too for the Scene.</L>
<L>Which is translated as the musick playes</L>
<L>Betwixt the acts: wherein he likewise prayes</L>
<L>You will conceive his battailes done, and then</L>
<L>The methode shall appeare, in which his pen</L>
<L>Hath smoothly drest the argument. 'Tis free</L>
<L>As ever Play was from scurrility.</L>
<L>Nor need you Ladies feare the horrid sight:</L>
<L>And the more horrid noise of target sight</L>
<L>By the blue-coated Stage-keepers: our spheares</L>
<L>Have better musick to delight your eares,</L>
<L>And not a straine that's old, though some would taske</L>
<L>His borrowing from a former play. We aske</L>
<L>Your patience but two houres, by which time hee</L>
<L>Shall either dye or live to Poesie.</L>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dramatis personae">
<PB REF="4"/>
<HEAD>The speaking persons.</HEAD>
<P><TABLE>
<ROW>
<CELL><HI>Maharball.</HI></CELL>
<CELL>By <HI>William Shurlock.</HI></CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL><HI>Himulco.</HI></CELL>
<CELL>By <HI>Iohn Sumner.</HI></CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL><HI>Souldier.</HI></CELL>
<CELL>By <HI>George Stutfield.</HI></CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL><HI>A Lady.</HI></CELL>
<CELL> </CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL><HI>Hannibal.</HI></CELL>
<CELL>By <HI>William Allen.</HI></CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>2. <HI>other Ladies.</HI></CELL>
<CELL> </CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL><HI>Nuntius.</HI></CELL>
<CELL>By <HI>Hugh Clerks.</HI></CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL><HI>Bomilcar.</HI></CELL>
<CELL>By <HI>Robert Axen.</HI></CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL><HI>Syphax</HI></CELL>
<CELL>By <HI>Hugh Clerks.</HI></CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL><HI>Piston.</HI></CELL>
<CELL>By <HI>Anthony Turner.</HI></CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL><HI>Crates.</HI></CELL>
<CELL> </CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL><HI>Messenger.</HI></CELL>
<CELL> </CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL><HI>Scipio.</HI></CELL>
<CELL>By <HI>Michael Bowyer.</HI></CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL><HI>Lelius</HI></CELL>
<CELL>By <HI>Iohn Page.</HI></CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL><HI>Sophonisba.</HI></CELL>
<CELL>By <HI>Ezekiel Fenn.</HI></CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL><HI>Massanissa.</HI></CELL>
<CELL>By <HI>Theophilus Bird.</HI></CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL><HI>Hanno.</HI></CELL>
<CELL>By <HI>Richard Perkins.</HI></CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL><HI>Gisgon.</HI></CELL>
<CELL>By <HI>Robert Axen.</HI></CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL><HI>Bostar.</HI></CELL>
<CELL>By <HI>George Stutfield.</HI></CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL><HI>Lucius.</HI></CELL>
<CELL> </CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL><HI>A young Lady.</HI></CELL>
<CELL> </CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL><HI>Prusias.</HI></CELL>
<CELL>By <HI>William Shurlock.</HI></CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL> </CELL>
<CELL><HI>Mutes.</HI></CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL><HI>Ladies.</HI></CELL>
<CELL><HI>Souldiers.</HI></CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL><HI>Attendants.</HI></CELL>
<CELL><HI>Senators.</HI></CELL>
</ROW>
</TABLE></P>
<P>I desire thee Reader to take notice that some escapes have past the Presse; As Tuning for Tunny; dimacing for dunning: meane for meere; stand for share, &amp;c. which notwithstanding are corrected in divers of the copies: where they are not, let thine owne judge∣ment rectifie them, before thy rashnesse condemne me.</P>
<CLOSER>Farewell.</CLOSER>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="play">
<PB REF="5"/>
<PB REF="5"/>
<HEAD>HANNIBALL AND SCIPIO.</HEAD>
<DIV2 TYPE="act">
<HEAD>The Argument of the first Act.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Hanniball <HI>reprooving his Souldiers for their lascivi∣ousnesse at</HI> Capua, <HI>is himselfe taken with the love of a Lady of</HI> Salapia. <HI>Newes is brought him of</HI> Scipio, <HI>that hee hath recovered</HI> Spaine: <HI>and a command from the Senate that he returne to</HI> Carthage: <HI>which with much unwillingnesse hee assents to.</HI></STAGE>
<STAGE>The Scene Capua.</STAGE>
<DIV3 TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scene the first.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Maharball <HI>and</HI> Himulco.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mah.</SPEAKER>
<L>HEre's the right use of victory, to tame</L>
<L>Our furies with soft case and wantonnesse,</L>
<L>After so many travels. Had our <HI>Hanniball</HI></L>
<L>Possest himselfe of <HI>Rome</HI> without a Capua,</L>
<L>The conquest had beene poore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Himul.</SPEAKER>
<L>These spoyles of beauty,</L>
<L><PB REF="6"/>
And free ones too, that uncompel'd will runne</L>
<L>To imbrace a Souldier; rock him in her armes;</L>
<L>Sing him asleepe, and with her icy fingers</L>
<L>K<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mbing the knotted curles of his black haire</L>
<L>So long neglected, make her selfe the ravisher:</L>
<L>O<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l' is <HI>Elysium.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mahar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, to have such change</L>
<L>Of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>; as if their inventions</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>, busie to make our delights</L>
<L>The object of their care. Here we are feasted</L>
<L>With Chalcedonian Tuning; Rhodian guilt heads,</L>
<L>And more than Samian gluttony. We drinke</L>
<L>No wine, but of <HI>Campania's Mascicus,</HI></L>
<L>Or grape crownd <HI>Aulon.</HI> Boyes more faire than hee</L>
<L>That beares <HI>Ioves</HI> Cup, rapt on the duskie wings</L>
<L>O<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'s sky-borne Eagle, serve the banquet up</L>
<L>In golden dishes, or Corinthian plate,</L>
<L>Luxuries chiefest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Him.</SPEAKER>
<L>To crowne the entertainment,</L>
<L>Here sits a Lady, <HI>Hebe</HI> never blusht</L>
<L>A colour like her checke: and in her eye</L>
<L>A thousand <HI>Cupids</HI> move in wanton friskes,</L>
<L>To catch the gazers. There's another deckt</L>
<L>In the Seas riches, which the Negro dives for:</L>
<L>Her pearles reflexion dimacing the darke tapers,</L>
<L>As if all light were borrow'd from those Sunnes</L>
<L>Their orient roundnesse mockes us with. A third</L>
<L>Betrayes through a transparent lawne the beauty</L>
<L>Of a complexion, white and red did never</L>
<L>Mix<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>a more perfect; and a shape exact</L>
<L>As Natures first <HI>Pandoras.</HI> The possession</L>
<L>After desire hath made a preparation</L>
<L>In every sense to entertaine these joyes,</L>
<L>Can earth affoord a Heaven, and this not bee</L>
<L>The best hope ever faign'd?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mahar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then to be cloth'd</L>
<L>In silkes of Tyrian dye; tosleepe on downe,</L>
<L><PB REF="6"/>
And waking claspe a Goddesse in ones armes,</L>
<L>Lovely as Cytharea; revell sometimes,</L>
<L>And dance to th'Mermaides musicke, 'till the night</L>
<L>Is made one artificiall day, inverting</L>
<L>The course of time and's actions: oh delights,</L>
<L>Beyond weake comprehension! Wee begin</L>
<L>To taste them without sense, did not diversity</L>
<L>Whet appetite anew?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Him.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet so much change</L>
<L>Should make invention barren: but 'tis fruitfull,</L>
<L>Pregnant, and teemes as fast as 'tis delivered.</L>
<L>Delicious <HI>Capua!</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mah.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pleasures onely storehouse!</L>
<L>Were I an <HI>Hanniball?</HI> and conquest quiet me</L>
<L>As faire as day-light spreads his christall wings.</L>
<L>One <HI>Capua</HI> should ransome all.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scene the Second.</HEAD>
<STAGE>To them a common Souldier, with a faire Lady courting him.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Him.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's here?</L>
<L>Shee courts him with as earnest zeale, as <HI>Cynthia</HI></L>
<L>Would her <HI>Endymion,</HI> or the gray-ey'd Morne</L>
<L>Her earely <HI>Cephalus.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mah.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now by my Sword.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Him.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is that a Souldiers oath in <HI>Capua?</HI></L>
<L>By the bright tresses of my Mistresse haire,</L>
<L>Fine as <HI>Arachne's</HI> webbe, or <HI>Gosshimere:</HI></L>
<L>Whose curles when garnisht with their dressing, show</L>
<L>Like that spunne vapour when 'tis pearl'd with dew.</L>
<L>Or by the Sunshine of her christall eyes,</L>
<L>Wherein the God of Love his wet wings dry's</L>
<L>After his bathing in sad Lovers teares.</L>
<L>These are the onely oathes a Souldier sweares.</L>
<L>What should we doe with swords?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mah.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeed 'tis true</L>
<L>Their bloody use hath beene so long neglected,</L>
<L><PB REF="7"/>
And for my part I am so cloy'd with women,</L>
<L>Mine must bee fil'd to powder, and prepar'd</L>
<L>To bee their Physick: the greene-sicknesse else</L>
<L>Will not bee cur'd by me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Him.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mine shall be drawne</L>
<L>To weare for pinnes: and that which oft hath raign'd</L>
<L>The blood of Romanes on my hilts and hand,</L>
<L>Wearied almost with slaughter, shall bee toucht</L>
<L>With trembling fingers, white as <HI>Othris</HI> snow;</L>
<L>Whilst the soft handler starts, if by mischance</L>
<L>The point but prick her skin, and must consult</L>
<L>With some learn'd unguentary to prevent</L>
<L>Th'invisible scarre. Why here we cannot quarrell</L>
<L>Amongst ourselves for wenches. There's a Lady,</L>
<L>As meane a beauty heretofore hath beene</L>
<L>The ground of a sad warre, or in a Campe</L>
<L>Sur'd up a mutiny: wee cannot envie it,</L>
<L>That he, a common Souldier, valours ciphar,</L>
<L>One onely prest to make the number up,</L>
<L>Enjoves her wholly, and perhaps hath change.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mah.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, stands upon nice <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> for his reward;</L>
<L>And must bee hir'd to pleasure, such as some</L>
<L>Would even through any danger to embrace.</L>
<L>Prethee observ..</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why should I be deny'd?</L>
<L>Am I not faire enough? My beauty fresh</L>
<L>As the new springs, when wanton <HI>Phoebus</HI> mounts</L>
<L>His ournish't chariot early to salute her,</L>
<L>And k<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="missing" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sse dew from her cheekes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soul.</SPEAKER>
<L>There are as faite</L>
<L>And free. A pension Lady must be thought of;</L>
<L>I cannot else be sportive.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lad.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is tha all?</L>
<L>Ile ful thy burgnet with Iberian gold</L>
<L>Stampt into medals; Sell my wanton treasurie,</L>
<L>Rings, Iewels, Catkanets, e're thou shalt want,</L>
<L>But what thy wish can covet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="7"/>
<SPEAKER>Soul</SPEAKER>
<L>This old buffe</L>
<L>Would be translated.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lad.</SPEAKER>
<L>Into Persian mantles,</L>
<L>Richly embroydred; no rough pelt of thrumbes</L>
<L>To fight with weather. Shalt be cloath'd in silkes,</L>
<L>Such as may vye for touch with their softnesse</L>
<L>When it is calmest, and no violent gust</L>
<L>Doth wave it into wrinckles.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soul.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must eate too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lad.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nothing but choycest caudies, and drink wine</L>
<L>That shall have pearles dissolv'd in't. Come let's hasten</L>
<L>To our delights. I have prepar'd a bed</L>
<L>Of artificiall Roses mixt with downe;</L>
<L>Wherein our dalliance we will emulate,</L>
<L>The Cyprian Queene and her lov'd warriour,</L>
<L>When in her Ivory armes she did imbrace</L>
<L>His Iron sides.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Soft Lady, there are yet</L>
<L>Stricter conditions. 'I is not come to that.</L>
<L>I must not be confin'd to times or place;</L>
<L>Nor to your single number. I must change</L>
<L>As I see cause.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lad.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shalt be thine owne disposer.</L>
<L>He minister, and like a hand-maide waite</L>
<L>When thou wilt grace another; nor repine,</L>
<L>But with a patient longing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soul.</SPEAKER>
<L>On these termes</L>
<L>I feele a provocation. Come. <STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mah.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did ease</L>
<L>Ever before produce such acts of shame?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Him</SPEAKER>
<L>No matter. 'Tis a better life than warre</L>
<L>Affords her sonnes. A hard cold bed of earth:</L>
<L>Sleepes broken with a thousand apprehensions</L>
<L>Of danger; diet course, and seldome seasonable;</L>
<L>Hunger and thirst; and death each houre presented.</L>
<L>Let us translate our <HI>Carthage</HI> unto <HI>Capua;</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="8"/>
We shall not need to toyle in blood and sweat</L>
<L>For more inlargement.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scene the third</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>To them</HI> Hanniball.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Musiek.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Husht. Our Generall.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mah.</SPEAKER>
<L>How doth he like this softnesse? it agrees not</L>
<L>With his rough nature.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hanm.</SPEAKER>
<L>Musick every place</L>
<L>Surfets with this lasciviousnesse.</L>
<STAGE>A Song as from some window.</STAGE>
</SP>
<L><HI>March on my merry mates</HI></L>
<L><HI>To</HI> Venus <HI>warres:</HI></L>
<L><HI>You need not feare your pates,</HI></L>
<L><HI>You shall receive no wounds nor scarres,</HI></L>
<L><HI>You may come naked to the fight:</HI></L>
<L><HI>Wee'l have no other vesle but night.</HI></L>
<L><HI>Onely you must not see</HI></L>
<L><HI>The blushes of your enemy.</HI></L>
<STAGE>Chorus.</STAGE>
<L><HI>The loving battail's set,</HI></L>
<L><HI>And we began</HI></L>
<L><HI>To counter meete</HI></L>
<L><HI>With active striving who shall win.</HI></L>
<L><HI>I saint and yet mee thinkes you yeeld,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Both lose, and yet both winne the sield.</HI></L>
<L><HI>Recover strength, and then</HI></L>
<L><HI>Wee'l to these pleasant warres agen.</HI></L>
<STAGE>A light.</STAGE>
<L>Bravely maintain'd and well come off on both sides.</L>
<L>Curse on this case. Y'are well met noble Captaines,</L>
<L>How doth your courage brooke this silken slavery?</L>
<L>Is't not an easie bondage to be ty'd</L>
<L>In bracelets of a wanton Ladyes haire?</L>
<L><PB REF="8"/>
And chayne your daring spirits to the awe</L>
<L>Of every glance her eye shoots? Tell me truely</L>
<L>How doe the pleasures of this <HI>Capua</HI></L>
<L>Relish upon your senses? are they not</L>
<L>Even what desire can shape?</L>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mah.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are my Lord</L>
<L>Most absolute.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>And you are pleas'd with them?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Him.</SPEAKER>
<L>They cannot bee refus'd, being offer'd us</L>
<L>So ap<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y after labour, as the fruits</L>
<L>And harvest of our paines. What stupid earth</L>
<L>Can be so void of apprehension,</L>
<L>As not to thinke them blessings?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>That can <HI>Hanniball;</HI></L>
<L>Who through the twarthy vizard age and cares</L>
<L>Have tann'd his face with, blusheth at the change</L>
<L>Of Souldiers into women. Why in stead</L>
<L>Of Plume-crown'd crests weare you not tyres? and deck</L>
<L>Your neckes with gemmes, in stead of arming them</L>
<L>With Corslets? Lay by all command, save onely</L>
<L>To set your distaffe-servants taskes, and study</L>
<L>Lascivious dressings, not warres discipline?</L>
<L>Better employ invention how to court</L>
<L>A Mistresse in the fashionable garbe,</L>
<L>Than to contrive a usefull stratagem</L>
<L>Where force prevailes not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mah.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whom have we to sight with?</L>
<L>Lead us againe to action, wee'l expresse</L>
<L>A courage doubled by this little rest:</L>
<L>And from the hopes of such another conquest</L>
<L>We will act wonders, to make victory</L>
<L>Dote on our valours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>You like Carthaginians</L>
<L>Speake from the sonles of men. Muster your Souldiers:</L>
<L>We will againe to <HI>Rome,</HI> and with the terrour</L>
<L>Of our approach make earthquakes in the hearts</L>
<L>Of her gown'd Senators; burne the proud trophees,</L>
<L><PB REF="9"/>
Adorne her Capitoll, or make them scar-crowes:</L>
<L>Bury her high-ascending Towers in heapes</L>
<L>Of their owne ruines; and till <HI>Tyber's</HI> dy'd</L>
<L>With bloud of his owne children, not an arme</L>
<L>Shall cease from slaughter. Have we cut our way</L>
<L>Thorow Mountaines, and thaw'd rocks of Ice for passage</L>
<L>To reach the head of <HI>Rome,</HI> and shall we not</L>
<L>Triumph in her rich spoyles? Yes; we will triumph.</L>
<L>Or by the <HI>Genius</HI> of my native <HI>Carthage,</HI></L>
<L>And the religious oath I made my Father,</L>
<L>When yet my youth had seene the progresse but</L>
<L>Of nine sunnes through the twelve celestial mansions,</L>
<L>Ile level all the rugged Appennines;</L>
<L>And mount the humblest valleys, 'till their heads</L>
<L>Be wrapt in clouds; whence thunder shall not force me,</L>
<L>Till I survey the playnes of <HI>Italy,</HI></L>
<L>Like earth manur'd chalkt with the bones of Romanes,</L>
<L>After their slesh is buried in the gorges</L>
<L>Of Kites and Vultures.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Him.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speake like <HI>Hanniball.</HI></L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scene the fourth.</HEAD>
<STAGE>To them two Ladyes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>What Lady's that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mah.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee's of <HI>Salapia.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>She's lovely. What unusuall passions</L>
<L>Soften me on a sudden? I me thinkes</L>
<L>Could play with ayre, and wanton with the breath</L>
<L>Of such a Mistresse: court her amorously,</L>
<L>And not mistake a phrase, nor fright her tendernesse</L>
<L>With any repetitions of warres horrours.</L>
<L>Cease your rebellion thoughts. I must be man,</L>
<L>And keepe my freedome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Him.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dost observe his eye</L>
<L>How it is fixt?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>What did creation meane</L>
<L><PB REF="9"/>
A woman for, but pleasure? Should not I</L>
<L>Pursue it then since 'tis the end of all</L>
<L>We either doe or wish? 'tis actions soule</L>
<L>That makes it live. I must enjoy it this way.</L>
<L>Desire's a law set downe by natures Counsell,</L>
<L>And not to be disputed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mah.</SPEAKER>
<L>So my Lord!</L>
<L>Example shall direct us: we may well,</L>
<L>If <HI>Anniball</HI> turne Courtier.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Lady,</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>One at once.</L>
<L>Sweet gentlemen. Though I should covet change</L>
<L>At once l'de not admit plurality.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>To you (faire storehouse of your sexes excellence)</L>
<L>I would direct the language of my heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Lady.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis sure a noble dialect, my Lord,</L>
<L>That must expresse it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lady it can speake.</L>
<L>Nothing but passion. You have wounded it.</L>
<L>And from the selfe same eye that shot the dart</L>
<L>I must have balme to cure it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Lady.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Y' are my Lord</L>
<L>A conqueror; and may command the wills</L>
<L>Of all beneath you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>But I am your captive.</L>
<L>And in that pleasant bondage would abide,</L>
<L>Though I might force my ransome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Lad.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Violence</L>
<L>Would it become those vertues same proclaim's</L>
<L>To have possest you: and I dare be confident</L>
<L>Nothing could tempt you to turne ravisher,</L>
<L>Though I should boast virginity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>Suspect</L>
<L>Of such an ill, wrong's your owne innocence.</L>
<L>My love is zealous, and the passive flame</L>
<L>Fed with a pure desire. I would enjoy you</L>
<L>To mixe our soules, not merely to delight</L>
<L>The wanton senses.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="10"/>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Lad.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>How can you, a man</L>
<L>Whom custome hath habituate in th'extremes</L>
<L>Of cruelty, change nature? and perhaps</L>
<L>Your first, innate, and not a second, onely</L>
<L>Borne out of use. Me thinkes it is not possible</L>
<L>Your thoughts should be possest of other objects,</L>
<L>Then what warres horrour paint's with bloudy colours.</L>
<L>Love and a Lady are for such as case</L>
<L>Hath softned into women: <HI>Hanniball</HI></L>
<L>Hath nothing in him, but what's masculine:</L>
<L>So hardned too, that those weake sires can never</L>
<L>Alter his temper.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes; your eyes have done it.</L>
<L>Although my skin be horney, and my flesh</L>
<L>Almost insensible through daily weight</L>
<L>Of heavie armes, the substance of my heart</L>
<L>Is flexible, and takes impressions</L>
<L>Of love from your perfections. It not derogates</L>
<L>From the best difference in mans composition</L>
<L>To love: for that best speakes him man, and argues</L>
<L>Hee hath a spirit capable of things</L>
<L>Worthy his being. Come then perfect me</L>
<L>With your addition: make my captivity</L>
<L>A conquest, and Ile fixc.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Lad.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>That were enough</L>
<L>To brand you with a lasting infamy.</L>
<L>You have designes for action. Should you stop</L>
<L>The prosecution of a warre begun</L>
<L>With such successe, and onely for a woman,</L>
<L>T' would make you be the scorne of men; the subject</L>
<L>Of jesters libels. I could court your valour</L>
<L>As you are <HI>Hanniball:</HI> but as a lover</L>
<L>The thought of that cooles all affection.</L>
<L>Had I at <HI>Cannas</HI> beene, or <HI>Thrasimenus,</HI></L>
<L>Guirt in an Amazonian male, my head</L>
<L>Wrapt in an Iron <HI>tyara,</HI> and my hand</L>
<L>Arm'd with a sword, I would have kept the side</L>
<L><PB REF="10"/>
Of <HI>Hanniball,</HI> to dote upon those wonders</L>
<L>His conquering arme then acted.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>As from water</L>
<L>Cast on <HI>bytumen,</HI> so from these sharpe checks</L>
<L>My flame encreaseth. You expresse a soule</L>
<L>Makes others valours but derivative</L>
<L>From yours; as if the spring of all flow'd thence;</L>
<L>And we but dranke our small proportions</L>
<L>From your abundance. Our embraces would</L>
<L>People the wasted world with Warriours.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scene the fifth.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>To them</HI> Nuntius.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mah.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whence speakes your hast? and what?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nun.</SPEAKER>
<L>I come from <HI>Spaine,</HI></L>
<L>And bring important newes; but sad.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Him.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall wee</L>
<L>By change ride through the Zodiack of your pleasures,</L>
<L>And feast our selves in every house?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Lad.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>You still</L>
<L>Mistake the signe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mah.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis not in <HI>Virgo</HI> sure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Lad.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Nor yet in <HI>Taurus,</HI> though I have a husband.</L>
<L>You two are <HI>Gemini:</HI> a payre of—Captaines.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Him.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee slouts us sure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nun.</SPEAKER>
<L>What should this courtship meane?</L>
<L><HI>Maharball</HI> and <HI>Himulco</HI> that were character'd</L>
<L>For valiant Captaines, turn'd sinock-souldiers?</L>
<L>And <HI>Hanniball?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Lad.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>The ayre of <HI>Capua</HI></L>
<L>Hath not so chang'd us, but we can preserve</L>
<L>Our modesties.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mah.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh miracle! that <HI>Capua</HI></L>
<L>Hath honest women in't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nun.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will <HI>Hanniball</HI></L>
<L>Attend my message?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="11"/>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hast thou brought her pearles</L>
<L>Ravish't from necks of richest Romane dames?</L>
<L>I'le pave the path we tread to <HI>Hymens</HI> joy</L>
<L>With spovles of all the cities I have conquer'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nunt.</SPEAKER>
<L>N<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t of new Carthage; Sagunt; Locris; Tarracon.</L>
<L>All these are re-orecome by <HI>Scipio;</HI></L>
<L>In Spaine he onely triumph's.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Lad.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Doth not <HI>Hannibal?</HI></L>
<L>Minde the sad newes? Revenge if nothing else</L>
<L>Should wing him to new conquest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hann.</SPEAKER>
<L>I perceive</L>
<L>Errours in my behaviour. Court a woman,</L>
<L>When I should threaten vengeance! But shee's faire.</L>
<L>Hang beauty: that and ease are th' onely engines</L>
<L>To ruine vertue. Ladies pray' withdraw:</L>
<L>Th' affaires of men are handling.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Lad.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>May they prove</L>
<L>Your honours more in valour th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>n in love. <STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am prepar'd: and if there were an accident</L>
<L>That did exceed in horrour, praise or wonder,</L>
<L>Discourse it lively, that it may impresse</L>
<L>Something within to beget an act</L>
<L>Shall paralell it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nunt.</SPEAKER>
<L>That must be new Carthage</L>
<L>Her siege and taking. When the Romane generall</L>
<L>Approach't the walls, a cold feare shoke her Genius:</L>
<L>The earth groning with weight of such a multitude.</L>
<L>His Navy likewise at that instant made</L>
<L>A cloud upon the Sea. So round about</L>
<L>The citty was beguirt. Our resolution</L>
<L>Mix't with despaire soone arm'd us; and th'assault</L>
<L>Being suddaine, we did doe before consider:</L>
<L>Yet what we did thus with the wals height proving</L>
<L>Successefull, we had respite to advice.</L>
<L>The Sea we thought sullicient to defend</L>
<L>That pait it washeth, and directed all</L>
<L>Our force to th'Isthmus: where we sallied forth.</L>
<L><PB REF="11"/>
The enemy retir's; but out of policy</L>
<L>To draw us farther on. And now the Sunne</L>
<L>Survey'd us from his heigth; when suddenly</L>
<L>A violent North-winde joyning with the ebbe</L>
<L>Swept all the channell dry. Of which the Romans</L>
<L>Being inform'd by certaine Fishermen</L>
<L>Seize th' opportunity, and freely passe</L>
<L>To th' unman'd walls; entring without resistance.</L>
<L>What more they, being fully conquerors, did,</L>
<L>Need's no relation: custome shew's it <HI>Hannibal.</HI></L>
<L>Th' example made some other citties yeeld;</L>
<L>Some policy wonne; some force; some trechery</L>
<L>Deliv'rd up: all are possest by <HI>Scipio.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then <HI>Rome</HI> shall ransome them. Revenge is able</L>
<L>Out of a flinty cowardize to strike</L>
<L>The fire of valour, with that new supply</L>
<L>I doe expect from Carthage we'l to Rome,</L>
<L>And emulate this victory; nor let it</L>
<L>Be your affliction that blinde chance hath rob'd</L>
<L>Your former labours of their due reward;</L>
<L>Rome will repaire all.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scene the sixth.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>To him</HI> Bomilcar.</STAGE>
<STAGE>See Bomilcar's come.</STAGE>
<L>Cozen what answer send's the Carthage Senate</L>
<L>To my demands? Thy lookes speake discontent;</L>
<L>As if the busines of thy errand choak't</L>
<L>Th' unwilling passage. Vtter it; my brest</L>
<L>Is proofe 'gainst all misfortune.</L>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must then</L>
<L>Deliver a relation of ingratitude</L>
<L>Beyond example. Those whom you have made</L>
<L>Masters of wealth and honour, and releas'd</L>
<L>Their palsied age from many a coward feare,</L>
<L>Not minding the rich benefits you have done them,</L>
<L><PB REF="12"/>
Deny your need reliefe. If you want ayde,</L>
<L>They say your conquest's but a lying rumour:</L>
<L>Nor will they credit doubtful, testimonies</L>
<L>Of any presents. They not stick to call</L>
<L>The ground of this your warre in <HI>Italy</HI></L>
<L>Your owne ambition, not their sa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ety: malice</L>
<L>Of <HI>Hannos</HI> faction having fra<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n'd pretences</L>
<L>To cloude the glory of your actions.</L>
<L>Which to confirme the more, see their command</L>
<L>That you should instantly withdraw your forces,</L>
<L>And to returne to <HI>Carthage.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not till now?</L>
<L>When in my tallons I had almost seiz'd</L>
<L><HI>Romes</HI> Eagle, and prepar'd my sharpned beake</L>
<L>To prey upon her heare?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis likewise fear'd</L>
<L>That <HI>Massanissa</HI> hath forsaken <HI>Carthage.</HI></L>
<L>So that unlesse some policy can winne</L>
<L><HI>Syphax</HI> unto us, we must never more</L>
<L>Expect Numidian ayde. His Counsailours</L>
<L>Seeme to desire it; for they wish your presence:</L>
<L>And that you'l put th'instructions here contein'd</L>
<L>Into a sudden act.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>Must I then leave</L>
<L><HI>Rome</HI> unsubverted? So a man that strives</L>
<L>To make himselfe eternall by erecting</L>
<L>Of some stupendious monument, is forc't</L>
<L>To his last quiet e're the worke be perfect.</L>
<L>Leaving it but a lame and halfe designe</L>
<L>Of his ambition.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Him.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hath not <HI>Hanniball</HI></L>
<L>His forces here? Let's forward with that strength</L>
<L>Which yet is left us; nor regard the tyes</L>
<L>Their doting policies would chaine us with.</L>
<L>Valour consists in hearts more than in number.</L>
<L>Let's on to <HI>Rome.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>No: passion shall submit</L>
<L><PB REF="12"/>
Vnto my best part. Conquest of my selfe</L>
<L>Shall speake me more in this, then if my power</L>
<L>Had level'd her seven hills. I leave her onely</L>
<L>To grow more worthy of my victory.</L>
<L>I will obey, though each unwilling step</L>
<L>Wounds me beyond the cure of common patience.</L>
<L>Commands of power must not be withstood.</L>
<L>Great actions make men great; good actions good.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="act">
<HEAD>The argument of the second Act.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Hanniball <HI>and</HI> Scipio <HI>meet accidentally at the Court of</HI> Syphax: <HI>who favouring the Romanes, and being a young man, is wrought upon by</HI> Hanniball, <HI>to dote upon</HI> Sophonisba: <HI>who after much unwillingnesse exprest, and reflexion on some former love shee bare</HI> Massanissa <HI>(who had beene the Carthaginians friend, but now become the Romanes) is given to</HI> Syphax <HI>for his Wife.</HI></STAGE>
<STAGE>The Scene, the Court of <HI>Syphax</HI> in <HI>Cyrtha.</HI></STAGE>
<DIV3 TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scene the first.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Syphax, Piston, Crates, <HI>Attendants.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pist.</SPEAKER>
<L>'T will prove I feare lame policy to hault</L>
<L>Betwixt these factions, aw'd by two such spirits,</L>
<L>As ne're were still'd from envie or revenge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Brave <HI>Hanniball;</HI> brave <HI>Scipio;</HI> great <HI>Carthage;</HI></L>
<L>But greater <HI>Rome:</HI> whose Eagle eyes have gaz'd</L>
<L>Against the Sunne of many a glorious triumph!</L>
<L>When the bright beames reflected from their riches</L>
<L>Have blinded day-light, as if heavens great eye,</L>
<L>Borrowed his onely from them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="13"/>
<SPEAKER>Crat.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Carthage</HI> is</L>
<L>Oar ancient friend, and friendship long continu'd</L>
<L>Should not be easily lost.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syph.</SPEAKER>
<L>A usefull tenent</L>
<L>Where the condition's private; but in Kings</L>
<L>It doth not hold. Warres chance is variable:</L>
<L>And he that now is victor may be conquer'd</L>
<L>Before his peace be settled. From example</L>
<L>We must consult our safety, more than from</L>
<L>A m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rall precept. Hath not <HI>Scipio</HI></L>
<L>Got <HI>Spa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/></HI> from <HI>Hanniball,</HI> and joyn'd unto him</L>
<L><HI>Massilia's</HI> King? Are not their armies flusht</L>
<L>With the rich spovles of <HI>Sagunt?</HI> and who knowes</L>
<L>But they'l transport then forces, and begirt</L>
<L><HI>Carthage</HI> it selfe. 'Tis better that we yeeld</L>
<L>Freely to amity, than be compel'd,</L>
<L>Than <HI>Scipio</HI> must bee welcome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pist.</SPEAKER>
<L>But if fortune</L>
<L>Prosper my counterplot, he will be greeted</L>
<L>With an affront shall cloud his entertainment;</L>
<L>And dimme the painted glory of that pompe</L>
<L>Your complement intends. Our youthfull King</L>
<L>Must not direct our counsels; nor affaires</L>
<L>Of state be order'd by th'affection</L>
<L>Of one so weake in policy, indulgent</L>
<L>To his owne passions. <HI>Carthage</HI> is set downe</L>
<L>By our experience for <HI>Numidia's</HI> love,</L>
<L>And shall possesse it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syph.</SPEAKER>
<L>We may then consider,</L>
<L>The Carthaginian Generall is a man</L>
<L>Worne with imployment into more decay</L>
<L>Of strength and yeares, than can give any hopes</L>
<L>Of a continuance. <HI>Romes</HI> greene Champion</L>
<L>Is full of growing sappe to make him spread.</L>
<L>Whilst the other like an aged Oke that long</L>
<L>Hath fought with tempests, and withstood the rage</L>
<L>Of burning ayre, now yeelds to every gust.</L>
<L><PB REF="13"/>
A bough or arme, 'till one more violent</L>
<L>Shatters the dry'd limbes, or quite roots it up.</L>
<L>Tis better to provide for lasting state,</L>
<L>Then meerely to prevent a present fate.</L>
<L>Then <HI>Scipio</HI> must be welcome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crat.</SPEAKER>
<L>But if <HI>Syphax</HI></L>
<L>Would heare our reasons.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syph.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Crates</HI> you have beene</L>
<L>Our worthy counsellour, and by your wisdome</L>
<L>Stear'd government in a right course whilst yet</L>
<L>Our youth did want it: but we are now growne</L>
<L>Riper in judgement, and we can distinguish <STAGE>To them Messenger.</STAGE></L>
<L>The different grounds of any politick act.</L>
<L>Nor doe we finde it safe in rules of state</L>
<L>If <HI>Seipio</HI> be not welcome. What's your hast?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mes.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Romane Generall is arriv'd, and entring.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syph.</SPEAKER>
<L>And no faygn'd thunder to informe us of it</L>
<L>From the lowd voyce of slocking multitudes,</L>
<L>Should throng to bid him welcome?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee's scarce knowne</L>
<L>To any but my selfe. His traine is private,</L>
<L>Without due state: onely some needfull servants</L>
<L>To wait upon his person.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Were they his army,</L>
<L>I would exhaust my treasury to feast them:</L>
<L>And every common souldier should drinke healthes</L>
<L>In his Corinthian Goblet, which should be</L>
<L>His largesse likewise. Let our ministers</L>
<L>Fill the shrill throats of warres loud instruments.</L>
<L>And Dodonean brasse be beaten deafe</L>
<L>Whilst it proclaimes his welcome. Let the Sea</L>
<L>Eccho the sounds to <HI>Sagant,</HI> and returne</L>
<L>Their shoots agen. <STAGE>Flourish.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="scene">
<PB REF="14"/>
<HEAD>Scene the second.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>To them</HI> Scipio, Lelius.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Welcome great <HI>Scipio.</HI></STAGE>
<L>Never did <HI>Syphax</HI> joyfull armes imbrace</L>
<L>A guest of so rich valew, in whose minde</L>
<L>Worlds of heroick vertues are congested</L>
<L>To make him up a worthy.</L>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scip.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le not answere</L>
<L>Your kindnesse <HI>Syphax</HI> with a complement.</L>
<L>My tongue's not oyld with slattery. I have stolne</L>
<L>A little time from action, to informe</L>
<L><HI>Numidia's</HI> King, how <HI>Rome,</HI> by my advice,</L>
<L>Hath chosen him a favourer of her cause</L>
<L>That suffers by false <HI>Carthage.</HI> The successe</L>
<L>Of my recovering <HI>Spaine,</HI> hath given new hopes</L>
<L>Vnto her fainting spirits, that were neere</L>
<L>Their last expiring by the massacres</L>
<L>The Carthaginian made. Sixe Consuls have</L>
<L>Already fall'n: my Father, and mine Vncle;</L>
<L><HI>Sempronius; Terentius</HI> and <HI>Flaminius;</HI></L>
<L>And last <HI>Marcellus,</HI> who receiv'd his death</L>
<L>Even in the sight of <HI>Rome.</HI> Yet there's a <HI>Scipio</HI></L>
<L>Surviv's to conquer him, or dye in th'enterprise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syph.</SPEAKER>
<L>And that brave <HI>Scipio</HI> shall not want what ayde</L>
<L>My person, or my Kingdome can affoord him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scip.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Rome</HI> shal make great esteem of <HI>Syphax</HI> friendship</L>
<L>And when she shall be wrapt in silken wings</L>
<L>Of victory and peace, his statue crown'd</L>
<L>Shall grace the triumph.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pist.</SPEAKER>
<L>I should rather joy</L>
<L>To see him chayn'd a captive, though my se<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>e</L>
<L>And family were sold to be his ransome,</L>
<L>In <HI>Carthage</HI> quarrell.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="scene">
<PB REF="14"/>
<HEAD>Scene the third.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>To them</HI> Hanniball, Himulco, Maharball.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>This cold entertainment</L>
<L>Doth make me jealous.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crat.</SPEAKER>
<L>See: how soone their eyes</L>
<L>Have found each other?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scip.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sure 'tis <HI>Hanniball.</HI></L>
<L>His name and nature's stampt upon his brow;</L>
<L>I in those wrinckles read it: valour mixt</L>
<L>With cruelty; to which ambition onely</L>
<L>As the first wheele in engines moves the rest.</L>
<L>That eye he lost passing the fennes of <HI>Arnus;</HI></L>
<L>And such a looke his counterfeit is drawne with.</L>
<L>If there be trechery.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syph.</SPEAKER>
<L>What would <HI>Hanniball?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scip.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is't <HI>Hanniball?</HI> We are betrai'd by <HI>Syphax.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>What art?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scip.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Romes</HI> Generall, and thy enemy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha! <HI>Scipio!</HI> Then the character report</L>
<L>Give's of him's false. He scornes ignoble wayes</L>
<L>Of honour; to ore-come by trechery.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scip.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thought the same of <HI>Hanniball.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>And findst it.</L>
<L>Tis onely thy conspiracy with <HI>Syphax;</HI></L>
<L>Who makes his Court a priviledge for that</L>
<L>Fame will proclaime with blushes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why this uproare?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Syphax</HI> th'art trecherous.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scip.</SPEAKER>
<L>To <HI>Rome</HI> and <HI>Scipio.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>To <HI>Hannibal</HI> and <HI>Carthage.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pist.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now observe</L>
<L>How he will calme the tempest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syph.</SPEAKER>
<L>What to answer</L>
<L>From sudden doubts you both possesse me with,</L>
<L>I cannot easily resolve. A jealousie</L>
<L><PB REF="15"/>
Is sometimes strengthned by th'excuse should kill it.</L>
<L>Yet if your confidence will give credit to</L>
<L>A Kings religious oath, by all that makes</L>
<L>The sacred difference in me I am free</L>
<L>From thought of ill to either. Your arrivals</L>
<L>Were unexpected; and if eithers danger</L>
<L>Be smother'd in intent, you brought it with you:</L>
<L>Which Ile prevent, if all <HI>Numidia's</HI> strength</L>
<L>Can doe it. Thinke not me perfidious,</L>
<L>For then Ile doubt you: since selfe cvills are</L>
<L>Most commonly the parents of suspicion.</L>
<L>But for your owne mistrusts, y'are safer here</L>
<L>Than in your owne campes, guarded with a maze</L>
<L>Of your best souldiers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis a satisfaction.</L>
<L>I blesse th' occasion makes us meet: my longings</L>
<L>Were violent to see thee <HI>Scipio.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scip.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mine more to see thee <HI>Hanniball;</HI> but rather</L>
<L>Arm'd in the sield, prepard for an encounter,</L>
<L>Then here to parlee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doubt not such a greeting</L>
<L>When next we meet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syph.</SPEAKER>
<L>I needs must interpose,</L>
<L>And moderate this contention. Pray my Lords</L>
<L>Let me be powerfull to dispose your tempers</L>
<L>For other mild impressions, that my Court</L>
<L>For entertaining two such enemies</L>
<L>At once, be made discourse for after-ages.</L>
<L>A banquet waits yee: musick usher it. <STAGE>Musick.</STAGE></L>
<L>Thus peace bids Souldiers welcome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scip.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Syphax</HI> no.</L>
<L>Thinke of <HI>Romes</HI> cause, and let your feast be season'd</L>
<L>With saith to that. If thou prove trecherous,</L>
<L>Expect a vengeance, justice never yet</L>
<L>Gave severe execution to a greater.</L>
<L>I must be gone; th'affaires of warre attend me</L>
<L>When I have settled <HI>Romes</HI> peace, wee'l comply</L>
<L><PB REF="15"/>
In the effects: action 'till then must live</L>
<L>By blood and labour. <HI>Hanniball</HI> farewell:</L>
<L>Next greeting will be rougher.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not to be calm'd</L>
<L>With words. Grow strong; be still a conquerour,</L>
<L>Till I shall conquer thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scip.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art but flatter'd</L>
<L>By an ambition vainer than thy dreames.</L>
<L>Ten <HI>Carthages</HI> and <HI>Hannibals</HI> will not weigh</L>
<L>Equall with the atchievment.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>One <HI>Hanniball</HI></L>
<L>And <HI>Carthage</HI> poys'd but in an equall scale</L>
<L>With twenty <HI>Romes,</HI> and twenty <HI>Scipios,</HI></L>
<L>Shall weigh like lead' gainst feathers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scip.</SPEAKER>
<L>Proud insister</L>
<L>Vpon his owne slight merits! Remember <HI>Syphax</HI></L>
<L>Thy vow hath made thee <HI>Romes.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Which Ile preserve</L>
<L>As sacredly inviolate, as if</L>
<L>Eternall seales had ratifi'd it. Vsher</L>
<L>The Romane Generall forth. <STAGE>Flourish. Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Him.</SPEAKER>
<L>Have words such power</L>
<L>Vpon our Generall to deject him thus?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>My braine is labouring.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Him.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile helpe to deliver it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>As giddy fancies when they doe present</L>
<L>Delightfull shaddowes, seeme to please the sense</L>
<L>When it is quiet, and not capable</L>
<L>Of any object, 'till the dreamers joy</L>
<L>Suddenly wakes him, and the false impressions</L>
<L>Vanish to their first nothing, so have I</L>
<L>Flatter'd my hopes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Him.</SPEAKER>
<L>I prophesie successe</L>
<L>Despight of <HI>Scipio. Syphax</HI> Counsailours</L>
<L>(Whose secret correspondency with us</L>
<L>Taught the great meanes by which their Masters love</L>
<L>Must be regain'd) a long experience</L>
<L><PB REF="16"/>
Confirmes our friends: then prosecute it throughly.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scene the fourth.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>To them</HI> Piston, Crates, <HI>and a little after</HI> Syphax.</STAGE>
<STAGE>They are return'd.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pist.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord' till now the accidents</L>
<L>Caus'd by the Romanes presence did prevent us</L>
<L>From giving satisfaction to your doubts,</L>
<L>Which were but justly grounded. Our young King</L>
<L>Is full of's youthfull passions, and so violant</L>
<L>Ith' prosecution ofthem counsell rather</L>
<L>Doth set a keener edge upon his appetite.</L>
<L>We therefore give him way. But if we cannot</L>
<L>Reduce his actions to a rule of judgement,</L>
<L>Wee'l openly oppose him, or conspire</L>
<L>As 'gainst a tyrant that makes will his law.</L>
<L>See hee's return'd: be confident.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syph.</SPEAKER>
<L>How! whispering!</L>
<L>I doe suspect.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>If <HI>Syphax</HI> dare be private.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dare <HI>Hannibal!</HI> Hadst thou intents more blaek</L>
<L>Than ever night gave execution to,</L>
<L>Even in <HI>Carthage</HI> Senate house as well</L>
<L>As in mine owne Court, I dare stand th'encounter</L>
<L>Of single <HI>Hannibal.</HI> Withdraw.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>They must not.</L>
<L>The wrongs thou hast done <HI>Carthage</HI> must be witness'd:</L>
<L>That when same speakes them lowdest, partiall men</L>
<L>Make not their incredulity an excuse</L>
<L>For what no satisfaction can restore,</L>
<L>Thy honour lost in infamy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou tempt'st me</L>
<L>With these darke prefaces. Yet thy upbraydings</L>
<L>Doe seeme so frivolous, my patience rather</L>
<L>Laughs at their vainnesse. Cleare my understanding</L>
<L>Without more circumstance, for yet my innocence</L>
<L><PB REF="16"/>
Knowesnot t' accuse my selfe, unlesse for<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>giving</L>
<L>Thy sawcy taunts a priviledge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>What errour</L>
<L>But to defend it selfe will strive (though vainly)</L>
<L>To mock truth out of truth? Well <HI>Syphax</HI> knowes</L>
<L>The expectation of a state deluded</L>
<L>Cannot but trouble it. A King is more</L>
<L>Than a meane person, bounded with dimensions</L>
<L>Of the bare man. His actions are his peoples;</L>
<L>And what he doth or suffers they must stand.</L>
<L>Consider then when <HI>Carthage</HI> shall call up</L>
<L>Revenge, and with all force pursue the injury</L>
<L>To satisfaction; when her souldiers</L>
<L>(Whom custome hath made pittilesse) shall plough</L>
<L>The wombes of teeming Mothers with their fauchions,</L>
<L>To prevent the issue that might vindicate</L>
<L>A father slaine; make your Numidian Virgins</L>
<L>The ruines of their pleasure, and not leave</L>
<L>An altar to your gods, nor private Lar</L>
<L>That may defend a houshould from their violence:</L>
<L>When these (whose very repetition carry's</L>
<L>Horrour enough to fright men into peace)</L>
<L>Shall happen—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syph.</SPEAKER>
<L>When they shall! it rather seemes</L>
<L>A positive threat. Tell <HI>Carthage</HI> were her power</L>
<L>Of an extent that limits could not bound</L>
<L>With any circumscription, I'de not feare it.</L>
<L>To dye for <HI>Rome</HI> were above victory.</L>
<L>Furnisht ten thousand choyce Numidian Horsemen</L>
<L>To wait on <HI>Scipio.</HI> Why are our commands</L>
<L>No more respected? Ile have execution</L>
<L>Forerunne my Edicts that concerne the good</L>
<L>Of <HI>Rome</HI> and <HI>Scipio.</HI> Stand yee like dull statues</L>
<L>Fixt to their first foundations; when your diligence</L>
<L>Should borrow speed from winds, as if yee rid</L>
<L>On the contracted ayre to hasten it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>Full well their age wise with experience knows</L>
<L><PB REF="17"/>
To disobey a Kings unjust commands</L>
<L>Law and religion warrants. <HI>Syphax</HI> youth</L>
<L>Were fitter to court beauty, than to sit</L>
<L>At a states helme, and steere the various course</L>
<L>It's subject to, by his greene violent passions.</L>
<L>With which his bed e're this had beene enricht,</L>
<L>Had <HI>Carthage</HI> found him kind: Faire <HI>Sophonisba.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crat.</SPEAKER>
<L>That name hath stattled him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>She from whose eyes</L>
<L>The amorous sunne, resigning first his owne;</L>
<L>Might be ambitious to derive new fires.</L>
<L>Yet she to be reserv'd for his embraces,</L>
<L>Who slights that honour all the neighbouring Kings</L>
<L>Have beene competitors for, and would lay downe</L>
<L>Their Crownes to purchase; sell their very beings</L>
<L>To be translated into a possession</L>
<L>Of <HI>Sophonisba.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pist.</SPEAKER>
<L>It begins to worke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whence did th'intent of this great honour to me</L>
<L>Derive it selfe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>From a desire of friendship</L>
<L>And league with <HI>Syphax:</HI> which his passionate love</L>
<L>To <HI>Rome</HI> and <HI>Scipio</HI> (that admits no reason)</L>
<L>Denying, I must publish the dishonour</L>
<L>Done to a Lady, at whose least command</L>
<L>A Nation shall be arm'd, led by such Captaines</L>
<L>As in their emulation will declare</L>
<L>What mortals owe to her divine perfections;</L>
<L>That warrant her revenge as just a quarrell,</L>
<L>As ever stir'd up valour in a conscience</L>
<L>Scruples had cowarded. Here my commission</L>
<L>Takes end, and I must goe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay <HI>Hanniball.</HI></L>
<L>Strange passions warre against my resolution;</L>
<L>And love begins to circle me in flames</L>
<L>E're my eye takes the fire. What's <HI>Rome</HI> or <HI>Scipio</HI></L>
<L>To <HI>Sophonisba?</HI> in whose richer beauty</L>
<L><PB REF="17"/>
Mor's comprehended, then the <HI>Macedonian</HI></L>
<L>Could from his many conquests, and subversion</L>
<L>Of Monarchies boast himselfe owner of.</L>
<L>What's a King's promise but a politick</L>
<L>(And that's allow'd) evasion to gaine time</L>
<L>For counsaill with his will? Ile be for <HI>Carthage</HI></L>
<L>To enjoy <HI>Sophonisba.</HI> I'am enflam'd</L>
<L>From the report, and if my senses find</L>
<L>Truth answering fame, great <HI>Hannibal</HI> shall lead</L>
<L>Numidias power' gainst <HI>Rome,</HI> or any place</L>
<L>He hath design'd for conquest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>But if <HI>Syphax</HI></L>
<L>Should againe suffer <HI>Scipio's</HI> menacies</L>
<L>To fright his weaknesse out of this resolve I</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syph.</SPEAKER>
<L>My weakenesse! tempt me not with a suspect.</L>
<L>Let me have <HI>Sophonisba,</HI> or I'le make</L>
<L>A rape upon your <HI>Carthage,</HI> not on her,</L>
<L>For what delight's in violence? Enquire</L>
<L>The cause of that lowd shout. <STAGE>Shout within. Messenger.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Messen.</SPEAKER>
<L>I come t'informe you.</L>
<L>A stately ship from her rich laden wombe,</L>
<L>Hath on our shore deliver'd such a traine</L>
<L>Of glorious Virgins that attend on one,</L>
<L>Who lead's the rest—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more; 'tis <HI>Sophonisba.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Receive her with religious ceremony.</L>
<L>Perfume the ayre with incence richer then</L>
<L>The Phoenix funerall pile. Let harmony <STAGE>Musicke.</STAGE></L>
<L>Breath out her soule at every artists touch.</L>
<L>Cover the pavement which her steps must hallow</L>
<L>With Persian Tapestry. How I am ravish't</L>
<L>With th'expectation? and like somelight matter</L>
<L>Catch't in a whirle-wind, all my faculties</L>
<L>Are hurried forward.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="scene">
<PB REF="18"/>
<HEAD>Scene the fifth.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Tothem</HI> Sophonisba, <HI>Ladies all in white, and veil'd: who to the musicke of the song, place themselves in a figure for a daunce.</HI></STAGE>
<STAGE>Veil'd! 'tis sure some mockery.</STAGE>
<STAGE>The Song.</STAGE>
<L><HI>Beautie no more the subject be</HI></L>
<L><HI>Of want on art to slatter thee:</HI></L>
<L><HI>Or in dull figures call thee spring;</HI></L>
<L><HI>Lillie or Rose, or other thing:</HI></L>
<L><HI>All which beneath thee are, and grow</HI></L>
<L><HI>Into contempt when thou dost show</HI></L>
<L><HI>The unmatch't glory of thy brow.</HI></L>
<STAGE>Chorus.</STAGE>
<L><HI>Behold a spheare of Virgins move,</HI></L>
<L><HI>None mongst them lesse then Queene of Love.</HI></L>
<L><HI>And yet their Queene so farre excels</HI></L>
<L><HI>Beauty and she are onely parallels.</HI></L>
<STAGE>A daunce too ▪ I'le expect th'event.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>In the daunce they discover themselves in order,</HI> Sophonisba <HI>last.</HI></STAGE>
<STAGE>A faire one:</STAGE>
<L>But 'tis not <HI>Sophonisba.</HI> Fairer yet.</L>
<L>Vnhappy <HI>Syphax</HI> from whose eyes such wonders</L>
<L>Have beene to long conceal'd. Which is the goddesse?</L>
<L>Which <HI>Sophonisba?</HI></L>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sopho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can thy sense distinguish?</L>
<L>See <HI>Syphax,</HI> thus I deigne to shew thee that</L>
<L>Kings have beene proud to worship.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="18"/>
<SPEAKER>Syph.</SPEAKER>
<L>E're I embrace</L>
<L>Let me admire. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>each eye sit's a Cupid;</L>
<L>Who as he skip's about to shoot his dartes.</L>
<L>Is himselfe fetter'd in the golden curles</L>
<L>That deck her brow. Elysium's but a fable.</L>
<L>And that eternity the Poets dreame of</L>
<L>Serv's but to figure this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sopho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Although my difference</L>
<L>Might challenge more, I'm not ambitious</L>
<L>Of shallow praise. My spirit must flie high</L>
<L>To catch at fame, not flattery.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Came you not</L>
<L>To love me then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sopho.</SPEAKER>
<L>I did: but not to thinke</L>
<L>All your expressions (though they were extended</L>
<L>Beyond my wish) can merit it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syph.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am</L>
<L>A King; and you me thinks should court the fortune</L>
<L>With a glad readinesse, to share my honours,</L>
<L>And to be made my equall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sopho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Were you more,</L>
<L>I am above addition in my selfe:</L>
<L>And should be lessen'd if I did confine</L>
<L>A thought to any person, and the act</L>
<L>Included nothing but bare satisfaction</L>
<L>Of a desire. I will not let a smile</L>
<L>Fall loosly from me, but shall be attended</L>
<L>By actions worth their history; which read</L>
<L>Shall with the apprehension of my greatnesse</L>
<L>Amaze posterity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can <HI>Sophonisba</HI></L>
<L>Be covetous of more then the earths honours?</L>
<L>When she shall sit incompass'd in a ring</L>
<L>Of noble Matrons that shall deifie</L>
<L>Her beauty with their praises? When she shall</L>
<L>Be crown'd with sparkling wreathesto blind the gazers,</L>
<L>As if a Constellation had beene rob'd</L>
<L><PB REF="19"/>
To make her shine. When in a Kings armes sleeping</L>
<L>All pleasures shall be minister'd, that Nature</L>
<L>And art in their contention strive to owne,</L>
<L>And take their glory from.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sopho.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hei'r prety baites</L>
<L>To catch an easie wanton, whose dull earth</L>
<L>A little varnish'to're doth know it selfe</L>
<L>No farther then the superficiall tincture</L>
<L>Discoverd in her glasse. I have a soule</L>
<L>Greater then <HI>Syphax</HI> Kingdome: and to bound it</L>
<L>Would take from what I am. 'Twill be your honour</L>
<L>'Bove all that your ambition can direct you</L>
<L>To hope for (next eternity) If I</L>
<L>Vouchsafe to add unto your petty royalty</L>
<L>My greater selfe; and the addition be</L>
<L>Greater then you can purchase by your conquests.</L>
<L>'Tis but her due when <HI>Sophonisba</HI> crav's</L>
<L>Worlds for her Kingdomes, their Kings for her slaves.</L>
<L>Should <HI>Syphax</HI> make a resignation</L>
<L>Of all he own's for me; 'twere but as if</L>
<L>He par'd a mol-hill from the earth, to place</L>
<L>An <HI>Atlas</HI> in its stead.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come <HI>Sophonisba</HI></L>
<L>You must consent: ther's fame in't that will give you</L>
<L>An everlasting being in the memory</L>
<L>O<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> benefits your Country will derive from't.</L>
<L>Children shall first be taught to speake your name;</L>
<L>And from their aged grandsires learne your story.</L>
<L>Whose often repetition shall take from</L>
<L>The tediousnesse of age, and make them seeme</L>
<L>As if they danc't for joy, when palsies shake them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Am I enslam'd, and shall I not enjoy?</L>
<L>Mock me not Lady into a despaire.</L>
<L>You shew me heaven, and shut the gates against me.</L>
<L>Make not a King, that daign's to be your servant,</L>
<L>A slave unto your cruelty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>To give</L>
<L><PB REF="19"/>
<HI>Syphax</HI> a satisfaction, your competitor</L>
<L>False <HI>Massanissa,</HI> he that shar's your Kingdome.</L>
<L>And would ingrosse it all, hath long solicited</L>
<L>For <HI>Sophonisbas</HI> love.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sopho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh <HI>Massanissa.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>He having now forsaken <HI>Carthage,</HI> shee</L>
<L>Out of her piety to doe her Country</L>
<L>A good, preferr's you: and that her revenge</L>
<L>May be pursu'd with greater violence,</L>
<L>Allow's her elfe your right; though she's a treasure</L>
<L>Might be dispos'd of to a more advantage</L>
<L>Of <HI>Carthage</HI> strength.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will <HI>Sophonisba</HI> love then</L>
<L>If I fight <HI>Carthag's</HI> quarrell?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sopho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes; your fortune</L>
<L>Wh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/> 'tis at hight: but the least declination</L>
<L>Waving it to an ebb, I from that fall</L>
<L>Must mount to higher honours, if a gale</L>
<L>Meete it to raise me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syph.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Massanissas</HI> person</L>
<L>It seem's could limit your desires.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sopho.</SPEAKER>
<L>He was</L>
<L>A man made up of fire; no grosse earth clog'd</L>
<L>His spirit when 'twould mount to honours top,</L>
<L>And load same with his acts. Had he not falln</L>
<L>From <HI>Carthage, Sophonisba</HI> had but beene</L>
<L>The price of his desert. And yet I love him.</L>
<L>Deere <HI>Massanissa!</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee hath overcome me.</L>
<L>I will be great; every dayes action</L>
<L>Shall raise me a step higher, and I'le take</L>
<L>You with me Lady: no; you shall lead me</L>
<L>The tribute I will pay for every kisse</L>
<L>Shall be a victory o're your enemies.</L>
<L>Proud <HI>Rome</HI> shall find <HI>Syphax</HI> can be a Souldier,</L>
<L>When <HI>Sophonisba</HI> bid's him put on steele.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>The not to be resisted power of beauty.</L>
<L><PB REF="20"/>
<HI>Carthage</HI> I will salute thee now with joy.</L>
<L>Nor shall the thought of thy ingratitude</L>
<L>Make me lesse willing to pursue thy good</L>
<L>Through a deepe sea of vanquisht. Roman's blood.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee'l feast, then fight. Who led by such bright eves</L>
<L>Would not match on to any enterprize? <STAGE>Exennt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="act">
<HEAD>The argument of the third Act.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Syphax <HI>warring against the Romans, at length is taken prisoner by</HI> Massanissa; <HI>who finding</HI> Sophonisba <HI>in the City of</HI> Cirtha, <HI>marry's her, with a vow not to deliver her up to the Romanes. For which marriage being reprov'd by</HI> Scipio, <HI>he giv's her poyson? which shee tak's to prevent the Romanes triumph over her.</HI></STAGE>
<STAGE>The Scene <HI>Vtica.</HI></STAGE>
<DIV3 TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scene the first.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Scipio, <HI>Souldiers: a little after</HI> Lelius.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scip.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Syphax</HI> so soone revolted I what weake man</L>
<L>Would mock away his safetie? Chldren thus</L>
<L>Playing with fire to please their foolish sense</L>
<L>Are often burn't and make their sport the instrument</L>
<L>Of their owne danger. <HI>Massanissa</HI> yet</L>
<L>Is constant, and by this time hath subdu'd him.</L>
<L>Successe must follow those attemps that rise</L>
<L>From a just cause, and crowne the enterprise.</L>
<L><HI>Lelius</HI> what newes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lelius.</SPEAKER>
<L>I labour with th'event;</L>
<L>Ioy hinder's a delivery. <HI>Massanissa</HI></L>
<L>Guirt in a conquest, greater never made</L>
<L>A triumph glorious, is returning back</L>
<L><PB REF="20"/>
To present <HI>Scipio</HI> with Numidias spoyles,</L>
<L>And <HI>Syphax</HI> cativ'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scip.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis a joyfull errant.</L>
<L>Iust <HI>Nemesis,</HI> thy Grirfins have beene swift,</L>
<L>And borne thee well to see the execution</L>
<L>Of a revenge upon perfidious <HI>Syphax.</HI></L>
<L>Hadst thou fail'd in't, we justly might disclaime</L>
<L>Thy deity, and without feare of punishment</L>
<L>Prophane thy altars: on whose marbles now</L>
<L>Wee'l pay a sacrifice of richest flame</L>
<L>Mixt with the blood of Kings, Discourse the progresse</L>
<L>To this event.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leli.</SPEAKER>
<L>When your successefull policy</L>
<L>Had destroy'd both the Campes of <HI>Asdrubal</HI></L>
<L>And <HI>Syphax</HI> with devouring fire, whose flames</L>
<L>seem'd to the distant gazers on't a prodigie</L>
<L>That threaten'd dissolution, and begot</L>
<L>Their greater feare, then when th' Artilerie</L>
<L>Of heaven speak's lowdest through the burning ayre</L>
<L>To tell the world <HI>Iove's</HI> angry: When you retir'd</L>
<L>To <HI>Vtica</HI> to prevent an invasion</L>
<L>Intended by the Carthaginian Navy,</L>
<L>Which dark't the Sea (much like a clowd of Vulturs</L>
<L>That are convented after some great fight</L>
<L>To glut their ravenous gorges with the gore,</L>
<L>Thousands of soul-lesse men lye reeking in)</L>
<L>The mad Numidian King, in whom despaire</L>
<L>Had kindled a new valour, gather's head.</L>
<L>And with a fresh supply of unman'd men</L>
<L>(For had they beene such as experience</L>
<L>Had taught the usefull order of a warre</L>
<L>Th'end had againe beene doubtfull) giv's us battaile.</L>
<L>Their first assault made us retire; yet still</L>
<L>We kept the suddaine forme hast put us in</L>
<L>For best advantage: 'till their heedlesse courage</L>
<L>Hurri'd them on, where our foot Legions</L>
<L>Observing their disorder (for they fought</L>
<L><PB REF="21"/>
In throngs so thick, that many times one striking</L>
<L>Wounded his fellow) giv's them new resistance.</L>
<L>At which they stop, mated with apprehension</L>
<L>Of their owne danger: whom th'incensed King</L>
<L>Mixing his threates with promises of honour</L>
<L>Labour's to bring one till his horse being kill'd</L>
<L>We tooke him prisoner, with two thousand more.</L>
<L>The rest not flame are fled.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scip.</SPEAKER>
<L>Brave victory</L>
<L>Worthy th'atchievers, to whose memories</L>
<L>Eternall statues shall be rais'd, and trophees</L>
<L>Rich as <HI>Romes</HI> Capitoll is glorious with.</L>
<L>But where is <HI>Massanissa?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leli.</SPEAKER>
<L>He pretended</L>
<L>To visit <HI>Cirtha, Syphax</HI> chiefest Citie:</L>
<L>Which is deliver'd up.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scip.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have new feares <STAGE>Flourish.</STAGE></L>
<L>That woman will agen bewitch him. Know</L>
<L>The cause.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scene the Second.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>To them</HI> Massanissa, <HI>Souldiers bringing in</HI> Syphax <HI>bound.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leli.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis <HI>Massanissa.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scip.</SPEAKER>
<L>Th'only wealth</L>
<L>I'de be possest of. I embrace in thee</L>
<L>A boundlesse treasure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Massa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let not <HI>Scipio</HI></L>
<L>Flatter me into pride for what is rather</L>
<L>Fortunes then mine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scip.</SPEAKER>
<L>The actions of thy vertue.</L>
<L>Fortun's an under power that is her selfe</L>
<L>Commanded by desert. 'Tis a meere vainnesse</L>
<L>Of our credulity to give her more</L>
<L>Then her due attribute; which is but servant</L>
<L>To an heroick spirit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Massa,</SPEAKER>
<L>This example</L>
<L><PB REF="21"/>
Might instance proofes for her divinity.</L>
<L>All's but endeavour untill perfected</L>
<L>By the successe, and that is fortunes only;</L>
<L>Desert shar's little in'r.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scip.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let not thy modesty</L>
<L>Maintaine such errors. To refuse just praise</L>
<L>Is an extreme worse then man's over-weening</L>
<L>Opinion of himselfe. Great <HI>Massanissa</HI></L>
<L>Shall have all honours due unto his conquest;</L>
<L>And weare triumphant Garlands; that false King</L>
<L>Chain'd to his Chariot from the gazers eyes</L>
<L>Inviting scorne, not pitty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syph.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis not manly</L>
<L>To insult over misery, to which</L>
<L>Thy self's as subject, and perhaps mai'st feele,</L>
<L>Chance mak's prosperity when 'tis at highest</L>
<L>But pastime to delight her giddy humour:</L>
<L>And will d ject the most seeme possessour,</L>
<L>When she command's a restitution</L>
<L>Of her lent favours, that she may conferre them</L>
<L>Vpon another. This consideration</L>
<L>Might invite mercy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scip.</SPEAKER>
<L>When superiour justice</L>
<L>Mak's us her instrument, should we be partiall</L>
<L>I th'execution, 'twere to mock the power,</L>
<L>And call downe vengeance. Yet I grieve for <HI>Syphax</HI></L>
<L>That he deserv's the punishment; whose weaknesse!</L>
<L>Suffer'd a peece of painted earth to tempt him</L>
<L>From his religion, and neglect the gods,</L>
<L>Whom he invok't for witnesse to that vow</L>
<L>A woman made him violate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syph.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis my hope</L>
<L>Shee may deceive thee too, and with her charmes</L>
<L>Bewitch the boasting Conquerour that's her slave</L>
<L>From's faith to <HI>Rome.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Massa.</SPEAKER>
<L>His madnesse will betray me</L>
<L>To a reproach</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="22"/>
<SPEAKER>Syph.</SPEAKER>
<L>It tak's from mine owne suffering</L>
<L>To see mine enemy in the same danger:</L>
<L>When he by his adulterous embraces</L>
<L>Receiv's the like infection int' his soule</L>
<L>That made me sick of vertue, and of all</L>
<L>But my disease.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scip.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe you enjoy the Lady?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Massa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes: she's my wife.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scip.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yoar act was somewhat rash;</L>
<L>Before her husbands death! Doth the religion</L>
<L>You pay <HI>Numidia's</HI> gods warrant it law full?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Massa.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Syphax</HI> is dead in his captivity.</L>
<L>Hislife was mine; which I but lent him only</L>
<L>For <HI>Romes</HI> great triumph.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scip.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee'l consult a little,</L>
<L>And then dispose you <HI>Syphax.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syph.</SPEAKER>
<L>As your will</L>
<L>Adviseth you. It is the curse of greatnesse</L>
<L>To be it's owne destruction. So we see</L>
<L>That mountaine Cedars have the least defence</L>
<L>Gainst stormes, when shrubs confront their violence. <STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scene the third.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Scipio, Massanissa <HI>remaining.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scip.</SPEAKER>
<L>When first you freely did commit your selfe</L>
<L>Vnto my charge, and promis'd with a vow</L>
<L>My liking only should dispose your actions,</L>
<L>Either you lov'd them, or your slattery</L>
<L>Pretended admiration of some vertues</L>
<L>You thought possest me. One I must confesse</L>
<L>I glory to be master of, that's continence.</L>
<L>I have converst with beauties rich as Nature</L>
<L>Did ever make art proud to counterfeit;</L>
<L>Might have commanded some that conquest gave me:</L>
<L>Yet have I still kept out desire, but you</L>
<L><PB REF="22"/>
Have yeelded to that passion doth betray</L>
<L>A weakenesse in you, will obscure the glory</L>
<L>Of all your other goodnesse. Thinke how dangerous</L>
<L>'Tis to a yong man (on whose expectation</L>
<L>Opinions eye is six't) to mixe his actions</L>
<L>With wanton pleasures, when his thoughts transferre</L>
<L>The wicked objects of his humorous sense</L>
<L>Vnto his soule, that poison all her faculties,</L>
<L>And make them uselesse. Noble <HI>Massanissa,</HI></L>
<L>Your good deeds sung by same are musicke to me:</L>
<L>Your errours I had rather you your selfe</L>
<L>Would silently consider, and reforme,</L>
<L>Before with any shew of least unkindnesse</L>
<L>You force me to reprove them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Massa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let not <HI>Scipio</HI></L>
<L>Deny those errors an excuse. If nature</L>
<L>Had a like cloth'd mens dispositions,</L>
<L>And all did weare one habit of the mind,</L>
<L>You need not urge th'example of your owne</L>
<L>T'instruct anothers continence: for all</L>
<L>From a necessited and innate temperance</L>
<L>Would be as you are. Though I doe not boast</L>
<L>Command o're pleasures, I pursue them not</L>
<L>With an intemperate appetite, but make</L>
<L>Reason my guide, that tell's me to provide</L>
<L>For a succession, doth become the judgement</L>
<L>Of a wise King. Posterity may well</L>
<L>Be call'd th'eternity of life: he never</L>
<L>Dy's that hath issue; for which I have marryed</L>
<L>Her mine owne conquest gave me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scip.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your owne conquest!</L>
<L>Pray doe not arrogate too much: you must not</L>
<L>Dispose <HI>Romes</HI> prisoners whilst you fight her quarrell.</L>
<L>The warr's not yours, though yours the victory.</L>
<L>She must attend her sentence from our Senate;</L>
<L>Which hardly will be partiall to her beauty,</L>
<L><PB REF="23"/>
Though 'twere adulterated with more art,</L>
<L>Then e're lasciviousinesse was mistresse of,</L>
<L>And rack 't invention for. Let <HI>Sophonisba</HI></L>
<L>Be then deliver'd up.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Massa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Perhaps your selfe</L>
<L>A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ter your boatted continence would have her</L>
<L>To be your owne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scip.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is that your jealousie?</L>
<L>Weake passionate man, that through thy blinded reason</L>
<L>Foresee'st not thine owne danger by th'example</L>
<L>Of others misery, and yet art ripe,</L>
<L>To maintaine grossest errours of thy will,</L>
<L>And seeme discretions master. Had not <HI>Syphax</HI></L>
<L>(Bewitch by magick of her wanton eye</L>
<L>Into a dotage) broke his faith with <HI>Rome,</HI></L>
<L>He might have flourish't in his height of glory;</L>
<L>And still commanded over his Division.</L>
<L>Which <HI>Rome</HI> will add to <HI>Massanissas</HI> Kingdome</L>
<L>Yeelding up <HI>Sophonisba.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Massa.</SPEAKER>
<L>You would seeme</L>
<L>To give me mines, upon condition</L>
<L>I should restore the gold, reserving only</L>
<L>The earth to trample on. In <HI>Sophonisba</HI></L>
<L>I have a treature mine owne life shall ransome,</L>
<L>If she be forc't away; and to consent</L>
<L>She should be yeelded up to any Romane</L>
<L>Were worse then sacriledge, though I should tcare</L>
<L>The hallowed sta'ues of <HI>Nunsidias</HI> gods</L>
<L>Downe from their altars, and convert their Temples</L>
<L>Into the loathsom'st uses of necessity.</L>
<L>Kings oathes are equall with decrees of Fate,</L>
<L>Those I have made I cannot violate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scip.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then I disclaime thee. Ther's not so much danger</L>
<L>In a knowne foe, as a suspected friend.</L>
<L>To preventan incendium it is best;</L>
<L>To quench a brand before it fire the rest. <STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Massa.</SPEAKER>
<L>He's angry, and I must not let it grow</L>
<L><PB REF="23"/>
To ripenesse of his hate. I am resolv'd</L>
<L>To be th'example of a constancy</L>
<L>Fame shall proclaime for wonder.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scene the fourth.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>To him</HI> Sophonisba.</STAGE>
<STAGE>She's already</STAGE>
<L>Come e're my wish could summon her. Her sight</L>
<L>Begins to shake the weake foundation</L>
<L>Of my resolves. Like stones shot from an engine</L>
<L>She ruin's with the battery of her eye</L>
<L>What my intents had built.</L>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why is my Lord</L>
<L>Thus clowdy? I expected entertainment</L>
<L>Of other difference; such as cheerefull love</L>
<L>Present's desire with from the enterchange</L>
<L>Of smiles and amorous glaunces.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Massa</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Sophonisba!</HI></L>
<L>I was new enter'd into meditations</L>
<L>Of death, and other wretchednesse, depend's</L>
<L>Vpon mortality.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is that the argument</L>
<L>Of your dejectednesse? it shew's too much</L>
<L>Of womans weakenesse. Man should have a spirit</L>
<L>Above the feare any consideration</L>
<L>Can worke within him. Death is but an entrance</L>
<L>To our eternity: and if our life</L>
<L>Merit a blessednesse hereafter, we</L>
<L>Should runne with joy to meete it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Massa.</SPEAKER>
<L>But if one</L>
<L>Possest of happinesse beyond the hope</L>
<L>Of any greater; that denies another</L>
<L>Can be in expectation (more then what</L>
<L>His soule enjoy's already) apprehended</L>
<L>A separation from it by the malice</L>
<L>Of death, or other accident, 'twould force him</L>
<L><PB REF="24"/>
Weep silently within, though shame restrain'd</L>
<L>His outward teares.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sopho.</SPEAKER>
<L>This circumstance would seeme</L>
<L>To prepare something that should have relation</L>
<L>Vnto your selfe or me. Perhaps the Consull</L>
<L>Hath urg'd that I should be deliver'd up</L>
<L>To <HI>Romes</HI> disposing. <HI>Massanissas</HI> vow</L>
<L>Made with religious ceremony cannot</L>
<L>If he respect the gods consent to it.</L>
<L>And rather then their tyranny should make me</L>
<L>Wretched a new, to my first earth returne me,</L>
<L>The worst remaines of <HI>Sophonisba.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Massa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dare shee</L>
<L>Dyethen to quit her feares?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sopho.</SPEAKER>
<L>And meete the instrument</L>
<L>With greater cherefalnesse, then fondest parents</L>
<L>Can shew at the returne of their decre child</L>
<L>From long captivity. This tender frame</L>
<L>Lodgeth a masculine and heroick spirit.</L>
<L>And if thy passionate love deny's thy selfe</L>
<L>To be the Actor in this benefit,</L>
<L>Give me thy sword; my owne right hand shall guide</L>
<L>The point unto my heart: I'le without trembling</L>
<L>Open a passage for the crimson drops;</L>
<L>And smile to see them diaper the pavement,</L>
<L>As if't were some conceited workemanship</L>
<L>Made by the lookers sancie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Massa.</SPEAKER>
<L>E're mine eyes</L>
<L>Should suffer such an object to offend</L>
<L>Their hitherto pleas'd sense, I would dissolve them</L>
<L>In their owne humour. No <HI>Sophonisba;</HI></L>
<L>This breath shall first wast into empty ayre,</L>
<L>And leave my naked bones i'th'hallow'd pile</L>
<L>E're I prove false to thee. Give me some wine:</L>
<L>I'le drinke a bridall health to <HI>Sophonisba,</HI></L>
<L>And mixe it with Nepenthe. Here's the juice</L>
<L>Will cause forgetfulnesse, and mock th'extremity</L>
<L><PB REF="24"/>
Of any adverse fortune. <STAGE>Messenger with wine.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sopho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sure 'tis poyson.</L>
<L>Will <HI>Massanissa</HI> leave me then unguarded</L>
<L>To <HI>Scipios</HI> violence? I have here no father</L>
<L>Nor uncle to defend me; not so much</L>
<L>As a poore teare by weeping to stirre up</L>
<L>A Romanes pity: I shall only dart</L>
<L>An anger from my burning eye, to shew</L>
<L>The Carthaginian spirit I was borne with,</L>
<L>Which not with standing will not quit this part</L>
<L>From a captivity: this <HI>Scipios</HI> rage</L>
<L>Will hurry in his triumph to be gaz'd at,</L>
<L>And scorn'd by the course rabble. Doe not then</L>
<L>By such a keeping of it breake thy vow;</L>
<L>For 'tis no lesse to me. I must still want</L>
<L>The benefice of such a constancy.</L>
<L>For though himselfe live not to yeeld me up</L>
<L>I am expos'd to't, and without least power</L>
<L>To make resistance. Let me then partake</L>
<L>That meanes of best security</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Massa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not to have</L>
<L>A Monument of lasting Adamant</L>
<L>Rais'd to my memory. No <HI>Sophonisba</HI></L>
<L>This is no potion to preserve a beauty</L>
<L>In it's first greene; or ripe it to a Summer;</L>
<L>Or prevent th' Autumme; or returne the Winter</L>
<L>Into a new Spring. This will pale the dye</L>
<L>Which thy cheek blusheth when it would cloth mo∣desty</L>
<L>In a rich scarlet: make that Ivorie brest</L>
<L>(Now Loves soft bed whereon he play's the wanton,</L>
<L>And ambusheth himselfe to catch the flames</L>
<L>He shoot's at others from thy eyes) as cold</L>
<L>As Scythian sands, bleak't with continuall freezing</L>
<L>Into a seeming christall. <HI>Scipio</HI> dar's not</L>
<L>Insult o're thee: thy face would check his malice</L>
<L>Into a silent admiration of it.</L>
<L>Or if he sin so much as to deject thee</L>
<L><PB REF="25"/>
With the least feare of ill, the gods themselves</L>
<L>Will leave their immortality to be</L>
<L>Each others rivals in thy love, and strive</L>
<L>Which should revenge thee best. This must not weaken</L>
<L>What is so powerfull.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sopho.</SPEAKER>
<L>If my Lord be then</L>
<L>Resolv'd to leave me widdow'd, being yet</L>
<L>Scarce warme in his embraces, let me mixe</L>
<L>A teare with his last drink, that he may carry</L>
<L>Something of <HI>Sophonisba</HI> with him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Massa</SPEAKER>
<L>That</L>
<L>Hath in't sufficient vertue to convert</L>
<L>All the Thessalian, Pontick, Phasian aconites</L>
<L>Into pretervatives, and turne this draught</L>
<L>Into an antidote: which yet is powerfull,</L>
<L>'Bove all that Art and Nature in conspiracy</L>
<L>Of mischiefe e're invented. We that are</L>
<L>Great, and yet subject to th'incertainty</L>
<L>Of Fortune, have this custome to prevent it.</L>
<L>We affect glory: and conclude no slate</L>
<L>That end's not in it selfe, is fortunate.</L>
<L>So— <STAGE>Offers to drinke.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let my Lord first give me leave to breath</L>
<L>An errant o're it; that when he is entred</L>
<L>Ely sium, throngs of Carthaginian Heroes</L>
<L>May bid him welcome, and informe themselves</L>
<L>From him of <HI>Sophonisba.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Massa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do't then quickly.</L>
<L>I'le beare it, and command the King of night</L>
<L>Resigne his ravish't Queene to be thy hand-maid.</L>
<L>Hell, I shall now be armed to meete thy horrours</L>
<L>With greater power then thine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soph.</SPEAKER>
<L>If there be Fate,</L>
<L>Why is't conceal'd? The revelation of t</L>
<L>Would make us strive to mock eternall providence,</L>
<L>Th'ingenious Artist that did forme this cup</L>
<L>Foresaw not such a use of't. Had he knowne</L>
<L><PB REF="25"/>
It should have minister'd death to a King,</L>
<L>His trembling hands could ne're have finish't it</L>
<L>With such exactnesse. What so e're decree</L>
<L>Is written in the Adamantine Tables</L>
<L>Of Destiny, we must subscribe to. Time</L>
<L>Though he keepe on his swift and silent pace,</L>
<L>Death's sure at first or last to win the race.</L>
<L>Pray keepe out <HI>Scipio:</HI> I have almost ended.</L>
<L>So— <STAGE>Drink's.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Massa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha! 'what hath <HI>Sophonisbas</HI> madnesse done'?</L>
<L>Oh <HI>Aesculapius</HI> if thy deity</L>
<L>Be not a feign'd one, then administer,</L>
<L>And shew it powerfull in restoring back</L>
<L>My <HI>Sophonisba</HI> to her former safety.</L>
<L><HI>Numidia</HI> shall pay worship to none other</L>
<L>But thee and <HI>Phoebus.</HI> Altars shall be rais'd</L>
<L>Made of Iberian gold, and flame with incense</L>
<L>Vntill <HI>Arabia's</HI> richest earth grow's barren</L>
<L>Of gummes and spices.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sopho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why doth <HI>Massanissa</HI></L>
<L>Invoke vaine aide? The gods are mercifull</L>
<L>In their denying it: and 'tis but justice</L>
<L>That I should dye; m'adulterous easinesse</L>
<L>Deserv'd it, that without the least resistance</L>
<L>Left my yet living husband to embrace</L>
<L>His enemy. But it had warrant from</L>
<L>The end, my Countries good, and the first love</L>
<L>I bare thee <HI>Massanissa.</HI> Now let <HI>Scipio</HI></L>
<L>Boast of his conquest; <HI>Sophonisba</HI> is</L>
<L>Her owne subverter. It begin's to worke</L>
<L>With a full strength: my blood would serve to heate</L>
<L>A Salamander, and convert his ice</L>
<L>Into a flame. Aetna's but painted fire</L>
<L>To that which burn's my marrow. Yet my lookes</L>
<L>Are cherefull and erected. Victory</L>
<L>Was never met more joyfully, then I</L>
<L>Embrace that death prevents my misery.</L>
<L><PB REF="26"/>
My weake earth totters underneath a weight</L>
<L>That sink's it downewards: my still living spirit</L>
<L>Rid's upon clowds to reach <HI>Ioves</HI> highest skie.</L>
<L>Who feare not death, but in the worst part dye. <STAGE>Dy's.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mass.</SPEAKER>
<L>She's dead. Sincke ye supporters of this fabrick</L>
<L>Into your deep foundations; make them graves</L>
<L>For your owne ruines, since there is not left</L>
<L>A weight worthy your bearing. Shee's not dead:</L>
<L>Only she hath translated her divinity</L>
<L>To it's owne blest abodes, and call's on me</L>
<L>To pay a mortals duty. Shallt have sacrifice,</L>
<L>And rich too. Kings out of devotion shall</L>
<L>Offer themselves in flames, and from their ashes</L>
<L>Rise glorious stars; whence learned curiosity</L>
<L>Deriving a new art, shall teach Astrologers</L>
<L>The vertues of an influence shall include</L>
<L>Secrets to make credulity astonish't</L>
<L>At their presages. I will be their president;</L>
<L>And make this earth, already consecrated</L>
<L>With <HI>Sophonisba's</HI> pretious feete, an altar.</L>
<L>Open thy crannies to receive my blood,</L>
<L>And from it's mixture spring a grove of Balsame.</L>
<L>Led by whose ravishing odour the new issue</L>
<L>Of every Phoenix shall neglect <HI>Panehaia,</HI></L>
<L>To bring her mothers spicy death bed hither,</L>
<L>That's likewise her owne cradle. But this action</L>
<L>Should have more state, and ceremony. No.</L>
<L>A King's the Priest; a King's the Sacrifice;</L>
<L>His owne sword whilst 'tis yet warme with his victory</L>
<L>Shall serve forth' axe, and so—Shall I but dye then?</L>
<L>I'le live to pay her more then th'expiration</L>
<L>Of a short breath, and dye to all delights,</L>
<L>But what I can derive from her faire memory:</L>
<L>Which shall be treasur'd here; and by it's virtue</L>
<L>Revive to kill me; every life it giv's</L>
<L>Causing another death.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="scene">
<PB REF="26"/>
<HEAD>Scene the fifth.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>To him</HI> Scipio, Lelius, <HI>Souldiers.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scip.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Lady dead!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Massa.</SPEAKER>
<L>To <HI>Scipios</HI> malice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scip.</SPEAKER>
<L>Could not <HI>Massanissa</HI></L>
<L>Acquit himselfe of one, but by committing</L>
<L>A greater folly! But I must not chide.</L>
<L>Most worthy <HI>Massanissa!</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Massa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Keep your flattery.</L>
<L>I have no <HI>Sophonisba.</HI> Touch her not:</L>
<L>None but my selfe shall beare her to the pile.</L>
<L>The sacrilegious hand besides attempt's it</L>
<L>I will cut off. Your triumph shall not twice</L>
<L>Kill <HI>Sophonisba.</HI> <STAGE>Exit with the body.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scip.</SPEAKER>
<L>With best care attend him</L>
<L>Vnto our Tent; least that his passion grow</L>
<L>Into a desperate frenzie, I must cure it</L>
<L>By counsell mixt with gifts. In that weake woman</L>
<L>Halfe <HI>Carthage</HI> strength is gone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leli.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our Spyes informe</L>
<L>That th'other halfe (which I conceive is <HI>Hannibal</HI>)</L>
<L>Intend's upon th'event of one great battell</L>
<L>To hazard all. His Camp's already pitch't</L>
<L>Neere <HI>Zama:</HI> whence a messenger is sent</L>
<L>That show's the Carthaginian much desit's</L>
<L>To have some conference with you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scip.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee'l dispose</L>
<L>Our Army thitherward. Me thinks I see</L>
<L>Victory crown'd already clap her wings</L>
<L>Over our heads. What a strange circulation</L>
<L>Is in times accidents? From victory</L>
<L>Peace is deriv'd; from peace security;</L>
<L>Thence lust; ambition: two maine grounds of jarres:</L>
<L>We fight for peace, and peace agen breed's warres. <STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="act">
<PB REF="27"/>
<HEAD>The argument of the fourth Act.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Hannibal <HI>being wholly overcome by</HI> Scipio <HI>at the bat∣tle of Zama, return's to</HI> Carthage: <HI>where being ill entertain'd by the Senate, he behav's himselfe roughly in the Senate house; and their intention of delivering him up to</HI> Scipio <HI>being discover'd, by the avde of his Faction, he escap's and flies. The Carthaginians sub∣mitting themselves are reprov'd by</HI> Scipio; <HI>who like∣wise imposeth upon them the strictest conditions, and by an example of his owne, reclaim's</HI> Massanissa <HI>from his passion.</HI></STAGE>
<STAGE>The Scene <HI>Carthage.</HI></STAGE>
<DIV3 TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scene the first.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Hanno, Gisgon, Bostar, <HI>a full Senate.</HI></STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Being sate, To them</HI> Nuntius.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hanno.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray' take no notice that we know th'event</L>
<L>Of the late battaile. I already have</L>
<L>Employ'd my Faction 'bout a peace, and <HI>Scipio</HI></L>
<L>Is not farre off. It shall not be the act</L>
<L>Of <HI>Hannibal</HI> to boast of. When we have</L>
<L>Betray'd him to the Romanes, the conditions</L>
<L>Besides are casie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gisg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mind the publick <HI>Bostar:</HI></L>
<L>D'you thinke it not concern's you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bost.</SPEAKER>
<L>I was my riches</L>
<L>Made me a Senatour: my wisedome never</L>
<L>Deserv'd the purple. Be you politick;</L>
<L>Let me preserve my state.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gisg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your wealth! 'tis granted</L>
<L>Rais'd you to this high place. Necessity</L>
<L><PB REF="27"/>
May corrupt justice in a Magistrate:</L>
<L>Which to prevent, at least our jealousies,</L>
<L>Our Carthaginian custome in election</L>
<L>Of Senatours, sometimes preferr's the rich</L>
<L>Before the best men. Take your seate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bost.</SPEAKER>
<L>To fill it:</L>
<L>Feare will not let me sleep.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hanno.</SPEAKER>
<L>Attend the Message:</L>
<L>It seem's from <HI>Hannibal.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bost.</SPEAKER>
<L>A worthy man.</L>
<L>He sent us home three bushels full of rings,</L>
<L>Of which I shar'd the most.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nunt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Before I speake,</L>
<L>Me thinks the ayre about me as the sound</L>
<L>Of my sad words doth passe through it, should thicken</L>
<L>Into a clowd; then melt at every periode</L>
<L>Into a weeping raine, till none be left</L>
<L>To give us breath for sighes. Our <HI>Hannibal</HI></L>
<L>Is vanquish't by the Romanes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bost.</SPEAKER>
<L>We shall then</L>
<L>Have no more wealth brought home, nor safely keepe</L>
<L>What we possesse already. Curse on chance</L>
<L>That mock's us thus. I'le never make her statue</L>
<L>Of gold hereafter, and by consequent</L>
<L>Ne're worship her: I have but cold devotion</L>
<L>Towards a wooden goddesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hanno.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis not fit</L>
<L>Evils remedilesse should be lamented.</L>
<L>From a misfortune something may arise</L>
<L>To prevent greater, if it be apply'd</L>
<L>With an exact consideration</L>
<L>O'all occurents that may make it usefull.</L>
<L>Relate it then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nun.</SPEAKER>
<L>Before the battaile joyn'd</L>
<L>The worlds two Captaines (for besides them none</L>
<L>Merit's the name in equall competition)</L>
<L>Mett to have conference: where for a space</L>
<L><PB REF="28"/>
They stood astonish't at each others presence:</L>
<L>And like two Comets tilting in the ayre</L>
<L>'Gainst one another, shot prodigious flames</L>
<L>From eithers eyes; and with a counterchange</L>
<L>Of fierce and angry lookes seem'd to begin</L>
<L>An eagre fight: 'till <HI>Hannibal</HI> broke silence,</L>
<L>And mov'd a peace: Which <HI>Scipio</HI> (or suspecting it</L>
<L>To be but wonted policy, or confident</L>
<L>Both of his owne strength and successe) refus'd.</L>
<L>Then like two clowds swoln big with a mights tempest,</L>
<L>And hurryed forward by contrary winds,</L>
<L>Iusling each other, 'till their ribbes being broken</L>
<L>The sulphurous issue slie's through the black ayre;</L>
<L>An inundation following that would fright</L>
<L>Natures Archeus from his quiet center;</L>
<L>To seeke an Aetna or Vesaevus out</L>
<L>Where he might drie himselfe: so met the Armies.</L>
<L>And with a shout, that out-noys'd thunder, charg'd</L>
<L>Each other bravely; at their first encounter</L>
<L>Mixing their bloods in streames, that every way</L>
<L>Flow'd like a tide. As yet the peacefull goddesse</L>
<L>Inclin'd to neither part, 'till <HI>Massanissa</HI></L>
<L>Brought up his right wing of Numidian horsemen,</L>
<L>And broke th'array; enforcing our first battle</L>
<L>Back to our second; when we were compel'd</L>
<L>To fight against our owne, least their retiring</L>
<L>Might put us out of order; 'till betwixt us</L>
<L>Dead bodies made a Bulwarke; so that neither</L>
<L>We nor the Romanes but by trampling on</L>
<L>Our fellowes carcasses could strike a blow</L>
<L>Of any use. The Romane Legions now</L>
<L>O're-prest us with their number, and both wings</L>
<L>Of horsemen wheel'd about t'assault our reere.</L>
<L>We then were compast; yet like angry Lyons</L>
<L>Whom the toyle hamper's, labour'd for our freedome;</L>
<L>But few escap't: five hundred only live</L>
<L>Of forty thousand, which to <HI>Adrumentum</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="28"/>
Are fled with <HI>Hannibal:</HI> whence he intend's</L>
<L>To visit <HI>Carthage</HI> suddainely.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hanno.</SPEAKER>
<L>His welcome</L>
<L>If he fore-knew't would give him small encouragement.</L>
<L>Th'incertainty of warre! Did <HI>Hannibal</HI></L>
<L>Solicite peace? l'le seeme t'oppose it then,</L>
<L>Though it intend a good. The inborne malice</L>
<L>Bet wixt our families will not permit me</L>
<L>Allow his acts or counsell. By his greatnesse</L>
<L>Mine is eclips'd: and though this overthrow</L>
<L>May make him lesse in popular opinion,</L>
<L>His Faction yet is strong.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gisg.</SPEAKER>
<L>What meane you <HI>Bostar!</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bost.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'm dead; that horrible relation kill'd me</L>
<L>In'ere shall see addition to my heape,</L>
<L>Now <HI>Hannibal</HI> is conquer'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hanno.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have stor'd</L>
<L>Enough wealth to maintaine another Army</L>
<L>That may bring home increase. Pray'let us use</L>
<L>Your state, wee'l spare your wisedome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bost.</SPEAKER>
<L>How's that <HI>Hanno!</HI></L>
<L>My state, and spare my wisedome. I'm a Senatour,</L>
<L>And weare my gowne as formally as you:</L>
<L>Can nodde and spet at th'end of every sentence,</L>
<L>And number with my owne Arithmetick</L>
<L>More somes of coyne then thy whole family.</L>
<L>Part with my wealth l I'le rather dye, and purchase</L>
<L>Hell with't, if <HI>Pluto</HI> would but sell his Kingdome.</L>
<L>Yet sure it cannot be so rich as I am.</L>
<L>The judges there are just; bribes cannot buy</L>
<L>A partiall sentence,</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scene the Second.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>To them</HI> Hannibal, <HI>some Souldiers.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha! me thinks they should</L>
<L>Salute me, though I bring not victory.</L>
<L><PB REF="29"/>
When I presented them with wealth, their flatteries</L>
<L>Were greater then became them. Am I lesse</L>
<L>In merit now, then when successe attended</L>
<L>My actions! glew'd unto their seates, and <HI>Hannibal</HI></L>
<L>Enter'd. Grave fathers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hanno.</SPEAKER>
<L>On sir: we are patient</L>
<L>To heare you speake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>But patient! he that stand's</L>
<L>Accus'd may challenge that, or justly taxe yee</L>
<L>Of more then tyranny.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hanno.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you so confident</L>
<L>You dare affront your Iudges?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha! my Iudges.</L>
<L>What envy though 'twere still'd from the black galls</L>
<L>Ofleane <HI>Erinnis</HI> Adders, can so blemish</L>
<L>My life or same, that from the least suspect</L>
<L>I might incurre a sentence! Wa'st for this</L>
<L>I have through blood and sweat made <HI>Carthage</HI> great</L>
<L>As <HI>Rome</HI> her selfe; and had not politick dotage</L>
<L>Infected with your private avarice</L>
<L>(That would not spare me what my selfe bestow'd</L>
<L>Vpon your case) prevented it by calling</L>
<L>Me and my Army home, I had e're this</L>
<L>Made <HI>Rome</HI> your tributary; and am I</L>
<L>Return'd now to be judge, because I have</L>
<L>After so many victories lost one battle!</L>
<L>The monstrous bi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>th of your ingratitude</L>
<L>Were able to fright manhood from posterity,</L>
<L>And check all undertakings.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hanno.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whence did you</L>
<L>Receive commission to move peace with <HI>Scipio?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>From mine owne judgement that foresaw the danger</L>
<L>My power could not prevent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hanno.</SPEAKER>
<L>It seem's you were</L>
<L>Declm'd to coward.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ther's no priviledge <STAGE>Pulls him downe.</STAGE></L>
<L>Vnder your gowne for that. Learne to know man;</L>
<L><PB REF="29"/>
Then be his judge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray heaven he hurt not me.</L>
<L>Most valiant <HI>Hanniball.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hate your slattery,</L>
<L>Tis mixt with scorne; and I will rather trample</L>
<L>Vpon your purple.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nunt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good my Lord forbeare</L>
<L>Your violence. Consider but their persons</L>
<L>And dignities.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>Should <HI>Jove</HI> himselfe provoke me</L>
<L>With a disgrace like this, l'de challenge him</L>
<L>To meet upon a cloud ram'd full of thunder:</L>
<L>And dart it at him, 'till with flames I had</L>
<L>Consum'd the brasse supporters of his heaven;</L>
<L>Tumbling him downe with all his petty gods</L>
<L>Vnto their first mortality.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nunt.</SPEAKER>
<L>The custome</L>
<L>Of <HI>Carthage</HI> government commands respect</L>
<L>Vnto their difference.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let the respect</L>
<L>Belikewise taught them that belongs to me.</L>
<L>And if my labour hath maintain'd their ease.</L>
<L>In which they have both studied and establish't</L>
<L>Civill formalities, my rugged life</L>
<L>Did never practise, it may well excuse</L>
<L>A greater errour. Who is my accuser?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hanno.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>My selfe! my selfe will be my judge then:</L>
<L>And maketh'abus'd seate honour'd for a justice,</L>
<L>Which your corrupted soules would never suffer</L>
<L>Your power to execute. Looke Carthaginians;</L>
<L>And if your reasons eyes can see the errours</L>
<L>Your blinded envie led it to, with blushes</L>
<L>Guide them to reformation. I that tooke</L>
<L>An oath at nine yeares old before the Altar,</L>
<L>When it was smoking with the horrid sacrifice</L>
<L>Of immolated men, to be <HI>Romes</HI> enemy,</L>
<L><PB REF="30"/>
And perfect what my Father had begun;</L>
<L>I that transferr'd the wealth of <HI>Spaine</HI> to <HI>Carthage,</HI></L>
<L>And thorow the frozen Alpes melted my way</L>
<L>Into the fertile plaines of <HI>Italy;</HI></L>
<L>That waded with my army thorow the fennes</L>
<L>Of gloomy <HI>Arnus,</HI> in whose fogges I lost</L>
<L>One of my bodies comfortable lights;</L>
<L>I that o'rethrew sixe Consuls, and at <HI>Cannas</HI></L>
<L>In one sight kill'd a hundred Romane Senators,</L>
<L>And thence presented <HI>Carthage</HI> with a prey</L>
<L>That might out-vye an Indian treasury</L>
<L>Cram'd with the choycest wealth; I that abroad</L>
<L>Whilst here you bath'd in pleasures made my body</L>
<L>Proose 'gainst a tempest, and endur'd the rage</L>
<L>Of more prodigious stormes then ever frighted</L>
<L>Mortals into religion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hanno.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet at <HI>Capua</HI></L>
<L>The faire Salapian <HI>Omphale</HI> could teach</L>
<L>Our Carthaginian <HI>Hercules</HI> to spin,</L>
<L>And mind his distaffe; else she would not smile</L>
<L>Vpon him for his worke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy malice <HI>Hanno</HI></L>
<L>Like to the broken some a rock beats back</L>
<L>Vpon the angry maine, fowl's thine owne bosome.</L>
<L>I am above it; and in spight of thee</L>
<L>Or all the battery of thy calumnies,</L>
<L>Will stand like a <HI>Colossus</HI> to be gaz'd at</L>
<L>By all beneath me, when the scorne of men</L>
<L>Shall lash thy envie with the whips of Satyres:</L>
<L>Who vainely dost attempt to ruine that</L>
<L>Is built for fame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hanno.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay you may keepe your seate,</L>
<L>It well becomes you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>It becomes you better,</L>
<L>When your grave nod and formall hem strik's terrour</L>
<L>Through the affrighted malefactors heart;</L>
<L>Who for some slight offence expects his judgement,</L>
<L><PB REF="30"/>
No lesse than banishment, or confiscation</L>
<L>Of all his substance; which is shar'd amongst you,</L>
<L>The publike use neglected. But in vaine</L>
<L>I taxe your vices, when your soules are fullyed</L>
<L>With an ingratitude to me, that makes</L>
<L>All others white as innocence compar'd</L>
<L>With that black monster. <HI>Carthage</HI> I disclaime thee,</L>
<L>And rather then imploy my power agen</L>
<L>To raise thy head 'bove others, in thy ruines</L>
<L>Ile hide mine owne. And but for reverence</L>
<L>I beare the ashes of mine ancestors,</L>
<L>I would my selfe plough furrowes in thy wombe,</L>
<L>And sow my faction onely for th'increase</L>
<L>Of mine owne greatnesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hanno.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray observe it Fathers.</L>
<L>He doth affect the Monarchie; he would</L>
<L>Alter our government.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are deceiv'd.</L>
<L>Y'are weake enough already; there's no need</L>
<L>Of a sedition to subvert your state.</L>
<L>Can yee resist the Romanes, and make peace</L>
<L>Vpon your owne conditions?</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scene the third.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>To them</HI> Himulco <HI>hastily.</HI></STAGE>
<STAGE>What's the meaning?</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Him.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are betray'd my Lord; your safety needs</L>
<L>A sudden resolution. <HI>Scipio's</HI> enter'd</L>
<L>The Gates of <HI>Carthage.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh inhumane trechery!</L>
<L>But for preventing justice that will fall</L>
<L>Heavie upon you by some other instrument,</L>
<L>'Twere piety to wash corruption</L>
<L>From this abus'd place with your bloods; whose staines</L>
<L>Would yet infect the pavement, and remaine</L>
<L>Like blushes in the marble to betray</L>
<L><PB REF="31"/>
The guilt yee dy'd for. When the Romanes practise</L>
<L>Their tyranny upon you, wish in vaine</L>
<L>Yee had an <HI>Hannibal.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Him.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your danger will not</L>
<L>Allow your passion vent. Pray 'fligh my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>Into some desart to converse with beasts;</L>
<L>Th'have gratefull soules. <HI>Carthage</HI> me thinkes an earthquake</L>
<L>Should palsey thy old joynts, &amp; shrink thy head</L>
<L>Into thy shoulders: or thy <HI>Genius</HI> wrap thee</L>
<L>In a perpetuall cloud to hide the shame</L>
<L>Of this base act. Revenge, Ile court thee through</L>
<L>The ruine of mine owne. <HI>Carthage</HI> shall see</L>
<L>Not mine from her, her greatnesse grew from me.</L>
<L>All those that love me follow. <STAGE>Exeunt, Senators remayning.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hanno.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would we had</L>
<L>Ensnar'd him better: but his faction wanting</L>
<L>A head, 'tis strengthlesse. Let a cryer publish</L>
<L>The sentence of his banishment, that <HI>Scipio</HI></L>
<L>May take it for our act. We must comply</L>
<L>With all occasions that may make our peace</L>
<L>A usefull good, no voluntary bondage.</L>
<L>We must receive the Romanes with a shew</L>
<L>Of lesse feare, then the straites of our necessity</L>
<L>Might excuse manhood for.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scene the fourth.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>To them</HI> Scipio, Massanissa, Lelius, <HI>some Souldiers.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scip.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now Carthaginians,</L>
<L>Although I am a conquerour, successe</L>
<L>Swelis me no higher to preferre my selfe</L>
<L>Above what judgement warrants. I have strove</L>
<L>With all opposing reasons to forget</L>
<L>Your often breach of faith: which you are tax't with</L>
<L>By all men for a vice that th'ayre you breath</L>
<L>Infects you with, as if the places nature</L>
<L>Enforc't it from necessity. But custome</L>
<L><PB REF="31"/>
Must be concluded, is the most efficient</L>
<L>To cause that barbarous neglect of piety,</L>
<L>Which should be mans sole object. I am strengthned</L>
<L>Sufficiently 'gainst feare; since I can easily</L>
<L>Compell you to subjection. But preferring</L>
<L>A mild command before imperious rigour,</L>
<L>Declare your selves, and you shall finde that we</L>
<L>Practise no cruelty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hanno.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most worthy Romane</L>
<L>We might excuse the generall, and conferre</L>
<L>The guilt upon some private few, who led</L>
<L>By an ambition made this warre without</L>
<L>Consent from us. Some we have justly punisht;</L>
<L>And him, by whom (as by the first great mover)</L>
<L>The rest were hurried forward, we have banisht,</L>
<L>To take from <HI>Rome</HI> all cause of after-jealousie.</L>
<L>His faction did prevent it, else we had</L>
<L>Yeelded him up to <HI>Scipio.</HI> Peace is now</L>
<L>The thing we crave, and the conditions</L>
<L>No stricter then the Carthaginians</L>
<L>Would have propos'd, had they beene conquerours,</L>
<L>And <HI>Scipio</HI> su'd to them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scip.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can there be faith</L>
<L>In those that would betray their owne! and such a one</L>
<L>As made the end of all his actions</L>
<L>Your greatnesse first, and when that fail'd your safety?</L>
<L>A man that more than figur'd <HI>Mars,</HI> and merited</L>
<L>A deifying by your gratitude.</L>
<L>Blush at it fame, and with thy hundred tongues</L>
<L>Till all are hoarse proclaime it. The conditions</L>
<L>Propos'd shall stand, if but to punish this,</L>
<L>This monstrous act. Nature me thinks should throw yee</L>
<L>From her warme bosome with an angry motion</L>
<L>Of all th'earths sinewes, and not suffer yee</L>
<L>To suck her milke; but dry her fruitfull wombe</L>
<L>Into a barrennesse, before such monsters</L>
<L>Should be againe produc't. As you performe</L>
<L><PB REF="32"/>
The strictest clause, and what afflicts yee most,</L>
<L>Call it not satisfaction for our injuries,</L>
<L>But punishment for your ingratitude</L>
<L>To <HI>Hannibal.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hanno.</SPEAKER>
<L>That will take from my suffering.</L>
<L>When those we hate in misery beare a part,</L>
<L>Envie growes fat by eating her owne heart. <STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scip.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Lelius</HI> attend the Carthaginian Senators;</L>
<L>Survey the City, and see execution <STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
<L>Of all the league includ's. Doth <HI>Scipio</HI> triumph,</L>
<L>And <HI>Massanissa</HI> hang the head! One article</L>
<L>Is that they shall restore to <HI>Massanissa</HI></L>
<L>All that they have depriv'd him of.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Massa.</SPEAKER>
<L>They cannot</L>
<L>Restore my <HI>Sophonisba.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scip.</SPEAKER>
<L>Still that passion!</L>
<L>I thought her memory had beene wash't away</L>
<L>With the large streames of blood so lately flow'd</L>
<L>From his victorious sword. Come <HI>Massanissa</HI></L>
<L>You shall enjoy a Romane Lady; one</L>
<L>That shall out-vye the glory of a sunne</L>
<L>Thron'd in his cleerest skie, and make his light</L>
<L>Appeare but as a shadow to her beauty,</L>
<L>One that shall comprehend within her selfe</L>
<L>All that was ever faign'd of other women,</L>
<L>And make their fables probable.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Massa.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Rome</HI> hath not</L>
<L>Another <HI>Sophonisba.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scip.</SPEAKER>
<L>That the wealth</L>
<L>Of <HI>Romes</HI> best province might but ransome home</L>
<L>His lost command o're passions.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="scene">
<PB REF="32"/>
<HEAD>Scene the fift.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>To them</HI> Lelius, Lucius, <HI>a young Lady.</HI></STAGE>
<STAGE>Who's this Lady?</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leli.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Spanish captive.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scip.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did ever innocence</L>
<L>Looke sweeter as if she were joy'd to make</L>
<L>This little frame her mansion. Why d'ee weepe?</L>
<L>They shall not hurt you pretty one.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lad.</SPEAKER>
<L>They say</L>
<L>They'l carry me to <HI>Rome.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scip.</SPEAKER>
<L>Suppose they doe;</L>
<L>Romanes are full of gentlenesse, and mildly</L>
<L>Will entertaine you; where you shall be taught</L>
<L>Civility of manners. Education</L>
<L>Clothing your minde in ornaments of vertue</L>
<L>Fitting your expectation, and your beauty</L>
<L>Rip't with mature age, Romane Knights shall court it.</L>
<L>Perhaps my selfe would take you to my bed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lad.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeed you should not. You are a rough souldier;</L>
<L>Your lookes would fright me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scip.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can you then deny</L>
<L>To cherish such a hope? You should enjoy</L>
<L>Delights above your wish. Your house should be</L>
<L>A court of pleasure. Spring should alwaies dwell</L>
<L>Within your gardens, as it Tempe were</L>
<L>Translated thither. Virgins should attend you</L>
<L>Faire as the morning, when she ushers in</L>
<L>The day with blushes. Your bathes should be the dew</L>
<L>Gather'd from Roses, and your garments soft</L>
<L>As the curl'd ayre, by mild Etesian windes</L>
<L>Made temperate, when the Sunne rides on his Lion</L>
<L>To hunt heavens Dog up. You should sleepe on downe</L>
<L>Driven from Swannes white necks; be visited</L>
<L>By Matrons; usher'd to solemnities;</L>
<L>And at the publike showes out-shine the glory</L>
<L><PB REF="33"/>
Of daylight with the lustre of those jemmes</L>
<L>You should be deckt in and a conquerour when</L>
<L>His head's wrapt in triumphant Lawrell, couch it</L>
<L>Vpon your lap.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Massa.</SPEAKER>
<L>He's taken. Mans weake judgement,</L>
<L>That calls it vice in others, which himselfe</L>
<L>Is equally inclin'd to.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lad.</SPEAKER>
<L>I nere heard</L>
<L>Of such fine things before.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scip.</SPEAKER>
<L>The barren soyle</L>
<L>That bred you is in fault. I must confesse</L>
<L>Nature hath in your yet imperfect beauty</L>
<L>Shew'd wonders to the world: you areth'epitome</L>
<L>Of her most curious labours; and if fortune</L>
<L>Should in so faire a booke blurre any lest</L>
<L>Exact drawne line, her deity were cruell.</L>
<L>Your owne's a barbarous country, where civility</L>
<L>Hath scarce a name. You cannot there expect</L>
<L>A value of your selfe, above the worship</L>
<L>Their eyes will give you, when they rudely gaze</L>
<L>Vpon your forme, and by the sense distinguish</L>
<L>The outward workmanship. We teach our soules</L>
<L>A glorious conversation with those vertues</L>
<L>That deck the inside of a beauteous frame,</L>
<L>And vary pleasures, honours, earths delights</L>
<L>To th'imitation of that infinite</L>
<L>And never dying part.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lad.</SPEAKER>
<L>You <HI>Lucius</HI></L>
<L>Did never court me thus. You'd onely tell me</L>
<L>That I should be a Queene, when your old Father</L>
<L>Went to the lower Kingdome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scip.</SPEAKER>
<L>What is <HI>Lucius?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luci.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Prince amongst the Celtiberians.</L>
<L>This Lady Nobly borne to me betroth'd,</L>
<L>If <HI>Scipio</HI> will be mercifull, l'de ransome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scip.</SPEAKER>
<L>You love her then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luci.</SPEAKER>
<L>Above my selfe: without her</L>
<L><PB REF="33"/>
My being is not perfect.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scip.</SPEAKER>
<L>Blest occasion.</L>
<L>Now <HI>Massanissa</HI> if example may</L>
<L>Rectifie errors in thee, make my act</L>
<L>An imitable president. Young Prince</L>
<L>Receive her from my hands; withall the summe</L>
<L>Intended for her ransome as a dowry.</L>
<L>Love <HI>Rome</HI> and <HI>Scipio.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luci.</SPEAKER>
<L>Noblenesse above</L>
<L>The reach of praise. How shall I shew my gratitude?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lad.</SPEAKER>
<L>When he hath made me Queen, He bid you wel∣come</L>
<L>To <HI>Lucius</HI> Court.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luci.</SPEAKER>
<L>And <HI>Lucius</HI> when growne man</L>
<L>Will bring you Souldiers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Massa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Seem'd he not to love her?</L>
<L>And yet without least pause he gave her back</L>
<L>Being possest. I am o'recome; I see</L>
<L>Passion's the noble soules worst enemy</L>
<L>I'm all for action. <STAGE>Musick.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scip.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Massanissa</HI> is</L>
<L>Become himselfe agen. Wherefore this musick?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lels.</SPEAKER>
<L>To gratulate your victory, and the peace</L>
<L>That gives them rest, the Souldiers have prepar'd</L>
<L>A slight solemnity: The Carthaginians</L>
<L>Mixe with the Romanes, though their heavie hearts</L>
<L>To part with so much treasure scarce admits it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scip.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis seasonable: there is cause to joy,</L>
<L>Since <HI>Massanissa's</HI> new wed to my bosome,</L>
<L>And this young Ladies nuptials.</L>
<PB REF="34"/>
<STAGE>The Souldiers led in by their Captaines, distinguisht severally by their Armes and Ensignes, to the Musick of the following, put themselves into a figure like a battalia.</STAGE>
<STAGE>The Song.</STAGE>
<L><HI>On bravely, on; the foe is met;</HI></L>
<L><HI>The Souldiers ranck't, the battaile set.</HI></L>
<L><HI>Make the earth tremble, and the skies</HI></L>
<L><HI>Redouble ecchoes from your cryes.</HI></L>
<L><HI>Bloud puts a scarlet mantle on</HI></L>
<L><HI>The late greene plaine: they 'l stie anon.</HI></L>
<STAGE>Chorus.</STAGE>
<L><HI>Then follow; but your orders keepe;</HI></L>
<L><HI>Take prisoners; set their ransomes deepe.</HI></L>
<L><HI>Retreat. For same and the delight</HI></L>
<L><HI>That peace brings onely Souldiers fight.</HI></L>
<STAGE>The dance expressing a fight.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Thankes to all.</STAGE>
<L>So you proportion pleasures, we give way to't.</L>
<L>Is <HI>Lelius</HI> yet inform'd of <HI>Hannibal?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leli.</SPEAKER>
<L>That he is fled unto <HI>Antiochus,</HI></L>
<L>Or else to <HI>Prusias</HI> of <HI>Bythinia.</HI></L>
<L>His ends are doubtfull.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scip.</SPEAKER>
<L>If his discontent</L>
<L>Should anew whet his envie to attempt</L>
<L>Their aydes, 'twould much disturb the Asian provinces.</L>
<L>Wee'l follow to prevent it. <HI>Lelius</HI> you</L>
<L>Shall carry our successe unto the Senate,</L>
<L>And with it <HI>Syphax,</HI> and the <HI>Carthage</HI> pledges.</L>
<L>Come my soules halfe, wee'l hunt this <HI>Affrick</HI> Lion</L>
<L>Into a stronger toyle. Fame shall waite on us</L>
<L>Till we have loaded her, and that shee see</L>
<L>Our triumph finisht in his tragedy. <STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="act">
<PB REF="34"/>
<HEAD>The argument of the last Act.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Hannibal <HI>being fled to</HI> Prusias <HI>King of</HI> Bythinia, <HI>re∣ceives his promise for his safety. The Romane Legates being arrived, and</HI> Hannibal <HI>perceiving</HI> Scipio <HI>and</HI> Flaminius <HI>(the Sonne of</HI> Flaminius <HI>whom hee had formerly slaine) to be amongst them, and understanding the house to be encompassed by armed men, suspect∣ing himselfe to be betray'd, takes poison, (which he al∣wayes carryed about him in his ring) Of which he dyes; and</HI> Scipio <HI>to prevent the like ingratitude from his Romanes, and out of a naturall addiction he alwayes had to learning (it being said of him, that</HI> Paediam Cyri de manu non ponebat; <HI>and</HI> nonnunquam incepto praelio cum philosophis disputabat) <HI>retires himselfe to his Country</HI> Villa; <HI>taking upon him as it were a voluntary banishment.</HI></STAGE>
<STAGE>The Scene <HI>Bythinia.</HI></STAGE>
<DIV3 TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scene the first.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Prusias, Hanniball, Himulco, <HI>Attendants.]</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'are welcome, though your fortun's ebb'd. The memory</L>
<L>Of what you have bin should cōmand respect</L>
<L>From good men to you. Vertue is not lessen'd</L>
<L>By want of a successe; that's but a glosse</L>
<L>Fortune sets on her: Misery doth make</L>
<L>Her inside glorious sometimes, when desertlesse,</L>
<L>And bastard actions as the heires of chance</L>
<L>Shine in their superficies: but being searcht</L>
<L><PB REF="35"/>
Are found like bladders, swolne with an enforcement</L>
<L>Of wind into them: which the least necessity</L>
<L>Or adverse fortune pricking, they dilate</L>
<L>Th'included ayre, and shrinke into their first</L>
<L>Narrow dimensions: When true vertue beares</L>
<L>Her owners head above afflictions waves,</L>
<L>And steeres him into harbour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are noble,</L>
<L>And like a King with judgement value me.</L>
<L>My mind was ne're subjected: I have knowne</L>
<L>So much of both, that neither of the pastimes</L>
<L>Fortune delights her selfe with, can incline me</L>
<L>To height above a moderate, nor decline me</L>
<L>Below my selfe. Prosperity, adversity;</L>
<L>Both make one even scale, and weight being added</L>
<L>To either, shews the difference. Hee's not man</L>
<L>Will be dejected or exalted. Every one</L>
<L>Should temper the condition of his state,</L>
<L>Such as the present makes it, with the feare</L>
<L>Or hope of after change: and when hee labour's</L>
<L>In the extremity of one, or slowes</L>
<L>I'th swelling height of th'other, still his mind</L>
<L>Should be the same. Chance varies every way;</L>
<L>But vertues course is constant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prus.</SPEAKER>
<L>You expresse</L>
<L>A noble resolution, and your soule</L>
<L>Shows rich and glorious even through the clouds</L>
<L>Of your misfortune. There's a readinesse,</L>
<L>And a propens<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> desire in me to ayde you.</L>
<L>But circumstance must make it probable</L>
<L>Whether the causes justnesse may command</L>
<L>Th'attendence of successe. For an attempt</L>
<L>That's warranted by justice, cannot want</L>
<L>A prosperous end.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>If to desend my Country.</L>
<L>Or to compell encroaching <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></L>
<L>To satisfaction, such as would deprive us</L>
<L><PB REF="35"/>
Of th'earth that nature in her legacy</L>
<L>Made our proportion be a justice, I</L>
<L>Did never injury; for these were onely</L>
<L>The motives to my actions. Fame I know</L>
<L>Could not be silent, but shee must informe</L>
<L>Even the remotest dwellers, how proud <HI>Rome</HI></L>
<L>(Whose infant greatnesse by ambition nurst</L>
<L>Is now in growing, and will spread it selfe</L>
<L>If a prevention stay it not, beyond</L>
<L>All limits of the yet knowne world) insults</L>
<L>Over her neighbouring Provinces. From <HI>Carthage</HI></L>
<L>She hath enfore't <HI>Sicilia</HI> (the worlds granary)</L>
<L>And other Hands: and her Generall</L>
<L>Swolne with his fortune, hath attempted farther</L>
<L>To overslow all <HI>Affrick.</HI> You may likewise</L>
<L>Expect he will encroach upon your <HI>Asia;</HI></L>
<L><HI>Antiochus</HI> being already vanquisht,</L>
<L>And sled to <HI>Ephesus.</HI> If nothing else,</L>
<L>Your safety should invite you to take armes,</L>
<L>Though but defensive. States that never knew</L>
<L>A change but in their growth, which a long peace</L>
<L>Hath brought unto perfection, are like steele;</L>
<L>Which being neglected will consume it selfe</L>
<L>With its ownerust. So doth security</L>
<L>Eate through he hearts of states whilst they are sleeping</L>
<L>And lull'd in her false quiet. Prusias therefore</L>
<L>Should dwell no longer in so great a danger.</L>
<L>If hee'l not be a Souldier, let him arme</L>
<L>His people; <HI>Hannibal</HI> will be their Captaine,</L>
<L>And lead them unto actions that shall take</L>
<L>Fam. with the wonder, 'till I have made <HI>Rome</HI></L>
<L>(Who like th'earths issue heapes up hills on hills,</L>
<L>To raise her proud head) nothing. My right hand</L>
<L><HI>Jove</HI>-like is arm'd with thunder, which shall sligh</L>
<L>Wing'd with prodigious slames of just revenge</L>
<L>To punish her impiety.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prus.</SPEAKER>
<L>I could gladly</L>
<L><PB REF="36"/>
Cherish your resolutions, being grounded</L>
<L>On justice: but t'engage my selfe or people</L>
<L>In an uncertaine warre, before provok't</L>
<L>By enemies, were rashnesse that excuse</L>
<L>Could no way glosse to make it show an act</L>
<L>Worthy a man, much lesse a King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>You value</L>
<L>Those scruples more than a full weight of honour.</L>
<L>Heaven gave the difference to you but to be</L>
<L>The sigure of that power, that will exact</L>
<L>A just account of a Kings greater actions,</L>
<L>Then what inferiours owe to their creation.</L>
<L>Th'essentiall part of your eternity</L>
<L>Depends upon that point: and can you more</L>
<L>Expresse your selfe heavens minister, then when</L>
<L>You doe the things agree with't?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prus.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Rome</HI> comply's</L>
<L>With us for peace. The violation</L>
<L>Of a religious oath, superiour justice</L>
<L>Cannot but punish: else we might be bold</L>
<L>To call the worship of the gods no more</L>
<L>Than th'issue of credulity, produc't</L>
<L>To fright us with a name that had no power</L>
<L>But what our feares allow'd it. <HI>Rome</HI> is yet</L>
<L>Our friend; and 'till she fall from honour, we</L>
<L>Must hold her deare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>In that consists your danger.</L>
<L>Shee's mask't in policy, and like a Statesman</L>
<L>Without religion, steeres her course by showes</L>
<L>And meere appearance to what ever ends</L>
<L>Amoition points her. Be not then too rash.</L>
<L>Make not the greatnesse which is yet your owne</L>
<L>Derivative from her. 'T will leave your name</L>
<L>A staine in times records, and blot the tables</L>
<L>That should preserve it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Noble <HI>Hannibal</HI></L>
<L>Be safe with us and confident. I expect</L>
<L><PB REF="36"/>
The Romane Legates; and if mediation</L>
<L>Or any practice which I can with honour</L>
<L>Assay to reconcile yee, may be usefull.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>To reconcile us! Time shall first runne back</L>
<L>To his beginning, and the world returne</L>
<L>To its first <HI>Chaos</HI> e're I will admit</L>
<L>Of such a word. L'et those that fawne upon</L>
<L>The smiles of peace and softnesse to delight</L>
<L>Their wanton appetites, practise their low</L>
<L>Effeminate soules in feares and passions.</L>
<L>Each thought of mine shall be a numerous Army</L>
<L>To lead' gainst <HI>Rome:</HI> in my imagination</L>
<L>I will fight with her still, though I want Souldiers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nobly resolv'd.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scene the Second.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>To them</HI> Scipio, Massanissa, Flaminius, <HI>other Romane Legates.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha! <HI>Scipio</HI> and <HI>Flaminius</HI></L>
<L>Amongst the Romane Legates! there's some treachery.</L>
<L>Informe thy selfe <HI>Himulco.</HI> His pursuing <STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
<L>My course, imports no good, and my sad soule</L>
<L>Labours with a prophetick apprehension</L>
<L>Of something he intends. Beready thou,</L>
<L>Thou my last refuge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sudden clouds me thinkes</L>
<L>Creepe o're your eyes. Though you be enemies,</L>
<L>Peace warrants gentle greeting. Shee is emblem'd</L>
<L>In Doves that have no gall. Y'are here my guests,</L>
<L>And shall partake a courtly entertainment</L>
<L>Worthy such persons.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scip.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Hannibal</HI> I know</L>
<L>Hath put of the rough habit which his mind</L>
<L>Was lately wrapt in: and since chance hath made him</L>
<L>The subject of my conquest, in the peace</L>
<L><HI>Rome</HI> hath allow'd his Country (the conditions</L>
<L><PB REF="37"/>
Being stricktly kept) all past contentions</L>
<L>Must lose their memory, and after strites</L>
<L>Be stisled in their first birth by prevention.</L>
<L>I must acknowledge my ambition</L>
<L>Bore my thoughts higher than my Countries good,</L>
<L>Or her enlargement onely. Had my fortune</L>
<L>Captiv'd the person of great <HI>Hannibal.</HI></L>
<L>My triumph should out-vye all the rich pompes</L>
<L>That ever made <HI>Rome</HI> shine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>That person yet</L>
<L>Is free, and capable of new designes,</L>
<L>To make himselfe full owner of a glory</L>
<L>'Bove <HI>Scipio's</HI> conquest. Tis not thy successe</L>
<L>Declines me the least step towards subjection</L>
<L>Of my still high built hopes: which being strongly</L>
<L>Propt with my resolutions, shall in time</L>
<L>Raise monuments of fame unto my actions.</L>
<L>Let not one chance exalt thee. <HI>Hannibal,</HI></L>
<L>Though <HI>Carthage</HI> ownes him not, command's a world</L>
<L>Greater than her, or <HI>Rome.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scip.</SPEAKER>
<L>But the dimensions</L>
<L>Are bounded with that strict necessity</L>
<L>They cannot be extended. Flatter not</L>
<L>Those hopes with expectation of a change</L>
<L>To any better than the now condition</L>
<L>Of thy subverted greatnesse: which being ruin'd</L>
<L>Beyond all reparation, thy attempts</L>
<L>To build it new, wanting materials,</L>
<L>Are vainer farre than the <HI>Sycilian</HI> Dogs</L>
<L>Barking against the Moone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be not deceiv'd</L>
<L>With too much confidence. The more th'are prest,</L>
<L>The more palmes flourish. That that would make <HI>Scipio</HI></L>
<L>Looke downewards, lifts me up.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scip.</SPEAKER>
<L>How thou art mockt</L>
<L>With selfe-opinion! Know I have a soule</L>
<L>So full instructed, it hath power to temper</L>
<L><PB REF="37"/>
The difference of my fortune with that meane,</L>
<L>That even the highest glory to my selfe</L>
<L>Is but adversity, and an abject state</L>
<L>No lesse then is my present greatnesse. Man</L>
<L>From outward accidents should not derive</L>
<L>The knowledge of himselfe: for so hee's made</L>
<L>The creature of beginnings over which</L>
<L>His vertue may command: Fortune and chance.</L>
<L>When he by speculation hath inform'd</L>
<L>His divine part hee's perfect; and 'till then</L>
<L>But a rough matter, onely capable</L>
<L>Of better forme. It oft begets my wonder</L>
<L>That thou a rude Barbarian, ignorant</L>
<L>Of all art, but of warres, which custome onely</L>
<L>Hath (being joyn'd to thy first nature) taught thee,</L>
<L>Shouldst know so much of man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>I study man</L>
<L>Better from practice, than thou canst from bookes.</L>
<L>Thy learning's but opinion, mine knowne truth;</L>
<L>Subject to no grosse errours, such as cannot</L>
<L>Be reconcil'd, but by production</L>
<L>Of new and greater. Did thy learned Masters</L>
<L>Of Arts, with whom even arm'd thou hast converst</L>
<L>Before a battayle joyn'd (if fame speake truth)</L>
<L>By their instructions show thee surer wayes</L>
<L>To victory, than Fortune joyn'd to valour,</L>
<L>And a full strength of men?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scip.</SPEAKER>
<L>That which consists</L>
<L>In action onely, and th'event, depends</L>
<L>Vpon no certaine rule demonstrative,</L>
<L>Is fates, not reasons.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fie, this strife sounds harshly,</L>
<L>Come <HI>Massanissa,</HI> you have shar'd your part</L>
<L>Of vertue and of fortune.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>Least of vertue,</L>
<L>That left a just cause to support a wrong one;</L>
<L>Such was his fall from <HI>Carthage.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="38"/>
<SPEAKER>Massa.</SPEAKER>
<L>You being judge</L>
<L>In your owne cause: but who will else subscribe</L>
<L>To such a partiall sentence?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray' no more.</L>
<L>My Court lookes like a Parliament of Souldiers;</L>
<L>Where warre me thinkes should be discours'd on; how</L>
<L>A battaile should be order'd, or what forme</L>
<L>Hath most advantage. What men have you knowne,</L>
<L>Or History doth mention, that exceoded</L>
<L>In the degrees of merit?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Alexander</HI></L>
<L>The first best Captaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scip.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who the second?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Pyrrhus.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prus.</SPEAKER>
<L>And who the third?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doubtlesse my selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scip.</SPEAKER>
<L>What then</L>
<L>Am I that conquer'd <HI>Hanniball?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>If I</L>
<L>Had conquer'd <HI>Scipio,</HI> I had then beene first.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scip.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did ever pride so swell th'infected parts</L>
<L>Of a rich soule! Were not his mind corrupted</L>
<L>With that disease of vertue, I should covet</L>
<L>To joyne mine with't in an eternall fellowship;</L>
<L>And onely here in outward enmity</L>
<L>Divide our bodies.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scene the last.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>To them</HI> Himulco.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>How art satisfy'd?</L>
<L>Am I yet safe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Him.</SPEAKER>
<L>My observation</L>
<L>Hath beene I feare too curious: for your danger</L>
<L>If any be intended wants all meanes</L>
<L>Of opposition. But my feare perhaps</L>
<L><PB REF="38"/>
Interprets worse than a consideration</L>
<L>Will from the circumstance; which yet hath shew</L>
<L>Of probability.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why what hast seene?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Him.</SPEAKER>
<L>Arm'd troupes guard all the passages by which</L>
<L>The house is enter'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am then betray'd.</L>
<L>Can Kings be trecherous? have they mortall parts</L>
<L>Subject to that corruption staines with leprosie</L>
<L>The glorious brow of honour! Can creation</L>
<L>Be in her different workes so negligent</L>
<L>As not to perfect them? Shee's idle when</L>
<L>She makes Kings, should be like gods, lesse then men.</L>
<L><HI>Prusias</HI> and <HI>Scipio,</HI> thus I mock your plots.</L>
<L>Be trecherous now; you shall have nothing but</L>
<L><HI>Hannibals</HI> earth to worke on. <STAGE>Takes the poison.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scip.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's the meaning</L>
<L>Of this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Massa</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis poison surely that he takes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scip.</SPEAKER>
<L>Restraine him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis too late.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Call our Physitians.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>All helpe is vaine as your conspiracy.</L>
<L>It was no juggling sop to wrap the senses</L>
<L>In slumbers like death, <HI>Colches</HI> never yeelded</L>
<L>A juyce more banefull. I went still prepar'd</L>
<L>Thus to o'recome your malice; which discover'd,</L>
<L>My death beares me above it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scip.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why should <HI>Hannibal</HI></L>
<L>From the weake warrant of a bare suspition</L>
<L>Be guilty of such barbarousnesse! By all</L>
<L>The hopes I have of good mens loves, or memory</L>
<L>'Mongst their true valuing of desert, I ever</L>
<L>Restrain'd m'uncertaine thoughts their liberty</L>
<L>From being busie 'bout betraying <HI>Hanniball</HI></L>
<L>By any practise honour might not father,</L>
<L>And gladly call his owne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="39"/>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>Perswade thy flatterers</L>
<L>To credit it: Those that would deifie</L>
<L>The vertues in thy booke, not of thy mind.</L>
<L>Practice hath taught me how to read mens soules.</L>
<L>Doe not I know then thy hypocrisie</L>
<L>Plasters the wounded credit of thy act!</L>
<L>But if thou healst it, there will be a scarre</L>
<L>To shew posterity that what thou didst</L>
<L>Was full of base corruption.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scip.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou didst much</L>
<L>Lessen thy selfe in thy first feare; and now</L>
<L>By the ill-grounded jealousie of my vertue</L>
<L>Wilt make thy owne taxt. From this <HI>Paedia</HI></L>
<L>I have beene truely morall; th'institutions</L>
<L>Have beene my guides in every action</L>
<L>Which I did either as a man, or Prince.</L>
<L><HI>Cyrus</HI> himselfe, to whom they were directed,</L>
<L>Pursu'd them not so strictly as I have.</L>
<L>Breath not thy soule forth then 'till thou art satisfy'd</L>
<L>Of my true innocence: for if thou dy'st</L>
<L>In thy suspition, be assur'd it will</L>
<L>Disturbe thy peace hereafter, and thy ashes,</L>
<L>As the pile hallows them, will fright thy ghost</L>
<L>With shapes of the dishonour thou unjustly</L>
<L>Would lay on <HI>Scipio.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tell thy Philosophers</L>
<L>The earth hath not a center; that the day</L>
<L>Is not illumin'd by the Sunne; that fire</L>
<L>Is colder than the ever-frozen rocks</L>
<L>That beare the North-end of th'earths Axeltree:</L>
<L>When they allow these paradoxes, I</L>
<L>Will credit <HI>Scipio.</HI> Worke on thou brave minister</L>
<L>Of my last victory over my selfe.</L>
<L>Quench thy unnaturall flames with my scortcht bowels.</L>
<L>Now thou hast met a heat, which joyn'd to thine</L>
<L>Makes all the frame like the bright forge, whence <HI>Jove</HI></L>
<L>Hath his artillery. My heatt, my heart;</L>
<L><PB REF="39"/>
Quench it <HI>Eridanus:</HI> but it would dry</L>
<L>Thy waters up. I'm wrapt in greater fires</L>
<L>Then the rash boy thou choak'st. Would this were <HI>Oeta;</HI></L>
<L>That like the furious Thebane I might build</L>
<L>Mine owne pile, and the flame as it ascends</L>
<L>Transforme it selfe into a constellation;</L>
<L>Or fixe ith' upper region of the ay re</L>
<L>Like a perpetuall comet to fright <HI>Rome</HI></L>
<L>With his prodigious light. Me thinkes an earthquake</L>
<L>Totters the aged fabrick that so long</L>
<L>Hath borne me on't, and the divided poles</L>
<L>Embrace to kisse each other. An inversion</L>
<L>Of natures order shall attend the fate</L>
<L>Of dying <HI>Hannibal.</HI> So Okes eradicated</L>
<L>By a prodigious whirlwind, teare the earth</L>
<L>Through which their large rootes spread themselves.</L>
<L>No lesse then the whole world to be my grave.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scip.</SPEAKER>
<L>He's dead: with him my glory. <HI>Scipio's</HI> acts (Ile have <STAGE>Dy's.</STAGE></L>
<L>Havenot another object worthy them,</L>
<L>Or his attempts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Him.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fame breake thy trumpet now;</L>
<L>Deafe thy wide eares, and silence all thy tongues</L>
<L>Since he's dead, who with his actions wont</L>
<L>To ympe new feathers to thy broken wings,</L>
<L>And make thee sligh a pitch above the reach</L>
<L>Of common eyes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Left that my honour suffer</L>
<L>In the suspition of betraying him,</L>
<L>I will provide a lasting monument,</L>
<L>And fixe his statue on't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scip.</SPEAKER>
<L>You <HI>Massanissa</HI></L>
<L>Ile see establisht in your Kingdome. <HI>Carthage</HI></L>
<L>Thy base ingratitude to him, whose merit</L>
<L>But justly challeng'd all that thou could'st owne</L>
<L>Shall teach me a prevention. Solitude</L>
<L>Is the souies best companion. At <HI>Linturnum</HI></L>
<L>My Country <HI>Villa</HI> I will terminate</L>
<L><PB REF="40"/>
My after life free from mens flatteries,</L>
<L>And feare of their leane envie. He that suffers</L>
<L>Prosperity to swell him 'bove a meane,</L>
<L>Like those impressions in the ayre, that rise</L>
<L>From dunghill vapours, scatter'd by the wind,</L>
<L>Leaves nothing but an empty fame behind.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="epilogue">
<HEAD><HI>The Epilogue by</HI> Scipio.</HEAD>
<L>Our strife is ended: yet in ones I spy</L>
<L>Peace smile, and warre frowne in anothers eye.</L>
<L>Being victorious I must not submit</L>
<L>To a dislike. Rather to him that writ</L>
<L>Our story, gratefully I would allow</L>
<L>One leafe of Lawrell torne from mine owne brow.</L>
<L>And with their faire opinion of it these</L>
<L>May make it a full Garland if they please.</L>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
<PB REF="40"/>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

