<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2004-02-19</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Emma Leeson Huber</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, etc.). Checked for signatures. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, and UNCLEARs. Corrected 4 $s of 231. Converted 227 $s to GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech". Checked spacing of foreign GAPs. Checked for EPIGRAPHs and ARGUMENTs. Checked for startqs, endqs, oes, q;s, and Qs. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Checked for CLOSERs, TRAILERs, and BYLINEs. DONE.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="A07971">
<STC T="S">18339</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99848285</BIBNO>
<VID>13369</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>COVENT
GARDEN:
A PLEASANT
COMEDIE:
Acted in the YEARE, MDCXXXII.
By the <HI>Queenes</HI> Majesties Servants.</P>
<P><HI>The Author</HI>
THOMAS NABBES.</P>
<P><HI>LONDON,</HI>
Printed by RICHARD OULTON, for
CHARLES GREENE; and are to be
sold at the Signe of the White <HI>Lyon,</HI> in
PAULS <HI>Church-yard.</HI>
1638.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>TO
THE RIGHT WORTHY
OF HIS HONOVRS
Sr. JOHN SUCKLING
Knight.</HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>SIR,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">T</SEG>Here is no excuse for this my
presumption, but a presump∣tion
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pon your <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/></P>
<P>It is likewise an error in
my weaknesse, to put so meane a piece to
a second tryall; when in your perusall it
will meet with a more piercing judge∣ment,
then the <HI>Stages,</HI> that gave it
some partiall allowance. For the stile,
'tis humble:
<Q><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>rpit humi tutus nimium, timidus{que} procellae.</Q></P>
<P><PB REF="3"/>
Your owne is <HI>Pindarus,</HI> mine <HI>Bacchy∣lides.</HI>
Yet I would have endeavour'd to
make the persons speake better, had it
been proper to their condition. As you
are a <HI>Patron</HI> to all good endeavours, you
merit to be the subject of many <HI>Encomi∣ums:</HI>
But your selfe by your selfe in ma∣king
the world (which can never be suf∣ficiently
gratefull for it) happy in the
publication of your late worthy labour,
have prevented the intentions of many to
dignifie that in you which is so farr above
them. My hope is, that by your favoura∣ble
acceptance of this, I may gaine some
opinion with others; to whom I have and
alwayes do declare my selfe in my desires
ambitious to be knowne by you at the be∣coming
distance of</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Your honourer and humble Servant
THOMAS NABBES.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="prologue">
<PB REF="3"/>
<HEAD>The PROLOGVE.</HEAD>
<L>DOe not expect th' <HI>abuses</HI> of a <HI>Place;</HI></L>
<L>Nor th'ills sprung from a Strumpets painted <HI>face</HI></L>
<L>To be exprest. Our <HI>Author</HI> doth not meane</L>
<L>With such vile <HI>stuffe</HI> to clothe his <HI>modest Scoene.</HI></L>
<L>Nor doth he brand <HI>it</HI> with a <HI>Satyres</HI> marke;</L>
<L>But makes a <HI>Justice</HI> wiser then his <HI>Clerke.</HI></L>
<L>His <HI>Rusticks</HI> likewise will pretend to <HI>Wit:</HI></L>
<L>So all the <HI>Persons</HI> which wee counterfeit.</L>
<L>He justifies that 'tis no borrow'd <HI>Straine,</HI></L>
<L>From the invention of anothers <HI>braine.</HI></L>
<L>Nor did he steale the <HI>Fancie.</HI> 'Tis the same</L>
<L>Hee first intended by the <HI>proper Name.</HI></L>
<L>'Twas not a toyle of <HI>yeares:</HI> few <HI>weekes</HI> brought forth</L>
<L>This <HI>rugged Issue,</HI> might have beene more worth</L>
<L>If he had lick'd <HI>it</HI> more. Nor doth he raise</L>
<L>From th' imitation of <HI>authenticke Playes</HI></L>
<L><HI>Matter</HI> or <HI>words</HI> to height: nor bundle up</L>
<L><HI>Conceits</HI> at <HI>Tavernes</HI> where the <HI>Wits</HI> doe sup.</L>
<L>His <HI>Muse</HI> issolitary, and alone</L>
<L>Doth practise her low <HI>speculation.</HI></L>
<L>He hath no <HI>faction</HI> in a partiall <HI>way,</HI></L>
<L>Prepar'd to <HI>cry it up,</HI> and boast the <HI>Play,</HI></L>
<L>Swelling your <HI>expectations:</HI> hee relies</L>
<L>Meerely upon your <HI>ingenuities.</HI></L>
<L>The <HI>Matter's</HI> weake: how can the <HI>Building</HI> stand?</L>
<L>Yes; if supported by a <HI>gratious Hand.</HI></L>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dramatis personae">
<PB REF="4"/>
<HEAD>The PERSONS.</HEAD>
<LIST>
<ITEM>DVNGVVORTH. <HI>A Countrey</HI> Gentle∣man.</ITEM>
<ITEM><LIST>
<ITEM>RALPH.</ITEM>
<ITEM>DOBSON.</ITEM>
</LIST> His Servants.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Mris. TONGALL. <HI>A busie Gossip.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>THEODORE ARTLOVE.</HI> A compleat Gentleman.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>LITTLEWORD.</HI> A reputed Witt.</ITEM>
<ITEM>HVGH IERKER. <HI>A wilde Gallant.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>IEFFEREY IERKER.</HI> A lad of the same humour.</ITEM>
<ITEM>DOROTHY WORTHY. <HI>Daughter to</HI> Sir GENE.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>SVSAN.</HI> A Waiting-woman to the <HI>Lady.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>WARRANT. <HI>Clerke to</HI> Sir GENEROVS.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>SPRVCE.</HI> Gentleman Vsher to the <HI>Lady.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Lady WORTHY.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Sir GENEROVS WORTHY.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Young WORTHY. <HI>His Son.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>DASHER.</HI> A complementing Vintener.</ITEM>
<ITEM>DRAVVER.</ITEM>
<ITEM>CONSTABLE.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<P><HI>The</HI> Scoene COVENT-GARDEN.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 N="1" TYPE="act">
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<PB N="1" REF="4"/>
<HEAD>Act. 1. Scoen. 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>DVNGVVORTH, RALPH,</HI> and
<HI>DOBSON,</HI> as newly come to Towne by
the right <HI>SCOENE.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOBSON.</SPEAKER>
<P>_<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> we are come to <HI>London,</HI> fellow <HI>Ralph</HI>
what shall we doe? or what course will our
Master take with us?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, <HI>Dobson;</HI> he may doe what
he will, and wee will doe what we list. A
little instruction and practice will make
us wicked enough, I dare warrant thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dobs.</SPEAKER>
<P>I hope we are not to learne that. But all this while
the Plough stands still.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sha, <HI>Dobson;</HI> thy mind's upon nothing but dirt.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dobs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeed heer's store of it, ankcle deepe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dung.</SPEAKER>
<P>What place is this <HI>Ralph?</HI> thou knowst <HI>London.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>It should be COVENT-GARDEN; but 'tis
much alter'd since I was here last.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dungw.</SPEAKER>
<P>A <HI>Garden</HI> call you it! 'Tis a very barren one.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dobs.</SPEAKER>
<P>I would I were at home againe, amongst the
<HI>Creame-bowles.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="2" REF="5"/>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>I cou'd be content to have the tother sm<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cke at o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r
<HI>Gillian</HI> the Dayry-Maids sugar-candy—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dobs.</SPEAKER>
<P>How, fellow <HI>Ralph!</HI> you kisse my Sweet-heart
<HI>Gillian!</HI> pronounce it againe, and by the faith of a new
made Serving-man, that puts his whole trust in his Live<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y
and the Quarter-dayes, I will kill thee presently, and chal∣lenge
thee the next Holi-day before the Congregation.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>Kill me fi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st, and then challenge me! for a kisse
or two! nay, good <HI>Dobsox;</HI> she has lips big enough to serve
us both. Prethee lets not fall o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t and beat one another:
these people would but laugh at us for't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dobs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeed 'tis a jolly company. Dwell they all here
abouts?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>I scarce thinke they are all of one Parish, neither
doe they goe to one Church. They come onely for an eve∣ning
recreation <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e COVENT-GARDEN.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dobs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Blessings on their hearts for it. 'Tis a goodly place.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>And a god<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y one too if rumour lie not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dung.</SPEAKER>
<P>What are all these things with rayles?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thinke mewes for hawkes, or ayrings for gen∣tles.
Other hawkes are not here in any request.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dung.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mewes for hawkes, thou wouldst make mee a
Buzzard.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dobs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Dost thinke we shall dwell hereabouts?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>I hope so: we shall then be n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ere the <HI>Cock-p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t,</HI>
and see a Play now and then.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dobs.</SPEAKER>
<P>But tell me <HI>Ralph,</HI> are those Players the ragged
fellowes that were at our house last <HI>Christmas,</HI> that bor∣rowed
the red blanket off my bed to make their Major a
gowne; and had the great Pot-lid for <HI>Guy</HI> of <HI>Warwicks</HI>
Buckler?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, <HI>Dobson;</HI> they are men of credit, whose acti∣ons
are beheld by every one, and allow'd for the most part
with commendations. They make no yearely Progresse
with the <HI>Anatomy</HI> of a S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mpter-horse, laden with the
sweepings of <HI>Long-lane</HI> in a dead Vacation, and purchas'd
<PB N="3" REF="5"/>
at the exchange of their owne whole Wardrobes. They
buy not their Ordinary for the Copie of a <HI>Prologue;</HI> nor
insinuate themselves into the acquaintance of an admiring
<HI>Ningle,</HI> who for his free comming in, is at the expence of
a Taverne Supper, and rinses their bawling throats with
Canarye.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dobs.</SPEAKER>
<P>But I would I had stay'd still in the Countrey,
now Sports are tollerated, in despite of Justice, <HI>Trouble∣some's</HI>
malicious Authoritie. I had rather see a Morris∣dance
and a May-pole, then ten Playes: what care I for
wit which I understand not?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>The duller Asse tho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dobs.</SPEAKER>
<P>How, Asse to my face! provoke me no more
with such foule language, lest I enter and act thy Tragedy.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, prethee fellow <HI>Dobson;</HI> if we abuse our
selves sometimes, 'twill be the better taken when wee a∣b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>se others.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dung.</SPEAKER>
<P>To morrow Ile have you acco<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tred in liveries,
and put my selfe into a gentile garbe. I am resolv'd to for∣sake
the Countrey profession of mine Auncestors; and
meane to turne Gallant. Ile sell some few dirty Acres, and
buy a Knighthood: Ile translate my Farme of <HI>Dirt-all</HI> in∣to
the Mannor of <HI>No-place.</HI> Would I were acquainted
with an honest Scrivener.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>You wish an impossibility, unlesse the Pillory
were more terrible.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dobson.</SPEAKER>
<P>But doe you meane to sell your Land?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dung.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes indeed; I shall be the likelier to goe to hea∣ven
when I forsake earth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>But 'tis a dangerous way through a Scriveners
conscience.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dung.</SPEAKER>
<P>What dost tell me of danger! 'Tis the Cowards
bug-beare; a scar-crow to City gulls, that dare not weare
swords for feare of being challeng'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dobs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, my Master is as tall a man of his inches.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dung.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, <HI>Dobson;</HI> thou hast seene me doe something.
<PB N="4" REF="6"/>
But sirrah, let it be your charge to finde out a good Inne;
see Crop eat his meat.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dobs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile warrant Sir, hee'l cat his meate, and 'twere
Good-friday.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>Had he but cares then, hee might make a very
good Puritan horse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dung.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeed, their best vertue is to heare well.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>But their doing sometimes, begets a hotter zeale
in the Sister-hood.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dungw.</SPEAKER>
<P>I'le have a lodging heere. Prethee aske that
Gentlewoman; shee seems an inhabitant.</P>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>The second Scoene.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Mris. TONGALL,</HI> by the right <HI>Scoene.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray Master, know you hereabouts any conve∣nient
Lodgings?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tong.</SPEAKER>
<P>Many Sir, for convenient persons.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dungw.</SPEAKER>
<P>Of credit, and unsuspicious.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tong.</SPEAKER>
<P>It is not in my understanding; wherefore the
satisfaction I can give you will be doubtfull. I know none
of my neighbours better then my selfe. I have as hand∣some
Lodgings as any are in <HI>Covent Garden:</HI> my fore∣roomes
have a faire prospect, and my back-roomes a
sweet ayre.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>Which is not usuall backwards.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dung.</SPEAKER>
<P>May we see them?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tong.</SPEAKER>
<P>If you please to let that Taverne receive you
till I have made them ready, I will returne and give you
notic<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dung.</SPEAKER>
<P>I'le sup there: shall I intreat your company?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tong▪</SPEAKER>
<P>I shall be ready to fulfill your desires.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dobs.</SPEAKER>
<P>And we our bellies: hitherto, we have had but
a hungry journey of it.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Dungwell and Dobson goe forth by the left <HI>Scoene.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<PB N="5" REF="6"/>
<SPEAKER>Tong.</SPEAKER>
<P>My friend, pray what's your Masters name?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>What if it be not in my Commission to tell you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tong.</SPEAKER>
<P>My demands are civill and for no hurt. I must
know before my house can give him entertainment.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>But I must not tell you, till I have a mind to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.
You may be the agent to an Informer: doe you not cor∣respond
with the Summer and Apparitour, to keepe your
selfe off some deserv'd punishment.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tong.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am a patient bearer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not unlikely, I have heard there are many such
in <HI>Covent-Garden.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tong.</SPEAKER>
<P>I meane with your unmanerlinesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>If a downe-right▪ Countrey thing will please
you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tong.</SPEAKER>
<P>A downe-right! you make me blus<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>This interest then, and—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tong.</SPEAKER>
<P>So Sir, the termes are not equall for such fami∣liaritie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why then you must seeke you a more proporti∣on'd
Schoole-master to enter you farther, and teach you
my Masters name. The Wine stayes, and I want it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tong.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good friend stay a little, and tell me thy Ma∣sters
name.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>What agen! Fare you well, I have forgot it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tong.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, prethee friend: my knowledge of it may
much concerne his, or (if not) thy good. My daughter
<HI>Iynny's</HI> a handsome girle, he that pleaseth me best shall
have her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>I rather thinke hee shall have her that pleaseth
her best, else I shall doubt her for a woman. But how
can s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e concerne our goods? your instance.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tong.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, credit me upon my word, 'tis earnest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>A Womans word! 'tis not worth an ounce of
feathers. Besides, you may be under covert barne. Have
you not a Husband?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tong.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes indeede.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="6" REF="7"/>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>What's his profession?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tong.</SPEAKER>
<P>An under-Lawyer, an Attourney.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>His word may be taken in the terme for a gown-facing
or so: but to doe any man good, is worth a double
fee, if he performe it. Mistris, if you must know my Ma∣sters
name, goe to <HI>Carterton</HI> in the Countie of <HI>Sussex,</HI> and
there in the Church-Register you shall finde, that <HI>Roger</HI>
the sonne of <HI>Rowland Dungworth</HI> of <HI>Dirtall</HI> Farme in the
Parish of <HI>Carterton</HI> aforesaid, was baptised—But stay,
I'le know first if he be resolved to continue a Christian;
'tis ordinary to change names with religion. Besides, hee
means to be a Knight; and <HI>Dungworth</HI> will stink in the de∣licate
nostrils of a Lady: it may make the heraul<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>s give
him a mock-coate with three kennell-rakers. Farewell
sweet Mistris, and if my Master chance to lie at your house,
I should be glad if I might lie over your Daughter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tong.</SPEAKER>
<P>Farewell good friend. The Gentleman to lye at
my house! very good. I must project a profit out of
the accident; a new Gowne, or a Beaver, or some com∣position
with a bond of assurance, when I procure him a
good Wife. Perhaps hee shall have my Daughter <HI>Iynny.</HI>
Who would thinke this little body of mine were so busie
in stirring actions, Master <HI>Theodore Art-love!</HI></P>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>The third Scoene.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>ART-LOVE</HI> by the right <HI>Scoene.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Artl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mistresse <HI>Tongall,</HI> you are delighting your selfe
with these new erections.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tong.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faire erections are pleasing things.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Artl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeed they are faire ones, and their uniformity
addes much to their beauty.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tong.</SPEAKER>
<P>How like you the Balconee's? They set off a
Ladies person well, when she presents her selfe to the view
<PB N="7" REF="7"/>
of gazing passengers. Artificiall fucations are not dis∣cern'd
at distance.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Artl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray which is Sir <HI>Generous Worthie's</HI> house?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tong.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your desires (I believe) are bent towards his
faire Daughter. Let me ayd you: my neighbour-hood
hath interested me in her acquaintance; I can make way;
and truely Mr. <HI>Art-love</HI> I like you so well, that (were she
worthy) you should have my daughter <HI>Iynnye.</HI> But doe
you love Mistris <HI>Dorothy?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Artl.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have seene her beauty, and her nimble eyes</L>
<L>Have shot a fire into me, that inflam<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'s</L>
<L>My cold desires. I that have resisted</L>
<L>Th' assaults of passion to a perfect conquest;</L>
<L>And call'd it (justly too) the height of folly</L>
<L>To give that wanton Power the attribute</L>
<L>Of a false Deity: I, that have out-gone</L>
<L>Th' example of <HI>Zenocrates,</HI> am captiv'd;</L>
<L>But by a Beauty, such as would review</L>
<L>Heat in the frozen bosome of an <HI>Anchorite,</HI></L>
<L>Who hath spent his age even to decrepitnesse</L>
<L>In such austerities as would mortifie</L>
<L>The strongest pamperd wantonnesse. I cove<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>A good successe, but faile in't. Never yet</L>
<L>Could I be blest with opportunity</L>
<L>To shew her my desires, and to try</L>
<L>The fortune of perswasion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tong.</SPEAKER>
<P>And would you not use me! hath so long pra∣ctise
in match-making made me politicke to contrive, and
my conversation with your selfe and the rest of the Wits
made me complementall, and doe you thinke I cannot fa∣cilitate
your entrance to Mistris <HI>Dorothy?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Artl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Should I be fortunate in my attempts</L>
<L>To win her liking; should my person please her,</L>
<L>Or that annexion to my better part</L>
<L>Of education, yet the disparitie</L>
<L>Betwixt our states, checks me from hoping</L>
<L><PB N="8" REF="8"/>
That the designe can prosper. The lighter fire</L>
<L>Nere mixeth with the earth, but to confusion:
Or from their severall natures bringing forth
Events prodigious.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tong.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, you are an Heyre to a thousand pound a
yeare. An officious lye may be dispens't with.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Artl.</SPEAKER>
<L>But simple honesty</L>
<L>Clad in the naked livery of truth</L>
<L>Is a most glorious vertue, that preserves</L>
<L>White innocence unstain'd with falshood.</L>
<L>Good meanes as well as good intention</L>
<L>Must make an act good.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tong.</SPEAKER>
<P>If you have such a tender conscience, so religi∣ously
scrupulous, you'l never be a Politician.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Artl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let those that study mischiefe</L>
<L>To satisfie their sensualties</L>
<L>Practise such wickednesse. I'de not abuse</L>
<L>A noble goodnes to possesse the <HI>Indies.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tong.</SPEAKER>
<P>But heere's one will, and I must ayd him int▪
Mr. <HI>Littleword.</HI></P>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>The fourth Scoene.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>LITTLEVVORD, IERKER</HI> and <HI>IEFFERY,</HI>
by the right <HI>Scoene.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ierk.</SPEAKER>
<P>Friend <HI>Art-love,</HI> the good fortune of a petticote
light upon thee, in the name of Venery what mak'st thou
here? art' in quest of a smock-bedfellow.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Artl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thy old humour still friend.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ierker.</SPEAKER>
<P>Prethee salute this little gentleman my Cousin:
he hath more age and wit then his small proportion doth
promise.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Artl.</SPEAKER>
<P>I shall be ready to serve him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ieffr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your acquaintance will adde much to my hap∣pinesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="9" REF="8"/>
<SPEAKER>Ierk.</SPEAKER>
<P>He hath gotten leave of his Vncle to liue here in
my tuition. Hee thrive's well in his conceit, a right <HI>Ier∣ker;</HI>
he begins to love a wench already.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Art.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thy instruction and example will soone enable
him that way.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ieffr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is not that a wench Cousin?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ierk.</SPEAKER>
<P>Try Cos. and satisfie your selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ieffr.</SPEAKER>
<P>My <HI>Little-word,</HI> if your salute be ended, pray re∣signe.
Nay, Mistris, I can kisse you without the helpe
of a joyn'd stoole: please you to walke, and let my hand
support you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tong.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whither pray you little sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ieffr.</SPEAKER>
<P>To the next vaulting<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>schoole.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tong.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas, you cannot get up without a stirrop.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ieff.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, and ride too without falling; please you to
trye my activenesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Art.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prethee recall thy wonted goodnesse home,</L>
<L>And with a vertuous scorne shake off this habit</L>
<L>Of loose desires; it hath infection in it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ierk.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nothing comes from thee but documents. I
sweare I should love thee much better if thou hadst lesse
vertue. I prethee leave thy <HI>Stoicisme,</HI> and become an Epi∣cure
with me. My little Cos. here shall prove with unde∣nyable
arguments that drinking and wenching are the one∣ly
vertues in a gentleman of the last edition: to be excel∣lent
at them is a master-piece of education. Besides, they
are the onely <HI>acumens</HI> of wit.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Artl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, to disease it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ierk.</SPEAKER>
<P>Take heed thy iudgement be not brought in que∣stion.
Why diseas'd wits are—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ieffr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Better play at small game then sit out. A young
gamester may throw in and in.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tong.</SPEAKER>
<P>Very seldome with three dice. Can your littlenesse
cogge?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ieffr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faire play is a gamesters glory. I love to shake the
boxe well, and than let them run their length.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="10" REF="9"/>
<SPEAKER>Artl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, I confesse it; where there is an union</L>
<L>Of loving hearts, the joy exceed's expression.</L>
<L>That love is vertuous whose desires doe never</L>
<L>End in their satisfaction, but increase</L>
<L>Towards the object. When a beautious frame</L>
<L>Garnish't with all the lustre of perfection</L>
<L>Invite's the eye, and tells the searching thoughts</L>
<L>It holds a richer minde, with which my soule</L>
<L>Would rather mixe her faculties.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ieffr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Iudge not of a man by his outward dimensions:
My shape is not so defective to make you doubt perfor∣mance:
let's finde out a convenient place and try.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tong.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas little one, you'l lose your selfe: you'l never
hit the way home.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ierker.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis a blisse above the faign'd <HI>Elysium</HI></L>
<L>To claspe a dainty waste; to kisse a lip</L>
<L>Melts into <HI>Nectar;</HI> to behold an eye</L>
<L>Shoot amorous fires, that would warme cold Statues</L>
<L>Into a life and motion; play with hayre</L>
<L>Brighter then that was stellifyed.</L>
<L>And when the wanton appetite is cloy'd</L>
<L>With thousand satisfactions of this kind,</L>
<L>Then follow's th' absolutenesse</L>
<L>Of all delight. But were desire restrain'd</L>
<L>From variation, soone 'twould satiate,</L>
<L>And glut it selfe to loathing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ieffr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Please you to drinke a pint or two of wine? there
may be provocation in it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tong.</SPEAKER>
<P>Preserve your courtesie child, and your money:
Lent's at hand, and then every street will afford boyes re∣creation.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ieff.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why how now impudence! do you slout a man?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ierk.</SPEAKER>
<P>How, a man Cousin!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ieffr.</SPEAKER>
<P>I want not so much of my full age to bee cal'd
a boy.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Artl.</SPEAKER>
<P>But you must not fall out with the Gentlewoman.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="11" REF="9"/>
<SPEAKER>Ieffr.</SPEAKER>
<P>I desire rather to have fal'n in with her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ierk.</SPEAKER>
<P>I would not have you so forward Cousin. You
must be sure to deale with sound ware.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ieffr.</SPEAKER>
<P>What care I? 'tis but the losse of a mans hayre;
an excrementall ornament: wit consists not in't. A man
may cover his baldnesse with a periwig, and the fashion
take's away the suspition. I hope I came to <HI>London</HI> to
learne wit and the fashion.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tong.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come Mr. <HI>Little-word.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Artl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Adiew Mistris <HI>Tongall.</HI></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Tongall and Little-word, by the right <HI>Scoene.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ieffr.</SPEAKER>
<P>I tooke her rather for a Wag-taile.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Art.</SPEAKER>
<P>What silent Gentleman's that?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ierk.</SPEAKER>
<P>His Character in his owne language is I and no;
yet he speaks well in paper. He is a wit, but somewhat
a dull one.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Artl.</SPEAKER>
<P>What serious affaire have they together?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ierk.</SPEAKER>
<P>There are hidden pollicies in the world. Thou
hast a bookish humour; I a wenching one; and why may
not his dulnes dreame of some rich match! Mris. <HI>Tongal's</HI>
the onely match-maker in the Towne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Artl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Those words create a hell of torment in me.</L>
<L>Is there no love</L>
<L>But what's attended by vaine jealousie!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ierk.</SPEAKER>
<P>Art thou in love?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Artl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, passionately.</L>
<L>My dreamings, wakings, thoughts and actions</L>
<L>Are nothing but desire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ierk.</SPEAKER>
<P>I can assoone credit an impossibility. Thou in
love! why 'tis more improbable then the projection of
draining Marsh-land with a wind-mill. But prethee what
is shee?</P>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="scene">
<PB N="12" REF="10"/>
<HEAD>The fifth Scoene.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> DOROTHY SVSAN <HI>in the</HI> Balcone.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Artl.</SPEAKER>
<L>See where my comforts Sun</L>
<L>Breaks through a clowd. Oh that this unkind distance</L>
<L>Might be contracted into lesser ayre:</L>
<L>I'de then convey my whispers to her eares;</L>
<L>And teach her understanding what delight</L>
<L>Society hath in it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ierk.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sure thou hast not boldnes enough to speake to
her. Thou wouldst blush, and fall into some patheticall
booke discourse, or tell her the story of <HI>Hero</HI> and <HI>Leander,</HI>
to make her tendernesse whine. Tis not the way. Get
accesse to her; and after one mannerly salute, double and
treble thy kisses; tumble her a little, and if opportunity
serve, offer the rest: Magick hath not a Philter like it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ieffr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is not that a house (Cousin) where the Wen∣ches
are?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ierk.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, questionlesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ieffr.</SPEAKER>
<P>I meane in the sense of—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dorot.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yonder Gentlemen observe us: let's be gone.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not yet (Mistris <HI>Dorothy.)</HI> Now I have drunke
a cup of Sack, I must be in love with one of them, him
that seemes most worthy of a gentleuman.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dorot.</SPEAKER>
<P>You have fall'n my glove.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sus.</SPEAKER>
<P>I'le fetch it.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt from the <HI>Balcone.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Artl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Blest accident;</L>
<L>Why doe you stop my hast? let me embrace it.</L>
<L>Thus with religious worship doe I kisse</L>
<L>What your white hand hath hallow'd. Ha! shee's gone▪</L>
<L>What envious mischiefe intercepts the meanes</L>
<L>Of my desired happinesse! or have mine eyes</L>
<L>Wasted their beames in gazing on the place</L>
<L><PB N="13" REF="10"/>
Where I first saw her, to imagination</L>
<L>Fancying her figure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ieffr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sure Cousin the gentleman is in love; he talks
very madly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Artl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where are the powers of my intellect?</L>
<L>Reason and understanding have forsaken</L>
<L>Their proper seates, and left strong passions</L>
<L>To triumph o're this captiv'd <HI>Microcosme.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ierk.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now I see thou art mad: but prethee strive to
conceale it; the place is publique.</P>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="6" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>The sixth Scoene.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>SVSAN</HI> by the middle <HI>Scoene.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray you Sir, did you take up a Gentleumans
glove?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Artl.</SPEAKER>
<P>It was my happinesse, and 'twould be much in∣creased,
if I might kisse the hand that wore it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>As I am a Gentleuman I shall be most carefull
to give your deservings their due commendations.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Artl.</SPEAKER>
<P>May I be bold to enter with you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>You are a stranger Sir, and it may give occasion
of jealousie. But I am my Ladies Gentleuman: I keepe
the key of her secrets, and if you please, her closet shall
conceale you; where you may dispose of Suckets and
Eringoe's for your refreshment. I pray Sir, call not a gen∣tleumans
freenesse immodesty.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Artl.</SPEAKER>
<P>My behaviour shall deserve your good opinion.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Truely Sir, a man could not stand better in the
conceit of a gentleuman at first sight, then you doe in mine.
I hope your goodnesse will not misconster my readinesse to
humble my desires to your disposing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Art.</SPEAKER>
<L>You teach me language which my selfe should use:</L>
<L>But if my gratitude doth seeme to want</L>
<L>Verball expression, I had rather act</L>
<L><PB N="14" REF="11"/>
Then promise what I owe you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>leffr.</SPEAKER>
<P>This is pretty foolery, Cousin.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, you appeare so repleat with goodnesse, that
I presume you cannot but answer the desires of a gentle∣uman,
who proft<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ates her love at the feete of your ac∣ceptance.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Artl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doth she love me? what greater secret</L>
<L>Hath Nature in her Workes then simpathie!</L>
<L>I do<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> conceive a thousand fond expressions,</L>
<L>Which throng so fast, they choake the passage up,</L>
<L>That none can finde an issue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ierk.</SPEAKER>
<P>Out of fooles Paradise: thou art in it. But pray
you Gentleuman protract not his satisfaction with these
circumstantiall delayes. Whilst Mris. <HI>Dorothy</HI> and he are
busie, you and I will tast the sweet-meats in your Ladies
Closet.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>I understand you not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ieffr.</SPEAKER>
<P>He meanes you should lie under him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fie little one, that you should so offend the chast
eares of a Gentleuman. But to you Sir, the Load-stone of
my heart, that turnes it selfe at your motions pointing still
to the North of your Love.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ieffr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeed Mistris 'tis a cold corner, pray turne it to
the South, and let my needle run in your Diall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>And since the ardor of my desires have urg'd my
blushes to discover them; let not your appearing worth
suffer such a disparagement to conte<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ne a Gentleumans
willingnesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Art.</SPEAKER>
<P>How's this! why friend, did she not seeme to come
instructed (by direction) with <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>embassie
As to prepare my love?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ierk.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, no, she loves thee her selfe. Take her. Me
thinks shee's very beautifull; what pinken-eyes; what
a sharpe chin! Why her features transcend <HI>Mopsa's</HI> in
the <HI>Arcadia.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ieffr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hath she not studied it Cousin, thinke you? and
<PB N="15" REF="11"/>
is transported to a humour of loving every man she sees.</P>
<P>I have known it in the Countrey in an age-d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cayed wai∣ting-woman.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Artl.</SPEAKER>
<P>I cannot answer her; my heart is bigg
With other thoughts; which till I am deliver'd of,
I suffer torments.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Vnfortunate Gentleuman as I am, to be thus re∣jected.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ieffr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Will you resigne your interest? I'le court her folly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Artl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take it,</L>
<L>But not t'abuse the others innocence.</L>
<L>Whilst I with sighes draw in th' unwilling ayre</L>
<L>Which she perfum'd at distance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ieffr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray Gentleuman could you love me a little? I'm
very sportive.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Truly young Gentleman, I doe not know what
I may doe when you come to your full growth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iaffr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Blirt my Ladies Gentleuman, who taught you to
scoffe at a mans person?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Cry ye mercy little Sir; you may be the father
of dwarfes. The sack begins to leave working and by this
time my Ladie expects her gentleuman. Farewell, un∣kind
Sir.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Goes forth by the middle Scene.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ierk.</SPEAKER>
<P>Farewell loving Gentleuman. She hath preven∣ted
me. Sure friend she came but to mocke thee. 'Twas
little lesse then downeright impudence.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ieffr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let's to the Taverne Sir, and drowne this passion
in a cup of Canary.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ierk.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come, come; I was ordained to doe thee good.
Thou knowst I had a Mistris, whose friends disliking my
wildnesse, marryed her to the Father of the Gentlewoman
whom thou lov'st (hornes be his punishment for it.) She
loves me still; and I doe not despaire of making him Cuc∣kold.
Wee'l arme our selves with a quart or two, and
then I'le bring thee to her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="16" REF="12"/>
<SPEAKER>Artl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ayd me love, wit and fate; that my desires</L>
<L>Burne not themselves without her equall fires.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ierk.</SPEAKER>
<L>More passions yet! It thou the marke wouldst hit,</L>
<L>Let Sacke inspire thee: 'tis the Soule of Wit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ieffr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sack that makes Prophets; gives a <HI>Poet</HI> birth:</L>
<L>And then a wench; <HI>Elysium</HI> upon Earth.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Goe forth by the left <HI>Scoene.</HI></STAGE>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="2" TYPE="act">
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Act. 2. Scoen. 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>SVSAN</HI> and <HI>WARRANT,</HI> by the
middle <HI>SCOENE.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVSAN.</SPEAKER>
<P>NOw I protest Mr. <HI>Warrant,</HI> you wrong the love of a
Gentleuman, in not imparting the cause of your dis∣content.
Come not fees in roundly? Doe not the Delin∣quents
understand, I'le speake a good word for you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warr.</SPEAKER>
<P>You are the onely object of my thoughts. 'Tis
your beauty hath animated my presumptuous weaknes to
expresse how much my desires are yours.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas Mr. Warrant how can a poore Gentleuman
deserve it?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, you have power of my Lady, and she much
acquaintance at Court. A pardon might be got.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>A pardon! blesse me, for what?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not for murder; but for killing (yet not a Man)
fairely in the field.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Are you earnest?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warr.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis not yet done; onely I am resolv'd to doe it,
were I but sure of my pardon.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sus.</SPEAKER>
<P>If not a man, what then is it?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="17" REF="12"/>
<SPEAKER>Warr.</SPEAKER>
<P>A meere superfluous complement of state for∣mality.
One of my Ladyes raising. A fellow that hath crosse
cape<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'d himselfe out of a Taylor into a gentleman Vsher.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who Mr. <HI>Spruce?</HI> but have you charng'd him?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, with all <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> and circumstance. The
weapon single Rapier; the place the P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>azz<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>; the time
this mooneshine night presently before supper.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>And your quarrell my love. Wel<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Mr. <HI>Warrant;</HI> I
know a Gentleuman hath interest in a Lord at Court, who
hath long beene inward with her. I'le warrant your par∣don.
But my Lady expects me.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Dearest part of my selfe: to get my pardon, here's
<HI>Spruce,</HI> now will I affront him.</P>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>The second Scoene.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>SPRVCE</HI> by the middle <HI>Scoene.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spruce</SPEAKER>
<P>Our being my Ladi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s Gentleman Vsher, her <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>
not protect you in the com∣pet<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>on
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spruce.</SPEAKER>
<P>Warrant, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> shred of basenesse
to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> favours, and mine owne de∣servings.
Mr. S. <HI>Secretary</HI> is my Ladies gentl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>woman, and
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> by priviledge.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warr.</SPEAKER>
<P>By priviledge <HI>Spruce!</HI> Thou art a Baboone of
forma<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ty, and an ap<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>-ship. When I have kill'd
thee, and get my pardon, I will have thy skin stuhh't; and
with a protection shew the<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> at countrey Faires and Mar∣kets
for a <HI>Ginney Pigmie.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spruce.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Warrant,</HI> thou art the <HI>Epitome</HI> of my Masters au∣thority,
and the abridgement of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> justiceship.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warr.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Spruce,</HI> thou art a very <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, bred in thy crosse∣legg<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d
profession; that having suckt a little bloud of Gen∣tility,
instead of thy usuall bread bre<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>kfast, art growne to a
fancy familiarity, with thy maintainers. T<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ou buy'st thy
<PB N="18" REF="13"/>
laundry in Long-lane or Hounsditch with the impude<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>c
of a cheater.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spruce.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Warrant,</HI> thou lyest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warr.</SPEAKER>
<P>How <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lie. That some-body were here to stand
betwixt us. Come not neere me, lest I blast thee with the
breath of my just indignation.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spruce.</SPEAKER>
<P>Keepe at distance <HI>Warrant,</HI> lest I <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ame thee, and
send thee from Constable to Constable in a Wheele∣barrow.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warr.</SPEAKER>
<P>For this <HI>Spruce</HI> I will not compassionate the good
parts which my Lady commends in thee. Thy Fiddle∣sticke
shall not save thee; nor thy capring lift thee an inch
from the ground which I have laid for thy destruction.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spruce.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Warrant,</HI> thou art the very parings of a Pedan∣ticke
to flout the compleatnesse of education. Because thy
dulnesse is capable of no more then to frame <HI>Hetroclites</HI>
from mens names, and scribble a warrant or a <HI>mittimus</HI> by
a president; yet thou art a Justices Clerke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warr.</SPEAKER>
<P>And thou a Ladies Gentleman Vsher, a bundle
of complementall follyes stitcht up with how-dee's. I
will send thee anon upon a visit to the Divell.</P>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>The third Scoene.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>SVSAN,</HI> by the middle <HI>Scoene.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan,</SPEAKER>
<P>Fie Mr. <HI>Spruce</HI> and Mr. <HI>Warrant,</HI> how loud you
are <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> my Ladie heares your noise, and is offended.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spruce.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, my Rapier and mine arme shall maintaine
it upon his life, I love you best.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeed Mr. <HI>Spruce</HI> and I love you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warr.</SPEAKER>
<P>I'le maintaine it against the life of all the world,
I love you best.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Truely Mr. <HI>Warrant</HI> and I love you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spruce.</SPEAKER>
<P>He that offers to love her besides my selfe, dies.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mr. <HI>Spruce</HI> and Mr. <HI>Warrant,</HI> send but for one
<PB N="19" REF="13"/>
bottle of Sack, and be friends; I'le love you both.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warr.</SPEAKER>
<P>I'le brooke no Rivall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spruce.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nor I; death must determine it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Remember then, I must to the Cutlers.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>WARRANT</HI> goes forth by the middle <HI>Scoene.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Though I am but a waiting-uman, I haue more
wit then to believe this is earnest. As if I did not know
them to bee as arrant Cowards, as a Justices Clerke or
Gentleman Vsher can be; and deserve rather to be whipt
by a Satire, then rewarded for their valours with the
love of a gentleuman. But Mr. <HI>Spruce</HI> doe you meane to
fight?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spruce.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, and kill him too. I feare nothing but death
and the Gallowes; from which you may save me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>As how? the meanes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spruce.</SPEAKER>
<P>Begg me, I say beg me. Let not my good parts
be made unusefull by an untimely turne at <HI>Tyburne.</HI> Me
thinks I see the pittifull spectators condoling me. The
fish-wives drowning their dead soles with salt water from
their eyes; the Oyster-wives weeping for me in most la∣mentable
pickle. An hundred Chamber-maids running
stark mad, and as many more falling into the greene sick∣nesse
with longing for me. Begg me therefore (I say) re∣solve
to begg me, and make great hast. It is my feare a∣bove
death, that otherwise some rich Citty Heyre will
prevent you. Resolve therefore to be the first that shall
begg me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>As I am a Gentleuman Mr. <HI>Spruce,</HI> if you kill
him fairely in a duell; and upon no base advantage I'le
doe it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spruce.</SPEAKER>
<P>Confirme it then with a kisse, and inspire an
<HI>Herculean</HI> valour into me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>By no meanes at this time. I'le kisse you at the
gallowes. My Lady.</P>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="scene">
<PB N="20" REF="14"/>
<HEAD>The fourth Scoene.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>LADY</HI> and <HI>DOROTHY</HI> by the middle <HI>Scoene.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>You see how my obedient youth</L>
<L>Hath j<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>yn'd it selfe with an unequall mate;</L>
<L>You ag<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d father, onely to satisfie</L>
<L>The Provident will of Parents. Doe you so.</L>
<L>Fortune hath made me now your Mother.</L>
<L>Had nature don't, my care could not be greater,</L>
<L>Nor more my providence to dispose your good.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doroth.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mother, the duty which I owe my Father</L>
<L>You (being his) must share: and this expression</L>
<L>Of more then common love, I must repay</L>
<L>With more then common gratitude.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ther. tell me,</L>
<L>Now time hath given your age perfection;</L>
<L>Your roses are full blowne, and fit for gathering,</L>
<L>Doe you not long for a husband?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not with much earnestnes: I have as yet</L>
<L>No passionate desires; as yet no breath</L>
<L>Poyson'd with <HI>Hyperbolicall</HI> flatteries</L>
<L>Hath courted my poore beauty; no deep vowes</L>
<L>Have paid idolatrous sacrifice of service</L>
<L>To my faire hand, whose whitenes if but kis't</L>
<L>Can purifie a soule. Beleeve me yet</L>
<L>The ma<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'s a stranger to my knowing memory</L>
<L>That ever said he lov'd me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>But take heed:</L>
<L>There are a sort of fond effeminate men,</L>
<L>Deepe studied in discoursive complement,</L>
<L>That many times will wast more ayery language</L>
<L>To take a sollemne leave, then would make up</L>
<L>A Citty Oratour.</L>
<L>Beware that no such oyle-tongu'd amorist</L>
<L><PB N="21" REF="14"/>
Sigh forth his passions in thy credulous eares,</L>
<L>And captivate thy weaknesse. 'Tis their practise</L>
<L>To glory in diversity of Mistrisses:</L>
<L>And when one frownes or chides their over-daring</L>
<L>With a repulse, will not stick to revenge it</L>
<L>With a foule defamation of her honour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Neither can a Gentleuman be in love now and
then out she is censur'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La</SPEAKER>
<L>Let not thine eares drink in their <HI>Rhetorick</HI> charms,</L>
<L>Lest they bewitch thy glorious understanding</L>
<L>To dote on their pretences, which perhaps</L>
<L>Shall be chast love for it's Creations end:</L>
<L>When but their c<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>vetous hopes preferre a portion</L>
<L>Before your beauty, birth or education;</L>
<L>And yet perhaps there is disparitie</L>
<L>'Twixt lower fortunes, and their weake desert.</L>
<L>Deceit's a cunning baud, and many times</L>
<L>Makes vertue prostitute it selfe to misery.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doroth.</SPEAKER>
<L>There is a power</L>
<L>Call'd Fate, which doth necessitate the will,</L>
<L>And makes desire obedient to it's rule.</L>
<L>All the resisting faculties of reason,</L>
<L>Prevention, feare and jealousie are weake</L>
<L>To disanull what in it's firme decrees</L>
<L>Is once determin'd. Yet my heart is free;</L>
<L>Vnbounded by the stricter limits of</L>
<L>Particular affection: so I'le keepe it.</L>
<L>No proud ingratefull man shall ever triumph</L>
<L>O're the captiv'd sweets of my Virgin love.</L>
<L>Nor a vain-glorious gull that offers service</L>
<L>To every noted beauty, boast my favour.</L>
<L>I'le cloath my thoughts in humorous observation;</L>
<L>And if on any that sollicits love</L>
<L>I fixe a liking, I'le refer my selfe</L>
<L>To what is destin'd for me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>The resolution's noble; I commend it.</L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="scene">
<PB N="22" REF="15"/>
<HEAD>The fifth Scoene.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>LITTLEVVORD</HI> and <HI>Mris. TONGALL,</HI> by
the middle <HI>Scoene.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<P>Welcome Mistris <HI>Tongall;</HI> welcome. You are
the onely company in the neighbour-hood. A Ladie can
ill be without you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tong.</SPEAKER>
<P>This Gentleman Madame, whom I presume to
commend to your Ladiships acquaintance, is of worthy
birth and education: the <HI>Littlewords</HI> are not moderne; be∣sides
their Auncestors were great Philosophers.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>And the latter great fooles.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tong.</SPEAKER>
<P>Goe, and talke to her. I'le tell your Ladiship a
strange thing of the <HI>Little-words.</HI> In seven generations
there was but one girle, and shee dyed an infant. Contra∣riwise
of the <HI>Tongalls</HI> there's but one man left, that's my
Husband, and he's a Lawyer: now your Ladiship knowes
hee gets nothing but wenches. Speake to her Mr. <HI>Little∣word.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is the Gentleman of so good education?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tong.</SPEAKER>
<P>Extraordinary Madame; hee's a wit. I would
my <HI>Iynny</HI> were worthy of him, he should seeke no further.
I pray Mr. <HI>Littleword</HI> speake to her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<P>Can he Poetise Mris. <HI>Tongall?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tong.</SPEAKER>
<P>Excellently Madame; hee hath things in print.
His next dedication shall be to your Ladiship. Why doe
you not goe and talke to her?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<P>What estate hath he?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tong.</SPEAKER>
<P>Five hundred a yeare present possession, more in
reversion. This Gentleman, Mris. <HI>Dorothy,</HI> is my friend,
and desire's to bee your servant. I have made way now,
why doe you not speake to her? I am bold to commend
him to your liking.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray you Mris. <HI>Tongall,</HI> what wages takes he?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="23" REF="15"/>
<SPEAKER>Tong.</SPEAKER>
<P>You mistake Mris. <HI>Dorothy;</HI> 'tis your love hee
would serve you for.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doro.</SPEAKER>
<P>That's a cold reward; a Livery would keepe
him warmer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ton.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fie, that you will not speake to her. And how
doth your Ladiship like an old man?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<P>A cold bed fellow. But Religion and Conscience.
Now 'tis done I must love him. Would hee were not
jealous.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tong.</SPEAKER>
<P>None are so confident (Madame) as cuckolds.
But your Ladiships knowne vertue will soone put out the
eyes of his suspition. Speake to her Mr. <HI>Littleword.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>I would not now for all the Sacke in <HI>Spaine</HI> my
loving humour were upon mee. This dumb Gentleman
would make me forsweare the qualitie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dorot.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sure Mris. <HI>Tongall</HI> your friend would make an
excellent midwife; he can keepe secrets.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tong.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis his modestie Mris. <HI>Dorothy.</HI> Blesse mee that
you would not speake to her.</P>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="6" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>The sixth Scoene.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>IERKER, ARTLOVE</HI> and <HI>IEFFREY,</HI>
by the middle <HI>Scoene.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ierk.</SPEAKER>
<P>Madame, I am bold to commend this Gentleman,
who will deserve your acquaintance.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Artl.</SPEAKER>
<P>As far as my power will extend to expression.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>You are welcome Mr. <HI>Ierker</HI> and this Gentleman,
and shall bee whilst your visits are seasonable. But you
know I have a jealous husband.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ierk.</SPEAKER>
<P>There are medicines to cure it Madame.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ieffr.</SPEAKER>
<P>May not I salute the Ladie Cousin?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ierk.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis but courtesie and manners.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ieffr.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am bold with your Ladiships lip.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis marvell you blush not. So bold and so young!
<PB N="24" REF="16"/>
By that time you come to your full growth pretty Gentle∣man,
you'l make up the number of the ten Worthies.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ieffr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Madame, I am neither Infidell, Iew<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> nor good
Christian; though I am little, I dare be your L<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ships
Champion in an active skirmish.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tong.</SPEAKER>
<P>This 'tis to be backward: you'l never thrive in
any thing unles you are more forward. Lose such an op∣portunity
with not speaking to her!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<P>Secretarie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Madame.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<P>Goe, and direct the Cooke.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>SVSAN</HI> goes forth by the middle <HI>Scoene.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Artl.</SPEAKER>
<L>How on a sodaine my resolves are numb'd,</L>
<L>And frozen into silence, that confirmes</L>
<L>The first distrust of my knowne indeservings,</L>
<L>I dare not speake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doroth.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shall I have another dumb servant! Are you
not well Sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Artl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well Ladie! yes. Health it selfe</L>
<L>Is a disease in others, if compar'd</L>
<L>With th' absolute state of mine. Where you are present</L>
<L>Sicknesse can have no power over frailtie.</L>
<L>The b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ames which you<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> bright e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es shoot, purifie</L>
<L>Th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> most infectious ayr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. Your words distill</L>
<L>A B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re more pr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cious then that Miracle</L>
<L>The <HI>Chymicks</HI> d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eame of.</L>
<L>At distance I have <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ften seene your beauty;</L>
<L>And thence receiv'd a fire, whose quickning flames</L>
<L>Did animate my soule, that else was earthy,</L>
<L>A lump of passive dulnesse; now 'tis active:</L>
<L>And if you please to cherish it, shall pay</L>
<L>All it's derivative abilities</L>
<L>Vnto your lowest service.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>You too much flatter my unworthinesse:</L>
<L>And in that likewise derogate</L>
<L>From your owne fulnesse of admired merit.</L>
<L><PB N="25" REF="16"/>
Th' vnskilful'st <HI>Physiognomist</HI> may read</L>
<L>In your bright forehead, and your formes exactnesse,</L>
<L>A man repleat with all perfections.</L>
<L>Whose very superfluities might be</L>
<L>Additions to the barren worths of others.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ierk.</SPEAKER>
<L>And can there be greater disparity?</L>
<L>Would it not seeme a Prodigie in nature,</L>
<L>To have greene Summer with her rose-crown'd head</L>
<L>Kisse the white isicles from Winters beard?</L>
<L>Extinguish her bright fires in his cold bosome?</L>
<L>Madame, I know your sportive Youth desires</L>
<L>A more proportion'd mixture. Come, let's trie.</L>
<L>Fire put to fire increaseth active Flames;</L>
<L>Contraries dull each other with confusion:</L>
<L>Such are the frozen kisses of your Husband,</L>
<L>Vnto your warme delights—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Art.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ladie, if any worth appeare in me</L>
<L>It must derive it's fulnesse from your liking:</L>
<L>Had I in<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>u<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'d into me all the excellence</L>
<L>Of those <HI>Heroicks</HI> whom the Poets fain'd;</L>
<L>Were I made up with all Perfections</L>
<L>That Fiction ever painted, to expresse</L>
<L>Desert in freshest colours;</L>
<L>Vnlesse you cal'd it worth, 'twere but a subject</L>
<L>For base contempt, though popular admiration</L>
<L>Gav't divine Attributes. Since you commend</L>
<L>The faculties your whitenesse must dispose of—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ieffr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Aske your husband leave! by this hand I would
not aske an Alderman leave to Cuckold him. So he might
take example from a Citty kinde one, whose Wife long'd
to kisse a Lord: upon which he grew so proud for being
exalted above the rest of his neighbours, that he would
suffer none to Cuckold him ever after but Lords.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dorot.</SPEAKER>
<L>By no meanes Sir.</L>
<L>Wrong not your judgement, which must needs bee ab∣solute.</L>
<L>The choice of me</L>
<L><PB N="26" REF="17"/>
Is too inferiour to your richer value.</L>
<L>The <HI>Cyprian</HI> Queene had shee but seene your face,</L>
<L>Would ne're have dy'd the roses with her blood,</L>
<L>Wept on their palenesse for <HI>Adonis</HI> losse:</L>
<L>But circled in a ring of all her graces</L>
<L>Court your celestiall forme upon the bosome</L>
<L>Of some more fragrant <HI>Tempe.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Artl.</SPEAKER>
<L>She mocks me sure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did <HI>Syrens</HI> heare your voice they would give o're</L>
<L>Their own malicious charms: and through the witchcraft</L>
<L>Of it's more powerfull musicke, rage with madnesse:</L>
<L>Leaving their proper element to dye</L>
<L>In the pursuit of sweeter melody.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Artl.</SPEAKER>
<L>This grosse flattery, Ladie,</L>
<L>Commends your wit, rather then your good nature.</L>
<L>My heart is a plaine heart, and my desires</L>
<L>Are truly vertuous, not to be contemn'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fie, Mr. <HI>Ierker!</HI> besides the words incivility,
I did not expect such absurditie in a reputed wit. Could
you not haue couch'd it better; shall I have leave to doe
your Ladiship a piece of night service; or so. Come,
come, forbeare these wicked sollicits, or I shall disclaime
the promise of my favours reversion when my old Hus∣band
die's, if nature be not mercilesse, and I goe first.</P>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="7" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>The seventh Scoene.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Sir GENEROVS WORTHY,</HI> and young <HI>WORTHY,</HI>
by the middle <HI>SCOENE.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Gen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha! what's here! Courtship on all hands?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Husband.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dorot.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Father, and my Brother.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Worth.</SPEAKER>
<P>I like not this.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Gen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mr. <HI>Ierker,</HI> you are welcome, I hope; having
fail'd in his old, hee hath not a new suit; that as I made
<PB N="27" REF="17"/>
her a Ladie, shee should bestow an hornourable Crest up∣on
mee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ierk.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let his jealousie conster it into truth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<P>He shall neuer be but a Vnicorne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ierk.</SPEAKER>
<P>Madame, however I appeare in my wildnesse, I
shall continue to your Ladiship in my first desires. So with
this tribute of my devotion.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Artl.</SPEAKER>
<P>I would first kisse your hand.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dorot.</SPEAKER>
<P>My lip being too unworthy.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tong.</SPEAKER>
<P>I take my leave Madame.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<P>Farewell Mistris <HI>Tongall.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Gen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Son, schoole your Sister. Come with me Wife.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ex.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Wor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sister, I can but wonder much, that you</L>
<L>Should make your selfe the object of their Courtship,</L>
<L>Who beare perhaps but th' empty names of Gentlemen,</L>
<L>Without the reall fulnesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doroth.</SPEAKER>
<L>What meane you (Brother) by this intro∣duction?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Wor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sister, to take the priviledge of discretion,</L>
<L>And schoole your ignorant courtesie, that upon</L>
<L>The shadowes and appearances of Men</L>
<L>Confer your favours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dorot.</SPEAKER>
<L>Brother, you may pretend your love</L>
<L>In this distrust; but 'tis an ill expression.</L>
<L>Thinke not my judgement subject to such weaknesse,</L>
<L>That I can build a faith on Complements,</L>
<L>Or (with rash passion) run into an error.</L>
<L>Nothing but knowne desert shall tye my thoughts</L>
<L>To a staid liking, if I may distinguish it.</L>
<L>And when my choice is fixt, it shall be such</L>
<L>As your fraternall love must not dispute.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Wor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sister, my counsel's milde.</L>
<L>Nor would I have you violent in defence</L>
<L>Of a suspected folly. Guilt is aptest</L>
<L>To make excuse. But if your resolution</L>
<L>Be bent thus wilfully to persist in actions</L>
<L><PB N="28" REF="18"/>
Of fear'd dishonour, be assur'd my Spirit</L>
<L>Shall rage with such an anger, playes ne're painted.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dorot.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dishonour Brother, I have a spirit too,</L>
<L>That scornes as much an Act of foule dishonour,</L>
<L>As you, or any Masculine pretender</L>
<L>To noble Vertues. Guilt is aptest still</L>
<L>To be suspitious. If a maid be free</L>
<L>In her discourse, and courteous entertainment,</L>
<L>She straight is censur'd. But let a man appeare</L>
<L>Stuck fu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l of apish Courtship; light, inconstant,</L>
<L>As talkative as Parrats, that are taught</L>
<L>A voyces imitation; one that courts</L>
<L>Every tam'd beauty with a seeming zeale;</L>
<L>As if his soules devotion were restrain'd</L>
<L>Onely to her Divinitie; this man's call'd</L>
<L>A well-bred complementall Gentleman.</L>
<L>Mens greatest follies, if compar'd with ours,</L>
<L>Are vertues, fit for our imitation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Wor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sister, your <HI>Satyr</HI> smart's not:</L>
<L>The lashes reach not me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dorot.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are but suppositions Brother.</L>
<L>And pray suppose the Gentleman that seem'd</L>
<L>To court my beauty, were indeed a man,</L>
<L>Not guilded imperfections; one whose words</L>
<L>Were full of weighty judgement, not mere sound;</L>
<L>Whose reall vertues did beget an envie,</L>
<L>Perhaps an emulation in all others;</L>
<L>And from the freedome of his richer minde</L>
<L>He gave himselfe and them to be my servants;</L>
<L>What gratitude in me might equall this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Wor.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know you are free.</L>
<L>And rather then a complementall servant</L>
<L>Should be discourag'd in his serious wantonnesse,</L>
<L>You'l give it countenance to make him bold</L>
<L>In's amorous pursuit; perhaps to th' impudence</L>
<L>Of a lascivious charge upon your modestie;</L>
<L>Because you scorne ingratitude.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="29" REF="18"/>
<SPEAKER>Dorot.</SPEAKER>
<L>Brother, did not the ties</L>
<L>Of love and nature check my forward aptnesse,</L>
<L>I'de tell you y'are not noble, and suspect</L>
<L>Whether your mind hold that derivative goodnesse</L>
<L>Which generous bloud communicates, to suspect</L>
<L>Her re<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>olute constancie whom you call Sister.</L>
<L>Thinke not your being a man prerogative</L>
<L>To be the onely Counsellor in manners</L>
<L>Brother, though to your person I am partiall.</L>
<L>Through confidence of your appearing vertue;</L>
<L>The generall vices noted in your sexe,</L>
<L>Such as with publique ostentation</L>
<L>You glory to be guiltie of, which in</L>
<L>Our very thoughts raise blushes—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Wor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sister no more.</L>
<L>Leaving these circumstantiall arguments,</L>
<L>Pray let a Fathers care and Brothers love</L>
<L>Commend him first whom you intend for Husband:</L>
<L>You'l finde us tyrants else. Nature is kind;</L>
<L>But if provokt, she hath a <HI>Tygers</HI> mind.</L>
<L>Ile finde him out and satisfie my selfe</L>
<L>How farre he is deserving.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Goes forth by the middle <HI>Scene.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dorot.</SPEAKER>
<L>How is our weaknes trodden and insulted on</L>
<L>By these imperious men! Aid me resolves</L>
<L>Against their threats and counsels, unlesse grounded</L>
<L>On stronger reasons then suspition.</L>
<L>As the pure Oare refin'd exceeds in value</L>
<L>Treble proportions of the courser drosse;</L>
<L>So true desert in Man an outward glosse.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Goes forth by the middle <HI>Scoene.</HI></STAGE>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="3" TYPE="act">
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<PB N="30" REF="19"/>
<HEAD>Act. 3. Scoen. 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>DOROTHY</HI> and <HI>SVSAN,</HI> in
the <HI>BALCONE.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come Mris <HI>Dorothy;</HI> here's a Moone would
make a great bellied uman long for greene cheefe. Me
thinks 'tis pleasant taking the ayre by Moone-shine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dorot.</SPEAKER>
<P>But 'tis not so healthfull The night infects the
ayre with unwholsome vapours.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>A figg for these Physicall observations. I have
knowne a Doctors prescriptions cast down a Gentleuman
for three quarters of a yeare. But if ever I lie under any of
them for the greene sicknes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dorot.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fie upon thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why I doe not meane naughtines. But what
doe you thinke made me so earnest to have you hither?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doroth.</SPEAKER>
<P>Some wanton humour. You have d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>unke a
cup of Sacke, and want a handsome Ge<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>leman to bee in
love with.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>No such matter. Ile not drinke a drop more till
towards supper. I brought you to see a Duell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doroth.</SPEAKER>
<P>Blesse me; betwixt whom?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Ladies Gentle-man, and Mr. <HI>Warrant.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doroth.</SPEAKER>
<P>They are unequally weapon'd. Mr. <HI>Spruce,</HI>
though hee be a Tailor weares a—the foolish rime runs
in my head. I had almost said a dagger, but 'tis a sword;
and my Fathers Clerke hath onely his inkhorne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>And that's a terrible one. But I saw the Cutler
bring him a sword; I saw it naked, which was enough
to fright many a gentleuman. I saw him trie it on a bar of
iron in the kitchin; and many more fearfull preparations.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="31" REF="19"/>
<SPEAKER>Dorot.</SPEAKER>
<P>But will not you prevent them?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>By no means, unlesse there were more dan∣ger.
'Twill be mirth for this twelve-month, if our eyes
(through this imperfect Moone-light) can but reach the
sight of them. What confident daring will be betwixt
them at some great distance?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dorot.</SPEAKER>
<P>And what's their quarrell?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>The love of a Gentleuman, I assure you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dorot.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your selfe perhaps.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>No otherwise indeed. My beauty is the object
of their valour. The Combatants will enter presently. The
Knight of the <HI>Inkhorue,</HI> and the Knight of the <HI>Spanish
Needle.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Both affecting the Lady of the <HI>Closet.</HI> But Mris.
<HI>Secretary,</HI> what if my Lady Mothers Chamber-maid and
<HI>Ioane</HI> in the Kitchen were here?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>For you to make them Ladies, as you have done
me. Indeed they might serve by Moone-light; the day
perhaps would discover a greasie Gentry.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dorot.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fie; now you forget your selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis ordinary for a waiting-Gentleuman but
newly made a Lady to forget her selfe. But see, I am pre∣vented
from proceeding. Let us observe.</P>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>The second Scoene.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>WARRANT,</HI> and a little after him <HI>SPRVCE,</HI>
by the middle <HI>SCOENE.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warr.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis a good sword; it cost me two pieces. No
matter. Many a mans death hath cost more at the Phy∣sitians.
Who would be affraid to kill a man; when hee is
sure of his pardon?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dorot.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hee is now in some deepe meditation of your
beautie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>See Mistris, there's the other.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="32" REF="20"/>
<SPEAKER>Spruce.</SPEAKER>
<P>That sure is <HI>Warrant.</HI> I'le goe this way. It
shall never be said I went after a man to kill him, though
I am confident Mistris <HI>Secretary</HI> will begg me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dorot.</SPEAKER>
<P>They goe contrary wayes. Wee shall not see
the fight. They meane to meete and end it at the <HI>An∣tipodes.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warr.</SPEAKER>
<P>But what should I thinke of killing him? I
know hee dare as well take the wall of a drunken Consta∣ble,
or justle a Buffe-coat leading a wench, as meet me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Me thinks I perceive them stand.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spruce.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, yes; 'tis <HI>Warrant:</HI> I smell him hitherto.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is not that <HI>Spruce?</HI> certainly 'tis hee. Me thinks
I see him tremble hitherto. Hee dare not come neere me;
and I scorne to goe to him to kill him: It may hinder my
pardon. Therefore he shall assault me first.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dorot.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, they are fixt. Hath not feare congeal'd
them into stones?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Dissolv'd them rather into gelley.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warr.</SPEAKER>
<P>That some good fellow would but come and
beat the cowardly Rascall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spruce.</SPEAKER>
<P>That some Sharke would come now and take
away his hat or cloake.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now could I fancy in my imagination what they
say. Mr. <HI>Warrant.</HI> O that I had this Coward <HI>Spruce</HI> here:
I would dismember him; and then what Gentleuman
would care a rush for him? Now Mr. <HI>Spruce</HI> hath studien
the <HI>Arcadia.</HI> He sayes. Oh that I had this <HI>Warrant</HI> here
It would cut him into <HI>atomes;</HI> that wheresoever the Sun
shines, the <HI>trophces</HI> of my renowned victorie might bee
visible.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aarr.</SPEAKER>
<P>That he would but come a little neerer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spruce.</SPEAKER>
<P>That hee were but within twice my swords
length.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warr.</SPEAKER>
<P>I would I had but a leg or an arme of him, since
he will not come, that I may kill him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spr.</SPEAKER>
<P>That I had but his head here; how I would shave it.</P>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<PB N="33" REF="20"/>
<HEAD>The third Scoene.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>RALPH</HI> and <HI>DOESON</HI> by the left <HI>Scoene.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>This is the vertue of Sack boy. Who would
toile in durt for whay and butter-milke, or the windie
juice of Pome-waters upon Sundayes? Now could I be as
valiant as—nothing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dobs.</SPEAKER>
<P>I could fight with an Army of <HI>Polecats,</HI> so they
were not Women.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>I could take the wall of three times three Tay∣lors,
though in the morning, and at a Bakers stall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dobs.</SPEAKER>
<P>That were a way to have thy skin bodkind full
of ilet holes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>If I should throw downe three or foure postes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dobs.</SPEAKER>
<P>What then?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>What then! why, I would not stay to take
them up.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who are these? observe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>Give me an armour of Sack; I am shot-free.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dobs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whilst my Master paye's the reckoning.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mistris <HI>Dorothy,</HI> I have fasten'd on a designe for
rare sport. My friends.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dorot.</SPEAKER>
<P>Will you talke to strangers in the street?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>What say you pretty paire of Wag-tailes? doe
you want Play-mates?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Will you doe a courtesie for a Gentleuman?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>Within dores, or without?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>You seeme to be valiant.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dobs.</SPEAKER>
<P>They that trie us shall finde our mettall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Perceive you not two men yonder in severall
places?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wee see somthing, but they may as well be
flockes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>For any manhood that's in them. If you will but
<PB N="34" REF="21"/>
beat them a little, besides a Gentleumans thankes, some o∣ther
reward shall attend it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>How are we sure they are Cowards?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>You may trust the word of a Gent<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>euman.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dobs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come, come, thou standest doubting like a cow∣ardly
foo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e, These may bee Gentlewoemen of good fa∣shion,
and apt to take fire at valour. Who knowes what
preferment's neere us? We have persons.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ral.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why then forwards: call upon sack, <HI>Dobson,</HI> sack.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who are these come towards me? my courage
begins to have an ague.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spruce.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who may these be? my wish (I hope) some
good fellowes to rob him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dobs.</SPEAKER>
<P>What was our Commission <HI>Ralph?</HI> to beat them,
and not kill them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>To kill them and not hurt them? Call upon
Sacke, <HI>Dobson:</HI> I begin to be affraid. I can perceive his
sword; he shakes it fearefully.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dobs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Draw thine-then; and sack, sack the walles
of <HI>Troy.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warr.</SPEAKER>
<P>The rogue <HI>Spruce</HI> hath sent them to beate mee.
'Tis so. I must shift for my selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sirrah, thou man of feare and trembling. Call
upon Sacke, <HI>Dobson.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas, what meane you Gentlemen?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not so gentle neither. Wee are fiery furious,
and command thee in the name of Sack, resigne thy wea∣pon,
and submit to be corrected by our valour.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Kinde Gentlemen, I hope you'l not kill me. I'le
doe any thing, rather then be kill'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>A handsome beating shall asswage our fury.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sweet Gentlemen, I'le doe any thing rather then
be beaten.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spruce.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis so; they are robbing him, and I scorne to
aid him. Teach the rogue to be such a coward: he might
have come to me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="35" REF="21"/>
<SPEAKER>Dobs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Are you prepar'd Sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mercifull Gentlemen; I have some money, a
Cloake and a good Beaver: I'le give you all, and forgive
you too, so you'l not beat me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dobs.</SPEAKER>
<P>This was beyond our expectation.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>Our mercy may bee brought to a composition.
But should we be pittifull, could you be content, since you
cannot fight in your owne defence, to lye in our defence.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warr.</SPEAKER>
<P>I'le say or sweare any thing, rather then be kill'd
or beaten.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>That we did beat you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warr.</SPEAKER>
<P>That you left mee dead. I'le lye at a Surgeons
these two moneths; and pretend that my skull was bro∣ken
in twelve places: that halfe my braines were putri∣fied
and taken out. I'le be mad all my life after to con∣firme
people in the beliefe of it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>Depart then, and praise us.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, at the gallowes. I'le have you hang'd for
ro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ing me: I shall teach you to attempt any thing on a
Ju<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>ces Clerke.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Goes forth by the right <HI>Scoene.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay: pray you stay a little longer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dorot.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am weary; wee'l imagine the rest done. I'le
send my Brother forth to make them friends.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt from the <HI>Balcone.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spruce.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis done sure. Now will I home, proclaime
him a coward, and triumph. Ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l doe they way-lay mee!
the rogue hath hi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'d them to beat or rob me. An ague of
feare is upon me. Now could I wish my selfe transform'd
into a beast, and have foure legs. These two which have
beene my most usefull members will surely faile.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sirrah, you Raskall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spruce.</SPEAKER>
<P>You mistake Sir, I am a Gentleman Vsher.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then thou abuser of wit and good cloathes, be
mannerly, and uncover to thy betters.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="36" REF="22"/>
<SPEAKER>Spruce.</SPEAKER>
<P>I hope Gentlemen you d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e not meane to rob
me? Trust me, I have no money, but a few farthings of
my Ladies to give poore people.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>We will be satisfied with a small diminution of
your plentifull Wardrobe. Wee know you have more
Cloakes and Beavers at home.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spruce.</SPEAKER>
<P>No I protest Gentlemen. I have but this onely
case for my Carkasse: and 'twill not be quite paid for til
the next quarter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dobs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why then Sir, we will beat you handsomly, and
that shall allay our fury.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spruce.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay kinde Gentlemen, I had rather stand to my
Ladies bountie, then be beaten.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why then thanke our mercy and depart, whilst
we like honest theeves share our booty.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spruce.</SPEAKER>
<P>And I find out the Constable.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Goes forth by the right <HI>Scoene.</HI></STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>The fourth Scoene.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>ARTLOVE</HI> by the left <HI>Scoene.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Artl.</SPEAKER>
<L>How glorious shews <HI>heaven</HI> with trembling lights</L>
<L>Sparkling their distant beames! The full orb'd Moone</L>
<L>Borne on nights dewie wings, rides in her <HI>Sphoere;</HI></L>
<L>And throwes the shine which from her brothers rayes.</L>
<L>She borrowes to illuminate the earth</L>
<L>Through thinner ayre, where no condensed vapours</L>
<L>Are interpos'd to let her piercing eye</L>
<L>From seeing that which she gives sight to. Yet</L>
<L>My heart is wrapt in clouds of leaden sadnesse.</L>
<L>Love is not that in me which others feigne it.</L>
<L>I dreame not of delights; my busie fancie</L>
<L>Presents no fabulous heaven. A hell of torment</L>
<L>Darken's my mind's bright faculties; and reason
suffers it selfe to be ecclips'd by passion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="37" REF="22"/>
<SPEAKER>Dobs</SPEAKER>
<P>Now we'e are enter'd <HI>Ralph.</HI> what if wee made
this our professi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n? many a one lives by it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>And many a one is hang'd for it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Artl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oft have these instruments of heavens influence</L>
<L>Seene my contemplative watchings;</L>
<L>When with profound and an unwearied search</L>
<L>I have scan'd the causes of their great effects;</L>
<L>And waded through the most inscrutable secrets</L>
<L>Both of the mediate and immediate nature▪</L>
<L>But comming once to read a Womans face,</L>
<L>There were so many heavens, that every thought</L>
<L>In me, requir'd a severall understanding,</L>
<L>To give each severall grace a severall name,</L>
<L>And definition.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dobs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou art affraid of the gallowes?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not much of the gallowes without a hangman.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Artl.</SPEAKER>
<L>The <HI>Chaos</HI> and the earth were loves first Parents;</L>
<L>And yet the child did give the Parents forme.</L>
<L>What Riddles are in nature!</L>
<L>Man's a disorder'd Masse, a meere confusion</L>
<L>Of rude, inanimate sense and understanding.</L>
<L>Vntill inspir'd with loves diviner soule.</L>
<L>The sense is tir'd, unlesse it varye's objects.</L>
<L>Knowledge would be finite, were not the mind</L>
<L>Delighted with diversitie.</L>
<L>But love's a subject for eternall studie;</L>
<L>And one faire booke preserv'd so, a full library.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dobson.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am resolv'd; I'le nor spare man, woman nor
child, whilst the sack works.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>For women and children let me alone: if I fall
upon the one, Ile soone get the other.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Artl.</SPEAKER>
<L>What fabulous errors learning is attended with!</L>
<L><HI>Plato's</HI> five Worlds; their sempiternitie;</L>
<L><HI>Pythagoras</HI> transmigration; and opinions</L>
<L>Judgement would blush to father. But a woman,</L>
<L>Did men contemplate such a one as I doe,</L>
<L><PB N="38" REF="23"/>
They'd Make her all those Worlds: and then include</L>
<L>All the fam'd excellence of former beauties</L>
<L>In her more perfect frame.</L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>The fifth Scoene.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter young <HI>WORTHY</HI> by the middle <HI>Scoene.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Wor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is't possible such shew of resolution</L>
<L>Should appeare in Cowards! I'le make them friends.</L>
<L>And that being done mine owne intentions</L>
<L>Must be pursu'd to finde that Gentleman</L>
<L>Courted my Sister. Love of all sorts bends</L>
<L>It selfe to courses for it's severall ends.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dobs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now for a daring Constable.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>Without his staffe of authoritie, or a fortifica∣tion
of Sack. A Constable may be valiant when hee com∣mands
others what he cannot doe himselfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Wor.</SPEAKER>
<P>What! my paire of valiant Cowards! friends
already.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dobs.</SPEAKER>
<P>How! Cowards! swallow that word, or it shall
choake thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. W.</SPEAKER>
<P>These fellowes have out-gone their Commission
and rob'd them. I was a wise man to come abroad with∣out
a sword.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hee hath never a sword. Sirrah, thou man of
presumption, that hast profan'd our incomparable valour,
redeeme thy forfeited life of our mercie with some gold
or silver pictures out of thy silken pockets.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Wor.</SPEAKER>
<P>They'l rob me too: Why, Gentlemen; silke
clothes have not money in them at all times.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>He lookes terribly <HI>Dobson.</HI> Call upon Sack.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dobs.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will cleave him at one stroke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. W.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doe you meane to murther a Gentleman?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Artl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Murder a Gentleman the voyce came thence.</L>
<L>Ile rescue him, though danger and destruction</L>
<L><PB N="39" REF="23"/>
Met me with open mouths. Villaines, desist.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. W.</SPEAKER>
<P>You have done a benefit I must acknowledge.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Artl.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's to reward it sir; from which base ends</L>
<L>Good actions should be free. I'de gladly heare</L>
<L>A short relation of the Accident.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dobs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why dost thou quake so <HI>Ralph?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralh.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why dost thou tremble so <HI>Dobson?</HI> I dare bee
whipt if these bee not some kin to the Gentle woman that
sent us hither from the thing at yonder house.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. W.</SPEAKER>
<P>Were you sent to rob or kill me?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dobs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas Gentlemen, we are very ingrums.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>Meere Country Animals. Wee have valour to
steale a May-pole, or rob the Parso<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s Hens-nest: but to
kill a man as far from our intents or daring, as pittie from
an Executioner, or bashfulnesse from a Jingo.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. W</SPEAKER>
<P>Forbeare the rest. This affords me matter: Re∣turne
to that house, there leave your bootie and receive
your reward; onely this I'le keepe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>With all our hearts: wee had rather any body
should have them, then the hangman both them and us
for them. Come <HI>Dobson,</HI> we have got the money yet; and
a little sack will animate us againe. My soul's under foot;
I must raise it: But if ever I quarrell againe by Moone∣shine
unlesse I am drunk, valour forsake me.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Goe forth by the left <HI>Scoene.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. W.</SPEAKER>
<L>Blest Accident! 'tis surely the same.</L>
<L>After a stricter view, my memory</L>
<L>Vnlesse it erres, tells me I have seene your person</L>
<L>Before this at my fathers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Artl.</SPEAKER>
<P>If you are the son of Sir <HI>Generous Worthy.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. H.</SPEAKER>
<L>It was the blessing</L>
<L>Nature and Fortune did bestow on me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Art.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is indeed a blessing, when the vertues</L>
<L>Of noble Races are hereditary;</L>
<L>And doe derive themselves from th' imitation</L>
<L>Of vertuous Ancestours. You have a faire Sister.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="40" REF="24"/>
<SPEAKER>Y. Wor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Her beaurie is not worth your commenda∣tions.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Artl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your modestie is too severe</L>
<L>In your restraint from praising her pure excellence,</L>
<L>Which should be Poets studie; not with fiction,</L>
<L>And common figures, but diviner attributes:</L>
<L>Then they must call it nothing but it selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. W.</SPEAKER>
<P>Have I found you? I shall search you deeper.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Artl.</SPEAKER>
<L>The subjects weight would make a Poem weighty;</L>
<L>And take away the imputation</L>
<L>Which seeming solidnesse would throw upon't</L>
<L>Of a light fancie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. W.</SPEAKER>
<P>It seemes you love my Sister?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Artl.</SPEAKER>
<L>He were a Divell did not love such goodnesse.</L>
<L>It is the onely vertue: frailty boasts of,</L>
<L>To love faire sensuall objects: but my soule</L>
<L>Hath noted inward beauty in her mind,</L>
<L>Which makes me glory (though it be presumption)</L>
<L>That I doe love her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. W.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cal't not presumption sir, you doe deserve her,</L>
<L>In that you have indear'd me for my life</L>
<L>Who am her Brother. And I commend you wit,</L>
<L>Which I presume my Sisters love hath whetted.</L>
<L>'Twas a quaint Plott. Were th' Actors here againe,</L>
<L>I'd pay their wages.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Artl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your Riddle needs some <HI>Oedipus</HI> to solve it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. W.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why sir, ridiculous fables</L>
<L>May sometimes serve for imitation.</L>
<L>Though twere a meere appointment in this rescue,</L>
<L>To shew your love and valour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Artl.</SPEAKER>
<L>What base suspition</L>
<L>Poysons his jealous thoughts! 'Tis injurie</L>
<L>Beyond all patience.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. W.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas sir, you are mov'd?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Art.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, to an indignation, whose just heat</L>
<L>Burnes me almost to rage. But there are charmes</L>
<L><PB N="41" REF="24"/>
And spels about you conjure downe my spirit.</L>
<L>You are her Brother.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Young. Wor.</SPEAKER>
<P>It seemes your guilt dare not denie the
truth?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Artl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dare not denie it!</L>
<L>Were thy hands armd with Thunder;</L>
<L>Hadst thou a <HI>Gorgons</HI> looke, wer't not her Brother,</L>
<L>Ring'd in the terror of a thousand Jibbets</L>
<L>And executioners, I have a point</L>
<L>Should finde thy hart out.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. W.</SPEAKER>
<L>But I must tell you sir,</L>
<L>Seldome high spirits that pursue their honours,</L>
<L>With earnest fllights, will stoop at weake respects:</L>
<L>But prey upon th' opinion of those men</L>
<L>That scan their actions; tearing their reputations</L>
<L>Out of suspitions bowels. Hee's not a Gentle man</L>
<L>Will not preserve his honour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Artl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your speech, Sir,</L>
<L>Savours of strange severity. My honour</L>
<L>Is that part of my selfe, without which</L>
<L>The man that's in me can have no subsisting.</L>
<L>Honour's the greatest of exteriour goods,</L>
<L>And must be still pursu'd as the reward</L>
<L>Due unto vertue, through the greatest dangers.</L>
<L>Yet fortitude is not the appetite</L>
<L>Of formidable things, nor inconsult</L>
<L>Rashnes; but vertue fighting for a truth;</L>
<L>Deriv'd from knowledge of distinguishing</L>
<L>Good or bad causes. Thinke me not a Coward</L>
<L>Because I am not rash: nor through defect</L>
<L>O<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> better counsell, doe not resist the force</L>
<L>Of will or passion; how soe're your jealousie</L>
<L>Proceeding from our better thoughts infection</L>
<L>Hath beene a provocation. And perhaps</L>
<L>The love I beare your Sister, will appeare</L>
<L>Your chiefest safety.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Wor.</SPEAKER>
<L>In an attempt of right</L>
<L><PB N="42" REF="25"/>
I have more safetie heere then your pr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>ences</L>
<L>Can arme m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> with But if you love my Sister,</L>
<L>It must be honourable and not wanton:</L>
<L>She will finde Champi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Artl.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must be honourable!</L>
<L>Those words include a doubt works strangely in me.</L>
<L>Love must not wrack my reputation.</L>
<L>Sir, I begin to scan the circumstance,</L>
<L>And conster your intention. You would trie me:</L>
<L>Bu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> your temptations have beene too abusive.</L>
<L>And now my resolution is prepar'd</L>
<L>To doe my credit justice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. W.</SPEAKER>
<P>You will not fight with me that am her Brother?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Artl.</SPEAKER>
<P>There's Magick in those words.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. W.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe presume my Sister will reward you</L>
<L>For these expressions. She is free to pay</L>
<L>Her servants promis'd wages; be it kisses,</L>
<L>Or any other dalliance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Artl.</SPEAKER>
<L>What a prophane breath from his blacke mouth flies,</L>
<L>Would poison all the idolatrous religions</L>
<L>That e're aw'd wicked mortalls.</L>
<L>He is not sure her brother, but some impostor,</L>
<L>That onely counterfeit's his worthier person,</L>
<L>I could be patient at the lye, or Coward,</L>
<L>Or any thing that can make passion violent.</L>
<L>But her bright honour staind's a cause of justice</L>
<L>To arme a Nation. Draw, if th'art a man;</L>
<L>And with the plea of valour, (if th'ast any)</L>
<L>Defend thy errours: Draw thy sword.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. W.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not against him that loves my Sister.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Artl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is my just anger mock't! love made ridiculous!</L>
<L>Draw; lest I make my selfe an Executioner.</L>
<L>And doe an act of justice on thy guilt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. W.</SPEAKER>
<L>Never against your bosome, where a spirit</L>
<L>So truely noble dwel's, that hath converted</L>
<L>All my faign'd jealousies to usefull love.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="43" REF="25"/>
<SPEAKER>Artl.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am confounded to amazement.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. W.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray reconcile all your distractions.</L>
<L>Let not the least distrust abuse your confidence</L>
<L>Of what I undertake. My Sister's yours,</L>
<L>If the advise of me that am her Brother,</L>
<L>And interested in her good or ill,</L>
<L>Can be prevailing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Artl</SPEAKER>
<L>Then requesting Sir,</L>
<L>That you'l presume no more upon the priviledge</L>
<L>Of that pure love I beare your vertuous Sister</L>
<L>T' admit a jealousie of any action,</L>
<L>Or thought of mine which tends not unto noblenesse,</L>
<L>Next unto her my bosome holds you deare,</L>
<L>And shall doe ever.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. W.</SPEAKER>
<L>So mine the like. Thus noble causes</L>
<L>Put fire into the spirits of full men.</L>
<L>Though sometimes seeming valour may arise</L>
<L>Through lust or wine, from hatefull cowardise.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Goe forth by the left <HI>Scoene.</HI></STAGE>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="4" TYPE="act">
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Act. 4. Scoen. 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>IERKER</HI> and <HI>IEFFREY,</HI> with a
Drawer, by the left <HI>Scoene.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BOY.</SPEAKER>
<P>ANon, anon Sir, by and by.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<P>Some more wine Boy. Is Mr. <HI>Art love</HI> return'd?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not yet Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ieffrey.</SPEAKER>
<P>Poore Gentleman; hee's complaining to the
Moone, or studying the event of his love in the Starres.
Mee thinks I could make a counterfeit expression of his
passions to the life.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="44" REF="26"/>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> Ministresse</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> light; dance <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> quall motions</L>
<L>On thy foure orbes; bu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> qu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ch thy paler fires</L>
<L>In Lovers teares, that <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> constancie</L>
<L>M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y so be drown'd. I would I were in love Cousin.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ierk.</SPEAKER>
<L>Before you are capable of it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ieffr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why Cousin, is it not defin'd to be youth's folly!</L>
<L>Indeed, all things in Youth are folly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ierk</SPEAKER>
<L>Not so Coz. all folly may be in Youth:</L>
<L>But many times 'tis mixt with grave discretion,</L>
<L>That tempers it to use; and make's it judgement</L>
<L>Equall if not exceeding that which Palseys</L>
<L>Hath almost shaken into a disease.</L>
<L>But why would you be in love Coz.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ieffr.</SPEAKER>
<P>That I might Poetize: you know 'tis the onely
dancing Master to teach the Art of Measures; though I
have knowne Poets scarce able to stand on their feet.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ierk.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then you would write <HI>Satyres</HI> Coz?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ieffr.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis your dancing conceit. But the Grinkums
Cousin cleaves not the feete.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> DASHER.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ierk.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mr. <HI>Dasher,</HI> this freenesse hath doubled the favor;
vizit us of your owne accord!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dash.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gentlemen my selfe, and all that depends on my
selfe, or on any thing that hath dependance on my selfe,
is at your service.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ieffr.</SPEAKER>
<P>I should desire your wife then.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dash.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sweet young Gentleman, you are the <HI>Epitome</HI> of
a faire body, and shall command the Commander of my
selfe and family. I will but present a glasse of Greeke
Sacke to the hands of a noble Lord, and returne to serve
you.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ierk.</SPEAKER>
<P>You have a vertue Sir, I could wish communi∣cated.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ieffr.</SPEAKER>
<P>What's that Cousin?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ierk.</SPEAKER>
<P>To cozzen Cousin.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="45" REF="26"/>
<SPEAKER>Ieffr.</SPEAKER>
<P>And would you learne it?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ierk.</SPEAKER>
<P>The <HI>Theorie,</HI> but not the <HI>Practicke.</HI> I converse
much in Tavernes; and the use should onely be a thrifty
prevention.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ieffr.</SPEAKER>
<P>As my observation hath taught me somthing in a
baudy house, where they cannot change money.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> DASHER.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dash.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now Gentlemen dispose of your seruant.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ierk.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeed Mr. <HI>Dasher</HI> our Wine's naught.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dash.</SPEAKER>
<P>How I naught I who drew it? name but your
drawer; he is punish't whilst you pronounce it. I'le not
keepe an offensive mouse that eats the crums under my ta∣ble,
but shall pay his life to doe you service.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ieffr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why Cousin, the Wine's good.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ierk.</SPEAKER>
<P>I onely gave him matter for a complement.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ieffr.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis pitty to abuse him that is so apt to abuse him∣selfe.
But what doe you muse on Cousin?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ierk.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am studdying a conceited health.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ieffr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why to the long standing of <HI>Banbury</HI> May-pole.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ierk.</SPEAKER>
<P>No Puritan will pledge that.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ieffr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, the Good-wives: they'l finde dancing a
more wholsome exercise for the body, then some of their
Doctrines for the Soule.</P>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>The second Scoene.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>ART LOVE</HI> and young <HI>WORTHY,</HI>
by the left <HI>Scoene.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ierk.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ar't come friend, and Mr. <HI>Worthy?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. W.</SPEAKER>
<P>Our mutuall loves.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> DASHER.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dash.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am bound to serve you Gentlemen, and I wish
my roofe were worthier, and my disordered houshould
order'd to your content.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="46" REF="27"/>
<SPEAKER>Artl.</SPEAKER>
<P>We are bound to thanke your readinesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dash.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gentlemen, your servant will send his servants
to wait upon you presently.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ierk.</SPEAKER>
<P>What accident brought you two together?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Artl.</SPEAKER>
<L>The mercie of my Startes: but what event</L>
<L>Their influence will direct, I cannot prophesie.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hee be carefull, hee's a <HI>Cynick</HI> noter</L>
<L>Of men and of their manners</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ierk.</SPEAKER>
<L>If he bite.</L>
<L>Here's that shall blunt his fangs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Artl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good friend be milde;</L>
<L>Temper thy passions here. Scandall may grow</L>
<L>From low foundations to an heighth of infamy.</L>
<L>Thou know'st my temperance doth not oft frequent</L>
<L>These publique places.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Wor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, the relation 'twixt a son and father</L>
<L>May make you jealous of my partiall nature.</L>
<L>Trust me, I never yet was so indulgent</L>
<L>To mine owne weaknesse, that untill my judgement</L>
<L>Had made a full distinguishment of causes,</L>
<L>I could bee violent in his defence</L>
<L>Farther then fisiall dutie; which sometimes</L>
<L>Hath stretcht it selfe to counsell and advice</L>
<L>Against suspition. For though your wild behaviour</L>
<L>In some particular actions might provoke him,</L>
<L>Shee whom new dutie makes me now call mother</L>
<L>Hath given large testimonie of her vertue</L>
<L>Even to satisfaction of all goodnesse;</L>
<L>Although his age (in other things judicious)</L>
<L>Cannot so easily admit beliefe,</L>
<L>And safer confidence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ierk.</SPEAKER>
<L>Though I appeare</L>
<L>In outward carriage apt to make distrust</L>
<L>Condemne me vicious; yet my Soule retaines</L>
<L>(Besides a generous disposition</L>
<L>Deriv'd from noble blood) some scrupulous sparkes</L>
<L>Of better conscience. Call it not selfe-flattery</L>
<L><PB N="47" REF="27"/>
In that I am mine owne defenses instrument.</L>
<L>Report sufficiently may informe your knowledge,</L>
<L>(Nor is it error) that my interest</L>
<L>In her you now call Mother</L>
<L>Was beyond all dispute: our equall loves</L>
<L>Mov'd in one circle; and our thoughts were fixt▪</L>
<L>Nor can I varie; shee's the object still</L>
<L>Of my desires. I confesse I use</L>
<L>Wanton sollicites; and should scarse resist</L>
<L>My wishes satisfaction she consenting.</L>
<L>But those delights would end in such a loathing,</L>
<L>That I should never more have mercifull thought</L>
<L>There can be any goodnesse left in Woman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. W.</SPEAKER>
<P>This jarres upon my heart-strings.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ierk.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dos't distast you Sir,</L>
<L>That I defend my selfe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. W.</SPEAKER>
<P>You must not wrong my Father.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ierk.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe abhor the thought of injurie.</L>
<L>Nor shall my spirit fall in the just plea</L>
<L>Of mine owne right.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. W.</SPEAKER>
<P>But not to wrong my Father.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ieffr.</SPEAKER>
<P>If he bee abusive, Cousin challenge him. I'le bee
your second.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ierk.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hee's not a Crane Coz.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ieffr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nor I a Pigmie; you mock my love.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ierk.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your forwardnesse is dangerous.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ieffr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, he can never have wit, that is not valiant.</L>
<L>I'le trie him my selfe, if not to disturb you Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. W.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thanke you little one.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ieffr.</SPEAKER>
<P>How little one I Is not that an affront Cousin?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ierk.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis as you take it Coz.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Artl</SPEAKER>
<P>Fill some Wine boy: never a Drawer here?</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> DASHER.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dash.</SPEAKER>
<P>What Gentlemen, none to attend you? (whooh)
An unlook'd for happines<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> that my unworthy selfe is
prefer'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="48" REF="28"/>
<SPEAKER>Y. W.</SPEAKER>
<P>An inferiour servant may serve, Mr. <HI>Dasher.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dash.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am the servant of my servant that shall serve
you. And unlesse hee serve you he is not my servant. I'le
tunre them all away presently for this neglect of your
worthy Persons.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ieffr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Men weare swords Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. W.</SPEAKER>
<P>And boyes too sometimes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ieffr.</SPEAKER>
<P>You'l answer it?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. W.</SPEAKER>
<P>Answer what Child?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ieffr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Little one! Boy! Child! I shall bee degraded
next to an infant.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ierker.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fie Cousin, containe. The Gentleman cannot
brooke it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. W.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes Sir, hee can brooke any thing but wronging
of his Father.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Artl.</SPEAKER>
<L>I pray no more, the subject is too harsh</L>
<L>To make good musicke in societie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ierk.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then here's a health to her that best deserves</L>
<L>The attribute of Faire: whose white and red</L>
<L>Prove what's lifes mixture. From whose forms exactnes</L>
<L>Rules of Proportion might be better drawne</L>
<L>Then from Arts Principles. To her whose Youth</L>
<L>Warmes Winters icie bosome with her Spring;</L>
<L>Yet will not wrong your Father. As it goes round,</L>
<L>Each give his Mistris some comm<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nding Character.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Artl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why then a health to her whose beauties are</L>
<L>Not a grosse Earth, with painted superficies;</L>
<L>But a more spright<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y Element of pure <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ire.</L>
<L>Within whose <HI>Sphaere</HI> a glorious M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nde doth move</L>
<L>All th' orbes of vertue with celestiall flame.</L>
<L>Whose active climbings carry her d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>si<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es</L>
<L>To th' utmost height of noblenesse and honour:</L>
<L>To her that calls you Brother.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. W.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let not your love appeare so full of flattery.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ierk.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, Coz; <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ieffr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then here's a health to her will freely put</L>
<L><PB N="49" REF="28"/>
Her sweets to use. Kisse, and be kist againe</L>
<L>Without a fie. Whose boldnesse will not blush</L>
<L>At an assault, or any wanton touch.</L>
<L>And if a man persist to farther doing,</L>
<L>Accounts it losse of time, a tedious wooing.</L>
<L>To her that I call Mistris.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. W.</SPEAKER>
<P>Bravely come off Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ieffr.</SPEAKER>
<P>I can come on Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Artl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now Sir, 'tis yours.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. W.</SPEAKER>
<L>This Sack shall then have my <HI>Encomium.</HI></L>
<L>Which had the youthfull Father ever tasted</L>
<L>He would have left his rites to Poetize;</L>
<L>And chang'd his Yvy Chaplets into Bayes:</L>
<L>Vnchain'd his spotted Linxes, and supply'd</L>
<L>His Chariots loftier course with <HI>Pegasus.</HI></L>
<L>And with bewitching numbers charm'd the gods</L>
<L>To be his <HI>Bacchanalls,</HI> that they might feast</L>
<L>With this most heavenly <HI>Nectar.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> DASHER.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ierk.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mr. <HI>Dasher,</HI> your Wine<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s highly commended.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dash.</SPEAKER>
<P>I can assure you Gentlemen, the Grape from
whence this Sacke was prest—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y▪ W.</SPEAKER>
<P>Grew in <HI>Spaine.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dash.</SPEAKER>
<P>I would have fetcht it farther Gentlemen to doe
you service. A voyage to the <HI>Indies</HI> should bee no more
then a descending into my cellar, and up agen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Art.</SPEAKER>
<P>You have handsomely contracted your journey.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ierk.</SPEAKER>
<P>But Mr. <HI>Dasher,</HI> you have an eminent House, ex∣traordinary
Wine and entertainment; but no Signe at first
to distinguish it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ieffr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Me thoughts Cousin, the Logger-heads was a
pretty conceit.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ierk.</SPEAKER>
<P>Had there not beene a third.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dash.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gentlemen; I intended a paire of Scales with a
glasse of Wine in one Ballance, and a piece of gold in the
other, or a jewell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="50" REF="29"/>
<SPEAKER>Y. Wor.</SPEAKER>
<P>An excellent conceit, to shew the value of
good Wine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dash.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sweet Gentlemen, I am the servant of your noble
wits. I must kisse the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re hand of an honourable Lord,
who is now departing: I will then returne to be dispos'd
by you.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>The third Scoene.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Sir <HI>GENEROVS,</HI> young <HI>WORTHY</HI> by
the left <HI>Scoene.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Wor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir 'tis my father.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Gen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha! my sonne here, and Mr <HI>Ierker!</HI></L>
<L>I came i'th' person of authoritie,</L>
<L>Invited by your noise. But that put off,</L>
<L>Out of my love borne to the generall good,</L>
<L>I doe advise you to be temperate:</L>
<L>That the faire hopes conceiv'd of growing vertues</L>
<L>Might not be lost. 'Tis pitty that your wits,</L>
<L>Which (joyn'd with some experience) might deserve</L>
<L>To fill the seats of Magistracie, and be</L>
<L>A speaking law) should spend themselves in places</L>
<L>And acts of sin and shame; wherein severitie</L>
<L>Of law and government must not be partiall.</L>
<L>Therefore I pray no more of these disorders.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Wor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray Sir, take nothing ill. 'Tis the necessity</L>
<L>Of his place: his disposition else is milder.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ierk.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, we are Gentlemen; and by that priviledge</L>
<L>Though we submit to politique Government</L>
<L>In publique things may be our owne law-makers</L>
<L>In morall life. If we offend the law</L>
<L>The law may punish us; which onely strives</L>
<L>To take away excesse, not the necessity</L>
<L>Or use of what's indifferent, and is made</L>
<L>Or good or bad by 'ts use. We doe not drinke</L>
<L><PB N="51" REF="29"/>
To a distemper, and from thence derive</L>
<L>Th' originall of mischiefes: nor is pleasure</L>
<L>Our law but temperance. Creation made</L>
<L>Every thing good, if we abuse it not.</L>
<L>Then good Sir, (though you find enormitles</L>
<L>Amongst the rabble) be not so suspitious</L>
<L>Of our more carefull carriage, that are gentlemen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Gen.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have said to satisfaction</L>
<L>And more then I expected. Harke you sonne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Art.</SPEAKER>
<P>I did not think th'adst beene so good an Oratou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ierk.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why friend? because wanton familiaritie</L>
<L>Make's us lesse serious when we are alone,</L>
<L>Must it necessitate we cannot speake</L>
<L>In a high cause! Cousin, you must be carefull</L>
<L>Of your behaviour: you are before a Iustice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ieffr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why Cousin, have Iustices power over a mans
will?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ierk.</SPEAKER>
<L>Some busie ones have arrogated much;</L>
<L>But being told their owne have ever since</L>
<L>Given Gentlemen a due respect.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ieffr.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le make a tryall here. Please you a little</L>
<L>To put off this severer gravitie;</L>
<L>And drinke a glasse of Sack. Your age is Priviledge</L>
<L>In what the law of moderation,</L>
<L>Denies our hotter blood.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Gen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pretty sweet Gentleman. Is't possible</L>
<L>That one so young, should have so gray a wit;</L>
<L>'Tis wanting many times in graver beards.</L>
<L>Please you Mr. <HI>Ierker,</HI> to bring these Gentlemen to my
house to supper. You'l find some emptie dishes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ierk.</SPEAKER>
<P>We know your table's plentifully furnisht.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Gen.</SPEAKER>
<P>This was very good Sacke, neighbour. Pray
send me home a dozen Bottles. And keepe good orders.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dash.</SPEAKER>
<P>The best orders that can be kept in my hous<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
or any office of my house shall bee at your Worships ser∣vice.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="52" REF="30"/>
<SPEAKER>Ieffr.</SPEAKER>
<P><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ogh; that complem<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nt stinckes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Gen.</SPEAKER>
<P>You are very cou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ou, neighbour. Will you
goe along with me Gentlemen!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Artl.</SPEAKER>
<P>We are your servants. 'Tis a blest opportunity.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Gen.</SPEAKER>
<P>You shall now make tryall of my profest love.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ierk.</SPEAKER>
<P>The reckoning M. <HI>Dasher</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Artl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wee'l take the Barr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/> our way.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Goe forth by the left <HI>Scoene.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dasher.</SPEAKER>
<P>You'l doe mee honour to pay it there. Ten
thousand welcomes wait upon you Gentlemen (whoo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>)
Come sirrah, be the <HI>Mercury</HI> of neatnesse, and nimbly set
this disorder'd roome in order. Then give the gentleman
below notice, that it is now ready to doe him service:
Hee's like to be a bountifull guest. He talks of selling his
Land, and being a Wit: but how can that agree together I
yes, very well. A countrey Gentleman to s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ll his land, is
as it were to change his copie: leave his knowne trade to
project a better profit. Which changing of Copie here
with us, ends many times in the citie freehold at Lud∣gate.</P>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>The fourth Scoene.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>DVNG VVORTH, RALPH</HI> and <HI>DOBSON,</HI>
by the left <HI>SCOENE.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dash.</SPEAKER>
<P>Worthy Sir, I have now made ready a roome to
entertaine your worthy person. My house was so cramd
with Lords; and this especially with most choyce gentle∣men,
some of the admired wits, to which very name I owe
respect and service.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis a fine Chamber, it shines like a Gold-smiths
shop in Cheap-side.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dung.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Twould much inde<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re mee to your kindnesse
to bring mee acquainted with some of those Wits: you
say they keepe their rendevous here many times. If I may
<PB N="53" REF="30"/>
mold my selfe capable I should gladly add to their number.
Indeed, I have had but Countrey breeding.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dobs.</SPEAKER>
<P>City bringing up forfooth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes; for we ridd like mad men.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dash.</SPEAKER>
<P>Questionlesse, Sir, there are of the wits some
mercenary ones, whom your money may command to be
your servants. But these are of a nobler straine. Howsoe∣ver,
I will upon the next occasion shew my desire to doe
you service.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dobs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Prethee <HI>Ralph,</HI> what be those Wits? A familie?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>No <HI>Dobson,</HI> they be of all tribes. Some are Iewes,
and some are Gentiles. Some are noble both in blood
and condition, and some in neither. Some studie Arts
of use; some of delight; some conceive well, but talke
wickedly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dobs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Those be the Women <HI>Ralph.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ral.</SPEAKER>
<P>No interruptions. Some breake jests; some breake
pates; some breake Tailours; and some breake their
fasts with Duke <HI>Humphrey.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dobs.</SPEAKER>
<P>A wise house-keeper belike.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>Some weare Plush that others pay for. Some
love Sacke, and some love wenches. Few will dye of the
Aldermans Gout, and some will never bee cur'd of their
owne—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dobs.</SPEAKER>
<P>I understand thee <HI>Ralph.</HI> But how com'st thou
to know all this?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tut man; I liv'd in <HI>London</HI> before now; was
servant to one that converst much with the wits, and kept
an Academie of Musicke. I tell thee <HI>Dobson,</HI> I have pickt
up mo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e learning among the crummes of a broken bisket,
after one of their meetings at a Taverne, then would
make twenty Ballad-makers commence Po<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tasters; and
with the over-plus indoctrinate ten Iustices Clerks, and
an under-Sheriffe.</P>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="scene">
<PB N="54" REF="31"/>
<HEAD>The fifth Scoene.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Mris. TONGALL, <HI>and</HI> LITTLEVVORD <HI>by
the left</HI> Scoene.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dungw.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sweet Mistris, you are welcome to my ex∣pectation.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tong.</SPEAKER>
<P>If my presumption to bring a worthy acquain∣tance
along with me, seem's not unmannerly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dungw.</SPEAKER>
<P>You rather expresse kindnesse to a stranger
that desires worthy company.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tong.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sweet Mr. <HI>Dasher,</HI> you are the best Woman Vin∣tener
that ever lov'd a Gossips tale. You have so many
good things to pleasure a woman with. You were wont to
have an excellent neat tongue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dash.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sweet Mris. <HI>Tongall,</HI> my best tongue, and all is
at your service.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tong.</SPEAKER>
<P>Kind Master <HI>Dasher.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dung.</SPEAKER>
<P>To your welcome Mistresse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tong.</SPEAKER>
<P>My humblenes receives your favour thankfully.
My service to you Mr. <HI>Dasher.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dash.</SPEAKER>
<P>I kisse the hand of your servant.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>And make a legg. This Vintener sure hath had
very mannerly breeding. he came not from the Bankes
side, where the surly Watermen live.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dash.</SPEAKER>
<P>Noble sir, I presume to present my desires to doe
you service.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dobs.</SPEAKER>
<P>This Gentleman hath lesse manners. Hee an∣swers
nothing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tong.</SPEAKER>
<P>My friend (Sir) though he be of few words,
is a fine wit, and a great observer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dung.</SPEAKER>
<P>A Wit, Mistris; I shall be the prouder of his ac∣quaintance.
But when I am a Witt, I shall preferre my
talking before my observation.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tong.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thank you Mr <HI>Little-word.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="55" REF="31"/>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mr. <HI>Littleword</HI> and Mris <HI>Tongall!</HI> very good.
Sure this woman had a French-man to her Father.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tong.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeed Mr. <HI>Dasher,</HI> 'tis excellent Sacke. If you
were unmarried you should have my daughter <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>inny,</HI> for
keeping such good Wi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> in your house.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dash.</SPEAKER>
<P>I retribute all due thanks for your kindnesse, that
you would doe me so great an honour.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mistris, you said I should have your daughter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tong.</SPEAKER>
<P>My friend, why so thou shalt. This Sacke makes
my heart merry.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who then shall my Master have?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tong.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why my Daughter linny.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>A right woman: so her tongue goe, no mat∣ter
what she sayes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dash.</SPEAKER>
<P>What will that Gentleman with his table-booke!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dung.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let's have a health to some body.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tong.</SPEAKER>
<P>Please you Sir, to my daughter Iinny.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dung.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let it goe round then.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tongall.</SPEAKER>
<P>And hee that will not pledge it, shall not
have her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dobs.</SPEAKER>
<P>I hope we shall drinke now <HI>Ralph.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>Else we lose both our share of the Sack, and our
hopes of her daughter Iinny.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ent. Drawer.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dung.</SPEAKER>
<P>Some more Wine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dash.</SPEAKER>
<P>(Whooh) be nimble sirrah; and bring of my
kingdome (that's my word for good wine) that it may
wait on these Gentlemen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tong.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>William,</HI> thou art an honest fellow; and if thou
bringst us good wine, thou shalt have my daughter Iinny
from them all.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dash.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sure this Gentleman write's what I speake. I
hope 'twas not treason to say my Kingdome. I would I
knew what he were.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dung.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Vi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tener seem's troubled at this Gentle∣mans
table-booke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tong.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis his practise of observation. Hee is taking
<PB N="56" REF="32"/>
a humour for a Play: perhaps my talking of my daugh∣ter
Iinny.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dung.</SPEAKER>
<P>I'le hatch some mirth from it. Sir, you must not
take it ill, if I tell you of your errours. You have spoken
somthing rashly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dash.</SPEAKER>
<P>Kind and worthy Sir, my life is your servant for
this noble care.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dung.</SPEAKER>
<P>That silent Gentleman is an intelligencer; a state
spie. Hee'<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> informe against you. Therefore complie with
him to prevent it. 'Tis his pollicie to say nothing him∣selfe,
that his observation may be the more, and his owne
danger the lesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dash.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, I owe your goodnesse all that ever I have
beene, am, or shall be. He writes againe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tong.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now Mr. <HI>Little-word,</HI> you have some fine mat∣ter
there to worke upon.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dash.</SPEAKER>
<P>To undoe me. Sir, I desire you will command
all that is to bee commanded in my house to doe you ser∣vice.
Yes, yes; he writes againe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dung.</SPEAKER>
<P>That word command is a word of great dan∣ger,
I would you had not us'd it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dash.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas Sir, Mris <HI>Tongall,</HI> 'twas not neighbourly
done of you to bring an informer into my hous<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tong.</SPEAKER>
<P>How, I bring an Informer! as I am a Matron, he's
a Gentleman, a wit, and a rare Projector.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dash.</SPEAKER>
<P>I believe it, to undoe a poore Vintener, that
cannot complement a Gentleman into a ten pounds ex∣pence;
but his necke must be in danger. Sir, if I were a
King I would be your servant. He writes againe.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter a <HI>BOY.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dung.</SPEAKER>
<P>Blesse me Sir, you have spoken treason.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dash.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas, Sir, I, am undone then.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>Master, the Constable and other officers are com∣ming
up.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dash.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, yes; to apprehend me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis for us, <HI>Dobson.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="57" REF="32"/>
<SPEAKER>Dung.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Constable▪ I hope wee are not suspected
persons.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tong.</SPEAKER>
<P>If I thought you were, you should never have my
daughter Iinny.</P>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="6" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>The sixth Scoene.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>CONSTABLE</HI> and <HI>OFFICERS;</HI> by
the left <HI>SCOENE.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Const.</SPEAKER>
<P>By your leave Gentlemen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>You are welcome Sir, and I pray be gone.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Const.</SPEAKER>
<P>But not without you Sir. You are suspected, and
must answer—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dung.</SPEAKER>
<P>Answer what? heere are neither Traitors nor
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dash.</SPEAKER>
<P>I feare I shall be prov'd both.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tong▪</SPEAKER>
<P>No Sir, nor night-walkers that are taken up, and
cast downe I have declar'd my selfe of as good carriage
as any in the neighbour-hood; and my daughter Iinny
waits upon an honourable Ladie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dash.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mr. Constable, I am your servant, I hope you
suspect no Traitors in my house. If you doe, they shall
wait upon you into the Cellar; and there commit what
treason you will against as good Sack as is in the King of
<HI>Spaines</HI> Dominions. The Gentleman writes still. I am ut∣terly
lost.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Const.</SPEAKER>
<P>There are two suspected to be heere, that have
broken the peace, and committed a robbery.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dobs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Denie it <HI>Ralph.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>I tell you Constable, there are none heere,
but can breake the peace, as well as you that are a Con∣stable.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dung.</SPEAKER>
<P>They shall obey your authority, and in the Vin∣teners
phraze wait upon you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="58" REF="33"/>
<SPEAKER>Dash.</SPEAKER>
<P>I feare I must wait upon the Gallowes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dungw.</SPEAKER>
<P>Being my servants, Ple goe likewise along
with you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dash.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, yes; a meere plot to goe along, that hee
may witnesse against me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dobs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Feare nothing <HI>Ralph,</HI> the Gentlewomen will
not see us hang'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>But they may suffer us, and that's a word for
hanging.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dung.</SPEAKER>
<P>You seeme apprehensive of your owne danger.
There's a reckoning to pay; if you but forgive it, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'le free
you from this Gentlemans information.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dash.</SPEAKER>
<P>Most gladly Sir, and bee your servant. But how
shall I be sure of it?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dung.</SPEAKER>
<P>You shall heare it from his owne mouth. You
will not (Sir) informe any thing against this man! I pray
say no.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Little.</SPEAKER>
<P>No.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dash.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am satisfied: and will be your servant in any
thing but treason.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tong.</SPEAKER>
<P>But be sure you speake to Mistris <HI>Dorothy.</HI> Nay
I'le along with you too, and perhaps speake a good
word.</P>
<P>I have acquaintance with the Iustice, and his Clerke
knows my daughter <HI>Iinny.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dash.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let mee bee your servant Mr. Constable, and
light you downe. I hope my house will receive no scan∣dall
by this.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dung.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Twas a beginning yet, and more may hit.</P>
<P>Thus in th' abus'd sense cheating is cal'd wit.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Goe forth by the left <HI>Scoene.</HI></STAGE>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="5" TYPE="act">
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<PB N="59" REF="33"/>
<HEAD>Act. 5. Scoen. 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>SVSAN,</HI> by the middle <HI>SCOENE.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVSAN.</SPEAKER>
<P>THanks honest <HI>Nicholas.</HI> 'Tis time to cover: my La∣dy
will to supper so soone as my Master comes home.
He brings strangers with him. This Butler is the kindest
fellow to a Gentleuman; and deserves my love more for
this bottle of Sacke, then <HI>Warrant</HI> or <HI>Spruce</HI> for fighting.
Come thou inspirer of a diviner soule, that teachest my∣steries,
of which without thee none are capable: to bee
valiant; to love; to Poetise: suffer a thirsty gentleuman
to delight her drye pallat with thy sweet moisture, and re∣fresh
her spirits with thy comfortable operation. <HI>(Drinks)</HI>
Excellent Sack, as I am a Gentleuman. Now am I in love
with my old Master for buying it; wth the Vintener for
selling it; with the Drawer for drawing it; nay, with the
very Porter that brought it home: but most of all with
kinde <HI>Nicholas</HI> for bestowing it upon mee; good heart,
hee hath v<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nt<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>'d a chiding if it should be mist. <HI>(Drinks.)</HI>
What foolish Poets were they that made the more foo∣lish
gods drinke <HI>Nectar!</HI> Had <HI>Apollo</HI> presented <HI>Daphne</HI>
but with a cup of such Sack, sh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e would have lov'd him,
as I d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e <HI>Nicholas:</HI> but not to lye with him. A gentle∣uman
must not humble her selfe to a Butler. <HI>(Drinks.)</HI>
My Ladie.</P>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<PB N="60" REF="34"/>
<HEAD>The second <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>LADIE,</HI> by the middle <HI>Scoene.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady▪</SPEAKER>
<L>What is't should make my Husbands jealousie</L>
<L>Rage <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o within him to suspect the visits</L>
<L>Of every friend! Cannot my carefull carriage</L>
<L>Kill his distrust, and make him confident!</L>
<L>Many a young Ladie that had such excuses</L>
<L>As I may well pretend, his age, diseases,</L>
<L>And all the cold defects are incident</L>
<L>To a decaying strength, would priviledge</L>
<L>Her rasher wills dispense with young desires.</L>
<L>Such are in me; but not to satisfaction:</L>
<L>I must not wrong my fame: though my hot bloud</L>
<L>Should danc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> a lustfull measure. But hee's jealous;</L>
<L>And I must practise some strange cure upon it.</L>
<L>Secretary.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Madame.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why doe you gaze upon me?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>I would not for th'exchange your Ladiship were
a man.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<P>And why so?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>I should runne madd, for love of your La∣diship.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<P>What humour have you got? you have sure beene
tipling. Fie Secretary.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>I hope your Ladiship hath a better opinion of
your uman, then to be earnest because she jests.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<P>You know Mr. <HI>Ierker?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>A very handsome gentleman. I wonder no wor∣thy
Gentleuman is in love with him:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<P>No Secretary; what thinke you of me?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="61" REF="34"/>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doth your <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> truely and so
doe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>But not as I doe▪</L>
<L>I could betray mine honour to his l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ve;</L>
<L>And s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ll my fame for his <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> embraces▪</L>
<L>Give those delights which are my Husbands due</L>
<L>To his enjoying.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>And w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ll your Ladiship discover this to mee?
Truely I meane not to bee degraded from your Ladiships
uman, to hold the doore, and crye, my Master's comming.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy employment shall be</L>
<L>Whe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> wee are closely set at dallyance</L>
<L>Blush not what ere thou seest; but call thy Master;</L>
<L>The service may be worth a new gowne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>How, call my Master! Did ever any Ladie en∣joy
a friend in a corner, and wish her Husband (who is
sufficiently jealous alreadie) to see it! Now as I am a
Gentleuman, and had rather bee a Ladie, 'tis not my
mind.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady▪</SPEAKER>
<L>But 'tis mine;</L>
<L>His knowledge of't would add to the delight,</L>
<L>And make th' offence lesse. Citie Dames can practise</L>
<L>Slights to deceive their Husbands, mine shall know it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>But is your Ladiship earnest?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<P>As earnest as resolves can make me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>But I am resolv'd not to obey your Ladyship.
Shall I that am my Ladies Secretary as it were, be treache∣rous
to her secrets? Then let me not be counted a gentle∣uman.
If it please your Ladiship Ile tell him you intend
such a thing that he may prevent it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dispute not my commands, but doe them:</L>
<L>O<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> I shall stop the current of my favours.</L>
<L>That hitherto have flow'd so fully on thee.</L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<PB N="62" REF="35"/>
<HEAD>The third Scoene.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter Sir</HI> GENEROVS WORTHY, IERKER,
ARTLOVE, <HI>Y.</HI> WORTHY, SVSAN, IEFFREY,
<HI>by the middle</HI> SCOENE.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Gen.</SPEAKER>
<P>I have brought you some guests Wife. Send
your entertainment be worth their labour.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<P>I could wish it much better for Master <HI>Ierkers</HI>
sake.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Gen.</SPEAKER>
<L>I feare you are too free that way.</L>
<L>I am yet a man, and my declining age</L>
<L>Hath not so weakened judgement in me,</L>
<L>That passion should betray my jealous thoughts.</L>
<L>Nor can I but suspect, and must be satisfied.</L>
<L>Her woman is the instrument. Mris. <HI>Susan.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. W.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray Sir, let me prepare her. No more will I</L>
<L>In the severer Person of a counsellour</L>
<L>Instruct your care. But since by curious search</L>
<L>I have inform'd my knowledge</L>
<L>Even to satisfaction of his worth,</L>
<L>Let me commend this noble gentleman</L>
<L>Vnto your best desires; let him possesse them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dorot.</SPEAKER>
<L>Brother, without mature consideration</L>
<L>I dare not doe an act; on which depends</L>
<L>Such dangerous events.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. W.</SPEAKER>
<L>My love's your warrant.</L>
<L>Have not I searchd him throughly? have not I</L>
<L>Found him deserving all that's due to man,</L>
<L>Though malice were his judge. View but his person,</L>
<L>Art could not shape a m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re exact prep<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rtion:</L>
<L>And through his Christall bosome read his heart</L>
<L>Wherein such noble thoughts are character'd—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="63" REF="35"/>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>You shall command a poore Gentleuman any
thing; neither doe I expect reward. I onely desire you
will accept it as an act of my love. But why should you
be jealous of my Lady.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Gen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Aske me no idle questions, but doe it. Thou
mayst bee a Lady thy selfe, if it lie in my power to raise
thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas Sir, an old man raise a Gentleuman.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dorot.</SPEAKER>
<L>We have a father (Brother) to whose care</L>
<L>We owe another dutie, then that onely</L>
<L>Which Nature hath injoyn'd us for receiving</L>
<L>Our beings from him. Let not our rash wills</L>
<L>Sway'd onely by desire, run any course</L>
<L>Agrees not with his liking: Yet I'le tell</L>
<L>The Gentleman how much he owes your love</L>
<L>For thus commending him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now Sir <HI>Generous?</HI></L>
<L>Courting my woman? am not I warme enough</L>
<L>To thaw your frozen appetite?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Truly Sir, if my Lady knew how much I lov'd</L>
<L>you, 'twould make her jealous.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeed it would not.</L>
<L>Revenge should be a remedie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Gen.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's my feare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, to her againe; you are not the first</L>
<L>That hath abus'd his Lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Gen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wife, forgoe these fond thoughts, and with
care apply your selfe to entertain these gentlemen.
I'le to my closet.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>goes forth.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>I want but th' opportunity of their absence,</L>
<L>Which I must straight contrive.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Artl.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am now animated</L>
<L>To come the neerest way without more circumstance;</L>
<L>And tell you how your beauty and your vertues</L>
<L>Have won on my desires to make them yours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="64" REF="36"/>
<SPEAKER>Dorot.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thanke you Sir, and could mine owne eyes see</L>
<L>But halfe that worth my Brother sayes is in you,</L>
<L>My equall thoughts should answer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y▪ W.</SPEAKER>
<P>What said she Sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Artl.</SPEAKER>
<P>It seemes you did commend me!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. W.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes by my hopes of good, no otherwise</L>
<L>Then I desire to have my selfe commended</L>
<L>Vpon the like occasion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Artl.</SPEAKER>
<P>I must thanke you Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. W.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe interpret it; and have thought upon</L>
<L>Another tryall. Let me intreat you Sister</L>
<L>To conster my intentions right. Though I</L>
<L>Commended him, 'twas onely to distinguish</L>
<L>Your passion and your reason. Now I find</L>
<L>The latter strongest, that you refuse the love</L>
<L>Of one so much defective.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dorot.</SPEAKER>
<L>How! defective!</L>
<L>Brother, my judgement hath as searching eyes</L>
<L>Can see the fulnesse of his manly worth</L>
<L>Through all the vailes of your detraction.</L>
<L>And now to shew how much I doe prefer</L>
<L>The freedome of my will before your counsell;</L>
<L>I'le tell him I doe love him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. W.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sister, I hope</L>
<L>You are not earnest!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dorot.</SPEAKER>
<L>As earnest as my love;</L>
<L>Which since I first beheld him tooke possession</L>
<L>Of all my though<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s, though customary nicenesse</L>
<L>Restraind me from discovering them; but now—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray daughter oversee the servants.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Dorothy.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. W.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mother beshrew your heart, she was in a good
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eine. But come sir, wee<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l pursue it.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt young Worthy, and Artlove.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ieffr.</SPEAKER>
<P>It hath beene no small punishment for mee to
<PB N="65" REF="36"/>
hold my peace all this while. My Cousin is morall be∣fore
companie and counsel's my manners. But now I hope
my tongue shall have libertie; and her's my Ladies gen∣tleuman
to exercise it with.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your little Cousin may stay. How like you the plot?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ierk.</SPEAKER>
<L>As the end proves it. And since your constancie</L>
<L>Hath held out 'gainst my leud temptations,</L>
<L>Which have as well beene tryals of your vertues</L>
<L>As acts of wantonnesse, I here desist.</L>
<L>Henceforth my tongue shall never uttor sound</L>
<L>Offensive to your modestie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray let's sit,</L>
<L>And enter on the project, though it be nice</L>
<L>When wit masks vertue in a cloke of vice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>They are going to it, and heer's a little one will
tell. Pray sir, can you keepe counsell?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ieffr.</SPEAKER>
<P>As well as a woman.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeed they and children are kin.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ieffr.</SPEAKER>
<P>You need not feare your secrets.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then I shall love you heartily. But pray Sir, no
medling with a gentleumans apron. Here's that will helpe
your growth: Please you to partake.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ieffr.</SPEAKER>
<P>She abuseth me, I must fit her. What is't Mistris?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sack I assure you Sir; and I hope you will love
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> poore gentleumans as she loves you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ieffr.</SPEAKER>
<P>If the Butler be not too deeply interested.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<P>Secretarie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Madame.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<P>You forget your imployment.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>I saw your Ladiship doe nothing yet.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doe we not kisse!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>I runne then, and dare not looke backe for feare
of blushing.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ieffr.</SPEAKER>
<P>What strange contrivement's this?</P>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="scene">
<PB N="66" REF="37"/>
<HEAD>The fourth Scoene.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Sir <HI>GENEROVS WORTHY</HI> with <HI>SVSAN,</HI>
by the middle <HI>Scoene.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, blush not Mr. <HI>Ierker,</HI> ours is no act of
shame, but to be gloried in; youth to youth. Sir <HI>Generous</HI>
are your hornes so lop-heavy they make you hang the
head. Never droop at it man. A Lord may bee a Cuck∣old
and never the wiser: you have gotten the knowledge
of what o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> did but suspect before.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir. Gen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Out of my warring thoughts discretion</L>
<L>Ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> horder'd a resolve, whose practise shall</L>
<L>Preserve my credit. Though I much wonder</L>
<L>A womans smooth hypocrisie should make</L>
<L>Even her secret'st actions to appeare</L>
<L>Most vertuous; yet in this to staine her whitenesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>I did it Sir to cure your jealousie</L>
<L>More then for satisfaction of desire,</L>
<L>Which I have often satiated, when</L>
<L>Your cold abilities were comforted</L>
<L>With downe and sileuce; when your dreames presented</L>
<L>The quiet of a grave.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ierk.</SPEAKER>
<L>I did it Sir,</L>
<L>In gratitude for your hospitality.</L>
<L>Please you to take my counsell. Be divore't.</L>
<L>You need no proofes, since shees her owne accuser.</L>
<L>I'le then procure a dispensation</L>
<L>And wee'l be marr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Gen.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis assented to.</L>
<L>Nay more, I'le give you all her portion backe:</L>
<L>Nor shall the least disquiet in my thoughts</L>
<L>Make me remember it. Think not (young man) mine age</L>
<L><PB N="67" REF="37"/>
So weake▪ but I can conquer passion.</L>
<L>My act sh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l instantly have confirmation;</L>
<L>And be a president where such inequality</L>
<L>Of yeares are joyn'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray good Sir <HI>Generous stay.</HI></L>
<L>I have not yet consented; and I thinke</L>
<L>The Law cannot dispense whilst either live.</L>
<L>If you resolve divorce, you<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l onely force me</L>
<L>To an unwil<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ing widdow-hood; and how little</L>
<L>My innocence deserves, the least suspect,</L>
<L>Though I did faigne a guilt for better ends,</L>
<L>Iust heaven can witnesse. There was no necessity</L>
<L>To tempt my woman to discover us.</L>
<L>It was my first command.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Gen.</SPEAKER>
<L>I heare strange words</L>
<L>Which must be scann'd and construed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ierk.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here my solicites cease. But I desire</L>
<L>I may <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>em<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ine the servant of your vertues,</L>
<L>And weare your favours livery, whose example</L>
<L>H<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>h won on my resolves to reconcile</L>
<L>My <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>lder soule.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whilst you persever in't,</L>
<L>I shall preserve you in my purest thoughts;</L>
<L>But never to infect them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Gen.</SPEAKER>
<L>The World reputes me</L>
<L>A man of full discretion; and mine age</L>
<L>Is not so rotten yet, to betwice childe.</L>
<L>Hence yee vaine jealousies, that in love diseas'd</L>
<L>Are peccant humours: therefore must be purg'd.</L>
<L>Come to my bosome patterne of true goodnesse.</L>
<L>Nere more those bug-beares to the minds blest quiet</L>
<L>Shall fright thee thence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then will my joyes be setled.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Gen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good Sir forgive</L>
<L>The rashnesse of my passion. I'le no more</L>
<L><PB N="68" REF="38"/>
Be jealous of your visits; but desire</L>
<L>The love I beare your person may beusefull</L>
<L>To all g<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>od ends.</L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>The fifth Scoene.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter Y.</HI> WORTHY, ARTLOVE, DOROTHY, <HI>&amp;c.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. W.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, blush not Sister;</L>
<L>Though it be vertues colour. Say't agen.</L>
<L>Here are more witnesses.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Gen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whence growe's this exultation?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. W.</SPEAKER>
<L>From in ward joy that she affects this gentleman,</L>
<L>Whose Vertues wonn</L>
<L>Vpon my love to be his Oratour;</L>
<L>And not respects infected with the mixture</L>
<L>Of any worse condition.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Gen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doe you love him?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dorot.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hope to your kind judgement 'twill appeare</L>
<L>A vertuous truth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Gen.</SPEAKER>
<L>If he be found deserving</L>
<L>In the dependances on bloud and fortune</L>
<L>I shall consent, and then may mutuall love</L>
<L>Render you happy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Artl.</SPEAKER>
<L>How am I blest that your white soule</L>
<L>Hath bounded it's desires within the circuit</L>
<L>Of my too narrow worth!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Gen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Supper not ready yet <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> my servants are musi∣call;
please you Gentlemen to dance a little. 'Tis a health∣full
exercise; bid them prepare their instruments. Come,
come, settle to it.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Spruce and Warrant, enter
with Musicke.</STAGE>
<SP>
<L>I love to see a nimble activenesse</L>
<L>In noble youth; it argues active minds</L>
<L>In well shap't bodies, and begets a joy</L>
<L>Dancing within me.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Dance.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="6" TYPE="scene">
<PB N="69" REF="38"/>
<HEAD>The sixth Scoene.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> LITTLEVVORD, TONGALL, DVNGVVORTH,
CONSTABLE, RALPH <HI>and</HI> DOBSON, <HI>by
the middle</HI> Scoene.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir. Gen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Welcome neighbour <HI>Tongall:</HI> what meane
these people?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Const.</SPEAKER>
<P>I have brought them, an't please your Wor∣shipp.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Gener.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whom, and't please you, Master Con∣stable.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Const.</SPEAKER>
<P>The theeves, and't please your Worship, that
rob'd your worships Clerke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spruce.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now <HI>Warrant.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warr.</SPEAKER>
<P>How! I rob'd! the Constable is surely drunke.
I was not rob'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Const.</SPEAKER>
<P>How's that! did not you bring mee to the Ta∣verne;
shew mee the fellowes, and direct me to appre∣hend
them? Did you not promise me a share if they might
be brought to a composition?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who? I? verily I say I know thee not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Consta.</SPEAKER>
<P>How! not know the Constable! Come Mr.
<HI>Warrant,</HI> let mee understand the mysterie without being
farther abus'd. You forget the place where wee had re∣creation
for nothing, onely promising the wenches favour
upon occasion: against whom wee afterwards inform'd
to get fees.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Gener.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is't noe otherwise? it shall raise some
mirth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dobs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Did not I tell thee <HI>Ralph,</HI> the Gentlewomen?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, 'tis a rare thing to bee a Justice. Were
I but swel'd with a little authoritie, mee thinks I could
<PB N="70" REF="39"/>
crye, you Rogue, you Rascall, or you Constable, most
gravely.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dobs.</SPEAKER>
<P>And 'tis as rare a thing to bee a Constable; to
command in the name of authority, and bee drunke at
midnight, without danger of the st<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ks.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Gen.</SPEAKER>
<P>I shall respect him Mris. <HI>Tongall.</HI> Mr. <HI>Con∣stable</HI>
I doe conceive an abuse done to my person, in that
you here traduce two strangers, pretending appointment,
when none will accuse them; nor can I suddainly disco∣ver
the errour.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Constable.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now by all the painted authoritie of my
staffe—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Gen.</SPEAKER>
<P>No swearing Constable; I have determin'd
to conferre a power upon the accused, to judge both
it and you; and the most offendors shall suffer what shall
be due.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Consta.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whither shall I fall! from my Empire of com∣mand,
to obey a mock-Constable! <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> danger of exam∣ple
forbid it, that Clownes and fooles b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> not made Justi∣ces
in earnest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Gen.</SPEAKER>
<P>No more of this modestie: I'le have it so;
and exercise your wit. I have knowne a Countrey fellow
full of knavish clinches.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dobson.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes Sir, 'tis ordinary in a Smith.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then if I fit you not for a Justice.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dobson.</SPEAKER>
<P>And I for a Constable. You shall heare my
tone.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Const.</SPEAKER>
<P>And I for an offendor.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>Can you write and read young gentleman?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ieffr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Like a gentleman.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then you shall be my Worships Clerke. And
so I assume authoritie. (hem, hem)</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spruce.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now shall we be jeer'd out of our skins.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Set a good face on't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>(hem, hem,) what are you sirrah?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="71" REF="39"/>
<SPEAKER>Dobs.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am <HI>Dobson,</HI> the Constable and'<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> please your
Worsh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>p.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Const.</SPEAKER>
<P>He lies and't please your Worship, I am the
Constable.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>You were the Constable; but your dignitie is
justly taken from you, and conferr'd upon honest <HI>Iohn
Dobson.</HI> Thou hast beene a raskall sirrah, a corrupt Con∣stable.
Thou hast converst with deeds of darknesse, ha∣ting
the all light, but wenches and a lanthorne: which a
married Constable can never want at midnight. Thou
hast watch't little and pray'd lesse: thou shalt therefore
fast thy selfe into amendement. And so I commit thee
with thy guard of Bill-men to the mercie of a Shrove-Tuesdayes
rebellion. (hem, hem.)</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dobson.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here's an other refendant, and't please your
Worship.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>N<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>w Sir, what are you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warr.</SPEAKER>
<P>A Justices Clerke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh, I know you sirrah.</P>
<P>You write true Latine, not to be understood by the Wor∣shipfull
bench.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your Worship is misinform'd. I cannot write
true <HI>Orthographie</HI> without a Copie; and for Latine, I
have lesse then the Dean<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> of Dunstable. I have read <HI>Igno∣ramus:</HI>
but finding hard words which were not in the
Dictionary; I sweare I understand it no more then <HI>Igno∣ramus</HI>
himselfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>Make his <HI>Mittimus</HI> and send him to schoole;
(hem, hem,) what are you Sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spruce.</SPEAKER>
<P>A Gentleman Vsher.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>You are a Malki<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> of mock-Gentry; made up
of silke and vaine-glory. You begin to grow out of fa∣shion.
I will therefore have you stitcht into a case of com∣plements,
and commended to some thrifty house-keeping
Ladie in the Countrey, where you may save her Ladiship
<PB N="72" REF="40"/>
the charge of a Taylour; and if you can read, serve for a
house-Chaplaine in rainy weather. (hem, hem.) Bring
that Countrey Gentleman before me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ng.</SPEAKER>
<P>You'<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> grow saucie sirrah.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Gene.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray let's uphold the jest. I'le not spare mine
owne person. Your servant's witty.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>You are a Countrey Gentleman; a Gallant out
of fashion all the yeare; but especially at Se<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sions, and
upon high Holi-dayes, when your sattin doublet drawes
away the eyes of the simple, aud distracts their devoti∣on
almost into Idolatry: giving it more worship then the
Heraulds ever gave your Auncestors. You intend as I
understand to come forth in a new Edition: and whe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
the Mercers and Tailors have new printed you; and that
some gentile wit may be read in your Character to marry
a Wife in the City. You shall then have a passe sealed up∣on
her by a Courtier; be ship't at Cuckolds haven, and
so transported into <HI>Cornwall.</HI> (Hem, hem.) Now Sir,
what are you? never a wise word to answere a Ju∣stice?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tong.</SPEAKER>
<P>He is my friend Sir; and if you abuse him, you
shall not have my daughter <HI>Iinny.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>There is a tempest in her tongue able to shake
the foundation of the wisest Justice-ship.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dobs.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Ladie Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>Madame, I have heard complaints of your La∣diship,
that you rise early every morning before noone,
and are readie before night, unlesse there bee a maske at
Court. You are likewise a great frequenter of the balls,
meerely out of charitie to the poore Fidlers.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Gen.</SPEAKER>
<P>He hits you home Wife.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ieffr.</SPEAKER>
<P>And this is my Ladies Gentleuman.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>Stop your eares Gentlewomen, here's a foule
businesse towards. But you may tell the man, the time
and place, though not the manner.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="73" REF="40"/>
<SPEAKER>Secre.</SPEAKER>
<P>Truely Sir, if I am with child, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> but with a
bottle of Sack.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>Give it me; I'le keepe it. Many a Justi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> in the
City keepes children are none of his owne. <HI>(Drinks.)</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ierk.</SPEAKER>
<P>A right Sack Justice.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>And now for you Gentlemen. You are of the
wits that give Poets Sack and old Bevers, and vent their
conceits in Tavernes for your owne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ieffr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Please you Sir, these Gentlemen are my friends.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>How's that! a Justice take bribes! the exam∣ple
is too frequent, and I will have it mended.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Gen.</SPEAKER>
<P>You begin now to overdoe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>Bribes have purchas'd more then the whole
race of A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>dermen since <HI>Luds</HI> time.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Gen.</SPEAKER>
<P>You are bitter now: 'tis time to resigne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ralph.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis time indeed, when I will not take bribes
to be a Justice <HI>Quondam.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Gen.</SPEAKER>
<L>When Wit makes not abuse it's exercise,</L>
<L>The users of it then are truely wise:</L>
<L>But 'tis a foolish Vanitie, not Wit,</L>
<L>When Conscience bounds are broke to practise it.</L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="epilogue">
<PB REF="41"/>
<HEAD>The EPILOGVE.</HEAD>
<L>Y' Ave seene a <HI>Play,</HI> wherein was no <HI>disguise;</HI></L>
<L>No <HI>Wedding;</HI> no impro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>able <HI>devise:</HI></L>
<L>But all an easie <HI>matter,</HI> and contein'd</L>
<L>Within the time of <HI>action.</HI> 'Tis arraign'd;</L>
<L>And doubtfull stands before your <HI>judgements barre,</HI></L>
<L>Expecting what your severall <HI>censures</HI> are.</L>
<L>Some that pretend <HI>commission</HI> to the <HI>Stage,</HI></L>
<L>As th'only <HI>Cato's</HI> of this <HI>Critick Age;</HI></L>
<L>Condemning all not done by imitation,</L>
<L><HI>Because this</HI> new Play <HI>hath a</HI> new foundation</L>
<L>Wee feare will cry <HI>it</HI> downe: our hope is then</L>
<L>That your faire <HI>hands</HI> will raise <HI>it</HI> up agen.</L>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
<PB REF="41"/>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

