<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2002-10-24</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Rina Kor</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Checked for TYPE="book". Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, etc.). Checked for signatures. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, and UNCLEARs. Corrected 84 $s of 84. Converted __ $s to GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc". Checked spacing of foreign GAPs. Checked for EPIGRAPHs and ARGUMENTs. Checked for startqs, endqs, oes, q;s, and Qs. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Checked for CLOSERs, TRAILERs, and BYLINEs. Sample: 15 minutes. Proofing: 90 minutes. Tag review and corrections: 150 minutes. DONE.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A09228">
<STC T="S">19540</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99845920</BIBNO>
<VID>10852</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT>
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>THE LOVE OF KING DAVID AND FAIR BETHSABE.</P>
<P>With the Tragedie of Absalon.</P>
<P>As it hath ben diuers times plaied on the stage.</P>
<P>Written by George Peele.</P>
<P>LONDON, Printed by Adam Islip. 1599.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>The loue of <HI>Dauid</HI> and faire <HI>Bersabe,</HI> with the Tragedie of <HI>Absolon.</HI></HEAD>
<DIV2 TYPE="prologue">
<HEAD>Prologus.</HEAD>
<L><SEG REND="decorInit">O</SEG>F Israels sweetest singer now I sing,</L>
<L>His holy stile and happie victories,</L>
<L>Whose Muse was dipt in that inspiring deaw,</L>
<L>Arch-angels stilled from the breath of Ioue,</L>
<L>Decking her temples with the glorious flowers,</L>
<L>Heauens raind on tops of Syon and Mount Synai,</L>
<L>Vpon the bosome of his yuorie Lute,</L>
<L>The Cherubins and Angels laid their brests,</L>
<L>And when his consecrated fingers strooke</L>
<L>The golden wiers of his rauishing harpe,</L>
<L>He gaue alarum to the host of heauen,</L>
<L>That wing'd with lightning, brake the clouds and cast</L>
<L>Their christall armor, at his conquering feet.</L>
<L>Of this sweet Poet Ioues Musition,</L>
<L>And of bis beauteous sonne I prease to sing.</L>
<L>Then helpe deuine Adonay to conduct,</L>
<L>Vpon the wings of my well tempered verse,</L>
<L>The hearers minds aboue the towers of Heauen,</L>
<L>And guide them so in this thrice haughty flight,</L>
<L>Their mounting feathers scorch not with the fire,</L>
<L>That none can temper but thy holy hand:</L>
<L>To thee for succour flies my feeble muse,</L>
<L>And at thy feet her yron Pendoth vse.</L>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="play">
<PB REF="3"/>
<STAGE>He drawes a curtaine, and discouers Bethsabe with her maid bathing ouer a spring, she sings, and Dauid sits aboue vewing her.</STAGE>
<Q><TEXT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="song">
<L><SEG REND="decorInit">H</SEG>Ot sunne, coole fire, temperd with sweet aire,</L>
<L>Black shade, fair nurse, shadow my white haire</L>
<L>Shine sun, burne fire, breath aire, and ease mee,</L>
<L>Black shade, fair nurse, shroud me and please me</L>
<L>Shadow (my sweet nurse) keep me from burning</L>
<L>Make not my glad cause, cause of mourning.</L>
<L>Let not my beauties fire,</L>
<L>Enflame vnstaied desire,</L>
<L>Nor pierce any bright eye,</L>
<L>That wandreth lightly.</L>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT></Q>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bethsabe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come gentle Zephire trickt with those perfumes</L>
<L>That erst in Eden sweetned Adams loue,</L>
<L>And stroke my bosome with the silken fan:</L>
<L>This shade (sun proofe) is yet no proofe for thee,</L>
<L>Thy body smoother then this wauelesse spring,</L>
<L>And purer then the substance of the same,</L>
<L>Can creepe through that his launces cannot pierse.</L>
<L>Thou and thy sister soft and sacred aire,</L>
<L>Goddesse of life▪ and gouernesse of health,</L>
<L>Keepes euery fountaine fresh and arbor sweet,</L>
<L>No brasen gate, her passage can repulse,</L>
<L>Nor bushly thicket, bar thy subtle breath,</L>
<L>Then decke thee with thy loose delightsome robes,</L>
<L>And on thy wings bring delicate perfumes,</L>
<L>To play the wantons with vs through the leaues,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Da.</SPEAKER>
<L>What tunes, what words, what looks, what wonders pierce</L>
<L>My soule, incensed with a suddain fire,</L>
<L>What tree, what shade, what spring, what paradise</L>
<L>Enioyes the beautie of so faire a dame?</L>
<L>Faite Eua plac'd in perfect happinesse,</L>
<L><PB REF="3"/>Lending her praise-notes to the liberall heauens,</L>
<L>Strooke with the accents of Arch-angels tunes,</L>
<L>Wrought not more pleasure to her husbands thoughts,</L>
<L>Then this faire womans words and notes to mine.</L>
<L>May that sweet plaine that beares her pleasant weight,</L>
<L>Be still enameld with discoloured flowers,</L>
<L>That precious fount, beare sand of purest gold,</L>
<L>And for the Peble, let the siluer streames</L>
<L>That pierce earths bowels to mainteine the sorce,</L>
<L>Play vpon Rubies, Saphires, Chrisolites,</L>
<L>The brims let be imbrac'd with golden curles</L>
<L>Of mosse that sleepes with sound the waters make,</L>
<L>For ioy to feed the fount with their recourse,</L>
<L>Let all the grasse that beautifies her bower,</L>
<L>Beare Manna euery morne in steed of dew,</L>
<L>Or let the dew be sweeter far then that</L>
<L>That hangs like chaines of pearle on Hermon hill,</L>
<L>Or balme which trickled from old Arons beard.</L>
<L>Cusay, come vp and serue thy lord the King.
<STAGE>Enter Cus.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cus.</SPEAKER>
<L>What seruice doth my lord the King command?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dauid.</SPEAKER>
<L>See Cusay see, the flower of Israel,</L>
<L>The fairest daughter that obeies the King,</L>
<L>In all the land the lord subdued to me.</L>
<L>Fairer then Isacs louer at the well,</L>
<L>Brighter then inside barke of new hewen Caedar,</L>
<L>Sweeter then flames of fine perfumed myrrhe.</L>
<L>And comelier then the siluer clouds that dance</L>
<L>On Zephires wings before the king of heauen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is it not Bethsabe the Hethites wife</L>
<L>Vrias, now at Rabath siege with Ioab?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe know, and bring her quickly to the King,</L>
<L>Tell her, her graces hath found grace with him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cusay.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will my lord.
<STAGE>Exit Cusay to Bethsabe.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dauid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bright Bethsabe shall wash in Dauids bower,</L>
<L>In water mix'd with purest Almond flower,</L>
<L>And bath her beautie in the milke of kids,</L>
<L><PB REF="4"/>Bright Bethsabe giues earth to my desires,</L>
<L>Verdure to earth, and to that verdure flowers,</L>
<L>To flowers, sweet Odors, and to Odors wings,</L>
<L>That carrie pleasures to the hearts of Kings.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Cusay to Bethsabe, she starting as something afright.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cusay.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faire Bethsabe, the King of Israell</L>
<L>From forth his Princely tower hath seen thee bath,</L>
<L>And thy sweet graces haue found grace with him,</L>
<L>Come then and kneele vnto him where he stands,</L>
<L>The King is gracious, and hath liberall hands.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beth.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ah what is Bethsabe to please the King,</L>
<L>Or what is Dauid, that he should desire</L>
<L>For fickle beuties sake his seruants wife?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cusay.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dauid (thou knowest faire dame) is wise and iust,</L>
<L>Elected to the heart of Israels God,</L>
<L>Then doe not thou expostulate with him</L>
<L>For any action that contents his soule.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beth.</SPEAKER>
<L>My lord the King, elect to Gods owne heart,</L>
<L>Should not his gracious ielousie incense,</L>
<L>Whose thoughts are chast, I hate incontinence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cusay.</SPEAKER>
<L>Woman thou wrongst the King &amp; doubtst his ho∣nour,</L>
<L>Whose truth mainteines the crowne of Israel,</L>
<L>Making him stay, that bad me bring thee strait.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beth.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Kings poore handmaid will obey my lord,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then come and doe thy dutie to his grace,</L>
<L>And doe what seemeth fauour in his sight.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dauid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now comes my louer tripping like the Roe,</L>
<L>And brings my longings tangled in her haire,</L>
<L>To ioy her loue Ile build a kingly bower,</L>
<L>Seated in hearing of a hundred streames,</L>
<L>That for their homage to her souereine ioies,</L>
<L>Shall as the serpents sold into their nests,</L>
<L>In oblique turnings wind the nimble waues,</L>
<L>About the circles of her curious walkes,</L>
<L><PB REF="4"/>And with their murmure summon easefull sleepe,</L>
<L>To lay his golden scepter on her browes,</L>
<L>Open the dores, and enterteine my loue,</L>
<L>Open I say, and as you open sing,</L>
<L>Welcome faire Bethsabe King Dauids darling.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Cusay with Bethsabe.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dauid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Welcome faire Bethsabe King Dauids darling,</L>
<L>Thy bones faire couering, erst discouered faire,</L>
<L>And all mine eyes with all thy beuties pierst,</L>
<L>As heauens bright eye burnes most when most he climes</L>
<L>The crooked Zodiake with his fierie sphere,</L>
<L>And shineth furthest from this earthly globe:</L>
<L>So since thy beautie scorcht my conquerd soule,</L>
<L>I cald thee neerer for my neerer cure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bethsa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Too neere my lord was your vnarmed heart,</L>
<L>When furthest off my haplesse beautie pierc'd,</L>
<L>And would this drerie day had turnd to night,</L>
<L>Or that some pitchie cloud had clok'd the Sun,</L>
<L>Before their lights had caus'd my lord to see</L>
<L>His name disparag'd, and my chastitie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dauid.</SPEAKER>
<L>My loue, if want of loue haue left thy soule,</L>
<L>A sharper sence of Honor then thy King,</L>
<L>(For loue leads Princes sometimes from their seats,)</L>
<L>As erst my heart was hurt, displeasing thee,</L>
<L>So come and tast thy ease, with easing me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beth.</SPEAKER>
<L>One medicine cannot heale our different harmes.</L>
<L>But rather make both ranckle at the bone,</L>
<L>Then let the King be cunning in his cure,</L>
<L>Least flattering both, both perish in his hand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dauid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Leaue it to me my deerest Bethsabe,</L>
<L>Whose skill is conuersant in deeper cures,</L>
<L>And Cusay hast thou to my seruant Ioab,</L>
<L>Commanding him to send Vrias home</L>
<L>With all the speed can possibly be vsed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cusay.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cusay will flie about the Kings desire.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="5"/><HI>Ioab, Abisay, Vrias, and others, with drum and ensigne.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ioab.</SPEAKER>
<L>Courage ye mightie men of Israel,</L>
<L>And charge your fatall instruments of war</L>
<L>Vpon the bosomes of prowd Ammons sonnes,</L>
<L>That haue disguisd your Kings Embassadors,</L>
<L>Cut halfe their beards, and halfe their garments off,</L>
<L>In spight of Israel, and his daughters sonnes,</L>
<L>Ye fight the holy battels of Iehoua,</L>
<L>King Dauids God, and ours and Iacobs God</L>
<L>That guides your weapons to their conquering strokes,</L>
<L>Orders your footsteps, and directs your thoughts</L>
<L>To stratagems that harbor victorie:</L>
<L>He casts his sacred eiesight from on high,</L>
<L>And sees your foes run seeking for their deaths,</L>
<L>Laughing their labours and their hopes to scorne,</L>
<L>While twixt your bodies, and their blunted swords,</L>
<L>He puts on armor of his honors proofe,</L>
<L>And makes their weapons wound the sencelesse winds.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Before this citie Rabath we will lie,</L>
<L>And shoot forth shafts as thicke and dangerous</L>
<L>As was the haile that Moises mixt with fire,</L>
<L>And threw with furie round about the fields</L>
<L>Deuouring Pharoes friends, and Egypts fruits.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrias.</SPEAKER>
<L>First mighty captaines, Ioab and Abisay,</L>
<L>Let vs assault and scale this kingly Tower,</L>
<L>Where all their conduits and their fountaines are,</L>
<L>Then we may easily take the citie too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ioab.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well hath Vrias counseld our attempts,</L>
<L>And as he spake vs, so assault the Tower,</L>
<L>Let Hanon now the king of Ammons sonne,</L>
<L>Repulse our conquering passage if he dare.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Hanon with King Machaas and others, vpon the wals.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hanon.</SPEAKER>
<L>What would the shepheards dogs of Israel</L>
<L>Snatch from the mighty issue of King Ammon,</L>
<L>The valiant Amonnes, and haughty Syrians?</L>
<L><PB REF="5"/>Tis not your late successiue victories,</L>
<L>Can make vs yeeld, or quaile our courages,</L>
<L>But if ye date assay to scale this Tower,</L>
<L>Our angrie swords shall smite ye to the ground,</L>
<L>And venge our losses on your hatefull liues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ioab.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hanon, thy father Nahas gaue releefe</L>
<L>To holy Dauid in his haplesse exile,</L>
<L>Liued his fixed date, and died in peace:</L>
<L>But thou in steed of reaping his reward,</L>
<L>Hast trod it vnderfoot, and scornd our King,</L>
<L>Therefore thy daies shall end with violence,</L>
<L>And to our swords thy vitall bloud shall cleaue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mach.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hence thou that bearst poor Israels shepherds hook,</L>
<L>The prowd lieutenant of that base borne King,</L>
<L>And kep within the compasse of his fold,</L>
<L>For if ye seeke to feed on Ammons fruits,</L>
<L>And stray into the Syrians fruitfull Medes,</L>
<L>The mastiues of our land, shall werry ye,</L>
<L>And pull the weesels from your greedy throtes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who can indure these Pagans blasphemies,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrias.</SPEAKER>
<L>My soule repines at this disparagement.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ioab.</SPEAKER>
<L>Assault ye valiant men of Dauids host,</L>
<L>And beat these railing dastards from their dores.</L>
<STAGE>Assault, and they win the Tower, and Ioab speakes aboue.</STAGE>
<L>Thus haue we won the Tower, which we will keepe,</L>
<L>Maugre the sonnes of Ammon, and of Syria.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Cusay beneath.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where is lord Ioab leader of the host?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ioab.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here is lord Ioab, leader of the host.</L>
<L>Cusay come vp, for we haue won the hold.
<STAGE>He comes.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cusay.</SPEAKER>
<L>In happie hower then is Cusay come.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ioab.</SPEAKER>
<L>What news then brings lord Cusay from the king.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cusay.</SPEAKER>
<L>His maiestie commands thee out of hand</L>
<L>To send him home Vrias from the wars,</L>
<L>For matter of some seruice he should doe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="6"/>
<SPEAKER>Vrias,</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis for no choler hath surpris'd the King,</L>
<L>(I hope lord Cusay) gainst his seruants truth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cusay.</SPEAKER>
<L>No rather to prefer Vrias truth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ioab.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here take him with thee then, and goe in peace,</L>
<L>And tell my lord the King that I haue fought</L>
<L>Against the citie Rabath with successe,</L>
<L>And skaled where the royall pallace is,</L>
<L>The conduit heads and all their sweetest springs,</L>
<L>Then let him come in person to these wals,</L>
<L>With all the souldiers he can bring besides,</L>
<L>And take the city as his owne exploit,</L>
<L>Least I surprise it, and the people giue</L>
<L>The glory of the conquest to my name.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cus.</SPEAKER>
<L>We will Lord Ioab, and great Israels God</L>
<L>Blesse in thy hands the battels of our King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ioab.</SPEAKER>
<L>Earewell Vrias, hast away the King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrias.</SPEAKER>
<L>As sure as Ioab breaths a victor here,</L>
<L>Vrias will hast him, and his owne returne.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abisa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let vs descend, and ope the pallace gate,</L>
<L>Taking our souldiors in to keepe the hold.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ioab.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let vs Abisay, and ye sonnes of Iuda,</L>
<L>Be valiant, and mainteine your victory.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ammon, Ionadab, Iethray, and Ammons page.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ionad.</SPEAKER>
<L>What meanes my lord, the Kings beloued son▪</L>
<L>That weares vpon his right triumphant arme,</L>
<L>The power of Israel for a royall fauor,</L>
<L>That holds vpon the Tables of his hands,</L>
<L>Banquets of honor, and all thoughts content</L>
<L>To suffer pale and grisely abstinence</L>
<L>To sit and feed vpon his fainting cheekes,</L>
<L>And sucke away the bloud that cheeres his lookes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ammo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ah Ionadab it is my sisters lookes,</L>
<L>On whose sweet beutie I bestow my bloud,</L>
<L>That makes me looke so amorously leane,</L>
<L>Her beautie hauing seafd vpon my heart▪</L>
<L><PB REF="6"/>So merrily consecrate to her content,</L>
<L>Sets now such guard about his vitall bloud,</L>
<L>And viewes the passage with such piercing eyes,</L>
<L>That none can scape to cheare my pining cheekes,</L>
<L>But all is thought too little for her loue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iona.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then from her heart thy lookes shall be releeued,</L>
<L>And thou shalt ioy her as thy soule desires.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ammon.</SPEAKER>
<L>How can it be my sweet friend Ionadab,</L>
<L>Since Thamar is a virgine and my sister?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iona.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thus it shall be, lie downe vpon thy bed,</L>
<L>Faining thee feuer sicke, and ill at ease,</L>
<L>And when the king shall come to visit thee,</L>
<L>Desire thy sister Thamar may be sent</L>
<L>To dresse some deinties for thy maladie:</L>
<L>Then when thou hast her solely with thy selfe,</L>
<L>Enforce some fauour to thy manly loue:</L>
<L>See where she comes, intreat her in with thee.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Thamar.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thamar.</SPEAKER>
<L>What aileth Ammon with such sickly lookes,</L>
<L>To daunt the fauour of his louely face?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Am.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweet Thamar sick, &amp; wish some wholesome cates</L>
<L>Drest with the cunning of thy daintie hands.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tham.</SPEAKER>
<L>That hath the King commanded at my hands</L>
<L>Then come and rest thee, while I make thee readie</L>
<L>Some dainties, easefull to thy crased soule.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Am.</SPEAKER>
<L>I goe sweet sister, eased with thy sight.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt. Restet Ionadab.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ion.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why should a Prince, whose power may command,</L>
<L>Obey the rebell passions of his loue,</L>
<L>When they contend but gainst his conscience,</L>
<L>And may be gouernd or supprest by will.</L>
<L>Now Ammon lose those louing knots of bloud,</L>
<L>That sokte the courage from thy kingly heart,</L>
<L>And giue it passage to thy withered cheekes:</L>
<L>Now Thamar ripened are the holy fruits</L>
<L><PB REF="7"/>That grew on plants of thy virginitie,</L>
<L>And rotten is thy name in Israel,</L>
<L>Poore Thamar, little did thy louely hands</L>
<L>Foretell an action of such violence,</L>
<L>As to contend with Ammons lusty armes,</L>
<L>Sinnewd with vigor of his landlesse loue,</L>
<L>Faire Thamar now dishonour hunts thy foot,</L>
<L>And followes thee through euery couert shade,</L>
<L>Discouering thy shame and nakednesse</L>
<L>Euen from the valeyes of Iehosophat,</L>
<L>Vp to the loftie mounts of Libanon,</L>
<L>Where Caedars stird with anger of the winds,</L>
<L>Sounding in stormes the tale of thy disgrace,</L>
<L>Tremble with furie, and with murmure shake</L>
<L>Eearth with their feet, and with their heads the heauens,</L>
<L>Beating the clouds into their swiftest racke,</L>
<L>To beare this wonder round about the world.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ammon thrusting out Thamar.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Am.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hence from my bed, whose sight offends my soule</L>
<L>As doth the parbreake of disgorged beares.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thama.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vnkind, vnprincely, and vnmanly Ammon▪</L>
<L>To force, and then refuse thy sisters loue:</L>
<L>Adding vnto the fright of thy offence,</L>
<L>The banefull torment of my publisht shame,</L>
<L>O doe not this dishonor to thy loue,</L>
<L>Nor clog thy soule with such increasing sinne,</L>
<L>This second euill far exceeds the first.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Am.</SPEAKER>
<L>Iethray come thrust this woman from my sight,</L>
<L>And bolt the dore vpon hir if she striue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iethray.</SPEAKER>
<L>Go madame goe, away, you must be gone,</L>
<L>My lord hath done with you, I pray depart.
<STAGE>He shuts her out.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tham.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whether alasse, ah whether shall I flie</L>
<L>With folded armes, and all amased soule,</L>
<L>Cast as was Eua from that glorious soile</L>
<L>(Where al delights sat bating wingd with thoughts,</L>
<L><PB REF="7"/>Ready to nestle in her naked breasts)</L>
<L>To bare and barraine vales with floods made wast,</L>
<L>To desart woods, and hils with lightening scorcht,</L>
<L>With death, with shame, with hell, with horrour sit,</L>
<L>There will I wander from my fathers face,</L>
<L>There Absolon, my brother Absolon,</L>
<L>Sweet Absolon shall heare his sister mourne,</L>
<L>There will I liue with my windie sighs,</L>
<L>Night Rauens and Owles to rend my bloudie side,</L>
<L>Which with a rustie weapon I will wound,</L>
<L>And makee them passage to my panting heart:</L>
<L>Why talkst thon wretch, and leaust the deed vndone.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Absolon.</STAGE>
<L>Rend haire and garments as thy heart is rent,</L>
<L>With inward furie of a thousand greefes,</L>
<L>And scatter them by these vnhallowed dores.</L>
<L>To figure Ammons resting crueltie,</L>
<L>And Tragicke spoile of Thamars chastitie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abs.</SPEAKER>
<L>What causeth Thamar to exclaime so much?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tham.</SPEAKER>
<L>The cause that Thamar shameth to disclose.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Absa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Say, I thy brother will reuenge that cause.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tham.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ammon our fathers son hath forced me,</L>
<L>And thrusts me from him as the scorne of Israel.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abs.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hath Ammon forced thee? by Dauids hand,</L>
<L>And by the couenant God hath made with him,</L>
<L>Ammon shall beare his violence to hell,</L>
<L>Traitor to Heauen, traitor to Dauids throne,</L>
<L>Traitor to Absolon and Israel.</L>
<L>This fact hath Iacobs ruler seene from heauen,</L>
<L>And through a cloud of smoake, and tower of fire</L>
<L>(As he rides vaunting him vpon the greenes)</L>
<L>Shall teare his chariot wheeles with violent winds,</L>
<L>And throw his body in the bloudy sea,</L>
<L>At him the thunder shall discharge his bolt,</L>
<L>And his faire spouse, with bright and fierie wings</L>
<L><PB REF="8"/>Sit euer burning on his hatefull bones,</L>
<L>My selfe as swift as thunder, or his spouse,</L>
<L>Will hunt occasion with a secret hate,</L>
<L>To worke false Ammon an vngracious end:</L>
<L>Goe in my sister, rest thee in my house,</L>
<L>And God in time shall take this shame from thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tham.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor God nor Time will doe that good for me.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Tham. restat Absolon.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Dauid with his traine.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dauid.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Absolon, what makst thou here alone,</L>
<L>And beares such discontentment in thy browes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abs.</SPEAKER>
<L>Great cause hath Absolon to be displeasd,</L>
<L>And in his heart to shrowd the wounds of wrath.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dauid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gainst whom should Absolon be thus displeased?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abs.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gainst wicked Ammon thy vngracious sonne,</L>
<L>My brother and faire Thamars by the King,</L>
<L>My stepbrother, by mother, and by kind,</L>
<L>He hath dishonoured Dauids holinesse,</L>
<L>And fixt a blot of lightnesse on his throne,</L>
<L>Forcing my sister Thamar when he faind</L>
<L>A sickenesse, sprung from root of hemous lust.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dauid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hath Ammon brought this euill on my house,</L>
<L>And suffered sinne to smite his fathers bones,</L>
<L>Smite Dauid deadlier then the voice of heauen,</L>
<L>And let hates fire be kindled in thy heart,</L>
<L>Frame in the arches of thy angrie browes,</L>
<L>Making thy forehead like a comet shine,</L>
<L>To force false Ammon tremble at thy lookes,</L>
<L>Sin with his seuenfold crowne and purple robe,</L>
<L>Begins his triumphs in my guiltie throne,</L>
<L>There sits he watching with his hundred eyes,</L>
<L>Our idle minuts, and our wanton thoughts,</L>
<L>And with his baits made of our fraile desires,</L>
<L>Giues vs the hooke that hales our soules to hell:</L>
<L>But with the spirit of my kingdomes God,</L>
<L><PB REF="8"/>Ile thrust the flattering Tyran from his throne,</L>
<L>And scourge his bondslaues from my hallowed court</L>
<L>With rods of yron, and thornes of sharpened steele:</L>
<L>Then Absolon reuenge not thou this sin,</L>
<L>Leaue it to me, and I will chasten him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abs.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am content, then graunt my lord the king</L>
<L>Himselfe with all his other lords would come</L>
<L>Vp to my sheepe feast on the plaine of Hazor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Da.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay my faire sonne, my selfe with all my lords</L>
<L>Will bring thee too much charge, yet some shall goe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abs.</SPEAKER>
<L>But let my lord the king himselfe take paines,</L>
<L>The time of yeare is pleasant for your grace,</L>
<L>And gladsome Summer in her shadie robes,</L>
<L>Crowned with Roses and with planted flowers,</L>
<L>With all her nimphs shall enterteine my lord▪</L>
<L>That from the thicket of my verdant groues,</L>
<L>Will sprinckle hony dewes about his brest,</L>
<L>And cast sweet balme vpon his kingly head,</L>
<L>Then grant thy seruants boone, and goe my lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let it content my sweet sonne Absolon,</L>
<L>That I may stay and take my other lords.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abs.</SPEAKER>
<L>But shall thy best beloued Ammon goe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dau.</SPEAKER>
<L>What needeth it that Ammon goe with thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abs.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet doe thy sonne and seruant so much grace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ammon shall goe, and all my other lords,</L>
<L>Because I will giue grace to Absolon.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Cusay, and Vrias, with others.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cusay.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pleaseth my lord the king, his seruant Ioab</L>
<L>Hath sent Vrias from the Syrian wars.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Welcome Vrias from the Syrian wars,</L>
<L>Welcome to Dauid as his deerest lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrias.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thankes be to Israels God, and Dauids grace,</L>
<L>Vrias finds such greeting with the king.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dau.</SPEAKER>
<L>No other greeting shall Vrias find,</L>
<L>As long as Dauids swaies the elected seat,</L>
<L><PB REF="9"/>And consecrated throne of Israel.</L>
<L>Tell me Vrias of my seruant Ioab▪</L>
<L>Fights he with truth the battels of our God,</L>
<L>And for the honor of the Lords annointed?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrias.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy seruant Ioab fights the chosen wars</L>
<L>With truth, with honour, and with high successe,</L>
<L>And gainst the wicked King of Ammons sonnes,</L>
<L>Hath by the finger of our souereines God,</L>
<L>Besieg'd the citie Rabath, and atchieu'd</L>
<L>The court of waters, where the conduits run,</L>
<L>And all the <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="bleedthrough" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> delight <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="bleedthrough" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> springs:</L>
<L>Therefore he wisheth Dauids mightinesse</L>
<L>Should number out the host of Israel,</L>
<L>And come in person to the citie Rabath,</L>
<L>That so her conquest may be made the kings,</L>
<L>And Ioab fight as his inferior.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dauid.</SPEAKER>
<L>This hath dot God, and Ioabs prowesse done,</L>
<L>Without Vrias valours, I am sure,</L>
<L>Who since his true conuersion from a Hethite,</L>
<L>To an adopted sonne of Israel,</L>
<L>Hath sought like one whose armes were lift by heauen,</L>
<L>And whose bright sword was edgd with Israels wrath:</L>
<L>Goe therefore home Vrias, take thy rest,</L>
<L>Visit thy wife and houshold with the ioies</L>
<L>A victor and a fauorite of the Kings</L>
<L>Should exercise with honor after armes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrias.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy seruants bones are yet not halfe so cra<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>de,</L>
<L>Nor constitute on such a sickly mould,</L>
<L>That for so little seruice he should faine,</L>
<L>And seeke (as cowards) refuge of his home:</L>
<L>Not are his thoughts so sensually stird,</L>
<L>To stay the armes with which the lord would smite</L>
<L>And fill <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="bleedthrough" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> circle with his conquered foes,</L>
<L>For wanton bosome of a flattering wife.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Da.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vrias hath a beauteous sober wife,</L>
<L>Yet yong, and framd of tempting flesh and bloud,</L>
<L><PB REF="9"/>Then when the King hath summond thee from armes,</L>
<L>If thou vnkindly shouldst refraine her bed,</L>
<L>Sinne might be laid vpon Vrias soule,</L>
<L>If Bethsabe by frailtie hurt her fame:</L>
<L>Then goe Vrias, <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="bleedthrough" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> in her loue,</L>
<L>Whom God hath knit to thee, tremble to lose.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrias.</SPEAKER>
<L>The King is much too tender of my ease,</L>
<L>The arke, and Israel, and Iuda dwell</L>
<L>In pallaces, and rich pauillions,</L>
<L>But Ioab and his brother in the fields,</L>
<L>Suffering the wrath of Winter and the Sun:</L>
<L>And shall Vrias (of more shame then they)</L>
<L>Banquet and loiter, in the worke of heauen?</L>
<L>As sure as thy soule doth liue my lord,</L>
<L>Mine eares shall neuer leane to such delight,</L>
<L>When holy labour cals me forth to fight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dauid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then be it with Vrias manly heart,</L>
<L>As best his fame may shine in Israel.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrias.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thus shall Vrias heart be best content,</L>
<L>Till thou dismisse me backe to Ioabs hands,</L>
<L>This ground before the king my masters dores,
<STAGE>He lies downe.</STAGE></L>
<L>Shall be my couch, and this vnwearied arme,</L>
<L>The proper pillow of a souldiours head,</L>
<L>For neuer will I lodge within my house,</L>
<L>Till Ioab triumph in my secret vowes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dauid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then fetch some flagons of our purest Wine,</L>
<L>That we may welcome home our hardie friend,</L>
<L>With full carouses to his fortunes past,</L>
<L>And to the honours of his future armes,</L>
<L>Then will I send him backe to Rabath siege,</L>
<L>And follow with the strength of Israel.</L>
<STAGE>Enter one with the flagons of Wine.</STAGE>
<L>Arise Vrias, come and pledge the King.
<STAGE>He riseth.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrias.</SPEAKER>
<L>If Dauid thinke me worthy such a grace,</L>
<L><PB REF="10"/>I will be bold, and pledge my lord the king.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Absolon and Cusay both shall drinke</L>
<L>To good Vrias, and his happinesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abs.</SPEAKER>
<L>We will my lord to please Vrias soule.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dau.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will begin Vrias to thy selfe,</L>
<L>And all the treasure of the Ammonites,</L>
<L>Which here I promise to impart to thee,</L>
<L>And bind that promise with a full carous.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrias.</SPEAKER>
<L>What seemeth pleasant in my souereines eyes,</L>
<L>That shall Vrias doe till he be dead</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fill him the cup, follow ye lords that loue</L>
<L>Your souereines health, and doe as he hath done.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abs.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ill may he thriue or liue in Israel,</L>
<L>That loues not Dauid, or denies his charge.</L>
<L>Vrias, Here is to Abisais health, lord Ioabs brother, &amp; thy lo∣uing friend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrias.</SPEAKER>
<L>I pledge lord Absolon and Abisais health.
<STAGE>He drinkes.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here now Vrias, to the health of Ioab,</L>
<L>And to the pleasant iourny we shall haue,</L>
<L>When we returne to mightie Rabath siege.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrias.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cusay I pledge thee all, with all my heart,</L>
<L>Giue me some drinke ye seruants of the king,</L>
<L>Giue me my drinke.
<STAGE>He drinkes.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Da.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well done my good Vrias, drinke thy fill,</L>
<L>That in thy fulnesse Dauid may reioice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrias.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will my lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abs.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now lord Vrias, one carouse to me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrias.</SPEAKER>
<L>No sir, Ile drinke to the King,</L>
<L>Your father is a better man then you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe so Vrias, I will pledge thee straight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrias.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will indeed my lord and souereine,</L>
<L>I once in my daies be so bold.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dauid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fill him his glasse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrias.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fill me my glasse.
<STAGE>He giues him the glasse.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Quickly I say.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrias.</SPEAKER>
<L>Quickly I say.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrias.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here my lord, by your fauour now I drinke to you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dau.</SPEAKER>
<L>I pledge thee good Vrias presently.
<STAGE>He drinkes.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="10"/>
<SPEAKER>Abs.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here then Vrias, once againe for me,</L>
<L>And to the health of Dauids children.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrias.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dauids children?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abs.</SPEAKER>
<L>I Dauids children, wilt thou pledge me man?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrias.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pledge me man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abs.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pledge me I say, or else thou louest vs not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrias.</SPEAKER>
<L>What doe you talke, doe you talke?</L>
<L>Ile no more, Ile lie downe here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dauid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rather Vrias goe thou home and sleepe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrias.</SPEAKER>
<L>O ho sir, would you make me break my sentence.</L>
<STAGE>He lies downe.</STAGE>
<L>Home sir, no indeed sir? Ile sleepe vpon mine arme,</L>
<L>Like a souldiour, sleepe like a man as long as I liue in Israel.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dauid.</SPEAKER>
<L>If nought will serue to saue his wiues renowne,</L>
<L>Ile send him with a letter vnto Ioab</L>
<L>To put him in the forefront of the wars,</L>
<L>That so my purposes may take effect.</L>
<L>Helpe him in sirs.
<STAGE>Exit Dauid and Absolon.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cusay.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come rise Vrias, get thee in and sleepe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrias.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will not goe home sir, thats flat.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cusay.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then come and rest thee vpon Dauids bed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrias.</SPEAKER>
<L>On afore my lords, on afore.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
<STAGE>Chorus.</STAGE>
<L>O prowd reuolt of a presumptious man,</L>
<L>Laying his bridle in the necke of sin,</L>
<L>Ready to beare him past his graue to hell,</L>
<L>Like as the fatall Rauen, that in his voice</L>
<L>Carries the dreadfull summons of our deaths,</L>
<L>Flies by the faire Arabian spiceries,</L>
<L>Her pleasant gardens, and delightsome parkes,</L>
<L>Seeming to curse them with his hoarse exclaimes,</L>
<L>And yet doth stoope with hungrie violence</L>
<L>Vpon a peece of hatefull carrion:</L>
<L>So wretched man, displeasd with those delights,</L>
<L>Would yeeld a quickning sauor to his Soule,</L>
<L><PB REF="11"/>Pursues with eagre and vnstanched thirst,</L>
<L>The greedie longings of his lothsome flesh,</L>
<L>If holy Dauid so shoke hands with sinne,</L>
<L>What shall our baser spirits glorie in.</L>
<L>This kingly giuing lust her raigne,</L>
<L>Pursues the sequell with a greater ill.</L>
<L>Vrias in the forefront of the wars,</L>
<L>Is murthered by the hateful Heathens sword,</L>
<L>And Dauid ioies his too deere Bethsabe,</L>
<L>Suppose this past, and that the child is borne,</L>
<L>Whose death the Prophet solemnly doth mourne.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Bethsabe with her handmaid.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beth.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mourne Bethsabe, bewaile thy foolishnesse,</L>
<L>Thy sinne, thy shame, the sorrow of thy soule,</L>
<L>Sinne, shame, and sorrow swarme about thy soule,</L>
<L>And in the gates and entrance of my heart,</L>
<L>Sadnesse with wreathed armes hangs her complaint.</L>
<L>No comfort from the ten string'd instrument,</L>
<L>The twinckling Cymball, or the Yuorie Lute,</L>
<L>Nor doth the sound of Dauids kingly Harpe,</L>
<L>Make glad the broken heart of Bersabe.</L>
<L>Ierusalem is fild with thy complaint,</L>
<L>And in the streets of Syon fits thy greefe:</L>
<L>The babe in sicke, sicke to the death I feare,</L>
<L>The fruit that sprung from thee to Dauids house,</L>
<L>Nor may the pot of Honny and of Oyle,</L>
<L>Glad Dauid or his handmaids countenance.</L>
<L>Vrias, woe is me to thinke hereon,</L>
<L>For who is it among the sonnes of men,</L>
<L>That sayth not to my soule, the King hath sind,</L>
<L>Dauid hath done amisse, and Bersabe</L>
<L>Laid snares of death vnto Vrias life.</L>
<L>My sweet Vrias, falne into the pit</L>
<L>Art thou, and gone euen to the gates of hell,</L>
<L><PB REF="11"/>For Bersabe, that wouldst not shrowd her shame.</L>
<L>O what is it to serue the lust of Kings,</L>
<L>How Lyonlike thy rage when we resist,</L>
<L>But Bersabe in humblenesse attend,</L>
<L>The grace that God will to his handmaid send.
<STAGE>Exit Beth.</STAGE></L>
<STAGE>Dauid in his gowne walking sadly, To him Nathan.</STAGE>
<L>The babe is sicke, and sad is Dauids heart,</L>
<L>To see the guiltlesse beare the guilties paine.</L>
<L>Dauid hang vp thy Harpe, hang downe thy head,</L>
<L>And dash thy yuorie Lute against the stones.</L>
<L>The dew that on the hill of Hermon fals,</L>
<L>Raines not on Syons tops, and loftie towers,</L>
<L>And Dauids thoughts are spent in pensiuenesse,</L>
<L>The plaines of Gath and Askaron reioice.</L>
<L>The babe is sicke, sweet babe, that Bersabe</L>
<L>With womans paine brought forth to Israel.
<STAGE>Enter Nathan.</STAGE></L>
<L>But what saith Nathan to his lord the king?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Nathan to Dauid.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nathan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thus Nathan saith vnto his Lord the King:</L>
<L>There were two men both dwellers in one towne,</L>
<L>The one was mighty and exceeding rich</L>
<L>In Oxen, sheepe and cattell of the field,</L>
<L>The other poore hauing nor Oxe, nor Calfe,</L>
<L>Nor other cattell, saue one little Lambe,</L>
<L>Which he had bought and nourisht by the hand,</L>
<L>And it grew vp, and fed with him and his,</L>
<L>And eat and dranke as he and his were wont,</L>
<L>And in his bosome slept, and was to liue</L>
<L>As was his daughter or his deerest child.</L>
<L>There came a stranger to this wealthy man,</L>
<L>And he refus'd and spar'd to take his owne,</L>
<L>Or of his store to dresse or make him meat,</L>
<L>But tooke the poore mans sheepe, partly poore mans store,</L>
<L>And drest it for this strangar in his house:</L>
<L>What (tell me) shall be done to him for this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="12"/>
<SPEAKER>Dau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now as the lord doth liue, this wicked man</L>
<L>Is iudgd, and shall become the child of death,</L>
<L>Foure fold to the poore man shall he restore,</L>
<L>That without mercy tooke his lambe away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nath.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art the man, and thou hast iudgd thy selfe,</L>
<L>Dauid, thus sayth the Lord thy God by me:</L>
<L>I thee annointed King in Israel,</L>
<L>And sau'd thee from the tyranny of Saul,</L>
<L>Thy maisters house I gaue thee to possesse,</L>
<L>His Wiues into thy bosome did I giue,</L>
<L>And Iuda aud Ierusalem withall,</L>
<L>And might (thou knowest) if this had ben too small,</L>
<L>Haue giuen thee more.</L>
<L>Wherefore then hast thou gone so far astray,</L>
<L>And hast done euill, and sinned in my sight?</L>
<L>Vrias thou hast killed with the sword,</L>
<L>Yea with the sword of the vncircumcised</L>
<L>Thou hast him slaine, wherefore from this day forth,</L>
<L>The sword shall neuer goe from thee and thine:</L>
<L>For thou hast tane this Hethites wife to thee,</L>
<L>Wherefore behold, I wil (saith Iacobs God)</L>
<L>In thine owne house stir euill vp to thee,</L>
<L>Yea I before thy face will take thy Wiues,</L>
<L>And giue them to thy neighbour to possesse:</L>
<L>This shall be done to Dauid in the day,</L>
<L>That Israel openly may see thy shame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dauid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nathan, I haue against the Lord, I haue</L>
<L>Sinned, O sinned greeuously, and loe</L>
<L>From heauens throne doth Dauid throw himselfe,</L>
<L>And grone and grouell to the gates of hell.
<STAGE>He fals downe.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nath.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dauid stand vp, Thus saith the Lord by me,</L>
<L>Dauid the King shall liue, for he hath seene</L>
<L>The true repentant sorrow of thy heart,</L>
<L>But for thou hast in this misdeed of thine</L>
<L>Stird vp the enemies of Israel</L>
<L>To triumph and blasphe me the God of hosts,</L>
<L><PB REF="12"/>And say, He set a wicked man to reigne,</L>
<L>Ouer his loued people and his Tribes:</L>
<L>The child shall surely die, that erst was borne,</L>
<L>His mothers sin, his kingly fathers scorne.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Nathan.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Da.</SPEAKER>
<L>How iust is Iacobs God in all his workes!</L>
<L>But must it die that Dauid loueth so?</L>
<L>O that the mighty one of Israel</L>
<L>Nill change his dome, and sayes the babe must die,</L>
<L>Mourne Israel and weepe in Syon gates,</L>
<L>Wither ye Caedar trees of Libanon,</L>
<L>Ye sprouting Almons with your flowring tops,</L>
<L>Droope, drowne, and drench in Hebrons fearefull streames.</L>
<L>The babe must die that was to Dauid borne,</L>
<L>His mothers sin his kingly fathers scorne.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Dauid sits sadly.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Cusay to Dauid and his traine.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seruus.</SPEAKER>
<L>What tidings bringeth Cusay to the King?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cusay.</SPEAKER>
<L>To thee the seruant of King Dauids court,</L>
<L>This bringeth Cusay, as the Prophet spake,</L>
<L>The Lord hath surely striken to the death,</L>
<L>The child new borne by that Vrias wife,</L>
<L>That by the sonnes of Ammon erst was slaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seruus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cusay be still, the King is vexed sore,</L>
<L>How shal he speed that brings this tidings first,</L>
<L>When while the child was yet aliue, we spake,</L>
<L>And Dauids heart would not be comforted?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Da.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yea Dauids heart will not be comforted,</L>
<L>What murmure ye the seruants of the King,</L>
<L>What tidings telleth Cusay to the King?</L>
<L>Say Cusay, liues the child, or is he dead?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cusay.</SPEAKER>
<L>The child is dead, that of Vrias wife, Dauid begat.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Da.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vrias wife saiest thou?</L>
<L>The child is dead, then ceaseth Dauids shame,</L>
<L>Fetch me to eat, and giue me Wine to drinke,</L>
<L><PB REF="13"/>Water to wash, and Oyle to cleere my lookes,</L>
<L>Bring downe your Shalmes, your Cymbals, and your Pipes,</L>
<L>Let Dauids Harpe and Lute, his hand and voice,</L>
<L>Giue laud to him that loueth Israel,</L>
<L>And sing his praise, that shendeth Dauids fame,</L>
<L>That put away his sinne from out his sight,</L>
<L>And sent his shame into the streets of Gath,</L>
<L>Bring ye to me the mother of the babe,</L>
<L>That I may wipe the teares from off her face,</L>
<L>And giue her comfort with this hand of mine,</L>
<L>And decke faire Bersabe with ornaments,</L>
<L>That she may beare to me another sonne,</L>
<L>That may be loued of the Lord of hosts:</L>
<L>For where he is, of force must Dauid goe,</L>
<L>But neuer may he come where Dauid is.</L>
<STAGE>They bring in water, wine, and oyle, Musike, and a banquet.</STAGE>
<L>Faire Bersabe, sit thou, and sigh no more,</L>
<L>And sing and play you seruants of the King,</L>
<L>Now sleepeth Dauids sorrow with the dead,</L>
<L>And Bersabe liueth to Israel.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>They vse all solemnities together, and sing, &amp;c.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dauid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now armes, and warlike engins for assault,</L>
<L>Prepare at once ye men of Israel,</L>
<L>Ye men of Iuda and Ierusalem,</L>
<L>That Rabba may be taken by the King,</L>
<L>Least it be called after Ioabs name,</L>
<L>Nor Dauids glory shine in Syon streets,</L>
<L>To Rabba marcheth Dauid with his men</L>
<L>To chastise Ammon and the wicked ones.
<STAGE>Exeunt omnes.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Absolon with two or three.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abs.</SPEAKER>
<L>Set vp your mules, and giue them well to ear,</L>
<L>And let vs meet our brothers at the feast,</L>
<L>Accursed is the maister of this feast,</L>
<L><PB REF="13"/>Dishonour of the house of Israel,</L>
<L>His sisters slander, and his mothers shame.</L>
<L>Shame be his share that could such ill contriue,</L>
<L>To rauish Thamar, and without a pause</L>
<L>To driue her shamefully from out his house,</L>
<L>But may his wickednesse find iust reward.</L>
<L>Therefore doth Absolon conspire with you,</L>
<L>That Ammon die what time he sits to eat,</L>
<L>For in the holy Temple haue I sworne</L>
<L>Wreake of his villany in Thamars rape.</L>
<L>And here he comes, bespeake him gently all,</L>
<L>Whose death is deepely graued in my heart.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Ammon with Adonia and Ionadab, to Absolon and his companie.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Am.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our shearers are not far from hence I wot,</L>
<L>And Ammon, to you all his brethren</L>
<L>Giueth such welcome as our fathers erst</L>
<L>Were wonr in Iuda and Ierusalem,</L>
<L>But specially Lord Absolon to thee,</L>
<L>The honour of thy house and progenie.</L>
<L>Sit downe and dine with me King Dauids sonne,</L>
<L>Thou faire young men, whose haires shine in mine eve</L>
<L>Like golden wyers of Dauids yuorie Lute.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abs.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ammon, where be thy shearers and thy men,</L>
<L>That we may powre in plenty of thy vines,</L>
<L>And eat thy goats milke, and reioice with thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Am.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here commeth Ammons shearers and his men,</L>
<L>Absolon sit and reioice with me.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Here enter a company of sheepeheards, and daunce and sing.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Am.</SPEAKER>
<L>Drinke Absolon in praise of Israel,</L>
<L>Welcome to Ammons fields from Dauids court.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abs.</SPEAKER>
<L>Die with thy draught perish and die accurst,</L>
<L><PB REF="14"/>Dishonour to the honour of vs all,</L>
<L>Die for the villany to Thamar done,</L>
<L>Vnworthy thou to be Kings Dauids sonne.
<STAGE>Exit Absa.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ionad.</SPEAKER>
<L>O what hath Absolon for Thamar done,</L>
<L>Murthred his brother, great king Dauids sonne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Run Ionadab away, and make it knowne,</L>
<L>What cruelty this Absolon hath showne.</L>
<L>Ammon, thy brother Adonia shall</L>
<L>Bury thy body among the dead mens bones,</L>
<L>And we will make complaint to Israel</L>
<L>Of Ammons death, and pride of Absolon.
<STAGE>Exeunt omnes.</STAGE></L>
<STAGE>Enter Dauid with Ioab, Abyssus, Cusay, with drum and ensigne against Rabba.</STAGE>
<L>This is the towne of the vncircumcised,</L>
<L>The citie of the kingdome, this is it,</L>
<L>Rabba where wicked Hannon sitteth king:</L>
<L>Dispoile this King, this Hannon of his crowne,</L>
<L>Vnpeople Rabba, and the streets thereof,</L>
<L>For in their bloud and slaughter of the slaine,</L>
<L>Lyeth the honor of King Dauids line.</L>
<L>Ioab, Abyshai, and the rest of you,</L>
<L>Fight ye this day for great Ierusalem.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ioab.</SPEAKER>
<L>And see where Hannon showes him on the wals,</L>
<L>Why then do we forbeare to giue assault,</L>
<L>That Israel may as it is promised,</L>
<L>Subdue the daughters of the Gentils Tribes,</L>
<L>All this must be performd by Dauids hand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Da.</SPEAKER>
<L>Harke to me Hannon, and remember well,</L>
<L>As sure as he doth liue that kept my host,</L>
<L>What time our young men by the poole of Gibeon,</L>
<L>Went forth against the strength of Isboseth,</L>
<L>And twelue to twelue did with their weapons play,</L>
<L>So sure art thou, and thy men of war</L>
<L>To feele the sword of Israel this day,</L>
<L><PB REF="14"/>Because thou hast defied Iacobs God,</L>
<L>And suffered Rabba with the Philislime</L>
<L>To raile vpon the tribe of Beniamin.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hannon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Harke man, as sure as Saul thy maister fell,</L>
<L>And gord his sides vpon the mountaine tops</L>
<L>And Ionathan, Abinadab, and Melchisua</L>
<L>Watred the dales and deepes of Askaron</L>
<L>With bloudy streames that from Gilboa ran</L>
<L>In channels through the wildernesse of Ziph,</L>
<L>What time the sword of the vncircumsed</L>
<L>Was drunken with the bloud of Israel:</L>
<L>So sure shall Dauid perish with his men,</L>
<L>Vnder the wals of Rabba, Hannons towne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ioab.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hannon, the God of Israel hath said,</L>
<L>Dauid the King shall weare that crowne of thine,</L>
<L>That weighs a Talent of the finest gold,</L>
<L>And triumph in the spoile of Hannons towne,</L>
<L>When Israel shall hale thy people hence,</L>
<L>And turne them to the tile-kill, man and child,</L>
<L>And put them vnder harrowes made of yron,</L>
<L>And hew their bones with axes, and their lims</L>
<L>With yron swords deuide and teare in twaine.</L>
<L>Hannon, this shall be done to thee and thine,</L>
<L>Because thou hast defied Israel.</L>
<L>To armes, to armes, that Rabba feele reuenge,</L>
<L>And Hannons towne become king Dauids spoile.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Alarum, excursions, assault, Exeunt omnes. Then the trumpets, and Dauid with Hannons crowne.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now clattering armes, and wrathfull storms of war,</L>
<L>Haue thundred ouer Rabbaes raced towers,</L>
<L>The wreakefull ire of great Iehouaes arme,</L>
<L>That for his people made the gates to rend,</L>
<L>And clothed the Cherubins in fierie coats,</L>
<L>To fight against the wicked Hannons towne,</L>
<L><PB REF="15"/>Pay thankes ye men of Iuda to the King,</L>
<L>The God of Syon and Ierusalem,</L>
<L>That hath exhalted Israel to this,</L>
<L>And crowned Dauid with this diademe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ioab.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beauteous and bright is he among the Tribes,</L>
<L>As when the sunne attird in glist'ring robe,</L>
<L>Comes dauncing from his orientall gate,</L>
<L>And bride groome-like hurles through the gloomy aire</L>
<L>His radiant beames, such doth King Dauid shew,</L>
<L>Crownd with the honour of his enemies towne,</L>
<L>Shining in riches like the firmament,</L>
<L>The starrie vault that ouerhangs the earth,</L>
<L>So looketh Dauid King of Israel.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abyshai.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ioab, why doth not Dauid mount his throne,</L>
<L>Whom heauen hath beautified with Hannons crowne,</L>
<L>Sound Trumpets, Shalmes, and Instruments of praise</L>
<L>To Iacobs God for Dauids victory.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Ionadab.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ionadab.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why doth the King of Israel reioice,</L>
<L>Why sitteth Dauid crownd with Rabbaes rule,</L>
<L>Behold there hath great heauinesse befalne</L>
<L>In Ammons fields by Absolons misdeed,</L>
<L>And Ammons shearers, and their feast of mirth</L>
<L>Absalon hath ouerturned with his sword,</L>
<L>Nor liueth any of King Dauids sonnes,</L>
<L>To bring this bitter tidings to the King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dauid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ay me, how soone are Dauids triumphs dasht,</L>
<L>How suddenly declineth Dauids pride,</L>
<L>As doth the daylight settle in the west,</L>
<L>So dim is Dauids glory, and his gite.</L>
<L>Die Dauid, for to thee is left no seed,</L>
<L>That may reuiue thy name in Israel.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iona.</SPEAKER>
<L>In Israel is left of Dauids seed.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Adonia with other sonnes.</STAGE>
<L>Comfort your lord, you seruants of the King,</L>
<L><PB REF="15"/>Behold thy sonnes returne in mourning weeds,</L>
<L>And only Ammon, Absalon hath slaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Da.</SPEAKER>
<L>Welcome my sonnes, deeret to me you are</L>
<L>Then is this golden crowne, or Hannons spoile.</L>
<L>O tell me then, tell me my sonnes I say,</L>
<L>How commeth it to passe, that Absolon</L>
<L>Hath slaine his brother Ammon with the sword?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ado.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy sonnes O King went vp to Ammons fields</L>
<L>To feast with him, and eat his bread and oyle,</L>
<L>And Absalon vpon his mule doth come,</L>
<L>And to his men he sayth, When Ammons heart</L>
<L>Is merry and secure, then strike him dead,</L>
<L>Because he forced Thamar shamefully,</L>
<L>And hated her, and threw her forth his dores:</L>
<L>And this did he, and they with him conspire,</L>
<L>And kill thy sonne in wreake of Thamars wrong.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dauid.</SPEAKER>
<L>How long shall Iuda and Ierusalem</L>
<L>Complaine and water Syon with their teares?</L>
<L>How long shall Israel lament in vaine,</L>
<L>And not a man among the mighty ones</L>
<L>Will heare the sorrowes of King Dauids heart?</L>
<L>Ammon thy life was pleasing to thy Lord,</L>
<L>As to mine eares the Musike of my Lute,</L>
<L>Or songs that Dauid tuneth to his Harpe,</L>
<L>And Absalon hath tane from me away</L>
<L>The gladnesse of my sad distressed soule.
<STAGE>Exeunt omnes.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Manet Dauid, Enter widdow of Thecoa.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Widdow.</SPEAKER>
<L>God saue King Dauid, King of Israel,</L>
<L>And blesse the gates of Syon for his sake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Woman, why mournest thou, rise from the earth,</L>
<L>Tell me what sorrow hath befalne thy soule.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Widdow.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy seruants soule O King is troubled sore,</L>
<L>And greenous is the anguish of her heart,</L>
<L>And from Thecoa doth thy handmaid come.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dauid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tell me, and say, thou woman of Thecoa,</L>
<L><PB REF="16"/>What aileth thee, or what is come to passe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Widdow.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy seruant is a widdow in Thecoa,</L>
<L>Two sonnes thy handmaid had, and they (my lord)</L>
<L>Fought in the field, where no man went betwixt,</L>
<L>And so the one did smite and slay the other.</L>
<L>And loe behold the kindred doth arise,</L>
<L>And crie on him that smote his brother,</L>
<L>That he therefore may be the child of death,</L>
<L>For we will follow and destroy the heire.</L>
<L>So will they quench that sparkle that is left,</L>
<L>And leaue nor name, nor issue on the earth,</L>
<L>To me, or to thy handmaids husband dead.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dauid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Woman returne, goe home vnto thy house,</L>
<L>I will take order that thy sonne be safe,</L>
<L>If any man say otherwise then well,</L>
<L>Bring him to me, and I shall chastise him:</L>
<L>For as the Lord doth liue, shall not a haire</L>
<L>Shed from thy sonne, or fall vpon the earth.</L>
<L>Woman to God alone belongs reuenge,</L>
<L>Shall then the kindred slay him for his sinne?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Widdow.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well hath King Dauid to his handmaid spoke,</L>
<L>But wherefore then hast thou determined</L>
<L>So hard a part against the righteous Tribes</L>
<L>To follow and pursue the banished,</L>
<L>When as to God alone, belongs reuenge.</L>
<L>Assuredly thou saist against thy selfe,</L>
<L>Therefore call home againe the banished,</L>
<L>Call home the banished, that he may liue,</L>
<L>And raise to thee some fruit in Israel.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Da.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou woman of Thecoa answere me,</L>
<L>Answere me one thing I shall aske of thee,</L>
<L>Is not the hand of Ioab in this worke?</L>
<L>Tell me is not his finger in this fact?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is my lord, his hand is in this worke,</L>
<L>Assure thee, Ioab captaine of thy host,</L>
<L>Hath put these words into thy handmaids mouth,</L>
<L><PB REF="16"/>And thou art as an angel from on high,</L>
<L>To vnderstand the meaning of my heart,</L>
<L>Lo where he commeth to his lord the King.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Ioab.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dauid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Say Ioab, didst thou send this woman in</L>
<L>To put this parable for Absalon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ioab.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ioab my lord did bid this woman speake,</L>
<L>And she hath said, and thou hast vnderstood.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dauid.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue and am content to do the thing,</L>
<L>Goe fetch my sonne, that he may liue with me.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ioab kneeles.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ioab.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now God be blessed for King Dauids life,</L>
<L>Thy seruant Ioab hath found grace with thee,</L>
<L>In that thou sparest Absolon thy child,</L>
<L>A beautifull and faire young man is he,</L>
<L>In all his bodie is no blemish seene,</L>
<L>His haire is like the wyer of Dauids Harpe,</L>
<L>That twines about his bright and yuorie necke:</L>
<L>In Israel is not such a goodly man,</L>
<L>And here I bring him to entreat for grace.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Absolon with Ioab.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dauid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hast thou slaine in the fields of Hazor</L>
<L>Ah Absalon my sonne, ah my sonne Absolon,</L>
<L>But wherefore doe I vexe thy spirit so,</L>
<L>Liue and returne from Gesur to thy house,</L>
<L>Returne from Gesur to Ierusalem,</L>
<L>What boots it to be bitter to thy soule,</L>
<L>Ammon is dead, and Absolon suruiues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abs.</SPEAKER>
<L>Father I haue offended Israel,</L>
<L>I haue offended Dauid and his house,</L>
<L>For Thamars wrong hath Absolon misdone,</L>
<L>But Dauids heart is free from sharpe reuenge,</L>
<L>And Ioab hath got grace for Absalon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="17"/>
<SPEAKER>Dauid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Depart with me you men of Israel,</L>
<L>You that haue followed Rabba with the sword,</L>
<L>And ransacke Ammons richest treasuries,</L>
<L>Liue Absalon my sonne, liue once in peace,</L>
<L>Peace with thee, and with Ierusalem.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt omnes.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Manet Absolon.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abs.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dauid is gone, and Absolon remaines,</L>
<L>Flowring in pleasant spring time of his youth,</L>
<L>Why liueth Absalon, and is not honoured</L>
<L>Of Tribes and Elders, and the mightiest ones,</L>
<L>That round about his Temples he may weare</L>
<L>Garlands and wreaths set on with reuerence,</L>
<L>That euery one that hath a cause to plead,</L>
<L>Might come to Absolon, and call for right?</L>
<L>Then in the gates of Syon would I sit,</L>
<L>And publish lawes in great Ierusalem,</L>
<L>And not a man should liue in all the land,</L>
<L>But Absolon would doe him reasons due,</L>
<L>Therefore I shall addresse me as I may,</L>
<L>To loue the men and Tribes of Israel.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Dauid, Ithay, Sadoc, Ahimaas, Ionathan, with others, Dauid barefoot, with some lose couering ouer his head, and all mourning.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Proud lust the bloudiest traitour to our soules,</L>
<L>Whose greedie throte, nor earth, aire, sea, or heauen,</L>
<L>Can glut or satisfie with any store,</L>
<L>Thou art the cause these torments sucke my bloud,</L>
<L>Piercing with venome of thy poysoned eies,</L>
<L>The strength and marrow of my tainted bones:</L>
<L>To punish Pharoh, and his cursed host,</L>
<L>The waters shrinke at great Adonaies voice,</L>
<L><PB REF="17"/>And sandie bottome of the sea appeard,</L>
<L>Offering his seruice at his seruants feet,</L>
<L>And to inflict a plague on Dauids sinne,</L>
<L>He makes his bowels traitors to his breast,</L>
<L>Winding about his heart with mortall gripes.</L>
<L>Ah Absalon the wrath of heauen inflames</L>
<L>Thy scorched bosome with ambitious heat,</L>
<L>And Sathan sets thee on a lustie tower,</L>
<L>Shewing thy thoughts the pride of Israel</L>
<L>Of choice to cast thee on her ruthlesse stones,</L>
<L>Weepe with me then ye sonnes of Israel.</L>
<STAGE>He lies downe, and all the rest after him.</STAGE>
<L>Lie downe with Dauid, and with Dauid mourne,</L>
<L>Before the holy one that sees our hearts,</L>
<L>Season this heauie soile with showers of teares,</L>
<L>And fill the face of euery flower with dew,</L>
<L>Weepe Israel, for Dauids soule dissolues,</L>
<L>Lading the fountaines of his drowned eyes,</L>
<L>And powres her substance on the sencelesse earth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sadoc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Weepe Israel, O weepe for Dauids soule,</L>
<L>Strewing the ground with haire and garments torne,</L>
<L>For tragicke witnesse of your heartie woes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ahimaas.</SPEAKER>
<L>O would our eyes were conduits to our hearts,</L>
<L>And that our hearts were seas of liquid bloud,</L>
<L>To powre in streames vpon this holy Mount,</L>
<L>For witnesse we would die for Dauids woes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iona.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then should this mount of Oliues seeme a plaine,</L>
<L>Drownd with a sea, that with our sighs should rore,</L>
<L>And in the murmure of his mounting waues,</L>
<L>Report our bleeding sorrowes to the heauens,</L>
<L>For witnesse we would die for Dauids woes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ith.</SPEAKER>
<L>Earth cannot weepe ynough for Dauids woes,</L>
<L>Then weepe you heauens, and all you clouds dissolue,</L>
<L>That pittious stars may see our miseries,</L>
<L>And drop their golden teares vpon the ground,</L>
<L>For witnesse how they weepe for Dauids woes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="18"/>
<SPEAKER>Sadoc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now let my soueraigne raise his prostrate bones.</L>
<L>And mourne not as a faithlesse man would doe,</L>
<L>But be assurd, that Iacobs righteous God,</L>
<L>That promist neuer to forsake your throne,</L>
<L>Will still be iust and pure in his vowes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Da.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sadoc high priest, preseruer of the arke,</L>
<L>Whose sacred vertue keepes the chosen crowne,</L>
<L>I know my God is spotlesse in his vowes,</L>
<L>And that these haires shall greet my graue in peace:</L>
<L>But that my sonne should wrong his tendred soule,</L>
<L>And fight against his fathers happinesse,</L>
<L>Turnes all my hopes into despaire of him,</L>
<L>And that despaire, feeds all my veines with greefe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ithay.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thinke of it Dauid, as a fatall plague,</L>
<L>Which greefe preserueth, but preuenteth not,</L>
<L>And turne thy drooping eyes vpon the troupes</L>
<L>That of affection to thy worthinesse,</L>
<L>Doe swarme about the person of the King,</L>
<L>Cherish their valours, and their zealous loues,</L>
<L>With pleasant lookes, and sweet encouragements.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Da.</SPEAKER>
<L>Me thinkes the voice of Ithay fils mine eares.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ith.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let not the voice of Ithay loth thine eares,</L>
<L>Whose heart would baulme thy bosome with his teares.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dauid.</SPEAKER>
<L>But wherefore goest thou to the wars with vs,</L>
<L>Thou art a stranger here in Israel,</L>
<L>And sonne to Achis mightie king of Gath,</L>
<L>Therefore returne, and with thy father stay,</L>
<L>Thou camst but yesterday, and should I now</L>
<L>Let thee partake these troubles here with vs?</L>
<L>Keepe both thy selfe, and all thy souldiors safe,</L>
<L>Let me abide the hazards of these armes,</L>
<L>And God requite the friendship thou hast shewd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ith.</SPEAKER>
<L>As sure as Israels God giues Dauid life,</L>
<L>What place or perill shall containe the King,</L>
<L>The same will Ithay share in life and death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Da.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then gentle Ithay be thou still with vs,</L>
<L><PB REF="18"/>A ioy to Dauid, and a grace to Israel.</L>
<L>Goe Sadoc now, and beare the arke of God</L>
<L>Into the great Ierusalem againe,</L>
<L>If I find fauour in his gratious eyes,</L>
<L>Then will he lay his hand vpon my heart</L>
<L>Yet once againe before I visit death,</L>
<L>Giuing it strength and vertue to mine eies,</L>
<L>To tast the comforts, and behold the forme</L>
<L>Of his faire arke, and holy tabernacle,</L>
<L>But if he say my wonted loue is worne,</L>
<L>And I haue no delight in Dauid now,</L>
<L>Here lie I armed with an humble heart,</L>
<L>T imbrace the paines that anger shall impose,</L>
<L>And kisse the sword my lord shall kill me with,</L>
<L>Then Sadoc take Ahimaas thy sonne,</L>
<L>With Ionathan sonne to Abiathar,</L>
<L>And in these fields will I repose my selfe,</L>
<L>Till they returne from you some certaine newes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sadoc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy seruants will with ioy obey the King,</L>
<L>And hope to cheere his heart with happy newes.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Sadoc, Ahimaas, and Ionathan.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ith.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now that it be no greefe vnto the King,</L>
<L>Let me for good enforme his maiestie,</L>
<L>That with vnkind and gracelesse Absalon,</L>
<L>Achitophel your auncient counsellor,</L>
<L>Directs the state of this rebellion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dauid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then doth it aime with danger at my crowne,</L>
<L>O thou that holdst his raging bloudy bound,</L>
<L>Within the circle of the siluer moone,</L>
<L>That girds earths center with his watrie scarfe,</L>
<L>Limit the counsell of Achitophel,</L>
<L>No bounds extending to my soules distresse,</L>
<L>But turne his wisdome into foolishnesse.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Cusay with his coat turnd, and head couered.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cusay.</SPEAKER>
<L>Happinesse and honour to my lord the King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="19"/>
<SPEAKER>Dauid.</SPEAKER>
<L>What happinesse or honor may betide</L>
<L>His state that toiles in my extremities?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cus.</SPEAKER>
<L>O let my gracious soueraine cease these greefes,</L>
<L>Vnlesse he wish his seruaut Cusayes death,</L>
<L>Whose life depends vpon my lords releefe,</L>
<L>Then let my presence with my sighs, persume</L>
<L>The pleasant closet of my soueraignes soule.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Da.</SPEAKER>
<L>No Cusay no, thy presence vnto me,</L>
<L>Will be a burthen since I tender thee,</L>
<L>And cannot breake thy sighs for Dauids sake:</L>
<L>But if thou turne to faire Ierusalem,</L>
<L>And say to Absalon, as thou hast been</L>
<L>A trusty friend vnto his fathers seat,</L>
<L>So thou wilt be to him, and call him King,</L>
<L>Achitophels counsell may be brought to naught.</L>
<L>Then hauing Sadoc and Abiathar,</L>
<L>All three may learne the secrets of my sonne,</L>
<L>Sending the message by Ahimaas,</L>
<L>And friendly Ionathan, who both are there,</L>
<L>Then rise, referring the successe to heauen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Da.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cusay I rise, though with vnweldie bones,</L>
<L>I carrie armes against my Absalon.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Absalon, Amasa, Achitophel, with the concubines of Dauid, and others in great state, Absalon crowned.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abs.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now you that were my fathers concubines,</L>
<L>Liquor to his inchast and lustfull fire,</L>
<L>Haue seene his honour shaken in his house,</L>
<L>Which I possesse in sight of all the world.</L>
<L>I bring ye forth for soiles to my renowne,</L>
<L>And to eclipse the glorie of your King,</L>
<L>Whose life is with his honour fast inclosd</L>
<L>Within the entrailes of a Ieatie cloud,</L>
<L>Whose dissolution shall powre downe in showers</L>
<L>The substance of his life and swelling pride:</L>
<L><PB REF="19"/>Then shall the stars light earth with rich aspects,</L>
<L>And heauen shall burne in loue with Absalon,</L>
<L>Whose beautie will suffice to chast all mists,</L>
<L>And cloth the suns spheare with a triple fire,</L>
<L>Sooner then his cleare eyes should suffer staine,</L>
<L>Or be offended with a lowring day.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Concub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy fathers honour, gracelesse Absalon,</L>
<L>And ours thus beaten with thy violent armes,</L>
<L>Will crie for vengeance to the host of heauen,</L>
<L>Whose power is euer armed against the prowd,</L>
<L>And will dart plagues at thy aspiring head,</L>
<L>For doing this disgrace to Dauids throne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<L>To Dauids throne, to Dauids holy throne,</L>
<L>Whose scepter angels guard with swords of fire,</L>
<L>And sit as Eagles on his conquering fist,</L>
<L>Ready to prey vpon his enemies,</L>
<L>Then thinke not thou the captaine of his foes,</L>
<L>Wert thou much swifter then Azahell was,</L>
<L>That could out-pace the nimble footed Roe,</L>
<L>To scape the furie of their thumping beakes,</L>
<L>Or dreadfull scope of their commanding wings.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Achip.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let not my lord the King of Israel</L>
<L>Be angrie with a sillie womans threats,</L>
<L>But with the pleasure he hath erst enioied,</L>
<L>Turne them into their cabinets againe,</L>
<L>Till Dauids conquest be their ouerthrow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abs.</SPEAKER>
<L>Into your bowers ye daughters of Disdaine,</L>
<L>Gotten by furie of vnbridled lust,</L>
<L>And wash your couches with your mourning teares,</L>
<L>For greefe that Dauids kingdome is decaied.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L>No Absalon, his kingdome is enchaind</L>
<L>Fast to the finger of great Iacobs God,</L>
<L>Which will not lose it for a rebels loue.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amasa.</SPEAKER>
<L>If I might giue aduise vnto the King,</L>
<L>These concubines should buy their taunts with bloud.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abs.</SPEAKER>
<L>Amasa no, but let thy martiall sword</L>
<L><PB REF="20"/>Empty the paines of Dauids armed men,</L>
<L>And let these foolish women scape our hands</L>
<L>To recompence the shame they haue sustaind.</L>
<L>First Absolon was by the Trumpets sound</L>
<L>Proclaimd through Hebron King of Israel,</L>
<L>And now is set infaire Ierusalem</L>
<L>With complete state, and glorie of a crowne.</L>
<L>Fiftie faire footmen by my chariot run,</L>
<L>And to the aire whose rupture rings my fame,</L>
<L>Where ere I ride they offer reuerence.</L>
<L>Why should not Absolon, that in his face</L>
<L>Carries the finall purpose of his God,</L>
<L>That is, to worke him grace in Israel,</L>
<L>Endeuour to atchieue with all his strength,</L>
<L>The state that most may satisfie his ioy,</L>
<L>Keeping his statutes and his couenants pure,</L>
<L>His thunder is intangled in my haire,</L>
<L>And with my beautie is his lightning quencht,</L>
<L>I am the man he made to glorie in,</L>
<L>When by the errors of my fathers sinne,</L>
<L>He lost the path that led into the land,</L>
<L>Wherewith our chosen ancestors were blest.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Cusay.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Long may the beautious King of Israel liue,</L>
<L>To whom the people doe by thousands swarme.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abs.</SPEAKER>
<L>What meaneth Cusay so to greet his foe,</L>
<L>In this the loue thou shewdst to Dauids soule,</L>
<L>To whose assistance thou hast vowed thy life,</L>
<L>Why leauest thou him in this extremitie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Because the Lord and Israel chuseth thee,</L>
<L>And as before I serud thy fathers turne,</L>
<L>With counsell acceptable in his sight,</L>
<L>So likewise will I now obey his sonne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abs.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then welcome Cusay to king Absalon,</L>
<L>And now my lords and louing counsellors,</L>
<L>I thinke it time to exercise our armes</L>
<L><PB REF="20"/>Against forsaken Dauid and his host,</L>
<L>Giue counsell first my good Achitophel,</L>
<L>What times and orders we may best obserue,</L>
<L>For prosperous manage of these high exploits.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Achi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me chuse out twelue thousand valiant men,</L>
<L>And (while the night hides with her sable mists</L>
<L>The close endeuors cunning souldiers vse)</L>
<L>I will assault thy discontented fire,</L>
<L>And while with weakenesse of their wearie armes,</L>
<L>Surchargd with toile to shun thy suddaine power,</L>
<L>The people flie in huge disordred troupes</L>
<L>To saue their liues, and leaue the King alone,</L>
<L>Then will I smite him with his latest wound,</L>
<L>And bring the people to thy feet in peace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abs.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well hath Achitophel giuen his aduise,</L>
<L>Yet let vs heare what Cusay counsels vs,</L>
<L>Whose great experience is well worth the eare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Though wise Achitophel be much more meet</L>
<L>To purchase hearing with my lord the King,</L>
<L>For all his former counsels, then my selfe,</L>
<L>Yet not offending Absolon or him,</L>
<L>This time it is not good, nor worth pursute:</L>
<L>For well thou knowest thy fathers men are strong,</L>
<L>Chafing as shee beares robbed of their whelpes.</L>
<L>Besides the King himselfe a valiant man,</L>
<L>Traind vp in feats and stratagems of warre,</L>
<L>And will not for preuention of the worst</L>
<L>Lodge with the common souldiers in the field:</L>
<L>But now I know his wonted policies</L>
<L>Haue taught him lurke within some secret caue,</L>
<L>Guarded with all his stoutest souldiers,</L>
<L>Which if the forefront of his battell faint,</L>
<L>Will yet giue out that Absalon doth flie,</L>
<L>And so thy souldiers be discouraged.</L>
<L>Dauid himselfe withall, whose angry heart</L>
<L>Is as a Lyons, letted of his walke,</L>
<L><PB REF="21"/>Will fight himselfe, and all his men to one,</L>
<L>Before a few shall vanquish him by feare.</L>
<L>My counsell therefore, is with Trumpets sound</L>
<L>To gather men from Dan to Bersabe,</L>
<L>That they may march in number like sea sands,</L>
<L>That nestle close in anothers necke:</L>
<L>So shall we come vpon him in our strength,</L>
<L>Like to the dew that fals in showers from heauen,</L>
<L>And leaue him not a man to march withall.</L>
<L>Besides if any citie succour him,</L>
<L>The nnmbers of our men shall fetch vs ropes,</L>
<L>And we will pull it downe the riuers streame,</L>
<L>That not a stone be left to keepe vs out.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abs.</SPEAKER>
<L>What saies my lord to Cusaies counsell now?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ama.</SPEAKER>
<L>I fancie Cusaies counsell better farre</L>
<L>Then that is giuen vs from Achitophel,</L>
<L>And so I thinke doth euery souldier here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cusaies counsell is better then Achitophels.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abs.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then march we after Cusaies counsell all,</L>
<L>Sound trumpets through the bounds of Israel,</L>
<L>And muster all the men will serue the King,</L>
<L>That Absalon may glut his longing soule</L>
<L>With sole fruition of his fathers crowne.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ach.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ill shall they fare that follow thy attempts,</L>
<L>That skornes the counsell of Achitophel.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Restat Cusay.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cusay.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thus hath the power of Iacobs iealous God</L>
<L>Fulfild his seruant Dauids drifts by me,</L>
<L>And brought Achitophels aduise to scorne.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Sadoc, Abiathar, Ahimaas, and Ionathan.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sadoc.</SPEAKER>
<L>God saue lord Cusay, and direct his zeale</L>
<L>To purchase Dauids conquest gainst his sonne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abia.</SPEAKER>
<L>What secrets hast thou gleande from Absalon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cusay.</SPEAKER>
<L>These sacred priests that beare the arke of God,</L>
<L>Achitophel aduisd him in the night</L>
<L><PB REF="21"/>To let him chuse twelue thousand fighting men,</L>
<L>And he would come on Dauid at vnwares,</L>
<L>While he was wearie with his violent toile:</L>
<L>But I aduisd to get a greater host,</L>
<L>And gather men from Dan to Bersabe,</L>
<L>To come vpon him strongly in the fields,</L>
<L>Then send Ahimaas and Ionathan</L>
<L>To signifie these secrets to the King,</L>
<L>And will him not to stay this night abroad,</L>
<L>But get him ouer Iordane presently,</L>
<L>Least he and all his people kisse the sword.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sadoc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then goe Ahimaas and Ionathan,</L>
<L>And straight conuey this message to the King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ahim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Father we will▪ if Absalons cheefe spies</L>
<L>Preuent not this deuise, and stay vs here.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Semei solus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Semei.</SPEAKER>
<L>The man of Israel, that hath rul'd as King,</L>
<L>Or rather as the Tyrant of the land,</L>
<L>Bolstering his hatefull head vpon the throne,</L>
<L>That God vnworthily hath blest him with,</L>
<L>Shall now I hope, lay it as low as hell,</L>
<L>And be depos'd from his detested chaire.</L>
<L>O that my bosome could by nature beare,</L>
<L>A sea of poyson to be powr'de vpon</L>
<L>His cursed head that sacred baulme hath grac'd,</L>
<L>And consecrated King of Israel:</L>
<L>Or would my breath were made the smoke of hell,</L>
<L>Infected with the sighs of damned soules,</L>
<L>Or with the reeking of that serpents gorge,</L>
<L>That feeds on adders, toads, and venomous roots,</L>
<L>That as I opened my reuenging lips</L>
<L>To curse the sheepeheard for his Tyrannie,</L>
<L>My words might cast rancke poyson to his pores,</L>
<L>And make his swolne and ranckling sinewes cracke,</L>
<L>Like to the combat blowes that breake the clouds,</L>
<L>When Ioues stout champions fight with fire,</L>
<L><PB REF="22"/>See where he commeth, that my soule abhors.</L>
<L>I haue prepard my pocket full of stones</L>
<L>To cast at him, mingled with earth and dust,</L>
<L>Which bursting with disdaine, I greet him with.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Dauid, Ioab, Abyshai, Ithay, with others.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Semei.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come forth thou murtherer and wicked man,</L>
<L>The Lord hath brought vpon thy cursed head</L>
<L>The guiltlesse bloud of Saule and all his sonnes,</L>
<L>Whose royall throne thy basenesse hath vsurpt,</L>
<L>And to reuenge it deepely on thy soule,</L>
<L>The Lord hath giuen the kingdome to thy sonne,</L>
<L>And he shall wreake the traitrous wrongs of Saule,</L>
<L>Euen as thy sinne hath still importund heauen,</L>
<L>So shall thy murthers and adulterie</L>
<L>Be punisht in the sight of Israel,</L>
<L>As thou deserust with bloud, with death, and hell.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Hence murtherer, hence, he threw at him.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why doth his dead dog curse my lord the King,</L>
<L>Let me alone to take away his head.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Da.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why medleth thus the son of Zeruia</L>
<L>To interrupt the action of our God?</L>
<L>Semei vseth me with this reproch,</L>
<L>Because the Lord hath sent him to reproue</L>
<L>The sinnes of Dauid, printed in his browes,</L>
<L>With bloud that blusheth for his conscience guilt,</L>
<L>Who dares then aske him why he curseth me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Semei.</SPEAKER>
<L>If then thy conscience tell thee thou hast sind,</L>
<L>And that thy life is odious to the world,</L>
<L>Command thy followers to shun thy face,</L>
<L>And by thy selfe here make away thy soule,</L>
<L>That I may stand and glorie in thy shame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Da.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am not desperate Semei like thy selfe,</L>
<L>But trust vnto the couenant of my God,</L>
<L>Founded on mercie with repentance built,</L>
<L>And finisht with the glorie of my soule.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="22"/>
<SPEAKER>Semei.</SPEAKER>
<L>A murtherer, and hope for mercie in thy end</L>
<L>Hate and destruction sit vpon thy browes</L>
<L>To watch the issue of thy damned ghost,</L>
<L>Which with thy latest gaspe theile take and teare,</L>
<L>Hurling in euery paine of hell a peece.</L>
<L>Hence murtherer, thou shame to Israel,</L>
<L>Foule letcher, drunkard, plague to heauen and earth.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>He throwes at him.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ioab.</SPEAKER>
<L>What is it pietie in Dauids thoughts,</L>
<L>So to abhorre from lawes of pollicie</L>
<L>In this extremitie of his distresse,</L>
<L>To giue his subiects cause of carelesnesse,</L>
<L>Send hence the dog with sorrow to his graue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dauid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why should the sons of Zeruia seeke to checke</L>
<L>His spirit which the Lord hath thus inspir'd:</L>
<L>Behold my sonne which issued from my flesh,</L>
<L>With equall furie seekes to take my life.</L>
<L>How much more then the sonne of Iemini,</L>
<L>Cheefely since he doth nought but Gods command,</L>
<L>It may be he will looke on me this day</L>
<L>With gracious eyes, and for his cursing blesse,</L>
<L>The heart of Dauid in his bitternesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Semei.</SPEAKER>
<L>What doest thou fret my soule with sufferance▪</L>
<L>O that the soules of Isboseth and Abner,</L>
<L>Which thou sentst swimming to their graues in bloud,</L>
<L>With wounds fresh bleeding, gasping for reuenge,</L>
<L>Were here to execute my burning hate:</L>
<L>But I will hunt thy font with curses still,</L>
<L>Hence Monster, Murtherer, Mirror of Contempt.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>He throwes dust againe.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Ahimanas and Ionathan.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ahim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Long life to Dauid, to his enemies death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Da.</SPEAKER>
<L>Welcome Ahimaas and Ionathan,</L>
<L>What newes sends Cusay to thy lord the King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ahim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cusay would wish my lord the King,</L>
<L><PB REF="23"/>To passe the riuer Iordane presently,</L>
<L>Least he and all his people perish here.</L>
<L>For wise Achitophel hath counseld Absalon</L>
<L>To take aduantage of your wearie armes,</L>
<L>And come this night vpon you in the fields.</L>
<L>But yet the Lord hath made his counsell skorne,</L>
<L>And Cusaies pollicie with praise preferd,</L>
<L>Which was to number euery Israelite,</L>
<L>And so assault you in their pride of strength.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ionat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Abiathar besides intreats the King</L>
<L>To send his men of warre against his sonne,</L>
<L>And hazard not his person in the field.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dauid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thankes to Abiathar, and to you both,</L>
<L>And to my Cusay, whom the Lord requite,</L>
<L>But tenne times treble thankes to his soft hand,</L>
<L>Whose pleasant touch hath made my heart to dance,</L>
<L>And play him praises in my zealous breast,</L>
<L>That turnd the counsell of Achitophel</L>
<L>After the praiers of his seruants lips.</L>
<L>Now will we passe the riuer all this night,</L>
<L>And in the morning sound the voice of warre,</L>
<L>The voice of bloudie and vnkindly warre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ioab.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then tell vs how thou wilt deuide thy men,</L>
<L>And who shall haue the speciall charge herein.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ioab, thy selfe shall for thy charge conduct,</L>
<L>The first third part of all my valiant men,</L>
<L>The second shall Abisaies valour lead,</L>
<L>The third faire Ithay, which I most should grace,</L>
<L>For comfort he hath done to Dauids woes,</L>
<L>And I my selfe will follow in the midst.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ith.</SPEAKER>
<L>That let not Dauid, for though we should flie,</L>
<L>Tenne thousand of vs were not halfe so much</L>
<L>Esteemd with Dauids enemies, as himselfe,</L>
<L>Thy people louing thee, denie thee this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Da.</SPEAKER>
<L>What seewes them best, then that will Dauid doe,</L>
<L>But now my lords and captaines heare his voice</L>
<L><PB REF="23"/>That neuer yet pierst pittious heauen in vaine,</L>
<L>Then let it not slip lightly through your eares,</L>
<L>For my sake spare the young man Absalon.</L>
<L>Ioab thy selfe didst once vse friendly words</L>
<L>To reconcile my heart incenst to him,</L>
<L>If then thy loue be to thy kinsman sound,</L>
<L>And thou wilt proue a perfit Israelite,</L>
<L>Friend him with deeds, and touch no haire of him,</L>
<L>Not that fair haire with which the wanton winds</L>
<L>Delight to play, and loues to make <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> curle,</L>
<L>Wherein the Nightingales would build their nests,</L>
<L>And make sweet bowers in euery golden tresse,</L>
<L>To sing their louer euery night asleepe.</L>
<L>O spoile not Ioab, Ioues faire ornaments,</L>
<L>Which he hath sent to solace Dauids soule.</L>
<L>The best ye see (my lords) are swift to sinne,</L>
<L>To sinne our feet are washt with milke of Roes,</L>
<L>And dried againe with coales of lightening.</L>
<L>O Lord thou seest the prowdest sinnes, poore slaue,</L>
<L>And with his bridle, pulst him to the graue,</L>
<L>For my sake then spare louely Absalon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ith.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee will my lord for thy sake fauour him.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Achitophel solus with a halter.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Achi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now hath Achitophel orderd his house,</L>
<L>And taken leaue of euery pleasure there,</L>
<L>Hereon depends Achitophels delights,</L>
<L>And in this circle must his life be closde.</L>
<L>The wise Achitophel, whose counsell prou'd</L>
<L>Euer as sound for fortunate successe,</L>
<L>As if men askt the Oracle of God,</L>
<L>Is now vsde like the foole of Israel,</L>
<L>Then set thy angrie soule vpon her wings,</L>
<L>And let her flie into the shade of death,</L>
<L>And for my death, let heauen for euer weepe,</L>
<L><PB REF="24"/>Making huge flouds vpon the land I leaue,</L>
<L>To rauish them, and all their fairest fruits.</L>
<L>Let all the sighs I breath'd for this disgrace,</L>
<L>Hang on my hedges like eternall mists,</L>
<L>As mourning garments for their maisters death.</L>
<L>Ope earth, and take thy miserable sonne</L>
<L>Into the bowels of thy cursed wombe,</L>
<L>Once in a surfet thou diddest spue him forth,</L>
<L>Now for fell hunger sucke him in againe,</L>
<L>And be his bodie poyson to thy vaines,</L>
<L>And now thou hellish instrument of heauen,</L>
<L>Once execute th'arrest of Ioues iust doome,</L>
<L>And stop his breast that curseth Israel.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Absalon, Amasa, with all his traine.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abs.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now for the crowne and throne of Israel,</L>
<L>To be confirmd with vertue of my sword,</L>
<L>And writ with Dauids bloud vpon the blade,</L>
<L>Now Ioue let forth the golden firmament,</L>
<L>And looke on him with all thy fierie eyes,</L>
<L>Which thou hast made to giue their glories light,</L>
<L>To shew thou louest the vertue of thy hand,</L>
<L>Let fall a wreath of starres vpon my head,</L>
<L>Whose influence may gouerne Israel,</L>
<L>With state exceeding all her other Kings.</L>
<L>Fight lords and captaines, that your soueraignes face</L>
<L>May shine in honour brighter then the sunne,</L>
<L>And with the vertue of my beautious raies,</L>
<L>Make this faire land as fruitfull as the fields,</L>
<L>That with sweet milke and hony ouerflow'd.</L>
<L>God in the whissing of a pleasant wind,</L>
<L>Shall march vpon the tops of Mulberie trees,</L>
<L>To coole all breasts that burne with any greefes,</L>
<L>As whylome he was good to Moyses men.</L>
<L>By day the Lord shall sit within a cloud,</L>
<L>To guide your footsteps to the fields of ioy,</L>
<L><PB REF="24"/>And in the night a piller bright as fire</L>
<L>Shall goe before you like a second sunne,</L>
<L>Wherein the essence of his godhead is,</L>
<L>That day and night you may be brought to peace,</L>
<L>And neuer swarue from that delightsome path,</L>
<L>That leads your soules to perfect happinesse.</L>
<L>This shall he doe for ioy when I am King:</L>
<L>Then fight braue captaines that these ioies may flie</L>
<L>Into your bosomes with sweet victorie.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
<STAGE>The battell, and Absalon hangs by the haire.</STAGE>
<L>What angrie angel sitting in these shades,</L>
<L>Hath laid his cruell hands vpon my haire,</L>
<L>And holds my body thus twixt heauen and earth?</L>
<L>Hath Absalon no souldier neere his hand,</L>
<L>That may vntwine me this vnpleasant curle,</L>
<L>Or wound this tree that rauisheth his lord?</L>
<L>O God behold the glorie of thy hand,</L>
<L>And choisest fruit of Natures workemanship,</L>
<L>Hang like a rotten branch vpon this tree,</L>
<L>Fit for the axe, and ready for the fire.</L>
<L>Since thou withholdst all ordinarie helpe</L>
<L>To lose my bodie from this bond of death,</L>
<L>O let my beautie fill these sencelesse pla<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>s,</L>
<L>With sence and power to lose me from this plague,</L>
<L>And worke some wonder to preuent his death,</L>
<L>Whose life thou madst a speciall miracle.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ioab with another souldier.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sould.</SPEAKER>
<L>My lord I saw the young prince Absalon</L>
<L>Hang by the haire vpon a shadie oke,</L>
<L>And could by no meanes get himselfe vnlosde,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ioab.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why slewst thou not the wicked Absalon,</L>
<L>That rebell to his father and to heauen,</L>
<L>That so I might haue giuen thee for thy paines</L>
<L><PB REF="25"/>Tenne siluer sickles, and a golden wast.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sould.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not for a thousand sickles would I slay</L>
<L>The sonne of Dauid, whom his father chargd,</L>
<L>Nor thou Abisay, nor the sonne of Gath,</L>
<L>Should touch with stroke of deadly violence.</L>
<L>The charge was giuen in hearing of vs all,</L>
<L>And had I done it, then I know thy selfe,</L>
<L>Before thou wouldst abide the Kings rebuke,</L>
<L>Wouldst haue accus'd me as a man of death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ioab.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must not now stand trifling here with thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abs.</SPEAKER>
<L>Helpe Ioab, helpe, O helpe thy Absalon,</L>
<L>Let not thy angrie thoughts be laid in bloud,</L>
<L>In bloud of him, that sometimes nourisht thee,</L>
<L>And softned thy sweet heart with friendly loue,</L>
<L>O giue me once againe my fathers sight,</L>
<L>My deerest father, and my princely soueraigne,</L>
<L>That shedding teares of bloud before his face,</L>
<L>The ground may witnesse, and the heauens record,</L>
<L>My last submission sound and full of ruth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ioab.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rebell to nature, hate to heauen and earth,</L>
<L>Shall I giue helpe to him, that thirsts the soule</L>
<L>Of his deere father, and my soueraigne lord?</L>
<L>Now see the Lord hath tangled in a tree</L>
<L>The health and glorie of thy stubborne heart,</L>
<L>And made thy pride curbd with a sencelesse plant,</L>
<L>Now Absalon how doth the Lord regard</L>
<L>The beautie wherevpon thy hope was built,</L>
<L>And which thou thoughtst his grace did glorie in?</L>
<L>Findst thou not now with feare of instant death,</L>
<L>That God affects not any painted shape,</L>
<L>Or goodly personage, when the vertuous soule</L>
<L>Is stuft with naught but pride and stubbornnesse?</L>
<L>But preach I to thee, while I should reuenge</L>
<L>Thy cursed sinne that staineth Israel,</L>
<L>And makes her fields blush with her childrens bloud?</L>
<L>Take that as part of thy deserued plague,</L>
<L><PB REF="25"/>Which worthily no torment can inflict.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abs.</SPEAKER>
<L>O Ioab, Ioab, cruell ruthlesse Ioab,</L>
<L>Herewith thou woundst thy Kingly soueraignes heart,</L>
<L>Whose heauenly temper hates his childrens bloud,</L>
<L>And will be sicke I know for Absalon.</L>
<L>O my deere father, that thy melting eyes</L>
<L>Might pierce this thicket to behold thy sonne,</L>
<L>Thy deerest sonne gor'de with a mortall dart▪</L>
<L>Yet Ioab pittie me, pittie my father, Ioab,</L>
<L>Pittie his soules distresse that mournes my life,</L>
<L>And will be dead I know to heare my death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ioab.</SPEAKER>
<L>If he were so remorsefull of thy state,</L>
<L>Why sent he me against thee with the sword?</L>
<L>All Ioab meanes to pleasure thee withall,</L>
<L>Is to dispatch thee quickly of thy paine,</L>
<L>Hold Absalon, Ioabs pittie is in this,</L>
<L>In this prowd Absalon is Ioabs loue.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>He goes out.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abs.</SPEAKER>
<L>Such loue, such pittie Israels God send thee,</L>
<L>And for his loue to Dauid pittie me,</L>
<L>Ah my deere father, see thy bowels bleed,</L>
<L>See death assault thy deerest Absalon,</L>
<L>See, pittie, pardon, pray for Absalon.</L>
<STAGE>Enter fiue or sixe souldiers.</STAGE>
<L>See where the rebell in his glorie hangs,</L>
<L>Where is the vertue of thy beautie Absalon,</L>
<L>Will any of vs here now feare thy lookes?</L>
<L>Or be in loue with that thy golden haire,</L>
<L>Wherein was wrapt rebellion gainst thy sire,</L>
<L>And cords prepar'd to stop thy fathers breath?</L>
<L>Our captaine Ioab hath begun to vs,</L>
<L>And heres an end to thee, and all thy sinnes.</L>
<L>Come let vs take the beauteous rebell downe,</L>
<L>And in some ditch amids this darkesome wood,</L>
<L>Burie his bulke beneath a heape of stones,</L>
<L>Whose stonie heart did hunt his fathers death.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="26"/><HI>Enter in triumph with drum and ensigne, Ioab, Abyshai, and souldiers to Absalon.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ioab.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well done tall souldiers take the Traitor downe,</L>
<L>And in this myerie ditch interre his bones,</L>
<L>Couering his hatefull breast with heapes of stones,</L>
<L>This shadie thicket of darke Ephrami</L>
<L>Shall euer lower on his cursed graue.</L>
<L>Night Rauens and Owles shall ring his fatall knell,</L>
<L>And sit exclaiming on his damned soule,</L>
<L>There shall they heape their preyes of Carrion,</L>
<L>Till all his graue be clad with stinking bones▪</L>
<L>That it may loth the sence of euery man,</L>
<L>So shall his end breed horror to his name,</L>
<L>And to his traitrous fact eternall shame.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
<STAGE>5. Chorus.</STAGE>
<L>Oh dreadfull president of his iust doome,</L>
<L>Whose holy heart is neuer toucht with ruth</L>
<L>Of fickle beautie, or of glorious shapes,</L>
<L>But with the vertue of an vpright soule,</L>
<L>Humble and zealous in his inward thoughts,</L>
<L>Though in his person loathsome and deform'd.</L>
<L>Now since this storie lends vs other store,</L>
<L>To make a third discourse of Dauids life,</L>
<L>Adding thereto his most renowmed death,</L>
<L>And all their deaths, that at his death he iudgd,</L>
<L>Here end we this, and what here wants to please,</L>
<L>We will supplie with treble willingnesse.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Absalon with three or foure of his seruants or gentlemen.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abs.</SPEAKER>
<L>What boots it Absalon, vnhappie Absalon,</L>
<L>Sighing I say what boots it Absalon,</L>
<L>To haue disclos'd a farre more worthy wombe</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="26"/><HI>Trumpets sound, enter Ioab, Ahimaas, Cusay, Amasa, with all the rest.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ioab.</SPEAKER>
<L>Souldiers of Israel, and ye sonnes of Iuda,</L>
<L>That haue contended in these irkesome broiles,</L>
<L>And ript old Israels bowels with your swords:</L>
<L>The godlesse generall of your stubborne armes</L>
<L>Is brought by Israels helper to the graue:</L>
<L>A graue of shame, and skorne of all the Tribes,</L>
<L>Now then to saue your honours from the dust,</L>
<L>And keepe your blouds in temper by your bones,</L>
<L>Let Ioabs ensigne shroud your manly heads,</L>
<L>Direct your eies, your weapons, and your hearts</L>
<L>To guard the life of Dauid from his foes.</L>
<L>Error hath maskt your much too forward minds,</L>
<L>And you haue sind against the chosen state,</L>
<L>Against his life, for whom your liues are blest,</L>
<L>And followed an vsurper to the field,</L>
<L>In whose iust death your deaths are threatened,</L>
<L>But Ioab pitties your disordered soules,</L>
<L>And therefore offers pardon, peace, and loue,</L>
<L>To all that will be friendly reconcil'de</L>
<L>To Israels weale, to Dauid, and to heauen.</L>
<L>Amasa, thou art leader of the host,</L>
<L>That vnder Absalon haue raisde their armes▪</L>
<L>Then be a captaine wise and polliticke,</L>
<L>Carefull and louing for thy souldiers liues,</L>
<L>And lead them to this honourable league.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amasa.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will, at least Ile doe my best,</L>
<L>And for the gracious offer thou hast made,</L>
<L>I giue thee thankes as much as for my head.</L>
<L>Then you deceiu'd poore soules of Israel,</L>
<L>Since now ye see the errors you incurd,</L>
<L>With thankes and due submission be appeasde,</L>
<L>And as ye see your captaines president</L>
<L><PB REF="27"/>Here cast me then our swords at Ioabs feet,</L>
<L>Submitting with all zeale and residence</L>
<L>Our goods and bodies to his gracious hands.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>All stand vp.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ioab.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stand vp and take ye all your swords againe,</L>
<L>Dauid and Ioab shall be blest herein.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iona.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now let me goe enforme my lord the King,</L>
<L>How God hath freed him from his enemies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ioab.</SPEAKER>
<L>Another time Ahimaas, not now,</L>
<L>But Cusay goe thy selfe, and tell the King</L>
<L>The happie message of our good successe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cus.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will my lord, and thanke thee for thy grace.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Cusay.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iona.</SPEAKER>
<L>What if thy seruant should goe to my lord?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ioab.</SPEAKER>
<L>What newes hast thou to bring since he is gone?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iona.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet doe Ahimaas so much content,</L>
<L>That he may run about so sweet a charge.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ioab.</SPEAKER>
<L>Run if thou wilt, and peace be with thy steps,</L>
<L>Now follow, that you may salute the King</L>
<L>With humble hearts and reconciled soules.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ama.</SPEAKER>
<L>We follow Ioab to our gracious King,</L>
<L>And him our swords shall honour to our deaths.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Dauid, Bethsabe, Salomon, Nathan, Adonia, Chileab, with their traine.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beth.</SPEAKER>
<L>What meanes my lord, the lampe of Israel,</L>
<L>From whose bright eyes all eyes receiue their light,</L>
<L>To dim the glory of his sweet aspects,</L>
<L>And paint his countenance with his hearts distresse?</L>
<L>Why should his thoughts retaine a sad conceit,</L>
<L>When euery pleasure kneeles before his throne,</L>
<L>And sues for sweet acceptance with his grace,</L>
<L>Take but your Lute, and make the mountaines dance,</L>
<L>Retriue the sunnes sphere, and restraine the clouds,</L>
<L><PB REF="27"/>Giue eares to trees, make sauage Lyons tame,</L>
<L>Impose still silence to the loudest winds,</L>
<L>And fill the fairest day with foulest stormes,</L>
<L>Then why should passions of much meaner power,</L>
<L>Beare head against the heart of Israel.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Da.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faire Bersabe, thou mightst increase the strength,</L>
<L>Of these thy arguments drawne from my skill,</L>
<L>By vrging thy sweet sight to my conceits,</L>
<L>Whose vertue euer serud for sacred baulme</L>
<L>To cheere my pinings past all earthly ioies,</L>
<L>But Bethsabe, the daughter of the highest,</L>
<L>Whose beautie builds the towers of Israel,</L>
<L>Shee that in chaines of pearle and vnicorne,</L>
<L>Leads at her traine the ancient golden world,</L>
<L>The world that Adam held in Paradise,</L>
<L>Whose breath refineth all infectious aires,</L>
<L>And makes the meddowes smile at her repaire.</L>
<L>Shee, Shee my dearest Bethsabe,</L>
<L>Faire peace, the goddesse of our graces here,</L>
<L>Is fled the streets of faire Ierusalem,</L>
<L>The fields of Israel, and the heart of Dauid,</L>
<L>Leading my comforts in her golden chaines,</L>
<L>Linckt to the life and soule of Absalon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beth.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then is the pleasure of my soueraignes heart,</L>
<L>So wrapt within the bosome of that sonne,</L>
<L>That Salomon, whom Israels God affects,</L>
<L>And gaue the name vnto him for his loue,</L>
<L>Should be no salue to comfort Dauids soule?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Salomon (my loue) is Dauids lord,</L>
<L>Or God hath nam'd him lord of Israel</L>
<L>In him (for that, and since he is thy sonne)</L>
<L>Must Dauid needs be pleased at the heart,</L>
<L>And he shall surely sit vpon my throne:</L>
<L>But Absalon the beautie of my bones,</L>
<L>Faite Absalon the counterfeit of loue,</L>
<L>Sweet Absalon, the image of content,</L>
<L><PB REF="28"/>Must claime a portion in his fathers care,</L>
<L>And be in life and death King Dauids sonne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet as my lord hath said, let Salomon raigne,</L>
<L>Whom God in naming, hath annointed King.</L>
<L>Now is he apt to learne th'eternall lawes,</L>
<L>Whose knowledge being rooted in his youth,</L>
<L>Will beautifie his age with glorious fruits,</L>
<L>While Absalon incenst with gracelesse pride,</L>
<L>Vsurpes and staines the kingdome with his sinne,</L>
<L>Let Salomon be made thy staffe of age,</L>
<L>Faire Israels rest, and honour of thy race.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Da.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tell me my Salomon, wilt thou imbrace</L>
<L>Thy fathers precepts graued in thy heart,</L>
<L>And satisfie my zeale to thy renowne,</L>
<L>With practise of such sacred principles</L>
<L>As shall concerne the state of Israel?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>My royall father, if the heauenly zeale</L>
<L>Which for my welfare seeds vpon your soule,</L>
<L>Were not sustaind with vertue of mine owne,</L>
<L>If the sweet accents of your cheerefull voice</L>
<L>Should not each hower beat vpon mine eares</L>
<L>As sweetly as the breath of heauen to him</L>
<L>That gaspeth scorched with the Summers sunne,</L>
<L>I should be guiltie of vnpardoned sinne,</L>
<L>Fearing the plague of heauen, and shame of earth:</L>
<L>But since I vow my selfe to learne the skill</L>
<L>And holy secrets of his mightie hand</L>
<L>Whose cunning tunes the musicke of my soule,</L>
<L>It would content me (father) first to learne</L>
<L>How th'eternall fram'd the firmament,</L>
<L>Which bodies lead their influence by fire?</L>
<L>And which are fild with hoarie Winters yse?</L>
<L>What signe is raignie, and what starre is faire?</L>
<L>Why by the rules of true proportion</L>
<L>The yeare is still diuided into months,</L>
<L>The months to daies, the daies to certaine howers?</L>
<L><PB REF="28"/>What fruitfull race shall fill the future world?</L>
<L>Or for what time shall this round building stand?</L>
<L>What Magistrates, what Kings shall keepe in awe</L>
<L>Mens minds with bridles of th'eternall law?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Da.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wade not too farre my boy in waues too deepe,</L>
<L>The feeble eyes of our aspiring thoughts</L>
<L>Behold things present, and record things past:</L>
<L>But things to come, exceed our humane reach,</L>
<L>And are not painted yet in angels eyes:</L>
<L>For those, submit thy sence, and say, Thou power</L>
<L>That now art framing of the future world,</L>
<L>Knowest all to come, not by the course of heauen,</L>
<L>By fraile coniectures of inferiour signes,</L>
<L>By monstrous flouds, by flights and flockes of birds,</L>
<L>By bowels of a sacrificed beast;</L>
<L>Or by the figures of some hidden art:</L>
<L>But by a true and naturall presage,</L>
<L>Laying the ground and perfect architect</L>
<L>Of all our actions now before thine eyes,</L>
<L>From Adam to the end of Adams seed,</L>
<L>O heauen protect my weakenesse with thy strength,</L>
<L>So looke on me that I may view thy face,</L>
<L>And see these secrets written in thy browes.</L>
<L>O sun come dart thy raies vpon my moone,</L>
<L>That now mine eyes eclipsed to the earth,</L>
<L>May brightly be refin'd and shine to heauen.</L>
<L>Transforme me from this flesh, that I may liue</L>
<L>Before my death, regenerate with thee.</L>
<L>O thou great God, rauish my earthly sprite,</L>
<L>That for the time a more then humane skill</L>
<L>May feed the Organons of all my sence,</L>
<L>That when I thinke, thy thoughts may be my guide,</L>
<L>And when I speake, I may be made by choice</L>
<L>The perfect eccho of thy heauenly voice.</L>
<L>Thus say my sonne, and thou shalt learne them all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Salo.</SPEAKER>
<L>A secret fury rauisheth my soule,</L>
<L><PB REF="29"/>Lifting my mind aboue her humane bounds,</L>
<L>And as the Eagle roused from her stand,</L>
<L>With violent hunger (cowring in the aire)</L>
<L>Seaseth her feathered prey, and thinkes to feed,</L>
<L>But seeing then a cloud beneath her feet,</L>
<L>Lets fall the foule, and is emboldened</L>
<L>With eies intentiue to bedare the sun,</L>
<L>And stieth close vnto his stately sphere:</L>
<L>So Salomon mounted on the burning wings</L>
<L>Of zeale deuine, lets fall his mortall food,</L>
<L>And cheeres his sences with celestiall aire,</L>
<L>Treads in the golden starrie Labyrinth,</L>
<L>And holds his eyes fixt on Iehouaes browes,</L>
<L>Good father teach me further what to doe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nath.</SPEAKER>
<L>See Dauid how his haughtie spirit mounts</L>
<L>Euen now of heigth to wield a diademe,</L>
<L>Then make him promise that he may succeed,</L>
<L>And rest old Israels bones from broiles of warre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dauid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nathan thou Prophet, sprung from Iesses root,</L>
<L>I promise thee, and louely Bethsabe,</L>
<L>My Salomon shall gouerne after me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beth.</SPEAKER>
<L>He that hath toucht thee with this righteous thought</L>
<L>Preserue the harbour of thy thoughts in peace.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Mess.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mess.</SPEAKER>
<L>My lord, thy seruants of thy watch haue seene</L>
<L>One running hitherward from forth the warres.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dauid.</SPEAKER>
<L>If hee bee come alone, he bringeth newes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mess.</SPEAKER>
<L>Another hath thy seruant seene my lord,</L>
<L>Whose running much resembles Sadocs sonne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Da.</SPEAKER>
<L>He is a good man, and good tidings brings.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Ahimaas.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ahim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace and content be with my lord the King,</L>
<L>Whom Israels God hath blest with victory.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Da.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tell me Ahimaas, liues my Absalon?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ahim.</SPEAKER>
<L>I saw a troupe of souldiours gathered,</L>
<L>But know not what the tumult might import.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="29"/>
<SPEAKER>Dau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stand by, vntill some other may informe</L>
<L>The heart of Dauid with a happie truth.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Cusay.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cusay.</SPEAKER>
<L>Happinesse and honour liue with Dauids soule,</L>
<L>Whom God hath blest with conquest of his foes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dauid.</SPEAKER>
<L>But Cusay liues the yong man Absalon?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cus.</SPEAKER>
<L>The stubborne enemies to Dauids peace,</L>
<L>And all that cast their darts against his crowne,</L>
<L>Fare euer like the young man Absalon,</L>
<L>For as he rid the woods of Ephraim</L>
<L>(Which fought for thee as much as all thy men)</L>
<L>His haire was tangled in a shadie oake,</L>
<L>And hanging there (by Ioab and his men)</L>
<L>Sustaind the stroke of well deserued death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dauid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hath Absalon sustaind the stroke of death?</L>
<L>Die Dauid for the death of Absalon,</L>
<L>And make these cursed newes the bloudy darts,</L>
<L>That through his bowels rip thy wretched breast.</L>
<L>Hence Dauid, walke the solitarie woods,</L>
<L>And insome Caedars shade the thunder slew,</L>
<L>And fire from heauen hath made his branches blacke</L>
<L>Sit mourning the decease of Absalon,</L>
<L>Against the body of that blasted plant</L>
<L>In thousand shiuers breake thy yuorie Lute,</L>
<L>Hanging thy stringlesse harpe vpon his boughs,</L>
<L>And through the hollow saplesse sounding truncke,</L>
<L>Bellow the torments that perplexe thy soule.</L>
<L>There let the winds sit sighing till they burst,</L>
<L>Let tempest mufled with a cloud of pitch,</L>
<L>Threaten the forrests with her hellish face,</L>
<L>And (mounted fiercely on her yron wings)</L>
<L>Rend vp the wretched engine by the roots</L>
<L>That held my dearest Absalon to death.</L>
<L>Then let them tosse my broken Lute to heauen,</L>
<L>Euen to his hands that beats me with the strings,</L>
<L>To shew how sadly his poore sheepeheard sings.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="30"/><HI>He goes to his pauillion, and sits close a while.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beth.</SPEAKER>
<L>Die Bethsabe to see thy Dauid mourne,</L>
<L>To heare his tunes of anguish and of hell,</L>
<L>O helpe my Dauid, helpe thy Bethsabe,</L>
<STAGE>She kneeles downe.</STAGE>
<L>Whose heart is pierced with thy breathie swords,</L>
<L>And bursts with burthen of tenne thousand greefes.</L>
<L>Now sits thy sorrowes sucking of my bloud,</L>
<L>O that it might be poison to their powers,</L>
<L>And that their lips might draw my bosome drie,</L>
<L>So Dauids loue might ease him, though she die.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nat.</SPEAKER>
<L>These violent passions come not from aboue,</L>
<L>Dauid and Bethsabe offend the highest,</L>
<L>To mourne in this immeasurable sort.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dau.</SPEAKER>
<L>O Absalon, Absalon, O my sonne, my sonne,</L>
<L>Would God that I had died for Absalon:</L>
<L>But he is dead, ah dead, Absalon is dead,</L>
<L>And Dauid liues to die for Absalon.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>He lookes forth, and at the end sits close againe.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Ioab, Abisay, Ithay, with their traine.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ioab.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why lies the Queene so prostrate on the ground?</L>
<L>Why is this companie so Tragicke hew'd?</L>
<L>Why is the King now absent from his men?</L>
<L>And marcheth not in triumph through the gates?</L>
<STAGE>He vnfolds the pauillion.</STAGE>
<L>Dauid awake, if sleepe haue shut thine eies,</L>
<L>Sleepe of affection, that thou canst not see</L>
<L>The honour offerd to the victors head,</L>
<L>Ioab brings conquest pierced on his speare,</L>
<L>And ioy from all the Tribes of Israel.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dauid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou man of bloud, thou sepulchre of death,</L>
<L>Whose marble breast intombe my bowels quicke,</L>
<L>Did I not charge thee, nay intreat thy hand,</L>
<L>Euen for my sake to spare my Absalon?</L>
<L>And hast thou now in spight of Dauids health,</L>
<L><PB REF="30"/>And skorne to doe my heart some happinesse,</L>
<L>Giuen him the sword, and spilt his purple soule?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ioab.</SPEAKER>
<L>What? irkes it Dauid, that he victor breaths,</L>
<L>That Iuda and the fields of Israel,</L>
<L>Should cleanse their faces from their childrens bloud?</L>
<L>What art thou wearie of thy royall rule?</L>
<L>Is Israels throne a Serpent in thine eyes,</L>
<L>And he that set thee there, so farre from thankes,</L>
<L>That thou must curse his seruant for his sake?</L>
<L>Hast thou not said, that as the morning light,</L>
<L>The cloudlesse morning, so should be thine house,</L>
<L>And not as flowers by the brightest raine,</L>
<L>Which growes vp quickly, and as quickly fades?</L>
<L>Hast thou not said, the wicked are as thornes,</L>
<L>That cannot be preserued with the hand,</L>
<L>And that the man shall touch them, must be armd</L>
<L>With coats of yron, and garments made of steele,</L>
<L>Or with the shaft of a defenced speare?</L>
<L>And art thou angrie he is now cut off,</L>
<L>That lead the guiltlesse swarming to their deaths,</L>
<L>And was more wicked then an host of men?</L>
<L>Aduance thee from thy melancholy denne,</L>
<L>And decke thy bodie with thy blisfull robes,</L>
<L>Or by the Lord that swaies the heauen, I sweare,</L>
<L>Ile lead thine armies to another King,</L>
<L>Shall cheere them for their princely chiualrie,</L>
<L>And not sit daunted, frowning in the darke,</L>
<L>When his faire lookes, with Oyle and Wine refresht,</L>
<L>Should dart into their bosomes gladsome beames,</L>
<L>And fill their stomackes with triumphant feasts,</L>
<L>That when elsewhere sterne warre shall sound his trumpe,</L>
<L>And call another battaile to the field,</L>
<L>Fame still may bring thy valiant souldiers home,</L>
<L>And for their seruice happily confesse</L>
<L>She wanted worthy trumpes to sound their prowesse,</L>
<L>Take thou this course and liue, refuse, and die.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="31"/>
<SPEAKER>Abisay.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come brother, let him sit there till he sincke,</L>
<L>Some other shall aduance the name of Ioab.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Offers to goe out.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beth.</SPEAKER>
<L>O stay my lords, stay, Dauid mournes no more,</L>
<L>But riseth to giue honour to your acts.
<STAGE>Stay.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>He riseth vp.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dauid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then happie art thou Dauids fairest sonne,</L>
<L>That freed from the yoke of earthly toiles,</L>
<L>And sequestred from sence of humane sinnes;</L>
<L>Thy soule shall ioy the sacred cabinet</L>
<L>Of those deuine Ideas, that present</L>
<L>Thy changed spirit with a heauen of blisse.</L>
<L>Then thou art gone, ah thou art gone my sonne</L>
<L>To heauen I hope my Absalon is gone,</L>
<L>Thy soule there plac'd in honour of the Saints</L>
<L>Or angels clad with immortalitie,</L>
<L>Shall reape a seuenfold grace, for all thy greefes,</L>
<L>Thy eyes now no more eyes but shining stars,</L>
<L>Shall decke the flaming heauens with nouell lampes,</L>
<L>There shalt thou tast the drinke of Seraphins,</L>
<L>And cheere thy feelings with archangels food,</L>
<L>Thy day of rest, thy holy Sabboth day</L>
<L>Shall be eternall, and the curtaine drawne,</L>
<L>Thou shalt behold thy soueraigne face to face,</L>
<L>With wonder knit in triple vnitie,</L>
<L>Vnitie infinite and innumerable,</L>
<L>Courage braue captaines, Ioab; tale hath stird,</L>
<L>And made the suit of Israel preserd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ioab.</SPEAKER>
<L>Brauely resolud and spoken like a King,</L>
<L>Now may old Israel, and his daughters sing.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
<PB REF="31"/>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

