<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2004-06-24</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Jonathan Blaney</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Checked for N=""s. Checked for GROUP tags. Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, etc.). Checked for signatures. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, and UNCLEARs. Corrected 82 $s and $$word$$s etc. of 243. Converted 161 $$s to GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex". Checked spacing of foreign GAPs. Checked for EPIGRAPHs and ARGUMENTs. Checked for &amp;cs with incorrect spacing. Checked for LBs. Checked for startqs, endqs, oes, q;s, and Qs. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Checked for CLOSERs, TRAILERs, and BYLINEs. Checked for missing page GAPs. DONE.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="A11153">
<STC T="S">21423</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99851489</BIBNO>
<VID>16763</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<P><PB REF="1"/>
A NEVV WONDER, A WOMAN NEVER VEXT.</P>
<P><HI>A PLEASANT CONCEITED</HI> Comedy: sundry times Acted: never before printed.</P>
<P><HI>Written by</HI> VVILLIAM ROWLEY, <HI>one of his Maiesties Servants.</HI></P>
<P>LONDON, Imprinted by <HI>G. P.</HI> for <HI>Francis Constable,</HI> and are to be sold at his shop at the signe of the Crane in Saint <HI>Pauls</HI> Churchyard. 1632.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 N="1" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB N="1" REF="2"/>
<HEAD>A NEVV VVONDER, A VVOMAN NEVER VEXT.</HEAD>
<HEAD>Actus Primus.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Old Foster, Alderman Bruy<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e and two Fact<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> chard, and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old Foster.</SPEAKER>
<L><SEG REND="decorInit">T</SEG>His ayre has a sweet a breath Master <HI>Bruy<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your partner Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, and in good I hope, this hal<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></L>
<P>Playes the lewd wanton with our <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> sayles,</P>
<L>And makes 'm big with vaporous envy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis no more yet, but then our fraught is full</L>
<L>When shee returnes laden with merchandize</L>
<L>And safe deliver'd with our customage.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Such a delivery heaven send us,</L>
<L>But time must ripen it? are our accounts made even?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geor.</SPEAKER>
<L>To the quantity of a penny, if his agree with mines</L>
<L>What's yours <HI>Richard?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ric.</SPEAKER>
<L>Five hundred sixty pounds;</L>
<L><PB N="2" REF="3"/>
Read the grosse summe of your broade cloathes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geor.</SPEAKER>
<L>68. peices at B, ss, and l; 57. at l, ss, and o.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ric.</SPEAKER>
<L>Iust; leade, xix tunne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>As evenly we will lay our bosomes as our bottome<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>With love as merchandise, and may they both increase</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o Infinites.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>Especially at home; that golden traffique love</L>
<L>Is scantier far than gold; and one myne of that</L>
<L>More worth than twenty Argoseyes</L>
<L>Of the worlds richest treasure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here you shall dig, and finde your lading.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s your exchange; and as in love</L>
<L>So wee'le participate in merchandize.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>The merchants casualty:</L>
<L>We alwayes venture on uncertaine ods,</L>
<L>Altho we beare hopes Embleme the anchor with us.</L>
<L>The winde brought it, let the wind blow't away agen;</L>
<L>Should not the Sea sometimes be partner with us</L>
<L>Our wealth would swallow us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r.</SPEAKER>
<L>A good resolve: but now I must be bold</L>
<L>To touch you with somewhat that concernes you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>I could prevent you; is't not my unthrifty brother?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, leave out the adjective (unthrifty,)</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> brother Sir, tis he that I would speake of.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L>He cannot be nam'd without unthrifty S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> his p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oper Epithite, would you conceite</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ut what my love has done for him</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, so chargeable, and so expensive,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> would not urge another addition.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay Sir, you must not stay acquantity</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> the name of brother</L>
<L>Which is inseparable, hee's now in Ludgate Sir,</L>
<L>And part of your treasure lyes buryed with him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>st.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, by vulgar blemish; but not by any good account;</L>
<L>There let him howle, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s the best stay he hath;</L>
<L>For nothing but a prison can containe him</L>
<L>So boundlesse is his ryot; twice have I raysde</L>
<L><PB N="3" REF="3"/>
His decayed fortunes to a faire estate</L>
<L>But with as fruitlesse charity, as if I had throwne</L>
<L>My safe landed substance backe into the Sea,</L>
<L>Or dresse in pitty some corrupted Iade,</L>
<L>And he should kick me for my courtesie.</L>
<L>I am sure you cannot but heare, what quicke.</L>
<L>Sands he findes out, as Dice, Cards, Pigeon-holes,</L>
<L>And which is more, should I not restraine it,</L>
<L>Hee'd make my state his prodigality.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>All this may be Sir, yet examples dayly shew</L>
<L>To our eyes, that Prodigalls returne at last</L>
<L>And the lowdest roarer, (as our Citty phrase is)</L>
<L>Will speake calme and smooth; you must helpe with hope Sir,</L>
<L>Had I such a brother, I should thinke that heaven had</L>
<L>Made him as an instrument for my best charity</L>
<L>To worke upon; This is a Maxime sure, Some</L>
<L>Are made poore, that rich men by giving may</L>
<L>Encrease their store. Nor thinke Sir, that I doe</L>
<L>Tax your labors and meane my selfe for to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></L>
<L>Idlely by, for I have vowd if heaven bu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> blesse</L>
<L>This voyage now abroad, to leave some</L>
<L>Memorable relique after me, that shall</L>
<L>Preserve my name alive till Doomesday.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>I Sir, that worke is good, and therein could I</L>
<L>Ioyne with your good intents, but to releeve</L>
<L>A wast-good, a spendthrift.—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>O no more, no more good Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sirra, when saw you my son <HI>Robert▪</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ric.</SPEAKER>
<L>This morning Sir, he said he would goe visit his Vncle</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>I pay for their meetings I'me s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e; that boy</L>
<L>Makes prize of all his fingers light on</L>
<L>To releeve his unthrifty Vncle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>Does he rob, introth I commend him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis partly your fault, Sitra you see'r, and suffer it,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ric.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, mine's a servants duty, his a sonnes,</L>
<L>Nor know I better how to expresse my love</L>
<L>Vnto your selfe, than by loving your son.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="4" REF="4"/>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>By concealing of his pilferings.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ric.</SPEAKER>
<L>I dare not call them so; he is my second Master,</L>
<L>And methink<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> tis far above my limits</L>
<L>Either to checke, or to complaine of him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <HI>Du<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</HI> then mak'st a good construction,</L>
<L>And your son <HI>Robert</HI> a naturall Nephewes part.</L>
<L>To releeve his poore Vncle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>in neither well; Sir, for note but the</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>tion of my estate; I'me lately marryed</L>
<L>To a wealthy Widow from whom my substance</L>
<L>Ch<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ly does arise, she has observed this in her</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 words" DISP="〈◊◊〉"/> often complaines and grudges at it,</L>
<L>And what <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> broyles such civili discords bring,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> married men are ignorant of:</L>
<STAGE><HI>Enter Mistris</HI> Foster.</STAGE>
<L>Nay will you see a present proofe of it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall I not live to breath a quiet houre?</L>
<L>I would I were a beggar with content</L>
<L>Rather than thus be thwarted for mine owne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why what's the matter Woman?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<P>I'le towse 'm up, tho you regard not of my just complaints</P>
<L>Neither in love to me, nor preserving me from others</L>
<L>Injuries, both which y'are tyed to, by all the rightfull</L>
<L>Lawes heavenly or humane, but Ile complaine</L>
<L>Sir, where I will be heard.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, thou'It be heard too farre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay Sir, I will be heard; some awkeward starre</L>
<L>Threw out his unhappy <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>eat my conception</L>
<L>And twill never quench while I have heate in me:</L>
<L>Would I were cold, there would be bonefires made</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> warme defa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e, my death would be a Iubilce to some.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O▪ Fost.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why Sir, how should I minister remedy and know not the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mother a pearle, woman, shew your husband the cause,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<P>Had he bin a husband Sir, I had had no cause to Complaine, I threw downe at his feete</P>
<L><PB N="5" REF="4"/>
The subjection of his whole estate:</L>
<L>He did not marry me for loves sake nor for pitty,</L>
<L>But love to that I had, he now neglects the love</L>
<L>He had before; A prodigall is suffer'd to lay waste</L>
<L>Those worldly blessings, which I long enclosde,</L>
<L>Intending for good uses.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's my sonne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, thou knowest it well enough, hee's the Condu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> pipe that throwes it forth into the common shore.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>And the other's my brother.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>You may well shame, as I doe grieve the kindred,</L>
<L>But I'de make the one a stranger, the other a servant,</L>
<L>No son, nor brother; For they deserve neither</L>
<L>Of those offices.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why did I ever cherish him, have not I threat<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></L>
<L>Him with disinheritance for this disorder?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why doe you not performe it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>The other's in Ludgate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>No; hee's in my house, approving to my face</L>
<L>The charitable office of his kinde Nephew,</L>
<L>Who with his pilfering purloind from me,</L>
<L>Has set him at liberty; if this may be suffer'd</L>
<L>Ile have no eyes to see.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prethee content thy selfe; Ile see a present</L>
<L>Remedy; sirra, go call 'm in; this worthy</L>
<L>Gentleman shall know the cause, and censure</L>
<L>For us both with equity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay good Sir, let not me be so imployd,</L>
<STAGE>Enter Robin and Stephen Foster.</STAGE>
<L>For I shall favour one for pitty, the other for your loves sake,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now Sir, are all my words with you</L>
<L>So light esteem'd that they can</L>
<L>Take no hold upon your duty?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Misconster not, I beseech you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, heele approve his good deeds I warrant you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>And you Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Step.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="6" REF="5"/>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>I had thought you had bin in Ludgate Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Step.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, you see where I am Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, where are you Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Step.</SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>bt Sir, in debt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeed that's a place you can hardly be remou'd</L>
<L>From, but this is not a place fit for one in</L>
<L>Debt, how came you out of prison Sirra?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L>As I went into prison Sirra, by the keepers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost</SPEAKER>
<L>This was your worke to let this bandog loose.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir it was my duty to let my Vncle loose.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your duty did belong to me, and I did not command</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>You cannot make a separation Sir, betwixt</L>
<L>The duty that belongs to me, and love unto</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>cle, aswell you may bid me love my</L>
<L>Maker, and neglect the Creature, which he</L>
<L>Hath bid me love; if man to man joyne not</L>
<L>A love on earth, they love not heaven, nor</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> that dwells above it, such is my duty</L>
<L>A strong Corelative unto</L>
<L>My Vncle why, he's halfe your selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beleeve me Sir, he has answered you well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>He has not worthy Sir, but to make voyde</L>
<L>That false construction; here I disclayme</L>
<L>The title of a brother; and by that disclayme</L>
<L>Hast thou lost thy childes part; be thou engag'd</L>
<L>For any debts of his, in prison rot with him;</L>
<L>My goods shall not purchase such</L>
<L>Fruitlesse recompence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Step.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then th'art a scurvy father, and a filthy brother.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, I, Sir, your tongue cannot defame his reputation</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Step.</SPEAKER>
<L>But yours can, for all the City reports what</L>
<L>An abominable scould he has got to his wife.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>If ere I know thou keep'st him company,</L>
<L>Ile take my blessing from thee whil'st I live,</L>
<L>And that which after me should blesse thy estate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Step.</SPEAKER>
<L>And Ile proclayme thy basenesse to the world;</L>
<L><PB N="7" REF="5"/>
Ballads I'l make, and make 'm Taverne musick</L>
<L>To sing thy churlish cruelty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>O.</HI> Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tut, tut, these are bables.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>Each Festivall day I'l come unto thy house,</L>
<L>And I will pi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>e upon thy threshold.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>You must be out of prison first Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>If e'r I live to see thee Shreiffe of London,</L>
<L>I'l gild thy painted postes <HI>cum privilegio,</HI></L>
<L>And kick thy Serjeants.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, good Vncle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, I'l beg for thee, Boy;</L>
<L>I'l breake this leg, and bind it up againe,</L>
<L>To pull out pitty from a stony brest,</L>
<L>Rather than thou shalt want.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>O.</HI> Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, doe; let him feare up his arme, and scarfe it up</L>
<L>With two yards of rope; counterfeit two villaines;</L>
<L>Beg under a hedge and share your bounty: but come</L>
<L>Not neare my house, not thou in's company, if thoul't obey,</L>
<L>There's punishment, for thee; for thee there's worse;</L>
<L>The losse of all that's mine, with my deare curse.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Manent.</HI> Stephen <HI>and</HI> Robin.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>Churle, Dog, you churlish rascally miser.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, good Vncle, throw not foule language;</L>
<L>This is but heate Sir, and I doubt not but</L>
<L>To coole this rage with my obedience:</L>
<L>But Vncle, you must not then heape on such fuell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cuz, I grieve for thee, that thou hast undergone</L>
<L>Thy fathers curse, for love unto thy Vncle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tut, that bond shall ne'r be cancel'd, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>I pitty that y'faith.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let pitty then from me turne to your selfe:</L>
<L>Bethinke your selfe Sir, of some course</L>
<L>That might befit your estate, and let me guide it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, a course? sfoot I hate: Cuz, canst lend me</L>
<L>40. shillings? Could I but repaire this old decay'd Tenement</L>
<L>Of mine with some new playster; for alas, what</L>
<L>Can a man doe in such a case as this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="8" REF="6"/>
<SPEAKER>Reb.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, but your course, Vncle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tush, leave that to me, because thou shalt wonder</L>
<L>At it: If you should see me in a scarlet gowne</L>
<L>Within the compasse of a gold chaine, then I</L>
<L>Hope you'l say, that I doe keepe my selfe in</L>
<L>Good compasse: then Sir, if the Cap of Maintenance</L>
<L>Doe march before me, and not a Cap be suffer'd</L>
<L>To be worne in my presence, pray doe not upbraide</L>
<L>Me with my former poverty: I cannot tell, state</L>
<L>And wealth may make a man forget himselfe;</L>
<L>But I beseech you doe not; there are things in my</L>
<L>Head that you dreame not of; dare you try me, Cuz?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, forty shillings, Vncle, shall not keepe backe Your fortunes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, gramerey Cuz; now if the dice doe run right,</L>
<L>This 40. shillings may set me up agen: To lay't on my backe,</L>
<L>And so to pawne it, there's ne'r a damb'd Broker</L>
<L>In the world will give me halfe the worth on't:</L>
<L>No, whil'st 'tis in ready cash, that's the surest</L>
<L>Way; 7. is better than 11. a pox take the bones</L>
<L>And they will not favour a man sometimes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Looke you Vncle, there's 40. shillings for you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>As many good Angells guard thee, as thou hast given</L>
<L>Me bad ones to seduce me, for these deputy divells</L>
<L>Dam worse than the old ones. Now Cuz, pray listen,</L>
<L>Listen after my transformation; I will henceforth</L>
<L>Turne an Apostate to prodigality; I will eate</L>
<L>Cheese and Onions and buy lordships, and will</L>
<L>Not you thinke this strange?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am glad y'are merry, Vncle; but this is fixt</L>
<L>Betwixt an Vncle and a Nephewes love,</L>
<L>Though my estate be poore, revenewes scant,</L>
<L>Whil'st I have any left, you shall not want.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why gramercy, by this hand Ile make</L>
<L>Thee an Alderman before I dye, doe but</L>
<L>Follow my steps.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE><PB N="9" REF="6"/>
Enter Widdow and Clowne.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sirra, will the Churchman come I sent you for?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, mistris, he will come: but pray resolve</L>
<L>Me one thing for my long service; What</L>
<L>Businesse have you with the Churchman?</L>
<L>Is it to make your Will, or to get you a new</L>
<L>Husband?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Suppose to make my Will, how then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then I would desire you to remember me, Mistris,</L>
<L>I have serv'd you long, and that's the best</L>
<L>Service to a woman: make a good Will if you</L>
<L>Meane to dye, that it may not be said, Though</L>
<L>Most women be long liv'd, yet they all dye</L>
<L>With an ill-will.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>So Sir, suppose it be for marriage.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why then remember your selfe mistris;</L>
<L>Take heede how you give away the head;</L>
<L>It stands yet upon the shoulders of</L>
<L>Your widdowhood; the loving embracing Ivie</L>
<L>Has yet the upper place in the house;</L>
<L>If you give it to the Holly, take heede,</L>
<L>There's pricks in Holly; or if you feare not</L>
<L>The pricks, take heede of the wands, you</L>
<L>Cannot have the pricks without the wands;</L>
<L>You give away the sword, and must defend</L>
<L>Your selfe with the scabbard; these are pretty</L>
<L>Instructions of a friend; I would be loth to</L>
<L>See you cast downe, and not well taken up.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well Sir, well, let not all this trouble you;</L>
<L>See, hee's come; Will you be gone?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Doctor.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will first give him a caveat, to use you</L>
<L>As kindely as he can. If you finde my mistris</L>
<L>Have a minde to this coupling at barly-breake,</L>
<L>Let her not be the last couple to be left in hell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would I knew your meaning, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<L>If she have a minde to a fresh husband, or</L>
<L><PB N="10" REF="7"/>
So, use her as well as you can; let her enter</L>
<L>Into as easie bands as may be.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, this is none of my traffique; I sell no husbands.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then you doe wrong, Sir, for you take mony for 'm:</L>
<L>What woman can have a husband, but you must</L>
<L>Have custome for him? and often the ware proves</L>
<L>Naught too not worth the Impost.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your mans pregnant, and merry, mistris.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee's sawcy Sir. Sirra, you'l be gone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, at the second hand you'l have a fee too;</L>
<L>You sell in the Church, and they bring 'm againe</L>
<L>To your Church-yarde, you must have tollage:</L>
<L>Me thinkes if a man dye whether you will or no,</L>
<L>He should be buryed whether you would or no.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay now you wade too far, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>You'l be gone, Sirra.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mistris make him your friend, for he knowes what rate</L>
<L>Good husbands are at; if there hath bin a dearth</L>
<L>Of women of late, you may chance picke</L>
<L>Out a good prize; but take heede of a Clerke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you yet Sir, after your needelesse trouble,</L>
<L>Be gone, and bid the maides dresse dinner.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mistris, 'tis fasting day to day, there's nothing but fish.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let there be store of that; let bounty furnish the</L>
<L>Table, and charity shall be the voyder.</L>
<L>What fish is there, Sirra?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Marry there is Sammon, Pike, and fresh Cod,</L>
<L>Soles, Maides, and Playce.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bid 'm haste to dresse 'm then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay mistris, I'le helpe 'm too; the maides shall first</L>
<L>Dresse the Pike, and the Cod, and then I'le dresse</L>
<L>The maides in the place you wot on.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Clowne.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<L>You sent for me, Gentlewoman?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, I did, and to this end:</L>
<L>I have some scruples in my conscience;</L>
<L>Some doubtfull problemes which I cannot answer</L>
<L>Nor reconcile; I'de have you make them plaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="11" REF="7"/>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is my duty; pray speake your minde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>And as I speak, I must remember heaven</L>
<L>That gave those blessings which I must relate:</L>
<L>Sir, you now behold a wondrous woman;</L>
<L>You onely wonder at the Epithete;</L>
<L>I can approve it good; Ghesse at mine age.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<L>At the halfe way 'twixt thirty and forty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twas not much amisse; yet nearest to the last;</L>
<L>How thinke you then; Is not this a wonder,</L>
<L>That a woman lives full seven and thirty yeares,</L>
<L>Mayde to a wife, and wife unto a widdow,</L>
<L>Now widdowed, and mine owne, yet all this while</L>
<L>From the extremest verge of my remembrance,</L>
<L>Even from my weaning houre unto this minute,</L>
<L>Did never taste what was calamity;</L>
<L>I know not yet what griefe is, yet have sought</L>
<L>A hundred wayes for its acquaintance; with mee</L>
<L>Prosperity hath kept so close a watch,</L>
<L>That even those things that I have meant</L>
<L>A crosse, have that way turn'd a blessing;</L>
<L>Is it not strange?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vnparaleld; this gift is singular,</L>
<L>And to you alone belonging; you are the Moone,</L>
<L>For there's but one, all women else are stars,</L>
<L>For there are none of like condition:</L>
<L>Full oft, and many have I heard complaine</L>
<L>Of discontents, thwarts, and adversities;</L>
<L>But a second to your selfe, I never knew</L>
<L>To groane under the superflux of blessings,</L>
<L>To have ever bin a lien unto sorrow;</L>
<L>No trip of fate? Sure it is wonderfull.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, Sir, tis wonderfull; but is it well?</L>
<L>For it is now my chiefe affliction.</L>
<L>I have heard you say, that the child of heaven</L>
<L>Shall suffer many tribulations;</L>
<L>Nay, Kings and Princes share them with their subjects;</L>
<L>Then I that know not any chastisement</L>
<L><PB N="12" REF="8"/>
How may I know my part of childhood?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis a good doubt; but make it not extreme,</L>
<L>'Tis some affliction, that you are afflicted</L>
<L>For want of affliction: Cherish that;</L>
<L>Yet wrest it not to misconstruction;</L>
<L>For all your blessings are free gifts from heaeven</L>
<L>Health, wealth, and peace; nor can they turnto</L>
<L>Curses, but by abuse. Pray let me question you:</L>
<L>You lost a husband, was it no griefe to you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>It was; but very small; no sooner I</L>
<L>Had given it entertainement as a sorrow,</L>
<L>But straite it turn'd unto my treble joy;</L>
<L>A comfortable revelation prompts me then,</L>
<L>That husband whom in life I held so deare,</L>
<L>Had chang'd a frailty to unchanging joyes;</L>
<L>Me thought I saw him stellified in heaven,</L>
<L>And singing Hallelujahs 'mongst a quire</L>
<L>Of white Sainted soules: then againe it spake,</L>
<L>And said; It was a sinne for me to grieve</L>
<L>At his best good, that I esteemed best:</L>
<L>And thus this slender shadow of a griefe</L>
<L>Vanish't againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<L>All this was happy; nor can you wrest it</L>
<L>From a heavenly blessing. Doe not appoint</L>
<L>The rod: leave still the stroake unto the</L>
<L>Magistrate; the time is not past, but</L>
<L>You may feele enough.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>One tast more I had, although but little,</L>
<L>Yet I would aggravate to make the most</L>
<L>On't: thus 'twas; The other day, it was my hap</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>ssing of the Thames,</L>
<L>To drop that wedlocke Ring from off my finger,</L>
<L>That once conjoyn'd me and my dead husband;</L>
<L>It sunke, I pris'd it deare; the dearer, 'cause it kept</L>
<L>Still in mine eye the memory of my losse;</L>
<L>Yet I griev'd the losse, and did joy withall</L>
<L>That I had found a griefe; and this is all</L>
<L><PB N="13" REF="8"/>
The sorrow I can boast of.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is but small.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay sure I am of this opinion,</L>
<L>That had I suffer'd a draught to be made for it,</L>
<L>The bottome would have sent it up againe,</L>
<L>I am so wondrouslie fortunate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<L>You would not suffer it?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Clowne.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not for my whole estate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<P>O mistris, where are you? I thinke you are the fortunat'st Woman, that ever breath'd of two shoes: the thiefe is Found.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<P>The thiefe; what thiefe? I never was so happy To be robb'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bring him away <HI>Iug;</HI> nay, you shall see the strangest</L>
<L>Piece of felony discover'd that ever you saw,</L>
<L>Or your great grandmothers Grandam before, or after,</L>
<L>A pirate, a water thiefe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's all this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<P>Bring him away <HI>Iug;</HI> yet the villaine would not Confesse a word till it was found about him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thinke the fellow's mad.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did you not lose your wedding Ring the other day?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes Sir, but I was not robb'd of it.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Ioane</HI> with a fish.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<L>No; well, thanke him that brings it</L>
<L>Home then; and will aske nothing for his paines.</L>
<L>You see this Sammon?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, what of it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<L>It cost but six pence: but had the Fisher knowne</L>
<L>The worth of it, 'twould have cost you forty shillings.</L>
<L>Is not this your Ring?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>The very same.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your maid <HI>Ioane</HI> examining this Sammon, that shee</L>
<L>Bought in the Market, found that he had swallowed</L>
<L>This Gudgeon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>How am I vext with blessings? how thinke you</L>
<L><PB N="14" REF="9"/>
Sir, is not this above wonder?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am amaz'd at it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>First that this fish should snatch it as a baite;</L>
<L>Then that my servant needes must buy that fish</L>
<L>Amongst such infinites of fish and buyers:</L>
<L>What fate is mine that runnes all by it selfe</L>
<L>In unhappy happinesse? My conscience dreads it:</L>
<L>Would thou hadst not swallowed it, nor thou not bought it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas, blame not the poore fish, mistris, hee being a fleg, matique</P>
<L>Creature, tooke Gold for Restorative. He tooke it faire,</L>
<L>And he that gets Gold, let him eate Gold.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nothing can hinder fate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<L>Seeke not to crosse it then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>About your businesse, you have not pleas'd me in this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ioane.</SPEAKER>
<L>By my mayde nhead if I had thought you would</L>
<L>Have tane it no kindlier, you should ne'r</L>
<L>Have bin vext with sight on't; the garbidge should</L>
<L>Have bin the Cookes fees at this time.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Ioane.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now doe I see the old proverbe come to passe;</L>
<L>Give a woman lucke, and cast her into th'sea:</L>
<L>There's many a man would wish his wife good</L>
<L>Lucke, on that condition he might throw her</L>
<L>Away so. But mistris, there's one within would</L>
<L>Speake with you, that vexeth as fast against</L>
<L>Crosses, as you doe against good lucke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know her sure then, 'tis my gossip <HI>Foster:</HI></L>
<L>Request her in; here's good company, tell her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile tell her so for my owne credits sake.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall now see an absolute contrary:</L>
<L>Would I had chang'd bosomes with her for atime,</L>
<L>'T would make me better rellish happinesse.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Mistris <HI>Foster</HI> and Clowne.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>O friend and gossip, where are you? I am</L>
<L>O're loaden with my griefes, and but in your bosome</L>
<L>I know not where to ease me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<L>I had rather helpe you to a close, stoole,</L>
<L><PB N="15" REF="9"/>
And't please you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ne'r had woman more sinister fate;</L>
<L>All ominous stars were in conjunction</L>
<L>Even at my birth, and doe still attend me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is a perfect contrary indeede.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>What ayles you Woman?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vnlesse seven witches had set spels about me,</L>
<L>I could not be so crost, never at quiet</L>
<L>Never happy houre, not a minutes content.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<L>You hurt your selfe most with impatience.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, I Physitions minister with ease,</L>
<L>Although the patient do receive in paine;</L>
<L>Would I could think but of one joyfull houre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have had two husbands to my knowledge;</L>
<L>And if you had not one joyfull houre betweene</L>
<L>Both, I would you were hang'd i'faith.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Full fourteene yeeres I liv'd a weary mayde,</L>
<L>Thinking no joy till I had got a husband.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>That was a tedious time indeede.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>I had one lov'd me well, and then ere long</L>
<L>I grew into my longing peevishnesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<L>There was some pleasure ere you came to that.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then all the kindenesse that he would apply,</L>
<L>Nothing could please; soone after it he died.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<L>That could be but little griefe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then worldly care did so o'reload my weakenesse,</L>
<L>That I must have a second stay; I chose againe,</L>
<L>And there begins my griefes to multiply.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>It cannot be, friend; your husband's kinde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<L>A man of faire condition, well reputed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<L>But it may be he has not that should please her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace Sirra: how can your sorrowes encrease from him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>How can they but o'rewhelme me? he keepes a Son</L>
<L>That makes my state his prodigality;</L>
<L>To him a brother, one of the Citty scandals;</L>
<L>The tone the hand, the tother is the maw;</L>
<L>And betweene both my goods are swallowed up;</L>
<L><PB N="16" REF="10"/>
The full quantity that I brought amongst'm</L>
<L>Is now consum'd to halfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>The fire of your spleene wasts it;</L>
<L>Good sooth Gossip, I could laugh at thee, and onely grieve</L>
<L>I have not some cause of sorrow with thee:</L>
<L>P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>thee be temperate, and suffer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis good counsell mistris, receive it so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Canst thou devise to lay them halfe on me,</L>
<L>And <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>e beare'm willingly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would I could, that I might laugh another while:</L>
<L>But you are wise to heede at others harmes;</L>
<L>You'l keepe you happy in your widdowhood.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not I in good faith, were I sure marriage</L>
<L>Would make me unhappy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Try, try, you shall not neede to wish;</L>
<L>You'l sing another song, and beare a part</L>
<L>In my griefes descant, when y'are vext at heart:</L>
<L>Your second choyse will differ from the first:</L>
<L>So oft as widdowes marry they are accurst.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, curst widdowes are; but if they had all stiffe husbands</L>
<L>To tame'm, they'd be quiet enough.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>You'l be gone Sir, and see dinner ready.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I care not if I doe mistris, now my stomack's ready;</L>
<L>Yet Ile stay a little and be but to vex you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>When goe you, Sirra?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will not goe yet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, ha, ha, thou makest me laugh at thee; prethee stay,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay then Ile goe to vex you.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Clowne.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have a light heart Gossip.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>So should you Woman, would you be ruld by me:</L>
<L>Come, we'l dine together, after walke abroad</L>
<L>Vnto my suburbe garden, where if thou'lt heare,</L>
<L>He read my heart to thee, and thou from thence</L>
<L>Shalt learne to vex thy cares with patience.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="2" TYPE="act">
<PB N="17" REF="10"/>
<HEAD>Actus Secundus.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Host Boxall, Stephen, Iacke, Dicke, Hugh.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Host.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVElcome still my merchants of <HI>bona Speranza;</HI></L>
<P>What's your trafficke Bulleyes? What ware deale you in?</P>
<L>Cards, Dice, Bowles, or Pigeon-holes; sort'm</L>
<L>Your selves; either Passage, Novum, or Mumchance?</L>
<L>Say my brave Bursmen, what's your recreation?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dice mine <HI>Host:</HI> Is there no other roome empty?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Host.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not a hole unstopt in my house, but this my Thrists.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iack.</SPEAKER>
<L>Miscall us not for our money, good mine Host, we are</L>
<L>None of your thrifts; we have scap'd that scandall long agoe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dick.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, his thrifts we are <HI>Iacke,</HI> though not our owne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Host.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tush, you are young men, 'tis too soone to thrive yet:</L>
<L>He that gathers young, spends when hee's old:</L>
<L>'Tis better to begin ill, and end well, than to</L>
<L>Begin well and end ill: Miserable fathers have</L>
<L>For the most part unthrifty sons; leave not</L>
<L>Too much for your heires, Boyes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iack.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee sayes well i'faith; Why should a man trust</L>
<L>To executors.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>As good trust to hangmen as to executors:</L>
<L>Who's in the bowling Alley mine Host?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Host.</SPEAKER>
<L>Honest traders, thrifty lads, they are rubbing on't;</L>
<L>Towardly Boyes, every one strives to lye nearest the Mistris.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>Give's a bayle of Dice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Host.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here my brave Wags.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>We feare no Counters now mine Host, so</L>
<L>Long as we have your bayle so ready.</L>
<L>Come, trip.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iack.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vp with's heeles.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="18" REF="11"/>
<SPEAKER>Dick.</SPEAKER>
<L>Downe with them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hugh.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now the dice are mine; set me now a faire</L>
<L>Boord; a saire passage sweet bones. <HI>Boreas.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>A noyse below in the bowling Alley, betting, rubbing and wrangling.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Host.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now my fine Trundletayles;</L>
<L>My wodden Cosmographers:</L>
<L>My bowling Alley in an uprore?</L>
<L>Is <HI>Orlando</HI> up in armes? I must be stickler;</L>
<L>I am Constable, Iustice, and Beadle in mine</L>
<L>Owne house, I accuse, sentence, and punish:</L>
<L>Have amongst you; looke to my box Boyes;</L>
<L>He that breakes the peace, I breake his pate</L>
<L>For recompence; looke to my box, I say.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Step.</SPEAKER>
<P>A pox o'your box, I shall ne'r be so happy to Reward it better; set me faire; aloft now.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iack.</SPEAKER>
<L>Out.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Step.</SPEAKER>
<L>What wast?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dick.</SPEAKER>
<L>Two Trayes, and an Ace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Step.</SPEAKER>
<L>Seven still, pox on't; that number of the</L>
<L>Deadly sinnes haunts me damnably; Come Sir, throw.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iack.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prethee invoke not so, all sinkes too fast already.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hugh.</SPEAKER>
<L>It will be found againe in mine hosts box.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iack.</SPEAKER>
<L>In still, two theeves and choose thy fellow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Step.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take the Miller.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iack.</SPEAKER>
<L>Have at them i'faith.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hugh.</SPEAKER>
<L>For a thiefe Ile warrant you, who'l you have next.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iack.</SPEAKER>
<L>Two Quaters and a Tray.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Step.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hope we shall have good cheere, when two</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aters, and a Tray goe toth' market.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Host.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Host.</SPEAKER>
<L>So all's whist; they play upon the still pipes now,</L>
<L>The Bull-beggar comes when I shew my head,</L>
<L>Silence is a vertue, and I have made'm vertuous,</L>
<L>Let'm play still till they be penny lesse; pawne</L>
<L>Till they be naked, so they be quiet, welcome,</L>
<L>And welcome.</L>
<STAGE>A noyse above at Cards.</STAGE>
<L>How now, how now, my roaring <HI>Tamberlaine,</HI> take</L>
<L><PB N="19" REF="11"/>
Heede the Soldan comes; And 'twere not for proffit,</L>
<L>Who would live amongst such Beares? why <HI>Vrsa</HI></L>
<L><HI>Major</HI> I say, what in <HI>Capite Draconis?</HI> is there</L>
<L>No hope to reclayme you, shall I never live in quiet</L>
<L>For you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dick.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good mine Host still'm: civill Gamesters cannot play for'm.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Host.</SPEAKER>
<L>I come amongst you, you maledictious slaves; I'l</L>
<L>Vtter you all; some I'l take ready money for, and lay</L>
<L>Vp the rest in the stocks: looke to my box, I say.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Step.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your box is like your belly mine Host, it</L>
<L>Drawes all; now for a suite of apparell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iack.</SPEAKER>
<L>At whose suit I pray? y'are out againe with the threes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Step.</SPEAKER>
<L>Foote, I thinke my father threw three when I was</L>
<L>Begotten; pox on't, I know now why I am so</L>
<L>Haunted with threes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iack.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, I prethee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Step.</SPEAKER>
<L>I met the third part of a knave as I came.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iack.</SPEAKER>
<L>The third part of a knave, s'foote what thing's that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Step.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why a Serjants Yeoman, man; the supervisor himselfe</L>
<L>Is but a whole one, and he shares but a groate in the</L>
<L>Shilling with him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dick.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's but the third part indeed: but goes he no further.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Step.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, he rests there.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hugh.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, let's give o're.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Step.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thanke you Sir, and so much a looser? there's but</L>
<L>The wast-band of my suite left: now sweete bones.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hugh.</SPEAKER>
<L>Twelve at all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Step.</SPEAKER>
<L>Soft, this dye is false.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hugh.</SPEAKER>
<L>False? you doe him wrong Sir, hee's true to his Master.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Step.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fullum:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dick.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le be hang'd then: where's Putney then I pray you</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Step.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis false, and I'le have my money againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hugh.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall have cold Iron with your silver then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Step.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, have at you Sir.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Host, and young Foster.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Host.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thinke hee's here, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB N="20" REF="12"/>
Young Foster assists his Uncle and the Host, and beat se them off; Enter the Bowlers and steale away their Cloakes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am sure hee's now, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hugh.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold, hold, and you be Gentlemen hold.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Get you gone Varlets, or there's hold to be taken.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Host.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay sweete Sir, no bloodshed in my house; I am lord Of misrule, pray you put up, Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Om.</SPEAKER>
<L>S'foote mine Host, where are our cloakes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Host.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, this is quarrelling; Make after in time:</L>
<L>Some of your owne Crew, to try the weight has</L>
<L>Lifted them; looke out I say.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iack.</SPEAKER>
<L>There will ever be theeves in a dicing house</L>
<L>Till thou bee'st hang'd I'l warrant thee.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt Cheat.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Step.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mine Host, my Cloake was lin'd through with</L>
<L>Oringe tawney velvet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Host.</SPEAKER>
<L>How, your cloake? Ine'r knew thee worth one.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Step.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'are a company of Conycatching rascals;</L>
<L>Is this a suite to walke without a Cloake in?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vncle, is this the reformation that you promis'd mee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Step.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cuz, shall I tell thee the truth; I had diminish't</L>
<L>But six pence of the forty shillings by chance meeting with a</L>
<L>Friend, I went to a taylor, bargain'd for a suite, it</L>
<L>Came to full forty, I tender'd my xxxix and a halfe,</L>
<L>And doe you thinke the scabby-wristed rascall would</L>
<L>Trust me for six pence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your credit is the better, Vncle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Step.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pox on him, if the taylor had bin a man, I had</L>
<L>Had a faire suite on my backe, so venturing for</L>
<L>The tother Tester</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>You lost the whole Bed-stead.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Step.</SPEAKER>
<L>But after this day, I protest Cuz, you shall never</L>
<L>See me handle those bones againe; this day I</L>
<L>Breake up schoole: if ever you call me unthrift after</L>
<L>This day, you doe me wrong.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>I should be glad to wrong you so, Vncle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>And what sayes your father yet, Cuz?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="21" REF="12"/>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le tell you that in your eare.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Mistris Foster, Widdow and Clowne.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, I pray you friend beare me company a little</L>
<L>This way, for into this dicing house I saw my good</L>
<L>Son in law enter, and 'tis ods but he meetes his</L>
<L>Vncle here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>You cannot tire me gossip in your company, 'tis the best</L>
<L>Affliction I have to see you impatient.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, I, you may make mirth of my sorrow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<L>We have hunted well, mistris; doe you not see</L>
<L>The hare's in sight?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did not I tell you so; I, I, there's good counsell</L>
<L>Betweene you, the tone would goe afoote to hell,</L>
<L>The other the horseway.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mother, I am sorry you have trod this path.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mother? hang thee wretch, I bore thee not, but</L>
<L>Many afflictions I have borne for thee; wert thou</L>
<L>Mine owne, I'd see thee stretcht a handfull, and</L>
<L>Put thee a Cossin into the Cart, ere thou shouldst vex</L>
<L>Me thus.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Were I your owne, you could not use me worse than you doe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'l make thy father turne thee out for ever, or else</L>
<L>I'l make him wish him in his grave; You'l witnesse</L>
<L>With me Gossip where I have found him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, I'l be sworne upon a booke of Callico for that.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>It shal not neede, I'l not deny that I was with my Vncle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>And that shall disinherit thee, if thy father</L>
<L>Be an honest man; thou hadst bin better to have</L>
<L>Bin borne a viper, and eate thy way through thy</L>
<L>Mothers wombe into the world, than to tempt my</L>
<L>Displeasure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou lyest <HI>Zantippe;</HI> it had bin better thou hadst</L>
<L>Bin prest to death under two Irish Rugs, than to</L>
<L>Ride honest <HI>Socrates</HI> thy husband thus, and abuse his</L>
<L>Honest childe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Out Raggamustin, dost thou talke? I shall see thee</L>
<L><PB N="22" REF="13"/>
In Ludgate againe shortly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou lyest agen, 'twilbe at More-gate, Beldam, where I shall see thee in the Ditch dancing in a Cucking-stoole.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'l see thee hang'd first.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou lyest againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay Sir, you doe wrong to give a woman so many lies,</L>
<L>Shee had rather have had twice so many standings, than</L>
<L>One lye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'l lye with him I'l warrant him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>You'l be a whore then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Little lesse I promise you, if you lye with him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you complaine upon mine honest Cuz,</L>
<L>And that his father be offended with him,</L>
<L>The next time I meete thee, though it be i'th' streete,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="3 words" DISP="〈◊◊◊〉"/> durt upon thy velvet Cap;</L>
<L>Nay worse, Plestaine thy Ruffe; nay worse than that,</L>
<L>I'l doe thus:</L>
<STAGE>Holds a wispe.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>O my hart Gossip, do you see this? Was ever</L>
<L>Woman thus abus'd?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Me thinkes 'tis good sport y'faith.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, I am well recompenc'd to complaine to you,</L>
<L>Had you such a kindred.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would rejoyce in't Gossip.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do so; choose herethen; Oh my hart! But I'l doe</L>
<L>Your e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>and; Oh that my Nayles were not par'd! But I'l doe</L>
<L>Your errand; Will you goe Gossip?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>No I'l stay awhile and tell 'm out with patience.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>I cannot hold a joynt still; Dost wispe me, thou</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>atterdemallion; I'l doe your errands, if I have a</L>
<L>Husband; Oh that I could spit Wild fire!</L>
<L>My heart, Oh my heart! If it does not goe pantle,</L>
<L>Pantle, pantle in my belly, I am no honest woman:</L>
<L>But I'l doe your errands.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Mistris Foster.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Kinde Gentlewoman, you have some patience.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have too much Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>You may doe a good office, and make your selfe a Peacefull moderator betwixt me and my angry</P>
<P><PB N="23" REF="13"/>
Father, whom his wife hath mou'd to spleene Against me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, I doe not disallow the kindenesse your</L>
<L>Consanguinity renders, I would not teach</L>
<L>You otherwise; I'd speake with your Vncle, Sir,</L>
<L>If you'l give me leave.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>You may talke with me Sir, in the meane time.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit. Robin and Clowne</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>With me would you talke, Gentlewoman?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes Sir, with you; you are a brave Vnthrift.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not very brave neither; yet I make a shift</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>When you have a cleane shirt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'l be no Pupill to a woman; leave your discipline.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, pray you heare me Sir, I cannot chide.</L>
<L>I'l but give you good counsell; 'tis not a good</L>
<L>Course that you <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>n.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet I must run to'th' end of it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would teach you a better, if you'd stay where you are.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would stay where I am, if I had any money.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>In the dyeing house?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thinke so too, I have play'd at Passage all</L>
<L>This while, now I'd go to Hazard.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dost thou want Money? Thou art worthy to be tatter'd</L>
<L>Hast thou no wit now thy Money's gone?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis all the portion I have;</L>
<L>I have nothing to maintaine me but my <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>it;</L>
<L>My Money is too little I'm sure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>I cannot beleeve thy wit's more than thy Money,</L>
<L>A fellow so well limb'd, so able to doe good service,</L>
<L>And want.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why Mistris, my shoulders were not made for a Froc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>And a Basket, nor a Coale-sacke neither, no nor</L>
<L>My hands to turne a trencher at a tables side.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>I like that resolution well; but how comes it</L>
<L>Then, that thy wit leaves thy body unfurnisht?</L>
<L>Thou art very poore?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>The fortune of the Dice you see.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="24" REF="14"/>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are the onely wizards, I confesse,</L>
<L>The onely fortune-tellers; but he that goes to</L>
<L>Seeke his fortune from them, must never hope</L>
<L>To have a good destiny allotted him: yet it is</L>
<L>Not the course that I dislike in thee, but that</L>
<L>Thou canst not supply that course, and out-</L>
<L>Crosse them that crosse thee; Were I as thou art</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>You'd be as beggarly as I am.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'l be hang'd first.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, you must be well hang'd e'r you can be as I am.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>So Sir, I conceite you; were I as well hang'd then</L>
<L>As you could imagine, I would tell some rich widow</L>
<L>Such a tale in her eare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha? Some rich widdow? By this pennilesse pocket,</L>
<L>I thinke 'twere not the worst way.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'd be asham'd to take such a fruitlesse oath:</L>
<L>I say, seeke me out some rich widow; promise</L>
<L>Her faire; shee's apt to believe a young man;</L>
<L>Marry her, and let her estate fly; no matter,</L>
<L>'Tis charity; Twenty to one some rich Miser rak'd</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t together; this is none of <HI>Hercules</HI> labours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha? let me recount these articles: Seeke her out;</L>
<L>Promise her faire; Marry her; Let her estate fly:</L>
<L>But where should I finde her?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>The easyest of all: Why man, they are more common</L>
<L>Than Taverne Bushes; two Fayres might be</L>
<L>Furnish'd every weeke in London with 'm, though no</L>
<L>Forrainers came in, if the Charter were granted once:</L>
<L>Nay, 'tis thought, if the Horse-market be remov'd, that</L>
<L>Smithfield shall be so imploy'd, and then I'l</L>
<L>Warrant you 'twill be as well furnishd with widowes as</L>
<L>Twas with Sowes, Cowes, and old trotting Iades before.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>S'foote, if it were, I would be a Chapman; I'd see for</L>
<L>My pleasure, and buy for my love, for money I have none.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou shalt not stay the Market; if thoul't be rul'd,</L>
<L>I'l finde thee out a widdow, and helpe in some of</L>
<L>The rest too; if thou'lt but promise me the last, but</L>
<L><PB N="25" REF="14"/>
To let her estate fly: for shee's one I loue not, and</L>
<L>I'd be glad to see that revenge on her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>Spend her estate, wer't five Aldermens; I'l put you</L>
<L>In security for that, sfoote all my neighbours shall be bound</L>
<L>For me, nay, my kinde Sister in law shall passe her word</L>
<L>For that.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Onely this I'l enjoyne you, to be matrimonially honest</L>
<L>To her for your owne healthes sake: all other injuries</L>
<L>Shall be blessings to her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'l blesse her then; I ever drunke so much,</L>
<L>That I was never great feeder; give me drinke,</L>
<L>And my pleasure, and a little flesh serves my turne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'l shew thee the party; What sayest thou to my self?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your selfe, Gentlewoman, I would it were no worse;</L>
<L>I have heard you reputed a rich widdow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have a lease of thousands at least, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'l let out your leases for you, if you'l allow me</L>
<L>The power I'l warrant you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's my hope Sir; but you must be honest withall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'l be honest with some; if I can he honest with all,</L>
<L>I will too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Give me thy hand; goe home with me, I'l give</L>
<L>The better clothes; and as I like thee then, we'l</L>
<L>Goe further, we may chance make a blinde</L>
<L>Bargaine of it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>I can make no blind bargaine, unlesse I be</L>
<L>In your bed, Widow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, I bar that Sir, lets begin honestly, how</L>
<L>E'r we end; marry for the waste of my estate</L>
<L>Spare it not; doe thy worst.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'l doe bad enough, feare it not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, will you walk, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>No Widow, I'l stand to no hazard of blinde</L>
<L>Bargaines; either promise me marriage, and give</L>
<L>Me earnest in a handfast, or I'l not budge</L>
<L>A foote.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>No Sir, are you growne so stout already?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="26" REF="15"/>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'l grow stouter when I am marryed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hope thou'lt vex me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'l give you cause I'l warrant you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall rayle, and curse thee I hope; yet I'd</L>
<L>Not have thee give over neither; for I would</L>
<L>Be vext; Here's my hand, I am thine, thou art mine,</L>
<L>I'l have thee withall faults.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall have one with some, and you have mee,</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Robin and Clowne.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here's witnesse, come hither Sir.</L>
<L>Cozin, I must call you shortly; and you</L>
<L>Sitra, be witnesse to this match; here's Man and Wife.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>I joy at mine Vncles happinesse, Widdow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe forbid the Banes: Alas poore Shagragge,</L>
<L>My Mistris does but gull him; you may</L>
<L>Imagine it to be T welfe-day at night, and the</L>
<L>Beane found in the corner of your Cake, but</L>
<L>Tis not worth a fetch I'l assure you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>You'l let me dispose of my selfe, I hope.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>You love to be merry Mistris; Come, come,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ve him foure Farthings, and let him goe.</L>
<L>He'l pray for his good Dame, and be drunke;</L>
<L>Why, if your blood does itch that way, we'l</L>
<L>Stand together; how thinke you? I thinke here</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> the sweeter bit, you see this Nap, and you</L>
<L>See this Lowse, you may cracke o' your choyse,</L>
<L>If you choose here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have put me to my choyse then; see, here I choose?</L>
<L>This is my Husband: Thus I begin the Contract.</L>
<STAGE>Kisse</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis seal'd, I am thine; now Cuz feare no blacke</L>
<L>Stormes; if thy father thunder, come to me for shelter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>His word is now a deede, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thanke you both. Vncle, what my joy conceives,</L>
<L>I cannot utter yet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will make blacke Munday of this: e'r I suffer</L>
<L>This disgrace, the kennell shall run with blood and rags,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, I am your apposite.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="27" REF="15"/>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have nothing to say to you, Sir; I ayme at your Vncle</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>He has no weapon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's all one, I'l take him as I finde him:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have taken him so before you, Sir; Will you be quiet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou shalt take me so too <HI>Hodge,</HI> for I'l be thy fellow,</L>
<L>Though thy Mistrisses Husband. Give me thy hand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'l make you seeke your fingers among the Dogs,</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt</STAGE>
<L>If you come to me; my Fellow? You lowsie</L>
<L>Companion; I scorne thee. S'foote, is't come to this?</L>
<L>Have I stood all this while to my Mistris, an honest,</L>
<L>Hansome, plaine-dealing, serving-Creature; and she to</L>
<L>Marry a Worson Tittere Tu Tattere with never a good rag</L>
<L>About him? Stand thou to me, and be my friend; and since</L>
<L>My Mistris has forsaken me:</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Robin.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now? what's the matter?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twas well you came in good time.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why man?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I was goingthe wrong way.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>But tell me one thing, I apprehend not; Why didst</L>
<L>Lay thy Cap upon the swords point?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do'st not thou know the reason of that? why, 'twas</L>
<L>To save my belly: dost thou thinke I am so mad to</L>
<L>Cast my selfe away for e'r a woman of'm all,</L>
<L>I'l see 'm hang'd first.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come <HI>Roger,</HI> will you goe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, since there is no remedy, Oh teares bee you my friend!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, prethee <HI>Roger</HI> doe not cry.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I cannot choose; nay I will steepe</L>
<L>Mine eyes in crying teares, and crying weepe.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="3" TYPE="act">
<PB N="28" REF="16"/>
<HEAD>Actus Tertius.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Alderman Bruine, Sir Godfry Speedwell, Innocent Lambskin, and Mistris Iane.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bruine.</SPEAKER>
<L>GEntlemen, y'are welcome; that once well pronounc'd</L>
<L>Has a thousand Ecchoes; Let it suffice, I have spoke</L>
<L>It to the full: here's your affaires, here's your merchandize,</L>
<L>This is your prise, if you can mix your names and gentle</L>
<L>Bloods with the poore Daughter of a Cittizen.</L>
<L>I make the passage free, to greete and court,</L>
<L>Traffique the mart of love, clap hands and strike</L>
<L>The bargaine through, (she pleas'd) and I shall like.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>God. Sp.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis good ware believe me, Sir, I know that by mine</L>
<L>Owne experience; for I have handled the like</L>
<L>Many times in my first wives dayes, I, by Knighthood,</L>
<L>Sometimes before I was marryed too; therefore I</L>
<L>Know't by mine owne experience.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well Sir, I know by observation, as much as you doe</L>
<L>By experience; for I have knowne many Gentlemen</L>
<L>Have taken up such ware as this is, but it has lyen</L>
<L>On their hands as long as they liv'd; this I</L>
<L>Have seene by observation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am like to have a couple of faire Chapmen:</L>
<L>If they were at my owne dispose, I would</L>
<L>Willingly rifle them both at twelve pence a share; they</L>
<L>Would be good foode for a new plantation; the</L>
<L>Tone might mend his experience; and the other his</L>
<L>Observation very much.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Speed.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, let me advise you: I see you want experience,</L>
<L>Meddle no further in this case, 'twilbe the</L>
<L>More credit for your observation; for I finde by my</L>
<L>Experience, you are but shallow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="29" REF="16"/>
<SPEAKER>Lamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>But shallow Sir? Your experience is a little wide;</L>
<L>You shall finde I wilbe as deepe in this case as</L>
<L>Your selfe; my observation has bin, where your</L>
<L>Experience must waite at doore; yet I will</L>
<L>Give you the fore Horse place, and I wilbe in the</L>
<L>Fill's, because you are the elder Tree, and I the</L>
<L>Young Plant; put on your experience, and I will</L>
<L>Observe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Speed.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweete Virgin, to be prolix and ted ious, fits <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></L>
<L>Experience; short words and large deedes are</L>
<L>Best pleasing to women.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>So, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Speed.</SPEAKER>
<L>My name is <HI>Speedwell,</HI> by my fathers Coppy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then you never serv'd for't it seemes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Speed.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, sweete Feminine, I have serv'd for it too:</L>
<L>For I have found my nativity suited to my name,</L>
<L>As my name is <HI>Speedwel,</HI> so have I sped</L>
<L>Well in divers actions.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>It must needes be a faire and comely suit then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>You observe very well, sweete Virgine; for his</L>
<L>Nativity is his Dublet, which is the upper part</L>
<L>Of his suite; and his name is in's breeches, for</L>
<L>That part which is his name, he defiles many times.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Speed.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your observation is corrupt, Sir; Let me shew min<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Owne Tale; I say, sweete Beauty, my name is</L>
<L><HI>Speedwell,</HI> my God-father by his bounty being an</L>
<L>Old Soldiour, and having serv'd in the wars as far as</L>
<L>Bulloyne, therefore cal'd my name <HI>Godfry;</HI> a</L>
<L>Title of large renowne; my wealth and wit has</L>
<L>Added to those, the paraphrase of Kinghthood;</L>
<L>So that my name in the full longitude is cal'd</L>
<L><HI>Sir Godfry Speedwell,</HI> a name of good experience.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ian.</SPEAKER>
<L>If every quality you have be as large in relation <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s</L>
<L>Your name Sir, I should imagine the best of them, rather</L>
<L>Than heare them reported.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Speed.</SPEAKER>
<P>You say well, sweet Modesty, a good imagination is good,</P>
<L><PB N="30" REF="17"/>
And shewes your good experience.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, if names can do any good, I beseech you observe</L>
<L>Mine; My name is <HI>Lambskin,</HI> a thing both hot and harmelesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<P>On Sir, I would not interrupt you, because you Should be briefe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lamb.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Godfather seeing in my face some notes of dispo∣sition,</P>
<L>In my Cradle did give me the title of <HI>Innocent,</HI> which I</L>
<L>Have practis'd all my life time; and since my fathers</L>
<L>Decease, my wealth has purchast me in the vanguard</L>
<L>Of my name, the paraphrase of gentility; So that</L>
<L>I am cald Master <HI>Innocent Lambskin.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>In good time; and what Trade was your father, Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>My father was of an Occupation before he was a</L>
<L>Tradesman; for, as I have observ'd in my fathers</L>
<L>And mothers report, they set up together in</L>
<L>Their youth; my father was a Starch-maker, and my</L>
<L>Mother a Laundresse; so being partners, they did</L>
<L>Occupy long together before they were marryed;</L>
<L>Then was I borne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>What, before your father was marryed?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Truly a little after, I was the first fruits, as they say;</L>
<L>Then did my father change his Copy, and set up</L>
<L>A Brewhouse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>I then came your wealth in, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your observation's good; I have carryed the Tallyes</L>
<L>At my girdle seven yeares together with much</L>
<L>Delight and observation; for I did ever love to</L>
<L>Deale honestly in the Nick.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>A very innocent resolution.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Speed.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your experience may see his course education; but to</L>
<L>The purpose, sweet Female; I doe love that</L>
<L>Face of yours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, if you love nothing but my face, I cannot sell it</L>
<L>From the rest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>You may <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> his slender observation; sweet Virgin,</L>
<L>I doe love your lower parts better than your face.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="31" REF="17"/>
<SPEAKER>Speed.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir you doe interrupt, and thwart my love.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>I Sir, I am your Rivall; and I will thwart your love▪</L>
<L>For your love licks at the face, and my love</L>
<L>Shall be Arsy-Versy to yours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would desire no better wooing of so bad suitors.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Speed.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mistake me not kinde Heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>He cals you Tooth drawer by way of experience.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Speed.</SPEAKER>
<L>In loving your face, I love all the rest of your body</L>
<L>As you shall finde by experience.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well Sir, you love me then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Speed.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let your experience make a tryall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>No Sir, I'l beleeve you rather, and I thanke you for't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>I love you too, faire Maide, double and treble,</L>
<L>If it please you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thanke you too Sir; I am so much beholding</L>
<L>To you both; I am affraid I shall never requite it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Speed.</SPEAKER>
<L>Requite one, sweete Chastity, and let it be</L>
<L>Sir <HI>Godfry,</HI> with the correspondencie of your</L>
<L>Love to him; I will maintaine you like a Lady,</L>
<L>And it is brave, as I know by experience.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will maintaine you like a Gentlewoman: And</L>
<L>That may be better maintenance than a Ladies,</L>
<L>As I have found by observation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Speed.</SPEAKER>
<L>How dare you maintaine that, Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>I dare maintaine it with my purse, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Speed.</SPEAKER>
<L>I dare crosse it with my sword Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you dare corsse my purse with your sword Sir,</L>
<L>I'llay an action of suspition of felony to you;</L>
<L>That's flat, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, pray you Gentlemen doe not quarrell,</L>
<L>Till you know for what.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, no quarrelling, I beseech you Gentlemen!</L>
<L>The reputation of my house is soyld, if any</L>
<L>Vncivill noyse arise in't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let him but shake his blade at me, and I'l</L>
<L>Throw downe my purse, and cry a rape; I</L>
<L>Scorne to kill him, but I'l hang his knighthood,</L>
<L><PB N="32" REF="18"/>
I warrant him, if he offer assault and battry on</L>
<L>My purse▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, good Sir, put up your sword.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Speed.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have confinde him prisoner forever,</L>
<L>I hope your experience sees hee's a harmelesse thing.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter George the Factor.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>G<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, heres young Master <HI>Foster</HI> requests</L>
<L>To speake with you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Does he? Prethee request him. Gentlemen,</L>
<L>Please you taste the sweetenesse of my Garden</L>
<L>A while, and let my daughter beare you company.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Speed.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where she is leader, there will be followers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>You send me to the Gallyes, Sir; pray you redeeme</L>
<L>Me as soone as you can; these are pretty</L>
<L>Things for mirth, but not for serious uses.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prethee be merry with them then a while,</L>
<L>If but for curtesie; thou hast wit enough;</L>
<L>But take heede they quarrell not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay I dare take in hand to part'm without</L>
<L>Any danger; but I beseech you let me not</L>
<L>Be too long a prisoner. Will you walke Gentlemen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>If it please you to place one of us for your conduct,</L>
<L>Otherwise this old Coxcombe and I shall quarrell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir <HI>Godfry,</HI> you are the eldest; pray lead the way.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Speed.</SPEAKER>
<L>Withall my heart, sweet Virgin; Ah, ha; this place</L>
<L>Promises well in the eyes of experience; Master</L>
<L><HI>Innocent,</HI> come you behinde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Right Sir; but I put the Gentlewoman before, and that</L>
<L>Is the thing I desire</L>
<L>And there your experience halts a little.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Speed.</SPEAKER>
<L>When I looke backe, Sir, I see your nose behinde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then when I looke backe, your nose stands here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Speed.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweet Lady, follow experience,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>And let observation follow you.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>So, now request you Master <HI>Foster</HI> in, <HI>George;</HI> but hark;</L>
<L>Does that newes hold his owne still, that our ships</L>
<L>Are so neare returne, as laden on the Downes</L>
<L><PB N="33" REF="18"/>
With such a wealthy fraughtage.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes Sir, and the next Tide purpose to put into the River:</L>
<L>Master <HI>Foster,</HI> your partner, hath now receiv'd more</L>
<L>Such intelligence, with most of the particulars</L>
<L>Of your merchandize, your venture is return'd</L>
<L>With trebble blessing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let him be ever blest that sent. <HI>George</HI> now call</L>
<L>In the young man; and hearke yee, <HI>George,</HI> from him</L>
<L>Run to my Partner, and request him to me, this</L>
<L>Newes I'm sure makes him a joyfull Merchant;</L>
<L>For my owne part, I'l not forget my vow,</L>
<STAGE>Ex. Ge<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</STAGE>
<L>This free addition heaven hath lent my state,</L>
<L>As freely backe to heaven I'l dedicate.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Robert Foster.</STAGE>
<L>I marry Sir, would this were a third Sutor</L>
<L>To my daughter <HI>Iane,</HI> I should better</L>
<L>Like him than all that's come yet. Now master <HI>Foster,</HI></L>
<L>Are your father annd your selfe yet reconcil'd?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, 'twas my businesse in your courteous tongue</L>
<L>To put the arbitration, I have againe</L>
<L>(Discover'd by my mother) reliev'd my poore Vncle,</L>
<L>Whose anger now so great is multiplyed,</L>
<L>I dare not venter in the eye of either,</L>
<L>Till your perswasions with faire excuse</L>
<L>Have made my satisfaction.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mother a pearle, Sir, 'tis a shrewd taske;</L>
<L>Yet I'l doe my best; your father hath so good newes,</L>
<L>That I hope't will be a faire motive too't;</L>
<L>But womens tongues are dangerous stumbling blocks</L>
<STAGE>Enter George.</STAGE>
<L>To lye in the way of peace. Now <HI>George.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Master <HI>Foster's</HI> comming, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>I beseech you Sir, let not me see him, till you</L>
<L>Have confer'd with him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, well, e'r your returne to Master <HI>Foster,</HI> call my</L>
<L>Daughter forth of the garden.</L>
<STAGE>Ex. George.</STAGE>
<L>And how does your Vncle, Master <HI>Foster?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="34" REF="19"/>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, so well, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></L>
<L>Same that shortly will o're-spread <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 words" DISP="〈◊◊〉"/> good fortunes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why I commend thee still,</L>
<L>He wants no good from thee, no not in report:</L>
<L>▪Tis well done Sir, and you shew duty in't.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Iane.</STAGE>
<L>Now daughter, Where are your Iusty Suitors?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>I was glad of my release, Sir: Suitors call you'm,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> keepe dish water continually boyling, but I'd</L>
<L>Seeth such Suitors; I have had much adoe to</L>
<L>Keepe'm from bloodshed; I have seene for all</L>
<L>The world, a couple of cowardly Curs quarrell</L>
<L>In that fashion, as t'one turnes his head, the</L>
<L>Other snaps behind; and as he turnes, his</L>
<L>Mouth recoyles againe: but I thanke my paines</L>
<L>For't, I have leagu'd with'm for a weeke without</L>
<L>Any farther entercourse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well daughter, well; say a third trouble come;</L>
<L>Say in the person of young Master <HI>Foster</HI> here</L>
<L>Came a third Suitor: how then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>Three's the womans totall Arithmeticke in</L>
<L>Deede, I would learne to number no farther,</L>
<L>If there was a good account made of that.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>I can instruct you so far, sweet Beauty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take heede, Sir; I have had ill handfell to day;</L>
<L>Perhaps 'tis not the fortunate season, you were</L>
<L>Best adjourne your journey to some happier time.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>There shall no Augurisme fright my plaine</L>
<L>Dealing: Sweete, I feare no houres.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>You'l not betray me with love-powder</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor with Gun-powder neither ifaith; yet I'l</L>
<L>Make you yeeld if I can.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe, get you together; your father will be comming;</L>
<L>Leave me with your suite to him, ply this your selfe;</L>
<L>And <HI>Iane,</HI> use him kindly, he shall be his</L>
<L>Fathers heire I can tell you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>Never the more for that, Father; If I use him</L>
<L><PB N="35" REF="19"/>
Kindely, it shalbe forsomething I like in him.</L>
<L>Selfe, and not for any good he borrowes of his father,</L>
<L>But come Sir, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>alke into the Garden; for</L>
<L>That's the field I have best fortune to overcome</L>
<L>My Suitors in.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>I feare not that fate neither, but if I walke</L>
<L>Into your Garden, I shall be tasting your sweetes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>Taste sweetely and welcome Sir; for there growes</L>
<L>Honesty, I can tell you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall be plucking at your honesty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>By my honesty but you shall not Sir: I'l hold</L>
<L>You a hand full of Penny-royall of that y'faith,</L>
<L>If you touch my honesty there, I'l make you eate</L>
<L>Sorrill to your supper, though I eate Sullenwood my selfe:</L>
<L>No Sir, gather first Time and Sage, and such wholsome</L>
<L>Hearbes; and Honesty and Hearts-ease will ripen</L>
<L>The whil'st.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have faire Roses, have you not?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes Sir, Roses; but no Gillyflowers.</L>
<STAGE>Ex. Ambo.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Master Foster and his Wife.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe, goe, and rest on <HI>Uenus</HI> Violets; shew he<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>A dozin of Batchelors Butto<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> Boy; Here comes</L>
<L>His father. Now my kind Partner, have we</L>
<L>Good newes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, in a word, take it; Your full lading and venture</L>
<L>Is return'd at sixty fold encrease.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heaven take the glory; A wondrous blessing;</L>
<L>Oh keepe us strong against these flowing Tides!</L>
<L>Man is too weak to bound himselfe below,</L>
<L>When such high waves doe mount him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>O Sir, care and ambition seldome meete,</L>
<L>Let us be thrifty; Titles will faster come,</L>
<L>Than we shall wish to have them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith I desire none.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why Sir, if so you please, I'lease your cares;</L>
<L>Shall I like a full adventurer now bid you</L>
<L>A certaine ready sum for your halfe traffique.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="36" REF="20"/>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, and I'd make you gainer by it too;</L>
<L>For then would I lay by my trouble, and begin</L>
<L>A worke which I have promis'd unto heaven,</L>
<L>A house, a <HI>Domus Dei</HI> shall be rays'd,</L>
<L>Which shall to Doomesday be establish'd for succour to</L>
<L>The poore; for in all Ages there must be such.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall I bid your venture at a venter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray you doe Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Twenty thousand pounds.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, then you under-rate your owne value much;</L>
<L>Will you make it thirty?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall I meete you halfe way?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<P>I meete you there Sir; for five and twenty thousand <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>nds the full ventures yours.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<P>If you like my payment, 'tis the one halfe in ready Cash, the other seal'd for six Monethes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis Merchant like and faire; <HI>George,</HI> you</L>
<L>Observe this? Let the contents be drawne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geo.</SPEAKER>
<L>They shall Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your hazard is now all past, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>I rejoyce at it, Sir, and shall not grudge your gaines,</L>
<L>Though multiplyed to thousands.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<P>Beleeve me Sir, I account my selfe a large Gainer by you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Much good may it be to you, Sir; but one</L>
<L>Thing at this advantage of my love to you</L>
<L>Let me entreate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>What is it, Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith my old fuite, to reconcile those breaches</L>
<L>Twist your kinde son and you; Let not the love</L>
<L>He shewes unto his Vncle, be any more a bar</L>
<L>To sunder your blessings and his duty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would you had enjoyn'd me some great labour</L>
<L>Far your owne loves sake, but to that my</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> stands fixt against; I'm deafe,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="3 words" DISP="〈◊◊◊〉"/> of them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>y, Sir, if you knew all, you would not waste your</L>
<L><PB N="37" REF="20"/>
Words in so vaine expence: since his last</L>
<L>Reformation, he has flowne out againe,</L>
<L>And in my sight relieved his Vncle in the</L>
<L>Dicing house; for which, either he shalbe no</L>
<L>Father to him, or no husband to me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well Sir, go call my Daughter forth of the</L>
<L>Garden, and bid her bring her Friend along</L>
<L>With her, troth Sir, I must not leave you thus;</L>
<L>I must needes make him your son againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, I have no such thing a kin to me.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Robin and Iane.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Looke you Sir, know you this duty?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not I Sir: hee's a stranger to me: Save your</L>
<L>Knee, I have no blessing for you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe, goe to your Vncle Sir; you know where to</L>
<L>Finde him, hee's at his old haunt, he wants</L>
<L>More money by this time; but I thinke the</L>
<L>Conduite pipe is stopt from whence it ran.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did he not say, hee'd beg for you, you'd best</L>
<L>Make use of's bounty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, good Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, if your daughter cast any eye of favour upon</L>
<L>This Vnthrift restraint, hee's a beggar: Mistris</L>
<L><HI>Iane,</HI> take heede what you doe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, I, be wise Mistris <HI>Iane;</HI> doe not you trust</L>
<L>To spleene and time worne to pitty, you'l</L>
<L>Not finde it so; therefore good Gentlewoman</L>
<L>Take heede.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay then you are too impenitrable.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, your money shall be ready, and your bills;</L>
<L>Other businesse I have none: For thee,</L>
<L>Beg, hang, dye like a slave;</L>
<L>Such blessings ever thou from me shalt have.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ex. Foster and his wife.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well Sir, I'l follow you; and Sir, be comforted,</L>
<L>I will not leave till I finde some remorse;</L>
<L>Meane time let not want trouble you;</L>
<L><PB N="38" REF="21"/>
You shall not know it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Su, 'tis not want I feare, but want of blessing</L>
<L>My knee was bent for; for mine Vncles state,</L>
<L>Which now I dare say out-weighes my fathersfarre,</L>
<L>Confirmes my hopes as rich, as with my fathers,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> love excepted onely.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy Vncles state, how for heavens love.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>By his late marriage to the wealthiest widow</L>
<L>That London had, who has not onely made him</L>
<L>Lord of her selfe, but of her whole estate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mother-a-pearle, I rejoyce in't: this newes</L>
<L>Is yet but young?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fame will soone speake it loud, Sir</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>This may helpe happily to make all peace;</L>
<L>But how have you parly'd with my daughter, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>Very well Father: We spake something, but did</L>
<L>Nothing at all; I requested him to pull me</L>
<L>A Catherin Peare, and had not I lookt to him</L>
<L>He would have mistooke and given me a Popperrin;</L>
<L>And to requite his kindenesse, I pluck'd him a Rose,</L>
<L>And he had almost prick'd my finger for my paines.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well said Wag, are there sparkes kindled, quench</L>
<L>'M not for me, 'tis not a fathers roughnesse,</L>
<L>Nor doubtfull hazard of an Vncles kindenesse</L>
<L>Can me deterre; I must to your father.</L>
<L>Where (as a chiefe affaire) I'l once more moue,</L>
<L>And if I can returne him backe to love.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Doctor and Stephens Wife.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, you see I have made a speedy choyse,</L>
<L>And as swift a marriage; be it as it will,</L>
<L>I like the man, if his qualities afflict me,</L>
<L>I shall be happy in't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must not distate, what I have help'd to make;</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> I that joyn'd you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>A good bargaine, I hope.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Roger.</STAGE>
<L><HI>Roger,</HI> Where's your Master?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="39" REF="21"/>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Good man of the house is within forsooth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not your Master, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis hard of digestion: Yes, my Master is within;</L>
<L>Hee masters you therefore I must be</L>
<L>Content: You have long'd for Crosses a good</L>
<L>While, and now you are like to be</L>
<L>Farther off them than e'r you were; For</L>
<L>I'm affraid, your good husband will leave</L>
<L>You ne'r a crosse i'th' house to blesse you with.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well Sir, I shall be blest in't: But where is he?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where he has mistaken the place a little,</L>
<L>Being his wedding-day; he is in <HI>nomine,</HI></L>
<L>When he should be in <HI>re.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>And where's that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>In your Counting-house; If he were a kinde</L>
<L>Husband, he would have bin in another</L>
<L>Counting-house by this time: hee's tumbling</L>
<L>Over all his money bags yonder; you shall</L>
<L>Heare of him in the bowling Alley againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why Sir, all is his, and at his</L>
<L>Dispose; who shall dare to twhart him?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Stephen with bills and bonds.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Looke where he comes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now, Sweete-heart? what hast thou there?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>I finde much debts belonging to you, Sweete;</L>
<L>And my care must be now to fetch them in;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, ha; prethee doe not mistake thy selfe,</L>
<L>Nor my true purpose; I did not wed to thrall,</L>
<L>Or binde thy large expence, but rather to adde</L>
<L>A plenty to that liberty; I thought by this,</L>
<L>Thou would'st have stuft thy pockets full of Gold,</L>
<L>And throwne it at a hazard; made Ducks and Drakes,</L>
<L>And baited fishes with thy silver flyes;</L>
<L>Lost, and fetcht more: why this had bin my joy;</L>
<L>Perhaps at length thou would'st have wast'd</L>
<L>My store; why, this had bin a blessing to</L>
<L>Good for me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="40" REF="22"/>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>Content thee, Sweete, those daies are gone,</L>
<L>I, even from my memorie;</L>
<L>I have forgot that e'r I had such follies,</L>
<L>And I'l not call 'm backe: my eares are bent</L>
<L>To keepe your state, and give you all content.</L>
<L><HI>Roger,</HI> goe, call your fellow-servants up to me,</L>
<L>And to my Chamber bring all bookes of debt;</L>
<L>I will o're-looke, and cast up all accounts,</L>
<L>That I may know the weight of all my cares,</L>
<L>And once a yeere give up my stewardship.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now you may see what hastie matching is;</L>
<L>You had thought to have bin vext, and now</L>
<L>You cannot: You have marryed a husband,</L>
<L>That, Sir reverence of the title, now being my Master in law,</L>
<L>I doe thinke hee'l proove the miserablest, covetous</L>
<L>Rascall, that ever beate beggar from his gate. But</L>
<L>'Tis no matter; time was when you were fairely</L>
<L>Offered, if you would have tooke it; you might have had</L>
<L>Other matches y'faith, if it had pleas'd you; and those</L>
<L>That would have crost you; I would have sold away</L>
<L>All that ever you had had; have kept two or three</L>
<L>Whores at liverie under your nose; have turn'd you out</L>
<L>In your smocke, and have us'd you like a woman; where</L>
<L>As now, if you'd hang your selfe, you can have none of</L>
<L>These blessings: but 'tis well enough, now you must</L>
<L>Take what followes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'm new to seeke for crosses, the hopes I meant</L>
<L>Turne to despaire, and smoother in content.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Robert.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>O Nephew are you come: The welcom'st wish</L>
<L>That my heart has; This is my hinsman, Sweete.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let him be largely texted in your love,</L>
<L>That all the Citty may reade it fairely;</L>
<L>You cannot remember me, and him forget.</L>
<L>We were alike to you in poverty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>I should have beg'd that bounty of your love,</L>
<L>Though you had scanted me to have given't him;</L>
<L><PB N="41" REF="22"/>
For we are one, I an Vncle Nephew,</L>
<L>He an Nephew Vncle, but my Sweete selfe,</L>
<L>My slow request you have anticipated</L>
<L>With proffer'd kindenesse; and I thanke you for it.</L>
<L>But how, kinde Cozin, does your father use you?</L>
<L>Is your name found againe within his bookes?</L>
<L>Can he reade son there?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis now blotted quite: for by the violent instigation</L>
<L>Of my cruell Stepmother, his Vowes and Othes</L>
<L>Are stampt against me, ne'r to acknowledge me,</L>
<L>Ne'r to call, or blesse me as a childe;</L>
<L>But in his brow, his bounty, and behaviour</L>
<L>I reade it almost plainelie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cozin, grieve not at it; that father lost at home,</L>
<L>You shall finde here; and with the losse of his inheritance,</L>
<L>You meete another amply profferd you;</L>
<L>Be my adopted son, no more my kinsman;</L>
<L>So that this borrowed bounty doe not stray</L>
<L>From your consent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>Call it not borrowed, Sir, 'tis all your owne;</L>
<L>Here 'fore this reverent man I make it knowne,</L>
<L>Thou art our childe as free by adoption,</L>
<L>As deriv'd from us by conception, birth, and</L>
<L>Propinquitie; Inheritour to our full substance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>You were borne to blesse us both,</L>
<L>My knee shall practise a sons duty</L>
<L>Even beneath sons, giving you all</L>
<L>The comely dues of parents: yet not</L>
<L>Forgetting my duty to my father;</L>
<L>Where e'r I meet him, he shall have my knee,</L>
<L>Although his blessing ne'r returne to me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come then my dearest son, I'l now give thee</L>
<L>A taste of my love to thee; be thou my deputy,</L>
<L>The Factour and disposer of my businesse;</L>
<L>Keepe my accounts, and order my affaires;</L>
<L>They must be all your owne; for you, deere Sweet,</L>
<L>Be merry, take your pleasure, at home, abroad;</L>
<L><PB N="42" REF="23"/>
Visit your neighbours; ought that may seeme good</L>
<L>To your owne will, downe to the Country ride;</L>
<L>For cares and troubles lay them all aside,</L>
<L>And I will take them up, it's fit that weight</L>
<L>Should now lye all on me: take thou the height</L>
<L>Of quiet and content, let nothing grieve thee;</L>
<L>I brought thee nothing else, and that I'le give thee.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ex. Stephen and Robin.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will the Tide never turne? Was ever woman</L>
<L>Thus burden'd with unhappy happinesse?</L>
<L>Did I from Ryot take him, to waste my goods,</L>
<L>And he strives to augment it? I did mistake him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<L>Spoyle not a good Text with a false Comment;</L>
<L>All these are blessings, and from heaven sent;</L>
<L>It is your husbands good, hee's now transform'd</L>
<L>To a better shade, the prodigall's return'd.</L>
<L>Come, come, know joy, make not abundance scant;</L>
<L>You 'plaine of that which thousand women want.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Alderman Bruine, Master Foster and Factors bearing or bags.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>So, so, haste home good Lads, and returne for the rest.</L>
<L>Would they were cover'd, <HI>George,</HI> 'tis too Publicke</L>
<L>Blazon of my estate; but 'tis no matter now;</L>
<L>I'l bring it abroad againe e'r it belong.</L>
<L>Sir, I acknowledge receit of my still halfe debt,</L>
<L>Twelve thousand five hundred pounds; it now remaines</L>
<L>You seale those writings, as assurance for the rest,</L>
<L>And I am satisfyed for this time.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray stay Sir, I have bethought me, let me once</L>
<L>Throw Dice at all, and either be a compleate</L>
<L>Merchant, or wracke my estate for ever:</L>
<L>Heare me Sir, I have of wares that are now vendible,</L>
<L>So much as will defray your utmost penny;</L>
<L>Will you accept of them, and save this charge</L>
<L>Of wax and parchment.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>He they vendible Sir? I am your Chapman:</L>
<L>What are they, Master <HI>Foster?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="43" REF="23"/>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Broad clothes, Karsies, Cutchineale, such</L>
<L>As will not stay two dayes upon your hands.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>I finde your purpose; you'd have your Ware.</L>
<L>Houses empty for the receit of your full fraught;</L>
<L>I'l be your furtherer, make so your rates, that</L>
<L>I may be no looser.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter George and Richard.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have no other end, Sir; let our</L>
<L>Factors peruse and deale for both.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mine is return'd; <HI>George,</HI> here's a new businesse,</L>
<L>You and <HI>Richard</HI> must deale for some commodities</L>
<L>Betwixt us, if you finde 'm even gaine or but</L>
<L>Little losse, take carriage presently and carry 'm home.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Richard,</HI> have you any further newes yet from our shipping?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ric.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not yet, Sir; but by account from the last, when they</L>
<L>Put from Dover, this Tide should bring them into</L>
<L>Saint <HI>Catharins</HI> Poole; the winde has bin friendly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O, Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Listen their arrivall, and bid the Gunner speake it</L>
<L>In his lowd thunder all the Citty over;</L>
<L>Tingle the Merchants eares at the report</L>
<L>Of my abundant wealth; now goe with <HI>George.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rich.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall doe both, Sir.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt Factors.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<P>I must plainely now confesse, Master Alderman, I shall gaine much by you. The halfe of your Ship defrayes my full cost.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<P>Beshrew me if I grudge it, being my selfe a Sufficient gainer by my venter, Sir.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Mistris Foster.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Still flowes the Tide of my unhappinesse,</L>
<L>The stars shoote mischiefe, and every houre</L>
<L>Is criticall to me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<P>How now woman? wrackt in the heaven of felici∣ty?</P>
<L>What ayl'st thou?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thinke the divel's mine enemy</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="44" REF="24"/>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hope so too; his hate is better than his friendship.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your brother, your goodbrother, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>What of him? hee's in Ludgate againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, hee's in Hye-gate; he struts it bravely,</L>
<L>An Aldermans pace at least.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O, Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, these are Oracles, doubtfull Enigmaes!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, I'm sure you have heard the newes;</L>
<L>Hee's marryed forsooth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<P>How, marryed? no woman of repute would choose So slightly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>A woman, in whose brest, I had thought had liv'd</L>
<L>The very quintessence of discretion; and who is't,</L>
<L>Thinke you? nay you cannot ghesse, though I should give</L>
<L>You a day to riddle it; 'tis my Gossip, Man, the rich</L>
<L>Widdow of Cornehill.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fye, fye, 'tis fabulous.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you my husband? then is shee his wife;</L>
<L>How will this upstart beggar shoulder up,</L>
<L>And take the wall of you? his new found pride</L>
<L>Will know no eldership.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>But wife, my wealth will five times double his, e'r</L>
<L>This Tide ebbe againe; I wonder I heare not the</L>
<L>Brazen Cannon proclame the Arrivall of my</L>
<L>Infinite substance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<P>But beggars will be proud of little, and shoulder at the best.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let him first pay his old score, and then reckon;</L>
<L>But that shee:—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, that's it mads me too.</L>
<L>Would any woman, lesse to spite her selfe,</L>
<L>So much prophane the sacred name of wedlock:</L>
<L>A Dove to couple with a Storke, or a Lambe a Viper?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Content thee; Forgive her; shee'l doe so no more;</L>
<L>She was a rich widdow, a wife hee'l make her poore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>So Sir, you have clos'd it well; if so ill it prove,</L>
<L>Leave it to proofe, and wish not misery</L>
<STAGE>Enter Stephen and Robert.</STAGE>
<L><PB N="45" REF="24"/>
Vnto your enemy looke, here he comes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>You say true 'tis my enemy indeede.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<P>Save you Master Alderman, I have some businesse with you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>With me, Sir, and most welcome, I rejoyce to see you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe you observe, Sir; he will not know you now?</L>
<L><HI>Iockeye's</HI> a Gentleman now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well fare rich widowes, when such beggars flourish;</L>
<L>But ill shall they fare, that florish o're such beggars.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, ha, ha.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>He laughes at you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>No wonder, woman, he would doe that in Ludgate;</L>
<L>But 'twas when his kind Nephew did relieve him:</L>
<L>I shall heare him cry there againe shortly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oysters, new Walfleet Oysters.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Gentleman is merry.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, no, no; he does this to spight me; as who Should say, I had bin a fish-wife in my younger dayes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fye, fye, Gentlemen, this is not well;</L>
<L>My eares are guilty to heare such discords.</L>
<L>Looke, Master <HI>Foster;</HI> turne your eye that way;</L>
<L>There's duty unregarded, while envy struts</L>
<L>In too much state: believe me, Gentlemen,</L>
<L>I know not which to chide first.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>What Idoll kneeles that heritique too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rise Boy; thou art now my son, and owest no knee</L>
<L>To that unnaturall; I charge you rise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe Sir, or turne your adoration that way;</L>
<L>You were kind to him in his tarter'd state;</L>
<L>Let him requite it now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe, doe, we have pai'd for't aforehand,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>I would I were devided in two halfes, so that Might reconcile your harsh devision</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>Proud Sir, this son which you have alienated</L>
<L>For my loves sake, shall by my loves bounty</L>
<L>Ride side by fide in the best Equipage</L>
<L>Your scornes dare patterne him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="46" REF="25"/>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, I, a beggars gallop up and downe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, 'tis up now, the next step downe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha, ha, I laugh at your envy Sir, my businesse <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s to you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good Sir, speake of any thing but this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, I am furnishing some shipping forth,</L>
<L>And want some English traffique, Broad-clothes, Karsics</L>
<L>Or such like, my voyage is to the Straites:</L>
<L>If you can supply me, Sir, I'l be your Chapman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>That I shall soone resolve you, Sir;</L>
<STAGE>Enter Factors.</STAGE>
<L>Come hither <HI>George.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is the rich Merchant-man;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's neither grave not wife;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who will kill a man at Tiburne shortly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>By Carts that may arise; Or if the hangman dye,</L>
<L>He may have his office.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then you have bargain'd, <HI>George.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geo.</SPEAKER>
<L>And the Warecarryed home, Sir; you must looke</L>
<L>To be little gainer; but lose you cannot.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis all I desire from thence, Sir I can furnish you</L>
<L>With Wares I lately from your brother bought;</L>
<L>Please you goe see them, for I would faine divide you,</L>
<L>Since I can win no nearer friendship.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'l goe with you, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Alderman, Stephen and George.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take your adoption with you, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>I crave but your blessing with me, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis my curse then; get thee out of mine eye.</L>
<L>Th'art a bcame in't, and I'le teare it out e'r it</L>
<L>Offend to looke on thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe, goe, Sir; follow your Vncle-father,</L>
<L>Helpe him to spend, what thrift has got together;</L>
<L>'Twilbe charity in you to spend,</L>
<L>Because your charity it was to lend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>My charity; you can a vertue name.</L>
<L>And teach the use, yet never knew the same</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB N="47" REF="25"/>
Enter Richard.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>See wife, here comes <HI>Richard.</HI></L>
<L>Now listen, and heare me crown'd</L>
<L>The wealthiest London Merchant.</L>
<L>Why dost thou looke so sadly?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why dost not speake; hast lost thy tongue?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rich.</SPEAKER>
<L>I never could speake worse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, thy voyce is good enough.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ric.</SPEAKER>
<L>But the worst accent Sir, that ever you heard,</L>
<L>I speake a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Screechowles note. Oh you have made</L>
<L>The most unhappiest bargaine that ever Merchant did!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha? what can so balefull be, as thou would'st <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></L>
<L>To make by this sad prologue? I am no traytor</L>
<L>To consiscate my goods: speake, what e'r it be.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ric.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would you could conceite it, that I might not speake it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dally not with torments, sinke me at once.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ric.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now y'ave spoke it halfe; 'tis sinking I must treate of</L>
<L>Your ships are all sinke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hah!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<P>O thou fatall Raven; Let me pull thine eyes out for this</P>
<L>Sad croake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold woman; hold prethee; 'tis none of his fauk.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, no, 'tis thine, thou wretch; and therefore</L>
<L>Let me turne my vengeance all on thee; thou</L>
<L>Hast made hot haste to empty all my Ware-houses,</L>
<L>And made roome for that the sea hath drunk before</L>
<L>Thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vndone for ever! Where could this mischiefe fail▪</L>
<L>Were not my ships in their full pride at Dover;</L>
<L>And what English <HI>Carybda's</HI> has the divell dig'd</L>
<L>To swallow nearer home.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ric.</SPEAKER>
<L>Even in the Mouth, and entrance of the <HI>Thames</HI></L>
<L>They were all cast away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dam up thy Mouth from any farther</L>
<L>Mischievous relation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rich.</SPEAKER>
<L>Some men were sav'd, but not one penny-worth of goods.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="48" REF="26"/>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Even now thy balefull utterance was chok'd,</L>
<L>And now it runs too fast; thou fatall Bird no more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>May Serpents breed, and fill this fatall Streame,</L>
<L>And poyson her for ever.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>O curse not, they come too fast!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me curse somewhere, Wretch, or else I'l throw</L>
<L>That all on thee; 'tis thou, ungodly Slave,</L>
<L>That art the marke unto the wrath of Heaven:</L>
<L>I thriv'd e'r I knew thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>I prethee split me too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would I could; I would I had never seene thee;</L>
<L>For I ne'r saw houre of comfort since I knew thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vndone for ever, my credit I have crackt,</L>
<L>To buy a Venture, which the Sea has sok'd;</L>
<L>What worse can woe report.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes worse than all,</L>
<L>Thy enemies will laugh, and scorne thy fall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be it the worst then; that place I did assigne</L>
<L>My unthrifty brother, Ludgate, must now be mine.</L>
<L>Breake, and take Ludgate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take Newgate rather.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>I scorn'd my child, now he may scorne his father.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Scorne him still.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will; would he my wants relieve,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> scorne to take what he would yeeld to give:</L>
<L>My heart be still my friend, although no other;</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> scorn the helpe of either son, or brother,</L>
<L>My portion's begging now; seldome before.</L>
<L>In one sad houre, was man so rich and poore.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="4" TYPE="act">
<PB N="49" REF="26"/>
<HEAD>Actus Quartus.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Mistris Iane, Godfry Speedewell, and Master Lambskin.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>GEntlemen, my Father's not within; please</L>
<L>You to walke a turne or two in the garden,</L>
<L>Hee'l not be long.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lamb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your father, Mistris <HI>Iane,</HI> I hope you have observa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> in you,</P>
<L>And know our humours; we come not a wooing to your Father.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Speed.</SPEAKER>
<P>Experience must beare with folly; Thou art all inno∣cent,</P>
<L>And thy name is <HI>Lambskin;</HI> grave Sapience guides me,</L>
<L>And I care not a pin for thy squibs, and thy Crackers,</L>
<L>My old dry wood shall make a lusty bonefire, when</L>
<L>Thy greene Chips shall lye hissing in the Chimney-</L>
<L>Corner. Remember Mistris, I can make you a Lady by</L>
<L>Mine owne experience.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prethee doe not stand troubling the Gentlewoman</L>
<L>With thy musty sentences, but let her love be laid</L>
<L>Downe betwixt us like a paire of Cudgells, and into</L>
<L>Whose hands she thrusts the weapons first, let him</L>
<L>Take up the Bucklers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Speed.</SPEAKER>
<L>A match betweene us</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>Must I be stickler then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are both to run at the Ring of your setting</L>
<L>Vp, and you must tell us who deserves most favour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>But will you stand both at my disposing?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Else let me never stand but in a Pillory.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>You love me both you say?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Speed.</SPEAKER>
<L>By this hand.—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hand? Zoundes by the foure and twenty Elements.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="50" REF="27"/>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray spare your oathes; I doe believe you doe</L>
<L>You would not else make all this stir to wooe.</L>
<L>Sir <HI>Godfry,</HI> you are a knight both tough and old,</L>
<L>A rotten building cannot long time hold.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lamb.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Speedewell,</HI> livewell, dye well, and be hang'd well.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> your coppy well, your experience will not carry it else.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'are rich too, at least your selfe so say;</L>
<L>What though? y'are but a gilded man of clay.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>A man of Ginger-bread; y'faith I could finde in</L>
<L>My heart to eate him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>Should I wed you, the fire with frost must marry</L>
<L><HI>Ianuary</HI> and <HI>May;</HI> I for a younger tarry.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's l; introth I'le be thy young <HI>Lambskin;</HI> thoushalt</L>
<L>Finde me as innocent as a sucking Dove: speake, Sweete</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, am I the youth in a basket?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane</SPEAKER>
<L>You are the sweete youth Sir, whose pretty eyes</L>
<L>Would make me love; but you must first be wise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Speede.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ah, hah, is your coxcombe cut? I see experience must</L>
<L>Boord this faire Pinnace: a word in private,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'l have no words in private, unlesse I heare too.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Master Bruine, Stephen and Robin.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come Gentlemen, we'l make few</L>
<L>Winds about it; Merchants in</L>
<L>Bargaining must not, like Souldiors lying at a siege, stay</L>
<L>Moneths, weekes, daies, but strike at the first parley.</L>
<L>Broad-clothes, and Woolls, and other rich Commodities, I</L>
<L>Lately from your brother bought, are all your owne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then be not angry gentle Sir,</L>
<L>If now a string be touch'd, which hath too long</L>
<L>Sounded so harshly over all the Citty;</L>
<L>I now would winde it to a musicall height.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good Master Alderman I thinke that string will still</L>
<L>Ostend mine eare; You meane the jarring</L>
<L>Twixt me and my brother?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>In troth the same.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hate no poyson like that brothers name</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>O Fye, not so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="51" REF="27"/>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vncivill churle, when all his sailes were up.</L>
<L>And that his proud heart danc'd on golden wayes:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>As heaven be thank'd it still does.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet Sir, then I being sunke, and drown'd in <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></L>
<L>Owne misery, he would not cast out a poore line</L>
<L>Of thred to bring me to the shore; I had bin</L>
<L>Dead, and might have starv'd for him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>A better fate Sir, stood at your elbow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>True Sir; this was he that lifted me from want</L>
<L>And misery, whose cruell father for that</L>
<L>Good cast him away; scorning his name and blood;</L>
<L>Lopt from his side this branch that held me deere.</L>
<L>For which hee's now my son, my joy, my heire,</L>
<L>But for his father hang him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fye, fye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>By heaven.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, come, live in more charity, he is your brother;</L>
<L>If that name offend, I'l sing that tune no more.</L>
<L>Yonder's my daughter busie with her suitors;</L>
<L>Wee'l visit them. Now <HI>Iane,</HI> bid your friends</L>
<L>Welcome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>They must be welcome Sir, that come with you;</L>
<L>To thee ten thousand welcomes still are due.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>My sweete Mistris.</L>
<STAGE>Kisse him.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lounds Sir knight, we have stood beating the Bush</L>
<L>And the bird's flowne away; this Citty</L>
<L>Bowler has kist the Mistris at first cast.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>How fare yee Gentlemen, what cheere Sir knight?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Speed.</SPEAKER>
<L>An adventurer still Sir, to this new found land.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lamb</SPEAKER>
<L>He sayles about the point Sir, but he cannot put in yet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>The winde may turne Sir. A word Master <HI>Foster.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>You see Sir <HI>Speedwell,</HI> what Card is turn'd</L>
<L>Vp for trumpe; I hold my life this spruce</L>
<L>Cittizen will forestall the market, Oh</L>
<L>These briske factors, are notable firkers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Speed.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doubt Sir, he will play the merchant with us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>They both are suitors Sir, yet both shoote wide;</L>
<L><PB N="52" REF="28"/>
My daughter sure must be your kinsmans bride.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'l give her a wedding Ring on that condition</L>
<L>And put a Stone in't worth a thousand pounde, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have my hand and heart too't, be she pleas'd so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lamb</SPEAKER>
<P>S'foote, let's shew our selves Gallants, or Gallymaw. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>yes:</P>
<L>Shall <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>y'd by a Cockney. A word</L>
<L>My <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 words" DISP="〈◊◊〉"/>; Doe you see Sir, here be those</L>
<L>That have gon a fishing, and can give you a</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L>You were best goe fish for better manners, or I</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> for <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>les with you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Zoundes are you a striker? Draw, Sir knight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not in my house; I pray be quiet Gentlemen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>He dares not doe't abroad believe me, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now by my life my Boy, for this brave spirit</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>g thee in mine armes: lose life and limbes</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> thou forsake thy love.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee's no Rivall here Sir; has struck me,</L>
<L>And we are Gentlemen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Speed.</SPEAKER>
<L>And heare yee, Sir, let him seeke out his equalls;</L>
<L>For some of us are in danger to make her</L>
<L>A Lady shortly: I know what I speake; what</L>
<L>I speake, I'l doe; yet I'l doe nothing, but</L>
<L>What comes from grave experience.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speake what you please Sir, hee's a Gentleman as</L>
<L>Good at either of you both, and shall in lists of</L>
<L>Love for such a bed-fellow, brave him that dares,</L>
<L>And here lay downe more gold to win her love,</L>
<L>Than both your states are worth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Speed.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha? doe you know us, Sir? You grow too bold;</L>
<L>My experience now hath found you;</L>
<L>You were once a tatter'd fellow, your name is</L>
<L><HI>Foster;</HI> have you such gold to give?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, yes, has won it betting at the bowling Alleyes,</L>
<L>O<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> at the Pigeon-holes in the Garden Alleyes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uddy Groomes to upbraid mee with that scorne,</L>
<L><PB N="53" REF="28"/>
Which vertue now gilds over; Pray yee Gentlemen</L>
<L>May I request your names.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our names are in the Heralds bookes I warrant you</L>
<L>My name is <HI>Innocent Lambskin;</HI> and this Knight,</L>
<L>Simply though he stands here, is knowne to be</L>
<L>Sir <HI>Godfry Speedewell.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Step.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well may he Speede Sir; <HI>Lambskin</HI> and <HI>Speedewell,</HI></L>
<L>Ha? Is't so? I thinke I shall give you a medicine</L>
<L>To purge this itch of love, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>No itch neither Sir, we have no scabs here,</L>
<L>But your selfe and your Cozin.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>Very good Sir, my little <HI>Lambskin.</HI> I have you</L>
<L>Here in Sheepeskin; looke you, 'tis so y'faith.</L>
<L>See, Master Alderman, these two crackt Gallants</L>
<L>Are in severall bonds to my Predecessor</L>
<L>For a debt of full two thousand apiece.</L>
<L>Cozin, fetch me a Serjeant straite.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Speed.</SPEAKER>
<L>O let him, I have a protection, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'l try that, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Speed.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Serjeant? Nay, then experience must worke,</L>
<L>Legs be strong and bold; when Serjeants waite</L>
<L>At feasts, the cheere's but cold.</L>
<L>I'l shift for one.</L>
<STAGE>Ex.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Knight, knight; S'foote if an errand Knight</L>
<L>Run away, I were an arrand Asse to tarry,</L>
<L>And be catch'd in the lime-bush: I love the</L>
<L>Wench well; but if they have no hole to</L>
<L>Place me in, but the hole in the Counter,</L>
<L>I'l be goue and leave'm; that's flat</L>
<STAGE>Ex.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have scar'd the suitors from the marke, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am glad on't Sir; they are but such as seeke</L>
<L>To build their rotten state on you, and with your</L>
<L>Wealth to underprop their weakenesse;</L>
<L>Believe me, reverend Sir, I had much rather</L>
<L>You'd venter that my Cuz might call you father.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Stephens Wife.</STAGE>
<SP>
<PB N="54" REF="29"/>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>We'l talke of that anon; See Sir,</L>
<L>Here comes your wife, the theame</L>
<STAGE>Ent. Stepen's Wife.</STAGE>
<L>Of all her <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e, with goodnesse mixt, the happy</L>
<L>Woman that was never vext; y'are welcome</L>
<L>M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>s <HI>Foller.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thanke yee Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wife, your two debtors were here but now;</L>
<STAGE>S. <HI>Speedwell</HI></STAGE>
<L>And <HI>Lambskin;</HI> A Wolfe could not have torne</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <HI>Lambskin</HI> worse, than the bare name</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Serjeant: the very thought made them both</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> take their heeles and run away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Las, they are poore and leane, and being so;</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> them not till they are fatter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>At thy girdle, Sweete, hangs the keyes, to</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> the prison dores or let them loose:</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 words" DISP="〈◊◊〉"/> my intent onely in way of mirth to</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> them from the presence of Mistris <HI>Iane,</HI></L>
<L>That our adopted son might have no bar</L>
<L>Vnto his love.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>The match is faire; and were that knot once tyed,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> send some Augels to attend the bride.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter George.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, here's your factor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are the wares ready.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, and deliver'd Sir, to Master <HI>Foster's</HI> servants,</L>
<L>Who conveyed them in Carts to the Custome.</L>
<L>House, there to be shipt; but going with them,</L>
<L>Sir, I met ill newes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ill newes? what ist?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Old Master <HI>Foster's</HI> ships so richly laden,</L>
<L>By strange misfortune, Sir, are cast away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now heaven forbid!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh mee!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>How? cast away; where?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis impossible; they rid at Dover safe,</L>
<L>When he out-bought my full share in the fraught,</L>
<L>And paid me downe neare thirty thousand pounds</L>
<L><PB N="55" REF="29"/>
In wares and money.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Which had he not done, you had lost your venture:</L>
<L>By Master <HI>Foster's</HI> owne appointment Sir, they weighed</L>
<L>Their Anchors up, and so to come for London;</L>
<L>But by a mercilesse storme they all were</L>
<L>Swallowed, even in the Theames mouth; yet</L>
<L>The men were sav'd, but all the goods were lost.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>O my poore father! This losse will breake his backe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha? What's that to you? if in my favour you'l</L>
<L>Sit warme, then bury all love to him,</L>
<L>Nay duty, heare you Sir? What shed'st thou teares</L>
<L>For him, that had no care to see thy heart drop</L>
<L>Blood? he was unnaturall, and heaven hath</L>
<L>Iustly now rewarded him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis a most strange Fate; he needes would buy my</L>
<L>Part at any rate, he car'd not what; and now all's lost,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>Greedy desire he swallowed, and now is swallowed:</L>
<L>'Tis but his hyre; and I'l not pitty it, no more</L>
<L>Than he, in his abundance, did my misery.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>I grieve for my poore Gossip, his good wife,</L>
<L>She never met good fortune all her life,</L>
<L>And this will breake her heart-strings:</L>
<L>In good sooth I'l goe and comfort her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>In good sooth you shall not,</L>
<L>Nor him, nor her at this time, gentle wife;</L>
<L>He scorn'd me in his height, now being poore,</L>
<L>If that he needes my helpe, he knowes my doore.</L>
<L>Sir, we'l for this time leave you, at fitter leasure,</L>
<L>We'l have this marriage talk't of.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>At your owne good pleasure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come wife; Goe not to see your father, Sir, I charge you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Iane,</HI> bring your friends toth'dore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'l helpe my father, though my selfe grow poore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where's my Factor?</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>What, are the square stones, and timber</L>
<L>Brought as I appointed?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="56" REF="30"/>
<SPEAKER>Geo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, Sir, and the workemen, that daily ply the</L>
<L>Worke, are in number fourescore at least.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>My vowes flew up to heaven, that I would make</L>
<L>Some pious worke in the brasse booke of Fame,</L>
<L>That might till Doo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>esday lengthen out my name.</L>
<L>Neare Norton Folga<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e therefore have I bought</L>
<L>Ground to erect this house, which I will call</L>
<L>And dedicate, <HI>Sa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>t Marie's Hospitall;</HI></L>
<L>And when 'tis finish'd, o'r the gates shall stand</L>
<L>In capitall letters, these words fairely graven</L>
<L>For I have given the worke and house to heaven</L>
<L>And cal'd it, <HI>Domus Dei,</HI> Gods house;</L>
<L>For in my zealous faith I know full well,</L>
<L>Where good deedes are, there heaven it selfe doth dwell.</L>
<STAGE>Ex.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Old Foster, Richard his factor, and the Keeper of Ludgate</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rich.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good Sir, resolve not thus; returne againe,</L>
<L>Your debts are not so great, that you should yeeld</L>
<L>Your body thus to prison unconstrain'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will not trust the iron hearts of men;</L>
<L>My credit's lost, my wealth the Sea has swallowed,</L>
<L>Wrack'd at my dore, even in the mouth o'th'Thames.</L>
<L>Oh my misfortune! never man like me</L>
<L>Was so throwne downe, and cast to misery.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rich.</SPEAKER>
<L>Deare Sir, be patient.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>I prethee get thee gone, and with thy diligence</L>
<L>Assist thy Mistris to keepe that little left, to</L>
<L>Helpe her selfe, whil'st here in Ludgate I secure</L>
<L>My body from Writs, Arrests, and Executions,</L>
<L>Which, well I know, my cruell Creditors will</L>
<L>Thunder on me. Goe, get thee gone; if what</L>
<L>Is left they'l take, doe thou agree;</L>
<L>If not, I am here resolv'd to stay and dye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rich.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'l doe my best Sir, to procure your peace.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do so, Come Sir, I yeeld my selfe your prisoner,</L>
<L>You are the Keeper of this Ludgate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Keep.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes Sir, your name is registred among the prisoners.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>So, I have seene the faire outside of this tombe before;</L>
<L><PB N="57" REF="30"/>
This goodly apple has a rotten core.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Keep.</SPEAKER>
<L>As all prisons have, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>I prethee bar me of no priviledge due to a free</L>
<L>Citizen; Thou knowest me well?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Keep.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes Master <HI>Foster,</HI> and I sorrow for your losses,</L>
<L>Yet doubt not but your son and brother.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>O speake not of them! doe not kisse and kill me:</L>
<L>I have no son nor brother that esteemes me,</L>
<L>And I for ever hate their memory:</L>
<L>Prethee no more; I am come sicke into a</L>
<L>Bad Inne, and looke for worse attendance,</L>
<L>I have taken a surfeit of misfortunes, and here</L>
<L>Must swallow pills</L>
<L>With poyson to recure me: I am sea-sicke, Sir,</L>
<L>And heave my hands to heaven; ne'r to so</L>
<L>Low an ebbe was <HI>Foster</HI> driven.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Keep.</SPEAKER>
<L>There be some Fees to pay, Sir, at your comming in.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>So, so, if this old Wall-nut-tree, after all this</L>
<L>Cudgelling, have but one cluster left, thou shalt</L>
<L>Have that too; if not, take off these leaves that</L>
<L>Cover me; pull off these white locks; rend them from</L>
<L>My head, and let me in my woes be buried.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Keep.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Las, Sir, this house is poore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thinke no lesse;</L>
<L>For rich men seldome meete with such distresse,</L>
<L>Well, well, what booke must I reade over now?</L>
<L>What servile Oare must I be tyed to here,</L>
<L>Slave-like to tug within this christian Galley?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Keep.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, being the youngest prisoner in the house,</L>
<L>You must beg at the iron grate above,</L>
<L>As others doe for your reliefe and their's.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>For a beggar to beg, Sir, is no shame;</L>
<L>And for the iron grate, it beares an embleme</L>
<L>O firon-hearted Creditors, that force men lye</L>
<L>In loathsome prisons thus to starve and die.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Robert and kneeles.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Keep.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who would you speake with, Sir?</L>
<L><PB N="58" REF="31"/>
Oh, cry you mercy; 'tis his sonne:</L>
<L>I'l leave them.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>O torment to my soule! What mak'st thou here?</L>
<L>Cannot the picture of my misery</L>
<L>Be drawn<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, and hung out to the eyes of men,</L>
<L>But thou must come to scorne and laugh at it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Deare Sir, I come to thrust my backe under your loade,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> make the bu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>den lighter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hence from my sight, dissembling villaine; goe,</L>
<L>Thine Vncle sends defiance to my woe,</L>
<L>And thou must bring it: Hence, thou Basyliske,</L>
<L>That kil'st me with mine eyes: nay, never kneele;</L>
<L>These scornefull mocks more than my woes I feele.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas, I mocke yee not; but come in love,</L>
<L>And naturall duty Sir, to beg your blessing;</L>
<L>And for mine Vncle—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Him, and thee I curse,</L>
<L>Pl starve, e'r I eate bread from his purse,</L>
<L>Or from thy hand; Out villaine, tell that Cur,</L>
<L>Thy barking Vncle, that I lye not here</L>
<L>Vpon my bed of ryot, as he did,</L>
<L>Coverd with all the villanies, which man</L>
<L>Had ever woven; tell him I lye not so,</L>
<L>It was the hand of heaven strucke me thus low,</L>
<L>And I doe thanke it. Get thee gone, I say,</L>
<L>Or I shall curse thee, strike thee; Prethee away;</L>
<L>Or if thou'lt laugh thy fill at my poore state,</L>
<L>Then stay, and listen to the prison grate,</L>
<L>And heare thy father, an old wretched man,</L>
<L>That yesterday had thousands, beg and cry,</L>
<L>To get a penny: Oh my misery!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Deere Sir, for pitty heare me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vpon my curse I chargeno nearer come,</L>
<L>I'l be no father to so vild a Son.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>O my abortive fate!</L>
<L>Why for my good am I thus pay'd with hate?</L>
<L>From this sad place of Ludate here I freed</L>
<L><PB N="59" REF="31"/>
An Vncle, and I lost a father for it;</L>
<L>Now is my father here, whom if I succour,</L>
<L>I then must lose my Vncle's love and favour.</L>
<L>My Father once being rich, and Vncle poore,</L>
<L>I him relieving was thrust forth of dores;</L>
<L>Baffled, revil'd, and disinherited:</L>
<L>Now mine owne Father here must beg for bread,</L>
<L>Mine Vncle being rich, and yet if I</L>
<L>Feede him, my selfe must beg. Oh misery,</L>
<L>How bitter is thy taste! yet I will drinke</L>
<L>Thy strongest poyson; fret what mischiefe can,</L>
<L>I'l feede my Father, though, like the Pellican,</L>
<L>I pecke mine owne brest for him.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Old Foster, and above at the grate, a box hanging downe.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bread, bread, one penny to buy a</L>
<L>Loafe of bread for the tender mercy!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>O me my shame! I know that voyce full well;</L>
<L>I'l help thy wants, although thou curse me still.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bread, bread; some Christian man send back</L>
<L>Your charity to an number of poore prisoners;</L>
<L>One penny for the tender mercy.</L>
<STAGE>Robin puts in money.</STAGE>
<L>The hand of heaven reward you, gentle Sir,</L>
<L>Never may you want, never feele misery;</L>
<L>Let blessings in unnumbred measure grow,</L>
<L>And fall upon your head where e'r you goe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>O happy comfort! curses to the ground</L>
<L>First strucke me, now with blessings I am crown'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bread, bread, for the tender mercy; one</L>
<L>Penny for a loafe of bread.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pl buy more blessings; Take thou all my store,</L>
<L>I'l keepe no coyne; and see my father poore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost,</SPEAKER>
<L>Good Angels guard you, Sir, my prayers shalbe</L>
<L>That heaven may blesse you for this charity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>If he knew me, sure he would not say so;</L>
<L>Yet I have comfort if by any meanes</L>
<L>I get a blessing from my fathers hands:</L>
<L>How cheape are good prayers? A poore penny buyes</L>
<L><PB N="60" REF="32"/>
That, by which man up in a minute flies,</L>
<L>And mounts to heaven.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Stephen.</STAGE>
<L>Oh me, mine Vncle sees me!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now Sir, what make you here so neere the prison?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>I was going, Sir, to buy meate for a poore bird I have,</L>
<L>That sits so sadly in the Cage of late,</L>
<L>I thinke he'l dye for sorrow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>So Sir, your pitty will not quit you paines, I feare me;</L>
<L>I shall finde that bird I thinke to be that churlish</L>
<L>Wretch, your father, that now has taken</L>
<L>Shelter here in Ludgate; Goe too, Sir, urge me</L>
<L>Not, you'd best; I have given you warning:</L>
<L>Fawne not on him nor come not neare him,</L>
<L>If you'l have my love.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Las Sir, that Lambe</L>
<L>Were most unnaturall that should hate the Dam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste,</SPEAKER>
<L>Lambe me no Lambs, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good Vncle; 'las you know when you lay here.</L>
<L>I succour'd you, so let me now helpe him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, as he did me,</L>
<L>To laugh and triumph at my misery;</L>
<L>You freed me with his gold, but 'gainst his will:</L>
<L>For him I might have rotted, and laine still;</L>
<L>So shall he now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alack the day!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>If him thou pitty, 'tis thine owne decay:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bread, bread, some charitable man remember</L>
<L>The poore prisoners; bread for the render mercy,</L>
<L>One penny.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>O listen Vncle; that's my poore father's voyce.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>There let him howle; Get you gon, and come not neare him</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>O my soule! what tortours dost thou feele?</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>rth neare shall find, a son so true,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> forc'd to be unkind.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, go thy waies, thou patterne of true vertue;</L>
<L>My <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> full, I could even weepe, and much adoe I had to for∣beare,</L>
<L><PB N="61" REF="32"/>
To heare a brother begging in a Iayle,</L>
<L>That but e'r while spred up a lofty sayle</L>
<L>As proudly as the best: Oh, 'twerea sin</L>
<L>Vnpardonable in me, should I not succour him?</L>
<L>Yes, I will doe't, yet closely it shalbe done,</L>
<L>And he not know from whence his comforts come.</L>
<L>What ho, Keeper there, a word I praye.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Keeper.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Keep.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's your pleasure, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's he that at the grate there beg'd even now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Keep.</SPEAKER>
<L>One Master <HI>Foster,</HI> Sir, a decayed Citizen new</L>
<L>Come in. Cry you mercy Sir, you know him</L>
<L>Better than my selfe, I thinke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>I should doe, knew he me as I would know</L>
<L>Him: prethee take him from the grate,</L>
<L>And that no more he stand to beg,</L>
<L>There's ten pound to pay his score, and</L>
<L>Take off all his wants; if he demand</L>
<L>Who sends it, tell him, 'tis thine owne free</L>
<L>Hand to lend him money.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Keep.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well Sir, I shall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>Spend what he will, my purse shall pay it all;</L>
<L>And at his parting hence, the poorest prisoner,</L>
<L>And all free Citizens that live in Ludgate,</L>
<L>Shall blesse his comming in; I'l for his sake</L>
<L>Doe something now, that whil'st this Citty stands,</L>
<L>Shall keepe the <HI>Foster's</HI> name engraven so high,</L>
<L>As no blacke storme shall cloud their memory.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Keep.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heaven blesse your purpose, Sir.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Stephens Wife, and her sister Old Fosters Wife.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sister, there's no way to make sorrow light</L>
<L>But in the noble bearing; be content;</L>
<L>Blowes given from heaven are our due punishment;</L>
<L>All ship wracks are no drownings, you see buildings</L>
<L>Made fairer from their Ruines; he that I married,</L>
<L>The brother to your husband, lay, you know,</L>
<L><PB N="62" REF="33"/>
On the same bed of misery, yet now</L>
<L>Hee's ranckt with the best Citizens.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>O you were borne to wealth and</L>
<L>Happinesse; I, to want and scorne!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, I will worke my husband; stay this griefe.</L>
<L>The longest sorrow findes at last reliefe.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Clowne.</STAGE>
<L>Now Sir, your businesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Marry mistris here are two creatures</L>
<L>S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e able to make one man, desires to speake</L>
<L>With you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>What are they, know their names.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, I know that already; the one is a</L>
<L>Thing that was pluc'd into the</L>
<L>World, by the head and shoulders to be</L>
<L>Wondered at, and 'tis cald a knight; the other</L>
<L>Is a coach-horse of the same over-ridden race;</L>
<L>And that's a foolish Gentleman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, they are my old debtors, <HI>Speedwell</HI> and <HI>Lambskin</HI></L>
<L>Goe call them in, and my gentle sister</L>
<L>Comfort your selfe and my imprison'd brother,</L>
<L>To whom commend me give to him this gold,</L>
<L>What good I can, I'l doe for him be bold.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>May heavenly blessings guard you from all ill:</L>
<L>Never was woman vext as I am still.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Speedewell and Lambskin.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now good Sir <HI>Godfry</HI> and Master <HI>Innocent.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>I put my innocent case into your hands</L>
<L>Mistris, as a simple country Clyent thrusts his money</L>
<L>Into a Lawyers, who stands upon no great</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>rmes to take it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Speed.</SPEAKER>
<P>We come about the old businesse, the sicknesse of the purse Lady</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>And they'd be loth to keepe their beds i'th'counter</L>
<L>Mistris; they are affraid of Serjeants, Master <HI>Lambskin,</HI></L>
<L>Knowes that Mace is a binder.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>No truly it makes me loose for I never smell it, though</L>
<L><PB REF="33"/>
It be two streetes off, but it gives me a stoole presently,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, you have bin a loose liver alwayes,</L>
<L>'Tis time to looke to you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Speed.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fayre Lady, we are your debtors, and owe you mony.</L>
<L>Experience tels us that our bonds are forfeit,</L>
<L>For which your husband threatned to arrest us; my</L>
<L>Shoulders love no such clappings, I love</L>
<L>Tobacco, but would be loth to drinke in Woodstreet.</L>
<L>Pipes; some money we will pay ere we goe hence:</L>
<L>I speake you see with grave experience.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know it well, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Had not your husband (when we went about fowling</L>
<L>For the Aldermans daughter) driven away the Bird</L>
<L>We might have bidden you to a better breakefast;</L>
<L>But now you must take what we can set before you.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ent. Robert.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am content to doe so: you shall finde</L>
<L>Nor me nor my husband carry a griping minde.</L>
<L>Now Cuz, where's your Vncle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>He's hard at hand, I saw him comming</L>
<L>With the Lord Maior and Aldermen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Zoundes Knight, if the Maior come</L>
<L>The shoulder clappers are not farre off.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>O feare not, I'l be your surety Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe you not smell Poultry ware, Sir <HI>Godfry?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Speed.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most horribly, I'l not endure the sent on't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vpon my trust none here shall doe you wrong;</L>
<L>What is his businesse with the Alderman?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>About the entertainment of the King</L>
<L>That meanes to visit <HI>London.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>Saw you your sad father?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>I did; would I might never see man more</L>
<L>Since he so hates my sight; the prison doore,</L>
<L>Which gapes for commers in, that mouth of hell,</L>
<L>Shut me out with a churlish cold farewell;</L>
<L>After my fathers most unnaturall part</L>
<L>Was plaid on miseries stage, mine Vncle comes</L>
<L><PB N="64" REF="34"/>
In thunder on me, threatning with blacke stormes</L>
<L>To nayle me to the earth, if I releeved my</L>
<L>Poore old father.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ent. Stephen.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here's my master now Gentlemen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>O Gentlemen, y'are both welcome,</L>
<L>Have you paid this money on your bonds yet?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not yet Sir, but here they come like honest Gentlemen</L>
<L>To take some order for it: good Sweetheart</L>
<L>Shall it be put to me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe as you please;</L>
<L>In all thy deeds th'rt govern'd with good starres,</L>
<L>Therefore if thou cry'st peace, I'le not raise warres.</L>
<L>E'ne order it how thou wilt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thanke ye Sir; then tell me Gentlemen,</L>
<L>What present money can you pay?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Speed.</SPEAKER>
<L>Two hundred pound we can lay downe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>And take up seven times as much if we knew</L>
<L>Where to get it; but there's our lamentable ease:</L>
<L>Mistris, if you strip us any neerer, you'l strip the</L>
<L>Skin and all I'le assure you,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>We'l sheare no sheepe so close.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>No sheepe forsooth, but a poore innocent Lambskin.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>You should be a Calfe by your white face.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>All your two thousand pound Gentlemen we quit,</L>
<L>For your two hundred: goe pay the money to</L>
<L>My Cuz, and receive your two bonds canceld:</L>
<L>Say Sir, are ye content.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wife I must stand to the arbitrement.</L>
<L>Goe Cozin, receive their</L>
<L>Money, and Sirra make them drinke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le make them drinke if they will; come</L>
<L>Gallants empty your bags, and I'l bumbast</L>
<L>Your bellies; this leane Gentleman lookes</L>
<L>As if he had no lining in'<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> guts, I could</L>
<L>Take him by the leg and hurle him into</L>
<L>The dog-house.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="65" REF="34"/>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now sweet wife, what art thou</L>
<L>Musing on?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must come a wooing to you Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>A wooing sweet, for what?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>For your brother; Oh 'tis unmeet</L>
<L>For soules fram'd by one square to grow uneven,</L>
<L>'Tis like a warre 'mongst the great lights of heaven,</L>
<L>One cannot lose his beauty, but the other</L>
<L>Suffers ecclipse; so brother against brother.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wouldst have me kisse him that would kill me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would you kill a man lying at your feet:</L>
<L>Doe good for ill.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy songs are Angels tunes, and on thy wings</L>
<L>I'l flye with thee to heaven.</L>
<L>Thou speakest as I would have thee;</L>
<L>His debts I have justly weighed, and finde them light.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>The easier then tane off.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou sayest most right,</L>
<L>But I of purpose keepe aloofe to try</L>
<L>My kinsman; whom I spied most dolefully</L>
<L>Hovering about the grate, where his father cry'd</L>
<L>With pitteous voyce, for bread; yet did I chide</L>
<L>And rayl'd against the Boy; but my heart sayes</L>
<L>(How ere my tongue) it was drown'd in teares,</L>
<L>To see such goodnesse in a sonne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>Such wheeles in childrens bosome seldome runne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'l lay a wager wife, that this two hundred pounde</L>
<L>Payd by these foolish fellowes, will by the Boy</L>
<L>Be given his father.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>Troth would it might:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>In doing me such wrong he does me right</L>
<L><HI>Ludgate</HI> was once my dwelling, and to shew</L>
<L>That I true feeling of his misery knew;</L>
<L>Albeit long since blowne o're; so thou'lt consent,</L>
<L>Within that place I'l raise some monument,</L>
<L>Shall keepe our names alive till doomes-day.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>I gladly shall agree.</L>
<L><PB N="66" REF="35"/>
To any act that tends to charity.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Mr. Bruine.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, where's Mr. <HI>Foster?</HI> Oh you lose time Sir,</L>
<L>Not meeting fortune that comes to kisse you.</L>
<L>The Lord Maior and Aldermen stay at the Guildhall,</L>
<L>Expecting you, as well to set downe order</L>
<L>Touching the entertainement of the King,</L>
<L>As to elect you for the following yeere a Sheriffe of <HI>London.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>Their loves out-strip my merit.</L>
<L>Yet since they lay that load on me, I'l beare it,</L>
<L>And wait in scarlet on my leige and King.</L>
<L>But pray resolve me, Master Alderman,</L>
<L>Why makes the King this visitation?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Troth Sir, to honour me, I thanke his highnesse,</L>
<L>Who with my Lord the Cardinall comes along</L>
<L>To see the dedication of my House,</L>
<L>Built for the weary travellers to rest in;</L>
<L>Where stands three hundred beds for their releefe,</L>
<L>With meat, drinke, and some money when they part,</L>
<L>Which I'l give freely with a willing heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>A pious, worthy, and religious act:</L>
<L>Come Sir, toth' Guildhall; Wife, looke to your</L>
<L>Kinsman, watch him neare; but doe not hinder</L>
<L>Hi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> if he releeve his father: Come Master Alderman,</L>
<L>With such sweet incense up your offerings flye,</L>
<L>I'l build one Altar more to charity.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="5" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus Quintus.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Old Foster, his Wife, and Keeper.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Keeper.</SPEAKER>
<L>COme, come, be merry Sir; doe as mourners doe at</L>
<L>Funerals, weare your Hat in your eyes, and</L>
<L><PB N="67" REF="35"/>
Laugh in your heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have no such fat legacie left me,</L>
<L>To teach me how to play the hypocrite.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Keep.</SPEAKER>
<L>No? Why looke yee Sir, you shall want neither</L>
<L>Meate, drinke, money, nor any thing that the</L>
<L>House affords, or if any thing abroad like yee,</L>
<L>Sir, here's money, send for what you will Sir:</L>
<L>Nay, you shall beg no more at the Grate neither.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha? Is not this Ludgate?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Keep.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Iayle, a prison, a tombe of men lock'd up;</L>
<L>Alive and buryed?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Keep.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis what you please to call it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, at what crevice then hath comfort</L>
<L>Like a Sun-beame crept? for all the doores</L>
<L>And windowes are of Iron, and barr'd to keepe</L>
<L>Her out; I had a limbe cut from my body</L>
<L>Deare to me as life; I had a son and brother too;</L>
<L>Oh griefe, they both would give me poyson first</L>
<L>In gold, before their hollow palmes ten</L>
<L>Drops should hold of natures drinke, cold water,</L>
<L>But to save my life one minute; whence</L>
<L>Should pitty come, when my best friends doe.</L>
<L>Beate it from this roome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Keep.</SPEAKER>
<L>No matter Sir, since you have good meat set</L>
<L>Before you, never aske who sent it; if heaven</L>
<L>Provide for you, and make the fowles of the</L>
<L>Ayre your. Cators, feed you fat, and be thankefull,</L>
<L>And so I leave you.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Keeper is your friend, and powres true balme</L>
<L>Into your smarting wounds; therefore deare</L>
<L>Husband endure the dressing with patience.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>O wife, my losses are as numberlesse as the</L>
<L>Sea's sands that swallowed them. And shall</L>
<L>I in reckoning them, my sad griefes multiply?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<P>You may Sir, but your dim eyes so thick with teares doe run.</P>
<L><PB N="68" REF="36"/>
You cannot see from whence your comforts come,</L>
<L>Besides your debts being truly counted cannot</L>
<L>Be great.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<P>But all my wealth and state lyes in the seas Bottome.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>It againe may rise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh never.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good Sir, so hope, for I from heaven espy</L>
<L>An arme to plucke you from this misery.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Keeper.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Keep.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, there's one without desires to speake with you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe send him in; none comes to doe me good</L>
<L>My wealth is lost, now let them take my blood.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Robert.</STAGE>
<L>Ha? what art thou? Call for the Keeper there</L>
<L>And thrust him out of doores, or locke me up.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>O 'tis your son, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost</SPEAKER>
<L>I know him not:</L>
<L>I am no King, unlesse of scorne and woe,</L>
<L>Why kneel'st thou then; why dost thou mock me so?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>O my deare father, hither am I come</L>
<L>Not like a threatning storme to encrease your wrack</L>
<L>For I would take all sorrowes from your backe</L>
<L>To lay them all on my owne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rise mischiefe, rise, away and get thee gone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>O if I be thus hatefull to your eye</L>
<L>I will depart, and wish I soone may dye;</L>
<L>Yet let your blessing, Sir, but fall on me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>My heart still hates thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweet husband.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Get you both gon;</L>
<L>That misery takes some rest that dwells alone;</L>
<L>Away thou villaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heaven can tell, ake but your finger, I to make it</L>
<L>Well, would cut my hand off.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hang thee, hang thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Husband.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="69" REF="36"/>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Destruction meete thee, turne the key there ho.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good Sir: I'm gone, I will not stay to grieve you:</L>
<L>Oh knew you (for your woes) what paines I feele,</L>
<L>You would not scorne me so. See Sir, to coole</L>
<L>Your heate of burning sorrow I have got</L>
<L>Two hundred pounds and glad it is my lot</L>
<L>To lay it downe, with reverence at your feete;</L>
<L>No comfort in the world to me is sweet,</L>
<L>Whil'st thus you live in moane.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good troth Sir, I'l have none on't back,</L>
<L>Could but one penny of it save my life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet stay and heare him; Oh unnaturall strife,</L>
<L>In a hard fathers bosome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>I see mine error now: oh can there grow</L>
<L>A Rose upon a Bramble? did theree'r flow</L>
<L>Poyson and health together in one tide?</L>
<L>I'm borne a man; reason may step aside.</L>
<L>And leade a father's love out of the way:</L>
<L>Forgive me, my good Boy, I went astray;</L>
<L>Looke, on my knees I beg it; not for joy</L>
<L>Thou bringst this golden rubbish, which I spurne</L>
<L>But glad in this, the heaven's mine eye balls turne,</L>
<L>And fixe them right to looke upon that face</L>
<L>Where love remaines with pitty, duty, grace.</L>
<L>Oh my deare wronged boy!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gladnesse o'rwhelmes my heart with joy I cannot speak</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Crosses of this foolish world.</L>
<L>Did never grieve my heart with <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ments more</L>
<L>Than it is now growne light,</L>
<L>With joy and comfort of this happy sight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet wife, I disinherited this boy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your blessings all I crave.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>And that enjoy for ever, evermore; my</L>
<L>Blessings fly, to pay thy vertues, love and charity.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Stephens Wife</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here comes your brothers wife,</L>
<L><PB N="70" REF="37"/>
Welcome deare sister.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thanke you; how fare you brother?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Better than your husband's hate could wish me,</L>
<L>That laughes to see my backe with sorrowes bow:</L>
<L>But I am rid of halfe my ague now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>Had you an ague then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, and my heart had every houre a fit.</L>
<L>But now 'tas left me well, and I left it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, 'tis well Cozin, what make you heare I pray?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>To support a weake house falling to decay.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis well, if you can doe't, and that the timber</L>
<L>You under-prop it with be all your owne.</L>
<L>Hearke Cuz, where's your Vncles mony?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith Aunt 'tis gone, but not at dice,</L>
<L>Nor drabbing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, I believe with your Vncles gold your father</L>
<L>You relieve.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are sav'd believing so, your beliefe's true.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>You cut large thongs of that's another's due</L>
<L>And you will answer't ill: now in good troth</L>
<L>I laugh at this jest, much good doe them both:</L>
<L>My wager I had won, had I but layd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>What has my poore boy done, that you have</L>
<L>Made so much blood rise in's cheekes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nothing deare brother, indeed all's well:</L>
<L>The course that he has runne I like and love,</L>
<L>Let him hold on the same;</L>
<L>A sons love to a father none can blame;</L>
<L>I will not leave your brother's <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>on heart</L>
<L>Till I have beate it soft with my intreates.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twill ne'r be musick 'tis so full of frets.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>Frets make best musike: strings the higher</L>
<L>Rack'd sound sweetest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>And sound nothing when they are crackt,</L>
<L>As is his love to me, and mine to him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hope you both in smoother streames shall swim:</L>
<L>He<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'s now the Sheriffe of London, and in counsell</L>
<L><PB N="71" REF="37"/>
Set at the Guildhall, in his scarlet Gowne</L>
<L>With Maior and Aldermen, how to receive the King,</L>
<L>Who comes to see Master <HI>Bruines</HI> Hospitall</L>
<L>To morow consecrated by'th Cardinall,</L>
<L>And old Saint <HI>Marie's</HI> Spittle, here by <HI>Shoreditch.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>I sister, he and you may sit 'bout what you will;</L>
<L>Heaven I'm sure prospers it, but I am ever crost;</L>
<L>You have bin bound for thee great voyages,</L>
<L>Yet ne're run a ground; maid, wife, and widdow,</L>
<L>And wife agen; have spread full and faire sayles,</L>
<L>No wracks you e're did dread, nor e're felt any;</L>
<L>But even close a shore, I'm sunke, and midst of</L>
<L>All my wealth made poore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>You must thanke heaven.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe indeed, for all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sister, that hand can raise that gives the fall.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Keeper.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Keep.</SPEAKER>
<L>Master <HI>Foster,</HI> the new Sheriffe your brother</L>
<L>Is come to <HI>Ludgate,</HI> and I am come in haste</L>
<L>To know your pleasure, if you would see him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'l see a fury first, hence, clap to the doore I prethee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, 'tis your brother Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Father let's flye the thunder of his rage.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stand valiantly, and let me beare the storme, all hurts</L>
<L>That are, and ruines in your bosomes I'l repayre.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Stephen Foster.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where's the Keeper, goe Sir, take</L>
<L>My Officers, and see your prisoners</L>
<L>Presently convey'd from <HI>Ludgate</HI> unto</L>
<L><HI>Newgate,</HI> and the Counters.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Keep.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let the Constables of the Wards assist you,</L>
<L>Goe, dispatch and take these with you; how now,</L>
<L>What mak'st thou here thou Catiffe? had com'st</L>
<L>Thou to stitch his wounds that seekes to cut</L>
<L>My Throate, dar'st thou in dispight releeve this</L>
<L>Dotard?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="72" REF="38"/>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Get thee from my sight, thou divell in red;</L>
<L>Com'st thou in scarlet pride to tread on thy poore</L>
<L>Brother in a Iayle, Is there but one small conduit-</L>
<L>pipe that runs could water to my comfort, and</L>
<L>Wouldst thou cut off that thou cruell man?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, I'l stop that pipe that thou maist pining sit,</L>
<L>When drops but fell on me, thou poysond'st it:</L>
<L>Thou thrus<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'st a sonnes name from thy cruell brest,</L>
<L>For cloathing of his Vncle; now that Vncle</L>
<L>Shall thrust him naked forth for clothing thee,</L>
<L>Banisht for ever from my wealth and me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou canst not be to nature so uneven,</L>
<L>To punish that which has a pay from heaven;</L>
<L>Pirty I meane, and duty; Wouldst thou strike?</L>
<L>Wound me then, that will kill thee if I can,</L>
<L>Tha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>t no brother, and I'le be no man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou ravest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>How can I choose? thou makest me mad,</L>
<L>For shame thou shouldst not make these white haires sad;</L>
<L>Churle, beat not my poore boy, let him not lose</L>
<L>Thy love for my sake, I had rather bruise</L>
<L>My soule with torments for a thousand yeeres, could</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 words" DISP="〈◊◊〉"/> live them, rather than salt teares thy</L>
<L>Malice draw from him; see here's thy gold,</L>
<L>Tell it, none's stole, my woes can ne'r be told.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>O <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Is nature quite forgot?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Choke with thy dung-hill muck, and vex me not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, keepe it, he perhaps, that money stole</L>
<L>From me, to give it thee, for which to vex thy</L>
<L>Soule, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> turne him forth of doores, make him</L>
<L>Thy h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e, of Iay<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es, miseries, curses, and dispaire;</L>
<L>For here I d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>herit him of all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>No matter, lands to him in heaven will fall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Husband.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>other.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Deare Vncle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 line" DISP="〈1 line〉"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></SPEAKER>
<L>And <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, the dive<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> thumbs stop thine eares.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="73" REF="38"/>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'l make thee wash those curses off with teares.</L>
<L>Keeper, away with him out of my sight,</L>
<L>And doe Sir, as I charg'd you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Keep.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes Sir; I will.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Poore tyranny; when Lions weake Lambs kill.</L>
<STAGE>Ex</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now wife, art vext yet?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>Never so well content, beleeve me Sir;</L>
<L>Your mildnesse weares this maske of cruelty well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'm glad th'are gone, mine eyes with raine did swell,</L>
<L>And much adoe they had from powring downe:</L>
<L>The Keeper knows my minde, Wife I have paid</L>
<L>My brothers debts; and when he's out of doore:</L>
<L>To march to Newgate, he shall be set free.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>O let me kisse thee for this charity;</L>
<L>But for your Cozin Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>He's my lives best health,</L>
<L>The Boy shall not miscarry for more wealth</L>
<L>Than <HI>London</HI> Gates looke safe up every night,</L>
<L>My breath in blacke clouds flyes, my thoughts</L>
<L>Are white.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why from <HI>Ludgate</HI> doe you remove prisoners?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is my meaning wife;</L>
<L>I'l take the prison downe and build it new,</L>
<L>With Leads to walke on, Roomes large and faire:</L>
<L>For when my selfe lay there, the noysome ayre,</L>
<L>Choaktup my spirits, and none better know,</L>
<L>What prisoners feele, than they that taste the woe.</L>
<L>The workmen are appointed for the businesse,</L>
<L>I will ha't dispatcht before 'tis thought on.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>In good deeds I will walke hand in hand with you,</L>
<L>There is a faire tenement, adjoyning close to the Gate</L>
<L>That was my fathers, I'l give it freely, take it downe,</L>
<L>And adde so much ground to the worke.</L>
<L>'Tis fairely given.</L>
<L>Thy soule on prisoners prayers shall mount to heaven:</L>
<L>The Plummers and the Workemen have survey'd the ground</L>
<L>From <HI>Paddington;</HI> from whence I'l have laid pipes</L>
<L><PB N="74" REF="39"/>
Long to <HI>London</HI> to convey sweet water into <HI>Ludgate;</HI></L>
<L>From fresh Springs: when charity tunes the, pipe the</L>
<L>Poore man sings.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Keeper.</STAGE>
<L>How now Keeper.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Keep.</SPEAKER>
<L>The prisoners are remov'd Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>What did you with my brother?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Keep.</SPEAKER>
<L>As you commanded Sir, I have discharged him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>How did he meet that unexpected kindnesse?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Keep.</SPEAKER>
<L>Troth Sir, as a man or'ecome 'twixt griefe and gladnes,</L>
<L>But turning to his sonne, he fetcht a sigh</L>
<L>So violent, as if his heart would breake,</L>
<L>And silent, wept, having no power to speake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Las good old man, some sweet bird must sing,</L>
<L>And give his sorrowes present comforting.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not yet, I'l wracke his sorrowes to the height,</L>
<L>And of themselves they'l then sinke softly downe;</L>
<L>Keeper, goe thou agen after my brother,</L>
<L>Charge in my name him and his sonne to appeare</L>
<L>Before the King, to whom I will make knowne</L>
<L>Their wrongs against me; shewing just cause</L>
<L>To disinherit both by course of law. Be gone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Keep.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am gone Sir.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come Wife.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's your meaning Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou shall know that anon.</L>
<L>The heavens oft scowle, clouds thicken, winds blow high,</L>
<L>Yet the brightest Sunne cleares all, and so will I.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter, Henry the third Mountford, Pembroke, Arundell, Lord Maior, Sheriffe Foster, Cardinall, Bru∣ine, &amp;c.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>O! welcome is all love, our peoples shouts</L>
<L>In their hearts language, make our benvenues,</L>
<L>Most high and soveraigne; we returne all thankes</L>
<L>Vnto our loving Cittizens, chiefely to you Sir,</L>
<L>Whose pious worke invites our Majesty to royallize</L>
<L>This place with our best presence, accompanied with this</L>
<L>Reverend Cardinall; would we might, after many broyles,</L>
<L>End our dayes in these religious toyles;</L>
<L><PB N="75" REF="39"/>
We would worke most faithfully; but bounteous Sir,</L>
<L>How doe you call your buildings?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vnlesse it please your Majesty to change it,</L>
<L>I call it, <HI>Domus Dei.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<P>The house of God, it is too good to change, pray you proceede.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>These are my ends to all distressed Christians,</L>
<L>Whose travailes this way bends the hospitall,</L>
<L>Shall free souccour be, for three dayes, and three nights</L>
<L>Sojourne, for dyet, and lodging, both sweet, and</L>
<L>Satisfying; and if their neede be such, as much in</L>
<L>Coyne, as shall for three dayes more defray their</L>
<L>Futher travaile; this unto heaven, be you</L>
<L>Testator, good my Liege, and witnesse with me, noble</L>
<L>Gentlemen, most free and faithfully, I dedicate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>An honourable worke, and deserves large memory.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Moun.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis a good example, 'tis pitty 'tis no better followed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arun.</SPEAKER>
<P>But say Sir, now in some future age, perhaps some two or three hundred yeere behinde us, this place</P>
<L>Intended for a use so charitable, should bee</L>
<L>Vnhallowed agen, by villanous inhabitants; say whores,</L>
<L>In the stead of christians, and your hospitable</L>
<L>Tenements, turn'd intostewes; would not this grieve</L>
<L>You in your grave?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>If my grave were capableof griefe: sure it would Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prethee be a false Prophet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arun.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will, if I can, my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let now our Heraulds in the streets proclaime,</L>
<L>The title, and office, of this hospitall;</L>
<L>Make knowne to all distressed travellors, that</L>
<L>We'le accept this charitable house, this <HI>Domus Dei:</HI></L>
<L>Shall be their free fojourne, as is propos'd.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter the one way, Stephens wife, the other, Mistris Foster, Iane, Old Foster, Robert and Keeper, All kneele.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>What are these peticioners?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Each hath a knee for duty, the other for petition,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="76" REF="40"/>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rise, your dutie's done, your petitionsshall neede</L>
<L>No knees, so your intents be honest, does</L>
<L>None here know them?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes my good Lord, there's now a wonder in your sight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>A wonder, Master Sheriffe, you meane for beauty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>No my Lege, I would not so boast mine</L>
<L>Owne wife, but 'tis a wonder that excels beauty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>A wonder in a woman; What is't I prethee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>Patience my Leige, this is a woman that</L>
<L>Was never vext.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>You may boast it largely; 'tis a subjects happinesse</L>
<L>Above a Q<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>enes; Have you suites to us?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am the suppliant plaintiffe, royall <HI>Henry</HI></L>
<L>From me their griefes take their originall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>What art thou?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Even what your Grace shall please to make of me;</L>
<L>I was the son to this distressed father, untill he</L>
<L>Tooke his pa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ity off, and threw me from his love,</L>
<L>Then I became son to mine Vncle by adoption,</L>
<L>Who likewise that hath tane away againe,</L>
<L>And throwne me backe to poverty; never was</L>
<L>Son so <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ost betwixt two fathers, yet knowes</L>
<L>Not one, for still the richest does despise his heire,</L>
<L>And I am backe expulst into despaire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>This may your vices cause.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>For that I come to your impartiall censure for a doome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>We heare, speake on, we know the parties,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ach one relate his griefe, and if it lye in us,</L>
<L>We'l yeeld reliefe; 'tis first requisite that we</L>
<L>Know of you Sir, the cause of this your Sonnes disinheritance</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Before I understood his vertuous minde,</L>
<L>Or weighed his disposition to be kind,</L>
<L>I did that froward worke; This now great man,</L>
<L>Was an unthrifty wretch, a prodigall then.</L>
<L>And I disdain'd to know his brotherhood,</L>
<L>Denyed reliefe to him; this childe kinde and good</L>
<L>Against my contradiction, did him releive, as his</L>
<L><PB N="77" REF="40"/>
Distressed Vncle, at this I chide; for bade,</L>
<L>Still hee holds on his course,</L>
<L>He growes more kinde, and he in wasting worse;</L>
<L>My rage continued as it had begun,</L>
<L>And in that rage I threw away my sonne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>The like plead I, my Lord: for when my state</L>
<L>Had rais'd itselfe by an uncertaine fate,</L>
<L>I tooke this out-cast childe, made him my owne,</L>
<L>As full and free, as I my selfe had sowne</L>
<L>The seede that brought him forth; for this my loue,</L>
<L>His oblieg'd duty presently did prove</L>
<L>A traytor to my trust, against my will,</L>
<L>Succouring that foe, which I did love so ill,</L>
<L>Onely for hating him; my charity being thus</L>
<L>Abus'd, and quit with injurie, what could I then</L>
<L>But as his father erst, so I agen might throw</L>
<L>Him from my love? for worse is love abus'd</L>
<L>Then new borne hate, and should be soe refus'de:</L>
<L>I did a fathers part, if it were bad,</L>
<L>Biame him for both, there I my patterne had.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>You fall betwixt two pillars Sir, is't not so?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vnhappy fate, my Lord, yet thus I pleade:</L>
<L>For this my fathers hate I might deserve,</L>
<L>I broke his precepts, and did unchildly swerve</L>
<L>From his commission, I to my Vncle gave</L>
<L>What was my fathers, striving thereby to save</L>
<L>His falne repute; he rag'd, I did it still,</L>
<L>Yet must consesse as it was well, twas ill,</L>
<L>Well in my love, me thought, ill to my fate:</L>
<L>For I thereby ruin'd my owne estate,</L>
<L>But that mine Vncle throwes me forth of doore</L>
<L>For the same cause he tooke me in before,</L>
<L>Beats forest, gainst my bosome; iftwere good</L>
<L>To <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> from a father for an Vncles foode,</L>
<L>In lawes of love and nature, how much rather</L>
<L>Might I abridge an Vncle for a father?</L>
<L>Charitie's, a vertue generally stands,</L>
<L><PB N="78" REF="41"/>
And should dispersed be through all mens hands.</L>
<L>Then would you keep't alone; for when your heire</L>
<L>I first adopted was, charity was there:</L>
<L>How er'rs your judgement then? seeing you see</L>
<L>What was good in you, makes sin in mee;</L>
<L>You'l say my father did it, oh throw away</L>
<L>That soule excuse; let not discretion stray</L>
<L>So farre a side; if custome lawfull make,</L>
<L>Then sin were lawfull for example sake;</L>
<L>Nor were these wasted goods only your owne,</L>
<L>Since part was mine having adoption;</L>
<L>Then doe him right, my Lord, yet doe no wrong,</L>
<L>For where my duty fai'ld my love was strong.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>With an impartiall eare we have heard your</L>
<L>Loving story, 'tis both fayre and honest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>O let me now anticipate your Grace,</L>
<L>And casting off the shadow of a face,</L>
<L>Shew my hearts true figure, how have I striv'd</L>
<L>To make this forc't counterfeit long liu'd,</L>
<L>And now it bursts; comeinto my heart,</L>
<L>I have two iewells here shall never part</L>
<L>From my loves eye watch, two worthy to be fil'd,</L>
<L>On times best record; a woman and a child,</L>
<L>Now Sir, to you I come, we must be friends,</L>
<L>Though envie wils not so, yet love contends</L>
<L>Gainst envy and her forces; my young yeares</L>
<L>Say I must offer first, a peace in teares.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>O let my shame my bosomes center breake!</L>
<L>Love is to young it coyes, but cannot speake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>You blesse mine eyes with objects that become</L>
<L>The theater of Kings to looke upon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>The keeper is discharg'd Sir, your debts are paid,</L>
<L>And from the prison yare a new free man made:</L>
<L>Theres not a Creditor can aske you onght,</L>
<L>As your sonne did forme, so have I bought</L>
<L>Your liberty with mine, and to encrease it more,</L>
<L>Because I know bare liberty is poore</L>
<L><PB N="79" REF="41"/>
Without assistance: to raise your state agen,</L>
<L>The thirds of mine are yours, say you Amen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, not to that, you are kind brothers now,</L>
<L>Divide by halfes that love, and I'l allow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art onely wise in vertue, as thou setst downe,</L>
<L>So let it be, halfe my estate's your owne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>It whole redownes agen, for I am yours;</L>
<L>Forget this minute my forgetfull houres.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, they are buried all Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>This union's good, such league should ever be in bro∣therhood.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet without boast, my Leige, let me relate</L>
<L>One small thing more, remorse of my owne state,</L>
<L>And my deare brothers worse succession;</L>
<L>For that we both have prisoners been in one</L>
<L>Selfe-same place of woe, and felt those throwes</L>
<L>That <HI>Ludgate</HI> yeelds; my charity bestowes</L>
<L>Some almes of comfort: Keeper you can speake it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Keep.</SPEAKER>
<L>And many hundreds more Sir, you have reedified</L>
<L>And built it faire, adding more ground to it,</L>
<L>And by pipes of lead from <HI>Paddingtun,</HI> drawne</L>
<L>Water thither, free for all prisoners, lodgings</L>
<L>Likewise free, and a hundred pounds yearely, to make</L>
<L>Them fues for better comfort: all this is almost finisht:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>A worthy work, the better being done in the Founders ere,</L>
<L>Not left unto succession.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>O my good Lord, I ever keep in mind an English</L>
<L>Sentence, which my tutor is, and teaches me to act my</L>
<L>Charity <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> mine <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="3 words" DISP="〈◊◊◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>full is</L>
<L>Performance, when the Benefactor's dead.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>What is't I prethee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>This my good Lord, women are forgetfull.</L>
<L>Children unkind, Executors covetous, and take what they find,</L>
<L>If any man aske where the deads goods became,</L>
<L>The Executor sweares he dyed a poore man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have prevented well, so has this good Alderman,</L>
<L>I wish you many Schollers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>You make some doubt of me in this Sir;</L>
<L><PB N="80" REF="42"/>
Did you not say that women were forgetfull,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have vext her now Sir, how doe you answer that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>No my Lord, she's exempt from the proverbe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>No my Lord, I'l helpe it better, I doe confesse</L>
<L>That women are forgetfull, yet ne'r the lesse</L>
<L>I am exempt, I know my fate, and finde</L>
<L>My deare husband must not leave me behind,</L>
<L>But I must goe before him, and 'tis said,</L>
<L>The grave's good rest when women goe first to bed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thankes for thy excuse good wife, but not thy love</L>
<L>To fill my grave before me, I would not live to see that day.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prethee no more, I had rather be angry than flatter'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have a wonder Master Sheriffe, a prizelesse jewell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>Many jewels my good Lord; a brother, wife, and child,</L>
<L>For this I would have strove even with a father,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> ere rough stormes did in my browsappeare,</L>
<L>Within my bosome it was alwaies cleare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>I give him to you now Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>I take him, and to him backe doe give,</L>
<L>All that my selfe behind in state shall leave.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Fost.</SPEAKER>
<L>And all that you gave me, I doe bestow,</L>
<L>So in one houre become full heire to two.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>I claime a third by this bonds vertue,</L>
<L>See as a third father, thou art heire to those.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will not goe to him father on any of these conditions.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall have love to boote too, sweet <HI>Iane.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, and y<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> play booty, I dare not trust you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>What shall I say, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="3 words" DISP="〈◊◊◊〉"/> and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>,</L>
<L>Ty'de in a True-loves Knot, ne'r to part.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>I marry Sir, these are better conditions than the</L>
<L>Inheritance of three fathers; let me have</L>
<L>Love in <HI>Esse,</HI> let lands follow in <HI>Posse:</HI></L>
<L>Now I'l have thee as fast as the Priest</L>
<L>Can dispatch us, let him read as fast as he can.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>The liveliest harmony that ere I heard;</L>
<L>All instruments compar'd to these sweet tunes,</L>
<L>Are dull and harsh; I joy to see so good a childe.</L>
<L><PB N="81" REF="42"/>
A woman wonder, brothers reconcil'd;</L>
<L>You worthy Sir, did invite us to a feast,</L>
<L>Wee'l not forget it, but will bee your guest,</L>
<L>Because wee'l veiw these wonders o're agen,</L>
<L>Whose records doe deserve a brazen Pen,</L>
<L>But this above the rest, in golden text,</L>
<L>Shall be insculpt; <HI>A Woman never Vext.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

