<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>10-01-04</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Benjamin Griffin</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page. Corrected all $s. Sample: 15 minutes. Proofing: 30 minutes. Tag review and corrections: 60 minutes. DONE.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A12078">
<STC T="S">22384</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99852464</BIBNO>
<VID>17788</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>THE FLEIRE.</P>
<P>As it hath beene often played in the
<HI>Blacke-Fryers</HI> by the Children of
the Reuells.</P>
<P><HI>Written by</HI> Edward Sharpham <HI>of the</HI>
Middle Temple, Gentle∣man.</P>
<P>AT LONDON,
Printed and are to be solde by <HI>F. B.</HI> in Paules-Church∣yard,
at the signe of the Flower de Luce and the
Crowne. 1607.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="publisher to the reader">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>TO THE READER
and Hearer.</HEAD>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">F</SEG>Riendlie perusers, or perusing
friendes, that haue bin ouer∣bold
with some of vs, giue mee
leaue to bee a little bold with
you: I haue printed a Booke
heere to make you laugh and
lie downe too, if you please:
I know it comes not like a Mous-trap to inueigle
your good opinions, nor like newes of great Ar∣mies,
very strange and vndreampt of, but like for∣feits
to a Vsurer long lookt for. If you finde anie
errors by me cōmitted correct thē or neglect thē.
The Author is inuisible to me (viz: ith' Country)
but where abouts I cannot learne; yet I feare hee
will see mee too soone, for I had of him before
his departure an Epistle or Apological praeamble
(this being his first Minerua) directed vnto you,
which should haue bin in this Page diuul'gd, and
(not to ieast with you because this booke plaies
that part sufficiently) I haue lost it, remembring
<PB REF="3"/>
none of the Contentes. And therfore (kinde Rea∣ders)
I doe presume thus to salute you; vse these
Comicall discourses fauourablie and you shall
haue some from the Author heereafter more
worthie your fauours and affections: through a
narrow window you may view a broad Field; so
in this <HI>modicum</HI> you may conceiue his great
desire to delight you, But howsoeuer, I
know this volume will be sweet in the
palates of your minds, though your
mouthes may finde it bitter in
digestion, and so I commit
your eyes to the
next Page.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="play">
<PB REF="3"/>
<HEAD>The Fleire.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Act. 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Signior Antifront, with a Lord.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lord.</SPEAKER>
<P>DEere Lord, I know it well becomes not mee
to counsell him that best can counsell mee:
yet if it please you but to lend your eares, &amp;
heare my loue if not my counsell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sig.</SPEAKER>
<P>No more, I know thy loue tends to the stopping of
my longing and my resolution: thou knowst that I no
longer now am Signior: Florēce hath got an other gouer∣nor,
and one step backe in state of Maiestie, is a greater fall
then to a meaner man that looseth all: Besides, thou knowst
our Daughters they are fled, the true inheritors of <HI>Florence</HI>
right, and mightie <HI>Piso</HI> now vsurps our regall seate: puis∣sant
in power and mightie in his wrong, hath mounted
Faulcon-like into the sky of state, seaz'd on our feeblenes,
and beate our weakenes downe. And therefore now I am
resolu'd to finde my two lost Children out, or like as <HI>Phae∣ton</HI>
in pride did ride, so I in grief will pace the world about.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Vnto your celsitude I wish, till their effects your
hopes may neuer faile.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sig.</SPEAKER>
<P>Farwell, some strange disguise I needes must take
both for my stelth away, as for my passage on the way: and
yet my fortunes fall, disguisement is to great if pleasd the
heauens, but their willes still are lawes, all is but Iustice &amp;
our sinnes the cause: <HI>cuor forterompe catiua sorte.</HI></P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="4"/>
Enter Florida, and Felecia, Daughters to Signior Antifront,
Madam Fromaga their waiting Gentlewoman, and
two or three Seruingmen.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo.</SPEAKER>
<L>With draw, leaue vs, we would be priuate:</L>
<L>Sister what thinke you of this trade of ours?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt all but the two Sisters</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis base to be a whore.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis base to abuse great place, or basenes to de∣ceiue
great trust.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<P>And is't not basenes to abuse great birth?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes if great birth abusde not vs: if <HI>Piso</HI> had not
prou'd the theife and rob'd vs of our right, t' had bin worse
then theft in vs to rob our selues of honor: youle say wee
are forbid to liue by sinne, and yet wee are commaunded
seeke to liue: the letter law expresse forbids to kill, and
yet the sence permits it rather then be kild: &amp; since of two
extremities the least is to be chosen, you knowe wee haue
no other meanes to liue, but had wee, yet wee are
faire by nature, scorning Art, and was not beauty made
to bee enioyed? doe wee not exclaime on those who haue
aboundant store of Coine, and yet for want suffer the nee∣die
perish at their doore? so might all doe on vs, hauing so
much beautie, if we should suffer men for loue of vs to die;
shall wee in whome beautie keepes her court bee curbd
and tide to one mans beneuolence? no, no, not I: rather
then in vertue to liue poore, in sinne Ile dye.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fele.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your resolutions hath confirmd my doubtes,
and since tis hatefull to liue poore, to maintaine our
state I am content: but these obseruances let vs keepe,
strangelye mongst strangers let vs holde our state, and let
our Seruants sildome knowe, how familiar with our
friendes wee bee, and though Englands wealth doe now
adorne vs; lets keepe the fashion still of Florence.</P>
<P>Content, let's in, who's neere? attend vs, ho!</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="4"/>
Enter Fromaga, and Ladyes Exeunt.
To her enter a Gentleman.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gent.</SPEAKER>
<P>This is the streete, and as I remember this is the
doore.</P>
<P>Ile aske this ancient Gentlewoman: health and beautie
dwell with you Lady.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fro.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thanke you sir, a has a courtly phrase yfaith.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gent.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doe the Florentine Ladyes dwell heere?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes forsooth sir, I am a poore Gentlewoman that fol∣lowes
'am.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gent.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am sent to 'am by a Knight, who promist mee he
had procurd me the place of a Gentleman Vsher to them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir <HI>Iohn Haue-little</HI> I thinke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gent.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes indeed the same.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fro.</SPEAKER>
<P>By my troth hee's an honest Knight, a has no fault
but that hees poore, and thats a small fault now adaies: but
let mee see sir I pray, were you neuer a Gentleman Vsher
before?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gent.</SPEAKER>
<P>No truely neuer yet.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then you must be instructed sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gent.</SPEAKER>
<P>I shall be glad to learne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fro.</SPEAKER>
<P>I hope you and I shall be more inward sir, and for
your instruction I shall bee glad to lay open any secrets
that I haue; therefore first you must obserue: ha you anye
Tables?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gent.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, sure I neuer go without Tables.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Plucke out your pin and write downe as I shall vt∣ter:
to be alwayes ready, standing bare, to bee ymployed,
when, where, and howsoeuer your Ladyes please. You
must neuer bee without moneye of your owne, to lay out
when your Ladyes bid you, as eighteen pence to the Por∣ter,
halfe a Crowne to the Coachman, or twelue pence for
a torch if their Ladyships come home late at night. If you
be sent by your Lady to another Lady, to know what rest
she tooke ith' night, you shall deliuer your answere iust as
it came from the Lady: you must alwayes bee in a cleane
band, and cleane cuffes, how fowle so ere your shirt be.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="5"/>
<SPEAKER>Gent.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will obserue all this.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fro.</SPEAKER>
<P>You may by vertue of your office were a Perewig,
prouided, it be iust of the colour of your beard: let me see,
you haue a hatch'd sword of your owne there, haue yee
not?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gent,</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes for sooth, I bought it for his Ladyships seruice.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fro.</SPEAKER>
<P>T'was well done, you may weare it by your office,
what, is your Cloake linde through?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gent.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, but tis of a good depth in.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis well done too, your Ladies loue to haue it</L>
<L>Linde a good depth in, tis for their credit.</L>
<L>What, are these siluer hangers of your owne?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gent.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, I borrow'd these, but I haue a payre of mine owne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fro.</SPEAKER>
<P>They are in trouble, are they?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gent.</SPEAKER>
<P>No truely they are at mending.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay though they be, tis no shame, you haue beene
long out of seruice perchance.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Some three monthes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Birlady tis a long time, but can you indure to walk
some halfe a day in the Hall or the great Chamber, while
some great Lord is busie with your Lady in an inner
roome? you may sleepe an honre or two as your Citizens
wiues doe at a Sermon to passe away the time, but you must
haue a care to wake at the rushing of a Satten gown, or
the creaking of a doore, that if your Lady come, you may
be presently vp and bare.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gent.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes sure, I could doe it well.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Florida.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fro.</SPEAKER>
<P>You must stand stiffe vp, and holde vp your head,
tis the chiefest thing belongs to your place, looke heere
comes the elder Lady: Madam heeres the Gentleman that
Sir <HI>Iohn Haue-little</HI> commended to your Ladyshippe for a
Gentleman Vsher.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let him draw neere vs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gent.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Knight commends his deere affection, and by
me makes tender of his humble seruice to your Ladyship.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Kisse your hand and goe forward vpon her.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Deliuers a Letter.</STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="5"/>
<SPEAKER>Flo.</SPEAKER>
<P>We accept it, haue red it, you are beholding to the
knight, and he hath spared no paines to make your worthy
partes well knowne to vs: draw neere vs, hence foorth we
accept you as our owne, and so wee bid you welcome: are
you a Gentleman?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gent.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes sure Madam, for I was both borne &amp; begotten
in an Innes Court.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sure Madam then hees a Gentleman, for he thats but
admitted to the house is a Gent. much more he thats be∣gotten
in the house.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo.</SPEAKER>
<P>You are the more welcome, and our bounty shall
deserue your industrie.</P>
<STAGE>Exit. Flo.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gent.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is the Lady a Princesse that she speakes <HI>vs</HI> and <HI>we</HI>
so much?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fr.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, she saies so meaning her selfe and her Sister, for
they are both one, and such things as they haue, they vse
in common, and must stand bare before them both: looke
heere comes the tother Lady.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Felecia.</STAGE>
<P>Madam heeres the Gentleman that Sir <HI>Iohn Haue-little</HI>
commended to your Ladyshipp for a Gentleman Vsher.</P>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fe.</SPEAKER>
<P>We like him &amp; hee's welcome, what good parts haue
you? haue you the tongues?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gent.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not very well Madam.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes Madam, a has the Scottish tongue very perfect∣ly,
&amp; a has some skill in the Irish tongue too.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fe:</SPEAKER>
<P>Thats a wilde speech.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay ile warrant your Ladyship heele not run away,
has traueld Madam too a sayes, for a has been in Wales.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fe.</SPEAKER>
<P>Has a no skill in the French tongue?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gent.</SPEAKER>
<P>Some little skill Madam.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fr.</SPEAKER>
<P>No sure Madam, I think your Ladyship hath more
knowledge of the French then he.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fe.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, wee will at more leasure suruey your good
partes, and make thereof the best for our owne vse.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gent,</SPEAKER>
<P>I pra'y what wages doe these Ladyes giue?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith your wages wil be much about the nature
of your office, verye bare standing wages: I thinke some
<PB REF="6"/>
fortie shillings a yeare.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gent</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, how meane they I shall liue in their ser∣uice?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, by their countenance: I ha knowne a Lord hath
giuen his foole nothing but his countenance to liue by,
and I can tell you, t'as proou'd a good Court-mainte∣nance
too.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gent.</SPEAKER>
<P>Countenance? I hope I haue a countenance good
inough of mine owne, I neede not serue for one.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fr.</SPEAKER>
<P>In troth and so a has for a Gentleman-vsher, I must
needs say a verie harmelesse silly countenance.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gent.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yet faith I meane to trie their bountie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come will you walke in sir? Ile follow you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gent.</SPEAKER>
<P>Verie willingly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fr.</SPEAKER>
<P>This is braue yfaith, a shall go bare before mee too,
a will serue vs all three when wee are abroad.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Mistresse Susan, and
Nan, sisters:</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Su.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come sister, come, wee were not borne to stand, t'is
against the nature of our sexes kinde: come, sit, and tell me,
how many suters you haue, and which you most doe loue?
and I will tell you all mine, and which I most respect.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith I haue a dozen at the least, and their deserts
are all so good, I know not which I should loue most: and
one last day did court me thus: <HI>O had my tongue the influence
to lead thy faire thoughts as thy faire lookes do mine: then shouldst
thou be his prisoner who is thine.</HI> I seeing my poore Gentleman
likely to be drownd in the depth of <HI>Hellespont,</HI> deliuered
him this verse to catch hold of: <HI>O be not faire, and so vnkinde:
misshapen stuffe, is of behauiour boystrous and rough.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sus.</SPEAKER>
<P>But come, what was a for a man?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan.</SPEAKER>
<P>What was a for a man? Why, a was a man for a wo∣man,
what should a be? and yfaith he was a neate lad too,
for his beard was newly cut bare; marry it showed some∣thing
like a Medow newly mowed: stubble, stubble.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="6"/>
<SPEAKER>Su.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well I haue a suter too, if hee had as much witte as
liuing, it may bee I should finde in my heart to loue
him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan.</SPEAKER>
<P>What, i'st Sir <HI>Iohn Haue-little</HI> that gallant Knight
that Courts delicate Ladies? spare not the sweate of my bo∣die,
man was made to labour, vse my creation, women to
bear, ile vse yours: Birds to flye, Fish to swimme, &amp;c. And
then sweares by my cōscience Lady, I esteem you as I doe
money, which buyes euerye thing, and thats but like a
Puncke, for euery man has to doe with it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Su.</SPEAKER>
<P>No Sister no, tis not he, for I thinke his wit cannot
cal his wealth Maister, nor his wealth his wit, and yet they
are both Seruants to a foole.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith who is't Sister, i'st a proper man? hath hee
a good face?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Su:</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis the person and conditions I respect, and not
face, for euery Boy has a good face, and its not worth a
hayre. No Sister no, my loue is more worthier then words
canne vtter: I cannot simpathize his rare perfections
with any earthye substance: this Globe of durt produceth
nothing worthye of his comparison, so soules perfection
so refines his body, as you would thinke an Angell were
his sire: his discourse, behauiour, and humanitie, attracts
to him my soules felicitie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray' heauen it bee not mine: nay come who is
your loue? tell me?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Su:</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay who is yours? speake first.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yet agen!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Su:</SPEAKER>
<P>If it be mine, my heart will breake: mine is Maister</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan:</SPEAKER>
<P>Who, who, who?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Su:</SPEAKER>
<P>Ruffell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan:</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray God 't be true.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Su:</SPEAKER>
<P>In troth tis he.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan:</SPEAKER>
<P>And mine is Maister Sparke, and looke heere
they come.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="7"/>
Enter Spark, Ruffell, Piso, Knight, and Petoune.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith Ladyes, youth and beauty alwaies bee your
handmaides.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff:</SPEAKER>
<P>Best fortunes your attendants.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Piso.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good clothes your companions.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff:</SPEAKER>
<P>Wee all of vs your seruants.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet.</SPEAKER>
<P>And let Tobacco be your perfumes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan,</SPEAKER>
<P>Lord Gentlemen how your wits Caper! me thinkes
twould become you well at first entrance, your discretions
came in with a sober measure.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ladies we are come to make a Gentleman of your ac∣quaintance
heere.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan.</SPEAKER>
<P>His name good Maister <HI>Spark?</HI> hee's very welcome.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spar,</SPEAKER>
<P>His name is <HI>Sig. Petoune</HI> a Traueller and a great To∣baconist.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet:</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith Ladyes I take it now and then fasting for the
purification of my wit.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sus:</SPEAKER>
<P>Purification? why has your wit layne in child-bed
sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff:</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes indeede Lady, brought to bed of a Moone-calfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet:</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith Ladies if you vsde but mornings when ye rise,
the diuine smoke of this Celestiall herbe, it will more puri∣fie,
clense and mundifie your complexions, by ten partes
then your dissolued Mercury, your iuice of Lemmons,
your distilled snailes, your gourd waters, your oyle of rar∣tar,
or a thousand such toyes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sure Ladies I must needes say th' instinct of this herb
hath wrought in this Gentleman such a diuine influence of
good words, excellēt discourse, admirable inuention, incō∣parable
wit: why I tel yee, when he talkes, wisdom stands
a mile off and dares not come neere him, for feare a should
shame her: but before a did vse this Tobacco, a was the ar∣rantst
Woodcock that euer I saw.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet:</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeed I was a very silly fellow.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay you were an arrant asse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sure I was a foole.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="7"/>
<SPEAKER>Kni:</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, you were a most monstrous puppie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet:</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeed I was an Idiot, a verie Idiot.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Piso.</SPEAKER>
<P>By this light thou wert a most egregious cox∣combe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeed I was, indeed I was.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp.</SPEAKER>
<P>But since, it hath imbellisht his good parts, perfec∣ted
his ill partes, and made his secrete actions correspon∣dent
to his outward wisdome, as you may well perceiue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith Ladie these Gentlewomen haue not long v∣sed
my companie, yet you see how Tobacco hath alreadie
refined their spirits.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Piso.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Petoune</HI> I wonder Tobacco hath not purifyed the
complexion of thy nose?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, what ayles my nose?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Piso.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, be not angrie, I do not touch thy nose, to th'end
a should take any thing in snuffe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why doy' play so about my nose?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>T'is a good turne hees no Flie signeur: if a were, a
would burne his wings.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan:</SPEAKER>
<P>O signeur, these Gentlewomen haue not long vsed
your companie, yet you see how Tobacco hath alreadie
refined their spirits.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet</SPEAKER>
<P>Fayth Ladie, would you bestowe but one fauour
of me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Truly signeur if you should haue as much fauour
as you haue complexion, you would bee highly fauoured.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet.</SPEAKER>
<P>Deare Ladie, now by this day I loue you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Cheape signeur, nowe by the light of this day, I
cannot loue you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now Ladie, what drugs of wit has this Apothecarie
of Tobacco sold you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith a solde me none sir, onely a gaue me a taste of
his good meaning.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith Ladie I must enquire your name.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sus:</SPEAKER>
<P>I pra'y doe sir, yond Gentlewoman knowes it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet.</SPEAKER>
<P>O, I know tit well inough.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Svs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why doe you enquire it then?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come, come, Ladie can you loue?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sus.</SPEAKER>
<P>I.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="8"/>
<SPEAKER>Pet.</SPEAKER>
<P>And can you loue me?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sus:</SPEAKER>
<P>No.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet.</SPEAKER>
<P>Euerie foole can say, I, and no,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sus:</SPEAKER>
<P>And I alwayes answere euerie foole so.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doy' thinke I want wit?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sus.</SPEAKER>
<P>If you do, t'is a shame you doe not learne it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet:</SPEAKER>
<P>Will you teach me? Ile come to you to schoole.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sus.</SPEAKER>
<P>T'is not my profession sir, to teach a foole.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp:</SPEAKER>
<P>Looke, looke, this fellow is like your vpright shoo,
he will serue either foote.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good Ladie, haue a better regarde of mee, doe but
thinke me made of the same mettall other men are.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sus:</SPEAKER>
<P>If others were of the same mettall you are, and
all mine, I should quickelie sell them to the Bel-ma∣kers.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, what mettall doe you thinke me?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sus:</SPEAKER>
<P>Copper sir, copper, for I take your bodie to be of
the same mettall your nose is.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet.</SPEAKER>
<P>Deare Ladie, now by this day I loue you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp:</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, how now signeur, what sayes the Ladie will
she loue thee man?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet;</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith I can get but a colde comfort of her:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp:</SPEAKER>
<P>Well thanke her for't:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet;</SPEAKER>
<P>For what?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp,</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, for her cold comfort, shee gaue it thee to coole
the heate of thy nose man?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sus:</SPEAKER>
<P>Signeur, you see these Gentlewomen haue not long
vsed your companie; yet you see how Tobacco hath al∣readie
refined their spirits:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf;</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, how now signeur? at blind-man-buffe? bob'd
on either side?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet:</SPEAKER>
<P>Prethe peace: deare Ladie, please you take a pipe
of Tobacco?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf:</SPEAKER>
<P>I, come: Ile beginne to her (<HI>tab</HI>) why, what a rogue
art thou to offer a faire Ladie an emptie pipe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sus.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why signeur? do you make a foole of me?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Piso:</SPEAKER>
<P>Had you no body signeur to haue bob'd with an
emptie Pipe but her?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why howe now signeur, could you finde neuer a
fitter block to whet your wit on, but my sister?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="8"/>
<SPEAKER>Sp.</SPEAKER>
<P>By the diuine smoke of Tobacco signeur, you haue
sham'd vs all.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet:</SPEAKER>
<P>Sweare not good sir, sweare not, prophane not the
Indian plant.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni,</SPEAKER>
<P>Had you no bodie else signeur, to breake an
emptie ieast on but this Ladie?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sus.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, no, a thinks any thing is good ynough for me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, would you make my Ladie and me friends?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay signeur, I haue no face to speake, now you
haue abusde her in your owne Element: if it had beene
in any thing but Tobacco, I would haue done my best.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff:</SPEAKER>
<P>Harke you sig you were best to aske her forgiue∣nes
on your knees, ther's no way to get her friendship else.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet:</SPEAKER>
<P>But wil she forgiue me thinke you if I ask eher mer∣cie
on my knees?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, proue signeur, you can but trie, weele al speake
for you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff:</SPEAKER>
<P>Good Lady will you forgiue this signeur? you see
his penitent, griefe hath brought him verie low, for hees
on's knees; besides he weepes; speake signeur speake for
your selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ladie, I must confesse I haue offred you an emptie
pipe, which me thinks hath smal reason to be takē in snuff.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp:</SPEAKER>
<P>And you are sorie for't signeur, are you not?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet.</SPEAKER>
<P>I with all my heart.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp:</SPEAKER>
<P>Forgiue him good Ladie, pra'y forgiue him,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Su.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am content Gent at your intreaties vpō conditions.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet</SPEAKER>
<P>Vpon any conditions.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Su:</SPEAKER>
<P>But you shall be sworne to them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nost willingly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff:</SPEAKER>
<P>Come, a shall be sworne on's owne Tobacco pipe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Piso:</SPEAKER>
<P>Looke you signeur, he told you there was no way to
get her good will but by kneeling; for he that will haue a
womans loue must stoope.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sus:</SPEAKER>
<P>Come maister</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff:</SPEAKER>
<P>you shall take his oath, and Ile
minister't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff:</SPEAKER>
<P>Come signeur, put your hand to the pipe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sus:</SPEAKER>
<P>First you shall neuer while you liue offer Ladie or
Gentlewoman an emptie pipe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet:</SPEAKER>
<P>Neuer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="9"/>
<SPEAKER>Su.</SPEAKER>
<P>Secondly, you shall neuer make Tobacco your I∣doll,
taking it in a morning before you say your prayers.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet:</SPEAKER>
<P>Neuer</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Su:</SPEAKER>
<P>Thirdly, you shall neuer in the praise of Tobacco
disclose or dispraise by the way of making comparisons,
the secrets of Ladies, or Gentlewomen, as repeating their
distil'd waters, their censing oyles, or their smoothing vn∣guents.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp:</SPEAKER>
<P>To this you sweare.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet.</SPEAKER>
<P>Most willingly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Su.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fourthly, you shall neuer come with your squibs
&amp; smoke-squirts amongst Ladies and Gentlewomē, fling∣ing
out fume at your Nostrels, as a whale doth salt-water,
vnlesse you be intreated by them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet.</SPEAKER>
<P>Neuer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Su.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fiftly, you shall presently conuey your selfe out of
our company, neuer to come more neere vs, vnlesse you be
sent for.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet.</SPEAKER>
<P>Neuer?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Su.</SPEAKER>
<P>No neuer: so, let him kisse the pipe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp:</SPEAKER>
<P>Come Signior, you haue kneeld to a faire end, to get
you a Mistris, and heere you haue for sworne her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet.</SPEAKER>
<P>I'me in a faire case now.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pis.</SPEAKER>
<P>I faith now thar't a combe for any case.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, ile keepe my oath, farewell Gentlemen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pis.</SPEAKER>
<P>Farwell Signior.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp:</SPEAKER>
<P>Adew Signior.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni:</SPEAKER>
<P>God bewe Signior.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet:</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, some shall smoke for this.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff:</SPEAKER>
<P>Let it be your nose then good Signior in any case:</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Signior Antifront disguised, called Fleire.</STAGE>
<P>Its a good soile, a whole some ayre, a pretty Towne, hand∣some
sleight buildings, well proportioned people, verie
faire women.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hayda, this is like a Lawyers studdie in the latter end
of a Terme, one's no sooner thrung'd out, but another's
thrust in, y'are welcome sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="9"/>
<SPEAKER>Fle.</SPEAKER>
<P>But I am not sir, for I am sicke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff:</SPEAKER>
<P>Would you speake with any man heere?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl:</SPEAKER>
<P>I care not greatlie sir, if I spoke with euery man here.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hee's a mad fellowe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp;</SPEAKER>
<P>What art?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle.</SPEAKER>
<P>Poore.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff:</SPEAKER>
<P>Dost meane to liue in this towne?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle:</SPEAKER>
<P>Ide be loth to die in't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>In what countrie wert borne?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle:</SPEAKER>
<P>In none.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni:</SPEAKER>
<P>Where then?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle:</SPEAKER>
<P>In a Towne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni:</SPEAKER>
<P>What nation art?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flei:</SPEAKER>
<P>An Italian:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni:</SPEAKER>
<P>O then thou canst make glasses.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle:</SPEAKER>
<P>I, and as wisemen as you Asses too, O are you there</P>
<P><HI>Piso?</HI> your father is my good Lord, but no more of that yet.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why Signior, I hope you wonnot swagger?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle:</SPEAKER>
<P>No, nor I care not greatlie for them that doe, for
your swaggerer is but like your walking spur, a gingles
much but heele neu'r pricke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni:</SPEAKER>
<P>Why art so melancholie?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Su.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile hold my life hee is in loue with some waiting
Gentlewoman.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle:</SPEAKER>
<P>Hee's a mad fellowe wil loue anie of you all, lon∣ger
then a pissing while.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pis:</SPEAKER>
<P>Why camst thou out of <HI>Italy</HI> into <HI>England?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl:</SPEAKER>
<P>Because <HI>England</HI> would not come into <HI>Italy</HI> to me?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pis:</SPEAKER>
<P>Why art sad?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle:</SPEAKER>
<P>Because I haue cause.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pis:</SPEAKER>
<P>Who doost follow?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle:</SPEAKER>
<P>My nose.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp:</SPEAKER>
<P>Who doost serue?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle:</SPEAKER>
<P>God.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff:</SPEAKER>
<P>Who art towards?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle:</SPEAKER>
<P>He thats before me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp:</SPEAKER>
<P>What doost want?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle.</SPEAKER>
<P>Money.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="10"/>
<SPEAKER>Sp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nothing else?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp,</SPEAKER>
<P>What?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flei.</SPEAKER>
<P>A good seruice.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shall I preferre thee?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flei.</SPEAKER>
<P>I cannot tell, tis as I like the man.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nai't shall be to a couple of Gentlewomen of thine
owne Countrie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl.</SPEAKER>
<P>I shall haue enough to doe then I hope, I haue heard
of one woman hath seru'd ten men, but I neuer heard that
one man should bee preferred to serue two women before:
y'are an Englishman.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp.</SPEAKER>
<P>I.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl.</SPEAKER>
<P>So I thought indeede, you cannot poyson so well as
we Italians, but youle finde a meanes to bring a man out of
his life as soone. Gods light serue two women quoth you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why thou shalt serue but one, yet take thy choice of
both.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl,</SPEAKER>
<P>I marry Sir, I like when 't comes to choosing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whats thy name?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fleire.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp:</SPEAKER>
<P>Whats thy profession?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle:</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue euer been a Courtier.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp:</SPEAKER>
<P>A Courtier! come Gentlemen, I like this fellowe so
well that ile prefer him straite.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Do so, you shall doe a deed of charitie in't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faire Ladies youle excuse vs.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Su.</SPEAKER>
<P>You haue bin very welcome Gentlemē.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>manent Su, Nan</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Na:</SPEAKER>
<P>Come sister, there rests nothing for vs now but this:
wele get vs mens apparrel, and serue them as Pages so shal
we hinder them in their marriages, and in th' end preferre
our selues to be their wiues.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Su,</SPEAKER>
<P>I like it well, come lets about it presently.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<TRAILER>Finis Actus Primi.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus secundus.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Fleire, Solus in a new Suite.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue not yet bin seauen daies heere, and yet I see
that grieues my very soule: my Daughters, my Ladies
I must say now, make lust, labour for their maintenance, &amp;
this foolish natiō wil sel their goods, their lands, nay their
very soules for nights delights and momentarie sportes,
<PB REF="10"/>
which like to lightning appeares, and vanisheth ere one
can say tis come: but then repentance sticks close. There
was a fellow with one of my Ladies this morning, and the
poore slaue has but seauen shillings a weeke boord wages,
and yet he has giuen sixe on't for a bit of extraordinarye
flesh, well: God giue him the grace to pray, for a must fast.
I askd the hot slaue why a did not marrie since a could not
bridle his lust? and a tolde me a had rather fal into the Sur∣gions
mercy, then the worldes beggery; well, I see it can∣not
be denide, mercinarie women are necessarie members:
they plucke downe the pride of the flesh, yet are not proud
themselues, for thei'le be as familiar with the men as with
the Master: they doe as many good deedes as some Fryers
that puts one to pennance for his sinnes, they put twentie
to paines: he out of charitie sends one to the Hospital once
a yeare, they send twentie to the Surgions once a month.
Say he bids men repent, they make a'm repent, yet for all
this some will call a'm damn'd Puncks: well, if they bee
damn'd, theile not be damn'd <HI>gratis</HI> like your yong coūtrie
Gentlemen, nor in hugger mugger like your Citizens
wife with her Prentise. They can practise without an o∣uerseer:
they scorne to haue a Suburbian Baw'd lend am a
Taffaty gown, &amp; they (like your common Players) let men
come in for two pence a peece, and yet themselues to haue
but the tenth penny, like the tenth Pigge, yet faith
the trade is a good trade: They for sweare not themselues,
in commendation of their wares, as your common Trades∣men
doe, swearing they cannot afford it at the price. They
are no prouerb breakers: beware the buyer say they, you
shall haue enough for your money, if halfe will not serue
your turne take the whole, measure by your own yard, you
shal haue Winchester measure. I was somewhat bold with
one of their Ladiships this morning, &amp; askt her why wo∣men
went to the generating sport al the yere, since beastes
themselues went too't but once? And she answered me, be∣cause
they were women, &amp; had reason to know what was
good for themselues, and so had not beasts: but soft, here
comes Signior <HI>Petoune.</HI></P>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="11"/>Enter Petoune taking Tobacco.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet.</SPEAKER>
<P>O <HI>Fleire,</HI> how doost <HI>Fleire?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle.</SPEAKER>
<P>O Signior, you may snuffe out your smoke here
Signior, and saue your oath too, heere are no Cuckold ma∣kers.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet</SPEAKER>
<P>What are they <HI>Fleire?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Women Signior, women: I heard what a rash Gen∣tleman
you are to forsweare your Mistris companie in the
verie heat of your affection.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet:</SPEAKER>
<P>Hang her, hang her, shees a very crickee, shee hath
written for me three or foure times, but ile see her damn'd
ere ile come to her, woot take anie Tobacco
<HI>Fleire?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, not I; ile not make my nose a red Herring, ile
not hang him ith' smoke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet:</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou art a good Courtier <HI>Fleire,</HI> tha'st got a sute
alreadie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl,</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, I haue two or three Offices too.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet:</SPEAKER>
<P>Prithe what are they?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl:</SPEAKER>
<P>Why I am Yeaman ath' Iurden, Gentleman ath' smock
and Squire of entertaynment: for when your Gallants ap∣proch,
I take their in combe, for if I stay till their out come,
the deuill a bit of any siluer sir can I get: for your new
made Gallants lay all on the backe and spend all ath belly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet.</SPEAKER>
<P>How doe thy two Ladies liue <HI>Fleire?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl:</SPEAKER>
<P>Like two musk-cast in a Coope.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet:</SPEAKER>
<P>Why? I heere say they liue gallantly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl,</SPEAKER>
<P>Pheu, they? why they keepe a little court.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet:</SPEAKER>
<P>And what art thou? a Sumner?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl.</SPEAKER>
<P>A Sumner, why?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet:</SPEAKER>
<P>Because thou art one of the; harke in thine eare.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well said Caulfe, hast bin a sucking all this while for
that iest? no, I haue an honorable place, I am one of their
leaders, for their shooes are so hie, and their heeles so short
if they should not beled, thei'd play domesticke trickes a∣broad,
and show all.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou their leader! why doe they meane to goe to
the warres?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="11"/>
<SPEAKER>Fle:</SPEAKER>
<P>I thinke so, for I am sure here were a couple of gen∣tlemen
last night that scowr'd their peeces.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet:</SPEAKER>
<P>I thinke <HI>Fleir</HI> thy Ladies are not wee rich.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle:</SPEAKER>
<P>How can they? they spend when others get.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet.</SPEAKER>
<P>Dost heare <HI>Fleir?</HI> woot prefer me to their seruice?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle.</SPEAKER>
<P>What! shall wee embrace? shall we haue red-nos'd
Corporals here: what you rogue? will you turne Sumner?
away you whale-nosd rogue away, goe, snufle, snufle in the
Ocean, away you slaue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet,</SPEAKER>
<P>Is thy name <HI>Fleir?</HI> tha'rt a flattering, fleering, cog∣ging
knaue.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter two Ladies, one singing:</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<L>His mansred hose, were the colour of his nose,</L>
<L>and his breech was made of blue,</L>
<L>And he in shape, but a French-mans Ape,</L>
<L>And so sweete sir adieu.</L>
<L>" Holla, holla ye pampred Iades of Asia,</L>
<L>" And can you draw but twentie miles a day?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Giue me a bowe, Ile hit the Sunne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel,</SPEAKER>
<P>Why ti's impossible.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo,</SPEAKER>
<P>No more canst thou hit true felicitie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel,</SPEAKER>
<P>O I am in an excellent humor, now I could laugh,
daunce, leape, or doe anie light tricks that belongs to a
light wench.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo;</SPEAKER>
<P>But looke who's here?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel,</SPEAKER>
<P>O signeur <HI>Fleir,</HI> how dost, how dost man? we may bee
merrie before thee, thoul't be secret, wo't not?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo:</SPEAKER>
<P>As your Midwife, or Barber Surgeon Madam;</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel:</SPEAKER>
<P>How lik'st the Citie <HI>Fleir,</HI> ha, how lik'st it?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo,</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith wel Madam, were not your Citizens, such hea∣uie
head fellowes:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel,</SPEAKER>
<P>Thats a signe they are no drunkards.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeede Madam, drinke lightens the head, the
heart, the heeles, the pot, the purse; but it makes heauie
chamberpots, full bowels, and foule roomes enough.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="12"/>
<SPEAKER>Fel:</SPEAKER>
<P>Howe dost like the Gentlemen of this Coun∣trey?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle:</SPEAKER>
<P>I can compare your Gentleman, and your Mar∣chant,
to nothing so fitly as your Flea and your Lowse: I
had rather trust your lowse with a hundred pound, then
your Flea with for tie; for your Lowse, like the Marchant,
standes too't, you shall knowe where to finde him, but
your Flea, like the Gentleman, if you take him not at first
sight a slips from you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo:</SPEAKER>
<P>Me thinks they haue a strange fashion heere, they
take money with their wiues, and giue money to their
wenches.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle:</SPEAKER>
<P>And good reason too (Madam) woulde you haue
a man bee troubled with a wife, as long as he liues for
nothing? A giues money to his wench, to be as soone rid of
her as he has done with her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel:</SPEAKER>
<P>Whats the reason <HI>Fleir,</HI> the Citizens wiues weare
all Corks in their shooes?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle:</SPEAKER>
<P>O Madam, to keepe the custome of the Citie, one∣ly
to bee light heeld. The Cittie is like a Commodie,
both in partes and in apparell, and your Gallants are the
Actors: for hee that yesterday played the Gentleman,
nowe playes the Begger; shee that played the Way∣ting-woman,
nowe playes the Queane; hee that played
the married-man, nowe playes the Cuckolde; and
shee that played the Ladie, nowe playes the Painter.
Then for their apparell, they haue change too: for shee
that wore the Petticote, now weares the Breech; hee that
wore the Coxcombe, now weares the feather; the Gentle∣man
that wore the long Sworde, nowe weares the short
Hanger; and hee that could scarce get Veluet for his
Cape, has nowe linde his Cloake throughout with
it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo:</SPEAKER>
<P>But how dost like the Court <HI>Fleir?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle:</SPEAKER>
<P>Well ynough, if they did not catch their meate so; it
comes no sooner from Table, but tone fellow has a fatte
Ducke by the rumpe, thother a slipperie Ele by the taile,
and an olde Courtier that best knew the tricks on't, was
<PB REF="12"/>
mumbling of a Cunnie in a corner alone by him∣selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<P>What good cheere didst see there?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle,</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith there was much good meate, but me thought
your faire Ladie was your onely dish.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, but thats a costly dish, and will aske rich saw∣cing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith for mine owne part when I had a stomacke, I
shoulde like it best in it owne naked kinde, without anie
sauce at all.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whats the newes now at Court <HI>Fleir?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith they say your Ladyes cannot endure the old
fashion Spurre, they say it hanges to a mans heele like a
Wheele-barrow, but they loue the fine little Scottes
Spurre, it makes the Court Gennet curuet, curuet gal∣lantly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo:</SPEAKER>
<P>I prethe <HI>Fleir,</HI> howe goes the report of vs two a∣broad?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle.</SPEAKER>
<P>If I should tell you, I feare your Ladiships woulde
be angrie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo.</SPEAKER>
<P>No not a whit.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle,</SPEAKER>
<P>But alas they are your common people, they are
like your Slippers, they are alwayes gaping, their mouthes
are neuer shut.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo,</SPEAKER>
<P>But what say they of vs?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle,</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas Madam, their tongues are like your drie lea∣ther
shooes, alwayes creaking:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo,</SPEAKER>
<P>But I prethe tell vs, what doe they say of vs?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle:</SPEAKER>
<P>I shall offend your Ladiships.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo,</SPEAKER>
<P>I tell thee no.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle,</SPEAKER>
<P>But alas Madam, I doe not beleeue them, because
I knowe the conditions of the slaues; whie Ile tell you,
their tongues are like the Iacke of a Clocke, still in la∣bour.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thinke tha'rt madde, I prethee tell vs what they
say.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle.</SPEAKER>
<P>I would be loath to displease you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo,</SPEAKER>
<P>I tell thee thou shalt not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="13"/>
<SPEAKER>Fle.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith they say your Ladiships are a couple of state∣ly
Curtizans.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith that was not much amisse said they no worse?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flei,</SPEAKER>
<P>You'l not be angry with me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo,</SPEAKER>
<P>No a'my word.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle.</SPEAKER>
<P>By my troth they said stately whores.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo,</SPEAKER>
<P>What pagan rogues be these? were they but roasted
Larkes for my sake, I would crush em bones and all.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel,</SPEAKER>
<P>Why? are you so angry sister? you know they speak
truth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo,</SPEAKER>
<P>Why are wee whores?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel,</SPEAKER>
<P>What are we else?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why we are Curtizans.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<P>And what difference pra'y?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flei.</SPEAKER>
<P>O great great madam, your whore is for euery ras∣call
but your Curtizan is for your Courtier.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo,</SPEAKER>
<P>He has giuen you a difference now.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flei,</SPEAKER>
<P>And indeed Madā I said so, for in truth I was very
āgry with 'am, but they said you were for euery seruingmā
too.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo,</SPEAKER>
<P>Did they say so?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flei,</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes indeede Madam, I hope I haue touch'd you now.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo,</SPEAKER>
<P>He hold my life this slaue the Seruingman, that was
with me this morning, has brag'd of my kindenes to him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flei,</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, thats like lie, neuer trust a fellow that wil flat∣ter,
fleire, and fawne for foure nobles a yeare.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo,</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, ile nere haue Seruingman touch anie linnin
of mine agen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flei,</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes Madam, a may touch't when tis at the Laun∣dresses.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo,</SPEAKER>
<P>I, at my Laundresses, or else not: but what a rascal's
this? by this light, ile neuer suffer seruingman come neere
me agen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flei,</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes Madame, to deliuer you a letter or so.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl.</SPEAKER>
<P>By this hand, not vnlesse the Rogue kisse his hand first.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flei,</SPEAKER>
<P>O Madam! why? since blew coates were left oft,
the kissing of the hand is the seruing mans badge, you shall
know him by't: but Madam, I speake something boldly of
you now and then, when I am out of your hearing, to heare
<PB REF="13"/>
what the world wil say of you, for you know thats the way
to pumpe filthie wordes out of their mouthes, if there bee
anie in them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<P>And doe so still, wee allow thee to say anie thing,
for thereby we shall know our friendes from our foes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flei,</SPEAKER>
<P>I assure your Ladiships, I loue you, and am sorrie
for you from my soule, although you know it not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo,</SPEAKER>
<P>Wee doubt it not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come sister will you in?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo,</SPEAKER>
<P>I prithee <HI>Fleire</HI> informe vs how the tide of opinion
runs on vs, least we be drown'd in the slaunderous imagi∣nations
of the world.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flei,</SPEAKER>
<P>I shall be very vigilant of your reputations.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amb,</SPEAKER>
<P>Be so.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Sisters.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Ruffell.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flei,</SPEAKER>
<P>VVho comes heere a Gods-name? O, my gallant
ruffles it out in silke, where haue you bin all this while?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff,</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith at Court <HI>Fleire,</HI> when wert thou there?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl,</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith but yesterday, where I saw a Farmers Son sit
newly made a courtier, that sat in the presence at cardes, as
familiar as if the chayre of state had bin made of a peece of
his fathers Barne-doore: O tis a shame: I would haue state
be state in earnest and in game, I like your Courtier for no∣thing
but often saying his praiers.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff,</SPEAKER>
<P>What, I thinke thou feldome faist thy prayers,
since thou hast almost forgot thy Pater-noster.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flei,</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith I pray once a weeke doost thou pray oftner?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff,</SPEAKER>
<P>I did pray oftner when I was an Englishman, but I
haue not praid often, I must confesse since I was a Brittaine:
but doost heare <HI>Fleire?</HI> canst tell me if an Englishman were
in debt, whether a Brittaine must pay it or no?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flei,</SPEAKER>
<P>No, questionlesse no.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff,</SPEAKER>
<P>I'me glad of that, I hope some honest statute will
come shortlie, and wipe out all my scores.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl,</SPEAKER>
<P>But whats the newes now abroad Maister <HI>Ruffell?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff,</SPEAKER>
<P>Why they say the Courtiers shall make the Citti∣zens
no more Cuckolds.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="14"/>
<SPEAKER>Fl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Excellent newes yfaith, excellent newes, then the
Court will grow rich.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff,</SPEAKER>
<P>Rich? Why man why?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl,</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhy then your Courtier will not bestow his mo∣ny
in buying the Merchants idle commodities to ly with
his wife.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff,</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Fleire</HI> I did but to trie thee, the tide of the floud is turn'd man.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl,</SPEAKER>
<P>Then let them sweat for't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff,</SPEAKER>
<P>For what?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl,</SPEAKER>
<P>If they striue against the streame.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, but I meane the Cittizens must cuckold the courtiers</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle,</SPEAKER>
<P>Excellent newes y faith, excellent newes, then the
court will grow rich.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff,</SPEAKER>
<P>What, like your weauers shuttle? make cloath
forward and backward, but how I prithe? but harke you
<HI>Fleire,</HI> are you capable of a secret?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl,</SPEAKER>
<P>As your common Cockatrice, that receiues the se∣crets
of euery man.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff:</SPEAKER>
<P>Then I must intreat, I may trust thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl,</SPEAKER>
<P>That's because I am no Taylor, for if I were, thou
wouldest intreate me to trust thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff,</SPEAKER>
<P>Sirra, they say your Ladies are a couple of com∣mon
Punckes, I hope I may trust you with a secret?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl,</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, sir, doy' heare, doy' thinke they are no worse?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff,</SPEAKER>
<P>VVorse! why can they be worse?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl,</SPEAKER>
<P>O sir, I they may be priuate Puncks: why I tell you
he that takes vp his priuate Punckes linnin, were better
take vp anie commodity about the Town: if twere a com∣moditie
of Mousetrappes, a should not loose much by the
bargaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff,</SPEAKER>
<P>But hark you <HI>Fleire</HI> hark you, tis suppos'd I can tell
you they are a couple of priuate Puncks.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, then theres some hope theile proue honest wo∣men.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yea, how <HI>Fleire</HI> how?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why your priuate punck would leaue being a punck,
rather then be priuate to one man for nothing, and then if
al men were like thee, they would be honest, for thou hast
<PB REF="14"/>
nothing to giue am.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff,</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhat a cogging fleiring Rogue is this, nothing
will anger him: but doy' heare <HI>Fleire;</HI> art thou a procurer,
or a knaue? for one of them I am sure thou art.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl.</SPEAKER>
<P>A procurer! whats that?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff.</SPEAKER>
<P>One that procures meanes for procreation, vul∣garly
cald a Pander.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl,</SPEAKER>
<P>By this light now, were I a notable Rogue, should I
denie my profession, why, I am a procurer sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff,</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, then thou art a Knaue too thats certaine, for
there is such a simpathie between a Procurer and a knaue,
as there is betwixt an Alcumist and a Begger.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl,</SPEAKER>
<P>But looke you sir, pra'y wil you tel me one thing now.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhats that?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl,</SPEAKER>
<P>Are you a VVhoremaster or a Theife, for one of
them ime sure you are.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff,</SPEAKER>
<P>By this light now a comes neere mee too, why I
am a whoremaster.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl,</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, then you are a theef too, thats certaine, for your
whoremaster alwaies filcheth for victuals, for you knowe
flesh is mans foode, mary sir you cannot be hang'd for't, tis
but pettilassarie at moste, but you may chance bee whipt
for't and burn'd too; but not ith' hand Signior, not ith'
hand.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Sparke.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Saue ye Gentles.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then we are enemies to the Iewes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle.</SPEAKER>
<P>O my good preferrer, how does your worshippe, you
are a stranger heere.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith I haue been with two Gentlewomen, in whose
companie thou first sawst vs, and there the Knight, Sir <HI>Iohn
Haue-little</HI> is so in loue with the younger, as a knowes not
whether a should reioyce, shee had so much beautie: or la∣ment,
because he is like to inioy none on't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl,</SPEAKER>
<P>By my troth I tooke him for a Coniurer, when I first
saw him, a talkt so much of his soule and the Deuill.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp:</SPEAKER>
<P>Why a sould his soule to the Deuillman, for the vel∣uet
that lines his cloake.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl.</SPEAKER>
<P>And when will he giue the Diuell his dew?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="15"/>
<SPEAKER>Sp,</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, a deales with him, as a does with his Tailor, goes
vpon trust and meanes to pay them both at the latter day.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo,</SPEAKER>
<P>But does not the Gentlemen iest at him?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp,</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, one of them asked if he were a celestriall or a ter∣restrial
Knight, &amp; he very ignorant lie asked what Knights
they were? your terrestriall Knight quoth she, is of a grosse
element, and liues vppon landes of his owne, but your ce∣lestrial
Knight, hee liues by the Heire, that is, by his elder
Brother. He it was, was Knighted, when so few scapt the
sword, and he it is that now liues by the sword.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl,</SPEAKER>
<P>And what said the Knight, what said he?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp,</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith as some Courtiers doe, laugh at that he did not
vnderstand, and swore an oath or two of the new fashion,
as, by my conscience Ladie you haue a verie good spirit, &amp;
so after two or three Court complements, beseech'd the
Ladies retaine him still in their good graces, kist his hand
and went his way.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl,</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith mee thinkes your English Ladies were verie
gallant Creatures, had they not one fault.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp,</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhat's that?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl,</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue hend say, they will rise sooner, and goe with
more deuotion to see an extraordinarie execution, then to
heare a Sermon.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp,</SPEAKER>
<P>O signor, condemne not all for some, indeede I must
confesse there haue been Ladies at executions.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl,</SPEAKER>
<P>I, and they sat bare fac't too, for feare the little fleet
holes of their maskes should not giue their eyes roome y∣nough
for such a prospect: one Ladie thrust her head so far
out at a windowe, with greedy desire to see all, that the
whole body was like to followe, making a forked tree with
her head downe, had nother Gentleman Vsher, contrarie
to the nature of his office, catcht hold of her behinde.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp,</SPEAKER>
<P>A forked tree, why what tree doost thou thinke shee
would haue made?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl:</SPEAKER>
<P>O sir, a Medler-tree, a Medler-tree.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp,</SPEAKER>
<P>But <HI>Fleire,</HI> how does the Gentleman Vsher liue with
thy Ladies?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith sir in the nature of a Munkie, that flatters and
<PB REF="15"/>
fawnes, and shakes his taile in his Mistres lap: but yfaith
Gallants, whether are you two bound now?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp.</SPEAKER>
<P>We are euen readie for your two Ladies Signeur;</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle,</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith and you shall finde my two Ladies as readie for
you two: Come, come, Ile put you in the way of all flesh,
Ile send you to Graues-ende, Ile see you in the Tilt-boat,
When you are there, ship your selues: in, in, in.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ex. Spe. &amp; Ruf.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Piso and Knight.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Piso,</SPEAKER>
<P>How is't <HI>Fleir?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle.</SPEAKER>
<P>O my Lord, you are a welcome man.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Saue you O signeur.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fleir:</SPEAKER>
<P>O my gracious knight, and whither are you two
bound now?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Piso.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith een to your two Ladies signeur,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle,</SPEAKER>
<P>Yea? and will you to the South-ward yfaith? will
you to the confines of <HI>Italie</HI> my Gallants? take heede how
ye goe Northwardes, tis a daungerous Coast, ieast not
with't in Winter, therefore goe Southwardes my Gal∣lants,
South-wards hoe: I haue shipt two Gallants in a
storme, I feare they haue spent their maine Mastes by
this time, and are comming home agen: but if you will
Southwards, my hearts of golde, Ile shippe you in pompe,
Ile sende yee vnder the verie line, where the Sunn's at
hottest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Piso.</SPEAKER>
<P>But come, shall we goe see thy Ladies, <HI>Fleir?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, I, I, Come: but my good Lord youle bee a wel∣come
man, for I haue heard her often sweare, that had she
such a Husband, a man so richly deckt in vertuous orna∣ments,
shee woulde forsake this life, her-selfe, nay, her
verie being, to be your's; O my good Lord, shee loues you
deerly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Piso.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pheu, but I cannot requite it,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why my good Lord?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Piso.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shees a common thing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle.</SPEAKER>
<P>But say she may turne my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Piso.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shee has beene so much worne, shees not worth the
turning now.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="16"/>
<SPEAKER>Fle.</SPEAKER>
<P>O my Lord, penitence doth purge a spotted soule,
and better leaue sinne late then not at all: and I doe knowe
my Lorde, that for your loue from her immodest life sheel
turne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Piso.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, I, I doubt not but sheele turne: but t'will bee
like a Buzzard Hawke that turnes her tayle to her
game.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni:</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Fleir,</HI> is the gentleman vsher that I preferd to your
Ladies in any fauour with them?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle.</SPEAKER>
<P>Great, great: a kisses his hand with an excellent
grace, and a will leire and fleire vppon am, hee's partly
their Phisitian, a makes am Suppositories, and giues am
Glisters.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni:</SPEAKER>
<P>And how liues he with am.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle:</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith like <HI>Thisbe</HI> in the play, a has almost kil'd
himselfe with the scabberd: but hearke you Knight, you'l
bee a welcome man to my yonger Ladie, I protest shee
thinkes worthily of you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni:</SPEAKER>
<P>Signeur, I must confesse, I am beholding to your
Ladie; and to tell you truly, I haue much affected her since
I first saw her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle:</SPEAKER>
<P>Vpon my worde sir, to my knowledge she is an
honest Gentlewoman, yet the worlde may chance speake
ill of her. Why I haue heard some say <HI>Penelope</HI> was a
Puncke, hauing no reason to suspect her, but because
shee set vp late a nightes, when t'was but to vndoe that
which shee did by day. I haue heard some say <HI>Hercules</HI>
was a coward because hee did not fight at single Rapier
like a gallant, but with a Club.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni:</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, I haue no reason to thinke the worse of her
for the report of the worlde; for the world signeur per∣chance
speakes ill of you, or me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle:</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, y'are inth' right, I haue heard some say, you
were a verie needie Knight, and that you had but one
shirt to your backe when you came first to this towne;
Nay more, when your Lackie carried it to the Laun∣dresse,
it was founde to bee a womans smocke, that you
had borrowed: but what? shoulde my Ladie, or I
<PB REF="16"/>
beleeue this nowe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>I hope shee doth not,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, no, no.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Piso:</SPEAKER>
<P>Come <HI>Fleir</HI> shall we see thy Ladies?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, I, hoe, whose within there?</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Seruingman.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seru.</SPEAKER>
<P>What would you haue maister <HI>Fleir?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle:</SPEAKER>
<P>Prethe shewe these Gentlemen vp into the great
Chamber, and giue my Ladies notice of their being here,
haue a little businesse my Lordes, Heele conduct yee,
yee shall finde a couple of your acquaintance there.
<STAGE>Exeunt: manet Fleir.</STAGE>
Could I but worke Lord <HI>Piso,</HI> and my eldest daughter, to
make am both affect and loue each other, that marriage
might vnite their hearts togither: O then there were as∣sured
hope wee might redeeme our honours lost, and
regaine our right in <HI>Florence.</HI> And for this Knight
though hee bee poore, yet would hee married were vnto
<HI>Feli<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ia▪</HI></P>
<L>For of a louing husbands awfull eye,</L>
<L>Sets right the womans steps that went awrie.</L>
<L>Heauen I know has grace ynough in store,</L>
<L>To make most chaste, a most lasciuious whore.</L>
<STAGE>Enter the two wenches in boyes apparell.</STAGE>
<L>How now? who haue we there? a couple of footmen?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Su.</SPEAKER>
<P>You see sir, we are not a horsebacke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle:</SPEAKER>
<P>Howe nowe my little fire-workes of witte? what?
flashes and flames? tell me true, were you neuer Vshers to
some great mans Coach-mares? did youe neuer run bare
before them?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan,</SPEAKER>
<P>Neuer we sir:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whither are you going?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sus.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir we want a serrice, end are going to get a Ma∣ster.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come, come▪ Ile preferre you both, thou shalt serue
a Countrey-man of mine, hees going to trauaile: shalt
<PB REF="17"/>
goe with him, &amp; thou shalt serue one of my Ladies.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Su.</SPEAKER>
<P>We would willingly serue two nere friendes, be∣cause
we are brothers, and indeed two twins, and therefore
are loath to be parted.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl:</SPEAKER>
<P>Two twins? that's all one, come, come, you shall
serue'am.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan.</SPEAKER>
<P>You shall pardon vs sir.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Flor, Sparke, Felec: Ruffell, Piso, Knight
and Fromaga.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flor.</SPEAKER>
<P>I hope youle not condemne me for my loue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp:</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue no reason Lady.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo:</SPEAKER>
<P>I offered you vnaskt.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp:</SPEAKER>
<P>That with a number oft hath bought.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo:</SPEAKER>
<P>Partlie they haue, and partlie not, for I would haue
you know, my function seldom sels affection: what though
I haue euill liu'd? repentant teares can wash away my sin,
which ile poore foorth like droppes of winter raine, and
now hencefoorth, euer Ile this life abhor, and to the earth
my knees ile dayly bow, to get mercy from heauen, loue
from you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan.</SPEAKER>
<P>O the deuill take impudencie she courts him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Madam, the loue that I may giue you, fully doe in∣ioy,
but I haue sworne with other loue then as a Brother
doth a sister neuer to loue any.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<P>O sir, my fortunes are not fellowes with my birth,
they make me stoope to base deiected courses, but would
you loue me, I would as swift as thought flie this life, and
leaue lusts fowlest sinne, for fleshlye beastes to sleepe and
wallow in.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Su:</SPEAKER>
<P>Shame to thy sex, no more.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff:</SPEAKER>
<P>Lady, in all the honest offices that friendship may
commaund, commaund me still, but yet I haue not seene
the face to which I owe so much of loue, as may iustly ar∣rest
my affections, and when I doe, ile pay so due a debt
without imprisonment.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pis:</SPEAKER>
<P>Methinkes yond Lady growes fayrer much then
<PB REF="17"/>
she was wont, me thinks her feature mendes, &amp; her come∣ly
gesture, much hath drawne my heart to loue her, O but
shee's a whore.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gentlemen doe you lack a Boy?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp.</SPEAKER>
<P>No,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan.</SPEAKER>
<P>O God, I am vndone.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Su:</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir do'y want a Seruant?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff:</SPEAKER>
<P>No.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Su:</SPEAKER>
<P>O Lord what shall I doe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pis:</SPEAKER>
<P>What canst doe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Na:</SPEAKER>
<P>Any thing that a Boy should doe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Woot dwell with me?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Su:</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis partly as youle vse me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni:</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile vse thee well.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Su:</SPEAKER>
<P>Well.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pis:</SPEAKER>
<P>Tell me, are you both content to dwel with vs two?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Both.</SPEAKER>
<P>As please you two.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pis.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then thou shalt liue with me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>And thou with me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp:</SPEAKER>
<P>Come Gentlemen will you bee going?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Both</SPEAKER>
<P>We attend you sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ladies our occasions cals vs hence, and I am sorrye
we must leaue you.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt: manent Piso and Nan.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gentlemen you all both haue, and euer shall bee
welcome.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pis:</SPEAKER>
<P>Lady I will leaue you much affection more then I
thought to lend you, but I deale on vse, and haue much in∣terest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flei:</SPEAKER>
<P>Caught I hope: hold hooke and line, hee's fast by
heauen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord, what you lend me, with much interest
shall be repaide.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pis.</SPEAKER>
<P>Adew.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fare you well; refusd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Contemn'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo:</SPEAKER>
<P>Disdain'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel:</SPEAKER>
<P>Abus'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo:</SPEAKER>
<P>Adyes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="18"/>
<SPEAKER>Fel,</SPEAKER>
<P>A shall not liue:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Disdaine the Daughter of such a Signior.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel,</SPEAKER>
<P>Condemne a Ladie borne? sister we are wrong'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo,</SPEAKER>
<P>But if youle consent I haue a proiect laid, that in re∣quitall
both of them shall die.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<P>You make my soule sweet harmony, come lets a∣bout
it then.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<TRAILER>Finis Act: Secundi.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="act">
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Actus Tertius scena prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter the Ladies each with a Letter, and Fleire aside.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Are we in priuate?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel,</SPEAKER>
<P>We are?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo,</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray Sister what moouing lines of loue has your
Knight toucht your affection with?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith his stile is plaine, onely a little courtlike silk∣en
phrase it has, but I hope your lord hath sent rich words
like iewels, for your eares against your nuptiall day.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith a woes with lines that might perswade ano∣ther
thought, not mee, which ile lend your eyes, vpon the
like receiued curtesie from you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<P>With all my heart.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Change Letters.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo.</SPEAKER>
<P>What haue we heere?</P>
<STAGE>Reade.</STAGE>
<P><LETTER>
<P>Lady I know the noblenes of your disposition defends you from
the least Sparke of basenesse, wherefore I inuocate euerie particu∣lar
vertue of yours to be mediators to your best iudgement for my
better estimation in your loue, my affection is zealous,
my intent honorable, my desire mariage: thus
desiring your resolued answere, I rest.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED><HI>Euer at your disposure:</HI>
lacke Haue-little
Knight.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</LETTER></P>
<P>Vpon my life some friend did pen it for the foole.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let me see what's this?</P>
<STAGE>Reade.</STAGE>
<P><LETTER>
<P>You the vnderstanding spirit of a woman, let the splender of
your Beautie, with some heate of your affection shine vpon the
<PB REF="18"/>
creature that adores yee, and with the heauenlye comfort of your
loue, melt and thaw dispaire from in dying heart which if it liue, it
liues to loue, it dye if it dyes in loue, but howsoeuer, tis
your's, twas made for you, liues by you,
and dies without
you.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Yours in the moste affectionate
degree of affection.
<HI>Don Piso De Florence.</HI></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</LETTER></P>
<P>Sister vpon my life this is sonne and heire to Duke <HI>Piso</HI>
that now is.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo:</SPEAKER>
<P>O would hee were! but whosoere he bee, a must bee
made a match to giue fire to the hell blacke pouder of our
reuenge, yet your loue: the wise Knight and he, are two in
one, there are no such friendes as they.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then let them march both hand in hand in one way.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo:</SPEAKER>
<P>Then shall be thus: these two being earnest suters
for our loues, weele graunt vpon condition, that suddenly
they murther <HI>Sparke</HI> and <HI>Ruffell,</HI> but first to take the Sacra∣ment
if euer it be knowne, os knowne 'twill be, to keep our
names vnspotted in the action; this being done,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let them challenge vs, wee and our loues are won.
but say they should reueale vs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo.</SPEAKER>
<P>O none will breake a Sacrament to heape vp periury
on other sinnes, when death &amp; hel stands gaping for their
soules.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<P>But say they raile on vs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo.</SPEAKER>
<P>If they doe, tis knowne, we lou'd <HI>Sparke,</HI> and <HI>Ruffel,</HI>
and men will thinke they kild a'm for our loues, since they
liu'd in our fauour these in disgrace.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel,</SPEAKER>
<L>I like it well, come lets hasten it,</L>
<L>For this is euen as true as er'e was text,</L>
<L>Plots are but dreames vntill they take effects.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle.</SPEAKER>
<P>O God, I think the path to hell that women tread
is broder then the way men goe: how they walke by cou∣ples
to the Deuill?</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="19"/>
Enter Piso.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pis.</SPEAKER>
<P>O that I should loue a whore, a very common Co∣catrise,
my thoughts are drown'd in a gulf of sinne, shee's a
very Canniball, which doth deuoure mans flesh, and a
Horse-leach that sucks out mens best blouds perfection: a
very prisoners box, thats ope for euery mans beneuolēce:
and I am Heire vnto a Duke, yet loue her: doth any man
heere loue a whore? I, who? I, I, I, tis I, an arrant puncke &amp;
common hirde Hackney, and yet I loue her; I adore her,
I doate on her, I worshippe her, O would some goodman
would cut my throate, and put me out of paine—of paine,
O that nature would not make an honest woman!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl:</SPEAKER>
<P>She did, she did my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pis,</SPEAKER>
<P>Ar't there? speake, who was't?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl,</SPEAKER>
<P>Eue, Eue my Lord, she was honest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pis,</SPEAKER>
<P>Art sure on't?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl.</SPEAKER>
<P>I sure my Lord, for there was no man to tempt her
but her husband.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pis,</SPEAKER>
<P>I thought twas some such countrie Gentlewoman,
O <HI>Fleire. Fleire</HI> I loue a whore.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl,</SPEAKER>
<P>Why my Lord, were you neuer a Soldier?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pis.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes. yes,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo</SPEAKER>
<P>Why then tis your profession, you neede not be a∣sham'd
of your trade.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pis.</SPEAKER>
<P>But <HI>Fleire</HI> woot helpe me, woot helpe me man?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, I, who i'st?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pis,</SPEAKER>
<P>Thy Lady, thy elder Ladie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl,</SPEAKER>
<P>O my Lord, loue her? why shee's a whore.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pis,</SPEAKER>
<P>I <HI>Fleire,</HI> but she may turne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl:</SPEAKER>
<P>But shee is so much worne my Lord, shee's not worth
turning now.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pis.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doe not vex me, doe not torment me: doe not tor∣ture
me vpon the racke of ieastes, I tell thee if shee please,
she may turne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl:</SPEAKER>
<P>I my Lord, taile to her game, like a buzard hauk, or so:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pis.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yet againe, now the Deuill take thy body, and dam∣nation
light vpon thy soule, destruction on thy bones,
<PB REF="19"/>
confusion in thy marrow, dost scorne me, mocke me, vexe
me, torment mee? dost? dost? Ile hang my selfe, nay, Ile
damne my self rather then loue thy Ladie, and be abusd by
thee: I will, I will.</P>
<STAGE>Exit Piso:</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Knight.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>O <HI>Fleir</HI> how does thy Ladie?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle.</SPEAKER>
<P>I deliuerd your letter sir, and she thanks you for't:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>And how does she? ha, how does she?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith not well, she has taken phisick, and your gen∣tleman
vsher there ministers to her: shees very great, and
she sayes she feeles much stirring in her bellie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni:</SPEAKER>
<P>Sure then <HI>Fleir</HI> she has eaten too much raw fruit.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle:</SPEAKER>
<P>Vpon my life then, they be plums, and the stones
make her swell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni:</SPEAKER>
<P>Sure ther. t'is so, I should send her something to
comfort her nowe beeing sicke: what doest thinke were
best <HI>Fleir?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle.</SPEAKER>
<P>Send her an Oten cake, t'is a good Northern token:
sir <HI>Raph</HI> Shaue sent his Mistris one, but I think a meant to
ride a iourney on her, and thought Otes woulde make her
trauell well.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, Oates is too great a binder after her Phy∣sicke,
I care not if I goe and visite her, and carrie her a
Woodcocke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle.</SPEAKER>
<P>You'le goe alone sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, I meane so, but how should I carrie him <HI>Fleir?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle:</SPEAKER>
<P>Vnder your Cloke sir, vnder your Cloke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni:</SPEAKER>
<P>Mas, and thou saiest true, Ile goe buy one straight,
and yet now I remember me, t'is no great matter if I defer
it till she be well, it shall be so <HI>Fleir,</HI> I will.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle:</SPEAKER>
<P>O y'are of a French humor sir, as inconstant as impa∣cient:
I thinke you haue scarce the pacience to tell the
clocke when it strikes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tush, I keepe a boy for such vses.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle.</SPEAKER>
<P>For nothing else?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, to weare a garded Cloke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle:</SPEAKER>
<P>Not till you be richly married.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, not till I be richly married: hee should weare
one now, if my money were come out o'th Countrey.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="20"/>
<SPEAKER>Fle.</SPEAKER>
<P>I wonder you would be knighted sir, since your mo∣ney
is so long a comming, that you cannot maintaine your
knighthood gallantly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith I was knighted to get mee a good wife
<HI>Fleir.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle.</SPEAKER>
<P>Get you a good wife? Why looke you sir, speake
but the Golden tongue verie perfectly, marry you must
speake it well, and call some great Lorde cousen: t'will
get you a better wife then three hundred pound ioynter.
You may report you haue Colepits too,, t'is a warme
commoditie I can tell you: they may bee sent about by
water; if they nere come, as your money dooth not,
you maye curse the windes, or complaine of Ship∣wracke:
and then though't bee a lie t'is drown'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, but say it should bee proou'd afterwards t'was
not true.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle.</SPEAKER>
<P>True? Gods my life, shee's a wise woman that will
goe as far as new Castle to search the depth of a Cole-pit
for your truth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>I would be loath to leaue my truth so far hence.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle.</SPEAKER>
<P>But I am sure heele bring his honestie no nearer hi∣ther;
but that comes about by water too as his mony does.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>But <HI>Fleir</HI> is not thy Lady a vertuous Gentlewoman?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle.</SPEAKER>
<P>O yes sir, I often find her in deepe contemplation.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Of what I prethe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Of Aratines pictures.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, I warrant her, O she can endure no bawdrie, shee
spits when she heares one speake on't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle:</SPEAKER>
<P>Thats because her mouth waters at it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shees wondrous musicall too.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle:</SPEAKER>
<P>Verie true, she euerie day sings <HI>Iohn for the King,</HI> and
at <HI>Vp tailes all,</HI> shees perfect.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Be these good tunes <HI>Fleir?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle:</SPEAKER>
<P>Excellent, excellent sir, farre better then your Scot∣tish
Iigges.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni:</SPEAKER>
<P>Yet many of our Ladies delight much in the Scot∣tish
Musicke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, with their Instruments.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="20"/>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou hast a good wit <HI>Fleir:</HI> if I were a greatman
thou shouldst be my Secretarie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle.</SPEAKER>
<P>And I hope I should discharge the place suffici∣ently:
for I haue learning enough to take a bribe, and
witte enough to be prowd: but whither are you going
now sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith I am going to thy Ladies <HI>Fleir.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle.</SPEAKER>
<P>You will not speake with am now; for my Ladies
will speake with none but Gentlemen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why sir, I hope I am a Knight, and Knights are be∣fore
Gentlemen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle.</SPEAKER>
<P>What Knights before Gentlemen, say ye?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith I.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thats strange, they were wont to bee Gentlemen
fore they were knighted: but for this newes Ile folow you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doe, and as occasion serues Ile preferre thee.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Piso, and Nan as his Boy.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Piso:</SPEAKER>
<P>Why should I loue her? because shes faire, because
shees faire; because shee's a whore: for if she wore not faire,
she would not be a whore; &amp; if she were not faire, I should
not loue her: <HI>Ergo,</HI> if shee were not a whore I shoulde
not loue her: well concluded witte, well concluded wit;
there is no man breathing could loue her but I, shee's a
whore, yet her beautie haunts me like a Ghost, I cannot
sleepe for't, her remembrance rides me like the Mare a
nights, I cannot rest for't, what shall I doe? I shall burst
boy.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Piso:</SPEAKER>
<P>Will thy tongue be secret?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan,</SPEAKER>
<P>As the clapper of a Mill, my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Piso.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is not that alwayes going?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan.</SPEAKER>
<P>I my Lord, but I hope it sayes nothing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Piso.</SPEAKER>
<P>O thou hast wit I see I am in loue boy, I am, I am.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan</SPEAKER>
<P>With whom my Lord?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Piso.</SPEAKER>
<P>With a verie Wagtaile an'arrant woman, a verie
Peace whose pride is maintaind by her taile.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Na.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thē it is maintaind by the worthiest part of her body</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="21"/>
<SPEAKER>Pis:</SPEAKER>
<P>Come, your wit boy, your proofe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan,</SPEAKER>
<P>If a hundred men in a company, mee't doth not
the worthiest man amongst them, first take his place, and
sit downe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pis.</SPEAKER>
<P>I graunt it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan.</SPEAKER>
<P>And I am sure my Lord, where ere the bodie comes
the taile first takes his place, and sits downe, and therefore
I hope tis the worthiest part of the body.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pis.</SPEAKER>
<P>O that I had the reason of a Sailor to knowe her like a
rocke, that I might saile from her and auoide her: or as a
vertuous man knowes sinne, to loath and leaue it. And yet
shee's wondrous faire, I would she were as honest: kinde v∣sage
may reclaime her from her sinne, and make her stoupe
vnto her Husbands will, as doth a wel-mand Hauke vnto
the lure.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Na:</SPEAKER>
<P>O I, shee has bin man'd alreadie, she knowes the lure
and will come to any call.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pis.</SPEAKER>
<P>O but her beautie may excuse the folly of her youth,
tis want of maintenance hath ouerthrowne her, want and
pride are two notorious bawdes: want makes the noblest
creature sell her soule for golde, and pride doth make the
gallants stoope to lust.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Na.</SPEAKER>
<P>And often sels pure honestye, to clad her taile in
glittering brauerie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pis.</SPEAKER>
<P>And tis well done, let euerie member weare that
which it won: why shold the head studdy to maintaine the
foote?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan:</SPEAKER>
<P>Or the foote trot to maintaine the head?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pis.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why should not euery member like a mechanicke
man in a common-wealth, labour in his own trade to main∣taine
it selfe? then since euery thing must liue, I wil no more
condemne beautie for being clad in luxurye, but hence∣foorth
I will loue her, and let my passion smoothly swimme
along the streame of loues affection: hencefoorth I will no
more with foule and hated thoughts, abuse so rare a crea∣ture,
whose behauiour and discourse, inchantes the eares of
men, and driues the world into a wonder—ay me!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Na.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith my Lord youl nere win a woman by sighing,
<PB REF="21"/>
crossing your armes, and crying aye mee! the onely way to
wiN them▪ is to care little for am: when they are sad doe yee
sing: when they sing and are merrie, then take your time &amp;
put am too't: if they will, so: if not, let them snick vp, if
you will walke in my Lord, ile shew ye manie principles
I learn't of my Mother, they may doe your lordship good.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Go go, I will: but O vnhappie fate,</L>
<L>When youth and weakenes must support our state.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Fleire one way, Sparke, Ruffell and Petoune
another way.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp:</SPEAKER>
<P>How now <HI>Fleire?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff:</SPEAKER>
<P>Saue you <HI>Fleire.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flei,</SPEAKER>
<P>Saue ye Gallants: O Signior <HI>Petoune,</HI> shall you and
I be friendes agen?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp:</SPEAKER>
<P>Why are ye enemies?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle,</SPEAKER>
<P>No great enemies, a quarrell rose betweene vs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet,</SPEAKER>
<P>I doe not like such quarrels, a struck mee sir, and I
protest and sweare to you sir by this Trinidado, had I not
taken the box on my cheeke, a had broke my Pipe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp:</SPEAKER>
<P>Why didst not strike him agen?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff:</SPEAKER>
<P>O no, his Father's a Iustice.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flei,</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay if the Father be of the peace, I see no reason
the Sonne should fight.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff</SPEAKER>
<P>What, a Coward Signior? fye, a coward?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl.</SPEAKER>
<P>A Coward? why thats his onely vertue, for a Coward
abuseth no man, but a makes him satisfaction: for if a wrōg
all men, a giues al men leaue to beate him, hee's like a whet∣stone,
he sets an edge on another, &amp; yet a wil not cut him∣selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come, come, we must needes haue you friendes, &amp;
thou'st doe him some good offices.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who? I? with all my heart, but what i'st sir? what i'st?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff:</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou shalt commend his loue to Madā <HI>Fromaga.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl:</SPEAKER>
<P>His loue to her? what Signior, in loue with my La∣dies
Antient?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp:</SPEAKER>
<P>Why her Ancient?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl:</SPEAKER>
<P>Because shee carries her colours for her, but tis in a
<PB REF="22"/>
box: but signior you shall haue a good match on't, though
she be not rich, yet shee's an ancient woman, and is able to
get her liuing, by midwiferie, and I can tell yee tis not the
worst trade going, considering how young and olde, and
all doe their good wils to set them a worke, and tis a good
hearing, better they gette then the Lawyers, for your mid∣wiues
liue by the agreement betweene partie and partie,
&amp; the falling in of louers, but the Lawyers liue by the fal∣ling
out of friendes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet:</SPEAKER>
<P>I pray sir what may she be worth?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Worth? let me see, shee hath three yellow pere∣wigs
of her own: she hath a Fan with a short siluer handle
about the length of a Barbors siringe; she has a Looking-glasse
too, but that has plaid the prodigall Cittizen with
her, tis broken, and much other goods of the same na∣ture.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp.</SPEAKER>
<P>But come Signior, how will you woe her?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will tell her she is so wise, that neither age nor
time could cousen her of beautie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl,</SPEAKER>
<P>And by my faith that will doe well.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will tell her that I loue her most for the whitenes
of her skin.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl:</SPEAKER>
<P>But you may not say the sweetnes of her breath, for
that stinks.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will praise the smalnes of her fingars.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl.</SPEAKER>
<P>But I assure you, you may better praise the length of
her nailes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am affraide that being olde shee has a drye hand.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl,</SPEAKER>
<P>Thats certaine, but she has a very moiste nose, you
may praise her for that: but my Gallants why are ye such
strangers at our little Court?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp:</SPEAKER>
<P>Because thy Ladies liue like the Beadles of Bride∣well.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl,</SPEAKER>
<P>How's that sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp:</SPEAKER>
<P>By the sinnes of the people.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff.</SPEAKER>
<P>They say the Lord <HI>Piso,</HI> hath bin a good Clyent
to thy elder Ladie of late.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl,</SPEAKER>
<P>The more foole hee? why your good Client is but
<PB REF="22"/>
like your studdie gowne, sits in the colde himselfe, to keep
the Lawyer warme.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp.</SPEAKER>
<P>And what fees hast thou out of their trade?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl,</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith my fee's are like a puny Clarkes, a penny a
sheete.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp,</SPEAKER>
<P>How a peny a sheete?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle,</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, if any lie with them a whole night, I make
the bed ith' morning, and for that I haue two pence, and
that's a peny a sheete.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff,</SPEAKER>
<P>What Gallants vse to come to your house?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl:</SPEAKER>
<P>All sortes, all nations, and all trades: there is first
Maister <HI>Gallant</HI> your Britaine, Maister <HI>Metheglins</HI> your
<HI>Welchman,</HI> Mounsieur <HI>Mustroome</HI> the Frenchman: Signi∣or
<HI>Fumada</HI> the Spaniard, Maister <HI>Oscabath</HI> the Irishman:
and Maister <HI>Shamrough</HI> his Lackey, O and Maister <HI>Slopdra∣gon</HI>
the Dutchman. Then for your Trades-men, there
comes first Maister <HI>Saluberrimum</HI> the Phisitian, Maister
<HI>Smooth</HI> the Silk-man, Maister <HI>Thimble</HI> the Taylor, Maister
<HI>Blade</HI> the Cutler, and Maister <HI>Rowell</HI> the Spurrier: but
Maister <HI>Match</HI> the Gunner of Tower-hill comes often;
he has taught my Ladies to make fire-workes, they canne
deale in Chambers alreadie, as well as all the Gunners that
make am flye off with a traine at Lambeth, whē the Maior
and Aldermen land at Westminster: but come Signior,
you haue Tobacco, and ile giue you a Cup of Muld-sacke
and weele ene goe drinke a health to our Mistresses.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<TRAILER>Finis Act. Tertii.</TRAILER>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus Quartus.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter the two Ladies Piso and Knight, and Fromaga one way:
Sparke, Ruffell, Petoune and Fleire an∣other
way.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo:</SPEAKER>
<P>Health to our best esteemed friends, Maister <HI>Spark</HI>
and Maister <HI>Ruffell.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel:</SPEAKER>
<P>Our, good wishes euer waite vpon our best belooued
friendes Maister <HI>Ruffell,</HI> and Maister <HI>Sparke.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="23"/>
<SPEAKER>Ambo:</SPEAKER>
<P>Wee both are much indebted to your Ladiships.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle:</SPEAKER>
<P>Looke yee signior, thats she: whose loue meanes to
assault your braines, since you haue blowne vp your owne
sconce with Tobacco.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet.</SPEAKER>
<P>As I am truely generous, shee's modest.
Faire Mistris, you are so wise, that neither time nor age
could euer cousen you of beautie, and I sweare euen by the
Alpes high heauen-touching tops, the trauelers narrowe
passage, and by the towring head of high mount <HI>Chiego,</HI> the
Sea-mās southward marke: by these the witnesses vnto my
trauell, I doe vow that you are passing fayre.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>From:</SPEAKER>
<P>If I be not faire sir, I must be foule.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet:</SPEAKER>
<P>A Foule Lady? what bird might that be?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fro:</SPEAKER>
<P>A foule Ladie? y'are a sawcy Iacke to call mee so,
that you are.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet.</SPEAKER>
<P>O be not angry, for I protest I cannot but commend
the whitenes of your skin.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>From:</SPEAKER>
<P>Mary muffe, I thinke a be a Tanner, and meanes
to buy me for my skin.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet:</SPEAKER>
<P>Gods mee; shee's angrie, what shall I doe now
Signior?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle.</SPEAKER>
<P>To her agen man, doe not leaue her, the Moone is
now vpon change, she will turne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet:</SPEAKER>
<P>I pray you Ladie knowe mee by the title of some
kindenes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>From.</SPEAKER>
<P>Kindenes; faith sir you are mistaken in mee, you
must seeke your flurts some other where, and I pra'y come
not to make a foole of me: alas man though I am a waiting∣woman▪
do not think I spend my time in nothing but tem∣pering
of colours, working of drawn-worke, warming of
Smockes, and pinning in of ruffes, faith yes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle:</SPEAKER>
<P>And you come to her Signior you must come to her
as countrie Gentlewomen doe into the fashion, that is: in
the taile and latter end on't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>From,</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith I, and ye come to begin your knauerie on
me, ile take you down: I am none of your young simpering 
waiting-women, that are asham'd to be counted proud, &amp;
therefore suffer euerie Seruingman to vse them at their
<PB REF="23"/>
pleasure.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now on my conscience Mistresse, my loue is honest,
and I desire marriage.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeed if you meane mariage, I am content to beare
the more with you: but I pra'y sir, when shal we be maried?
by my troth I aske you, because I haue beene so often de∣ceiued,
I warrant you I haue bin promised &amp; dealt vpon
promises in the way of mariage aboue an hundred times.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet.</SPEAKER>
<P>At our next meeting we wil set down a day for the
effecting of it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gentlemen, we haue some small discourse which
a little requires secrecie, therefore if it please ye to walke
in, and make vse of our better roomes, wee will not long
be absent from you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp. &amp; Ruf</SPEAKER>
<L>With all our heartes.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Manent two Ladies the Lord and Knight:
Felicia, and the two Wenches disguised, hide
themselues.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Worthy Lord, doe not thinke immodestie in mee
though contrarie to the bashfull habite of my sexe, I
am inforc'd by loues almightie power, to reueale the se∣cretes
of my heart. Your Letters haue so much pre∣uailed
with mee, that in a worde I must confesse I loue
you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Worthie Knight, I would my wordes had but the
power so worke in you, that which your lines haue done
in me, then should the happie consolation of my life dwell
euer in your loues embracements.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Assure ye Ladie, your gift of loue to mee shall bee
deserued, though nothing but my liues deare breath re∣quite
its.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Piso.</SPEAKER>
<P>And I will rather die a shamefull death, then liue
a hatefull life, which I must do vnlesse I find a meanes that
may deserue your loue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo.</SPEAKER>
<P>No we your tongue goes like a well tuned Instru∣ment,
and makes my heart within my bosome daunce
with ioy to heare such large requitall of my loue: but
duist you to maintaine this your affection, although it
<PB REF="24"/>
were with some daunger of your life?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Piso.</SPEAKER>
<P>Durst I? I vowe, euen by my soules eternitie, I
durst.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo:</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas, if you knew all, t'is your owne good, not mine:
and yet I lie, t'is my good too, since my life depends vpon
your safetie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Piso.</SPEAKER>
<P>What is't deare Ladie? although it be the death of
man, if it be pleasing vnto you Ile doo't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo:</SPEAKER>
<P>O let me embrace so deare a spirit in so deare a bo∣some:
and since you haue bound your selfe by promise, I
will be plaine, there are two that hate you two, because
wee loue you, and often haue perswaded vs by giftes
and large protestations to haue vs loue them if they kil'd
you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Piso:</SPEAKER>
<P>What vs?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni:</SPEAKER>
<P>Who wee?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo:</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay t'is too true; for while you liu'd, they said
there was no hope for them to looke for any loue from
vs: nowe wee poore sillie women, fearing least they
without consent of vs, should doe that which their ha∣tred
doth intend, wee thinke it fitte preuention first
be vsed, by giuing them to drinke of what themselues
haue brude.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Piso:</SPEAKER>
<P>First murther them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<L>True, so shall ye then be sure,</L>
<L>T'inioy our loues, we yours, and liue secure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Piso.</SPEAKER>
<P>But what are they Ladies?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sparke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<P>And Ruffell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pis:</SPEAKER>
<P>They die for't though they were my fathers sons.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>They shall not liue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Piso:</SPEAKER>
<P>Let little children feare the shallow Brookes, for
I can swim though't be through Seas of blood; let foolish
feare goe dwell with women, for bloodie resolution shall
not part from me, Ile kill them both euen with mine owne
hands, Ile doo't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo.</SPEAKER>
<P>O no▪ Ile reueale it then, vnlesse you first do swear
and take a Sacrament, what euer hap to keepe our names vntoucht.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Piso</SPEAKER>
<P>Vntoucht? weele doo't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="24"/>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then for the meanes:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni:</SPEAKER>
<P>Weele stabb them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Piso:</SPEAKER>
<P>Weele fight with them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo:</SPEAKER>
<P>No, so you may misse them, and they kill you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel:</SPEAKER>
<P>Giue them a Figg.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo:</SPEAKER>
<P>Make them drinke their last.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Poyson them:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Piso</SPEAKER>
<P>But for the meanes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo:</SPEAKER>
<P>You two shall make a banquet, and in a cuppe of
Wine a health shall passe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Piso:</SPEAKER>
<P>In which ile mingle mingle such a dram, as they
shall ride to heauen in post, vnlesse they misse the way.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>But where shall we get the poyson? because you
knowe t'is daungerous, and will breede suspect where ere
wee buy it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Piso.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue a Countrey-man in towne an Apothecarie,
one <HI>Signeur Aluino,</HI> a fellow that is well stor'd, and will
sell me of the best.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan:</SPEAKER>
<P>If a were of my minde, a would thinke no poyson
too good for you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo</SPEAKER>
<P>Come then, I would haue you goe about the prepa∣ration
of the feast.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle,</SPEAKER>
<P>Now boyes, you haue a couple of goodly maisters,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan.</SPEAKER>
<P>I <HI>Fleir,</HI> and thou hast a couple of vertuous Mistres∣ses,
O they are a couple of damn'd peeces, that will
plot or counsell the death of two such worthie Gentle∣men.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Su.</SPEAKER>
<P>For one of them the earth did neuer beare a wor∣thier
creature.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan:</SPEAKER>
<P>Which is that?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Su,</SPEAKER>
<P>Which is that? Why sister, haue you so oft confest
that his all perfection'd spirit poyntes him out for ver∣tue
herselfe to imitate, and yet doy' aske now which is
that?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle,</SPEAKER>
<P>Howe? sister, nay now I smell you yfaith, doy'
heare, doy' heare, whose Fidlers are you two? what In∣struments
do you beare I pra'y?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan.</SPEAKER>
<P>You haue tolde a wise tale, fayth fir wee carrie
none.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="25"/>
<SPEAKER>Fl:</SPEAKER>
<P>T'is true my little musitians, you carry but the cases
my little curtals, yfaith I smell a smock heere too, and are
you two wenches yfaith?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan:</SPEAKER>
<P>If we were, I hope thou wouldest not wrong vs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl:</SPEAKER>
<P>No, as I am true Italian borne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Su:</SPEAKER>
<P>Then tis true, wee confesse to thee wee are both
wenches, and the loue of these two Gentlemen, <HI>Sparke</HI> and
<HI>Ruffel</HI> hath made vs leaue our selues to waite on them
which by misfortune we did misse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle.</SPEAKER>
<P>But beleeue me my little Gallants, yee play the
Boyes well.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Na.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well? why ile tell thee, I haue plaid the boy so long
as I am chang'd into the nature of a boy, ile goe to span∣counter
with any page in <HI>Europe,</HI> for his best garters I can
tell baudie tales, drinke drunke, brag, sweare, and lye with
any Lackie in the towne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Su:</SPEAKER>
<P>I can man a punck to a play, or slaunder any Gentle∣woman
as well as anie Innes a Court puny, I can as well as
he, sweare such a Lady is in loue with me, and such a Citti∣zens
Daughter would haue come to bed to mee, when all
shall be as true as thy Ladies are honest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Na</SPEAKER>
<P>I wonder thoult liue in such a sinfull place.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Su:</SPEAKER>
<P>Thy Ladies are as common as any Tauerne doore.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good comparisons, for a man comes no sooner into
a Tauerne, but hees welcome, and the operation of the pot
makes him not able to stand when he comes out.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Na,</SPEAKER>
<P>But what shall we doe in this matter?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Su.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doe? Why complaine them to the Magistrates, and
preuent the murder.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl,</SPEAKER>
<P>No, not so, ile tell you how't shall bee, harke in your
eares.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Both:</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe it and we shall euer thanke thee.</L>
<L>Come lets about it then.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Signior Alunio the Apotheearie in his shop with
wares about him.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whats this? O this is <HI>Arringus;</HI> this makes the old
man able, and the young man lustie, strengthneth the
<PB REF="25"/>
nerues &amp; doth concoct the bloud, and her name is written
on the box, because my wife should knowe it in my ab∣sence:
this is Ciuet, this comes from the Cats taile, I would
my were such a Cat: this perfumes your Ladies, and not
without cause, for some, I meane whose sweet breath is
dead, and teeth mourne in blacke for the losse on't this
makes your young Gallants smell them nine daies before
they see them, like young poops: this drug is pretious &amp;
deere; whats this? O this is the sptrit of roses, nineteene
bushels and a halfe of Roses make but an ounce, &amp; a dram
on't, tis made of the Quinressence of the water after the
fifteenth distillation: none may kisse a Ladie after shee hath
annointed her lips with this, vnder the degree of a Lord at
least, tis worth nine poundes an ounce, yet I could neuer
still it so.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Fleire disguised.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle.</SPEAKER>
<P>Saue you Signior.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alu:</SPEAKER>
<P>Y`are welcome sir, what doe ye lacke?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<P>I want a seruice, and am by my profession an Apo∣thecarie,
and shall be glad to be intertained by you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alu:</SPEAKER>
<P>What countrie man art thou?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am a Florentine borne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alu,</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou art my Countrie man, and therefore welcom
and in happie time, for I am bound for Italy, and want a
man to take charge of my Shop, onely this is all: I shall re∣quire
of you, bee carefull of your cares, and obedient to
your Mistresse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle.</SPEAKER>
<P>I shall remember still not to forget what you giue
me in charge.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alu.</SPEAKER>
<P>What is thy name?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle,</SPEAKER>
<P>Iacomo.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alu:</SPEAKER>
<P>Well <HI>Iacomo,</HI> if I finde thee honest thou shalt find
me liberall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle.</SPEAKER>
<P>I would be loath to be found otherwise.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alu:</SPEAKER>
<P>Continue so, I prethee, and so farwell <HI>Iaques,</HI> but
ile enforme my wife before I goe to respect thee according
to thy merrit.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="26"/>
Enter Piso and Knight.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now come away my Customers, I hope I am fitted
for an Apothecary▪ s'hart I thinke ime turnd coniurer, for
I haue no sooner cal'd▪ but the Deuils are appeared, what
do yee lacke Gentlemen?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pis.</SPEAKER>
<P>Where's your Maister fellow?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Maister is gone into Italie sir, but if you want
any thing, ile vse you well, if you want any drugs to make
Lotiums, any Restringent Powders, anie Aqua Mirabilis,
any Cordiall receipts, or anie Pretious poysons?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>What poysons haue you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle.</SPEAKER>
<P>Excellent good sir, as euer was tasted, looke you sir,
this poysons by the smell, this by the sight, and this by the
tastes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pis,</SPEAKER>
<P>Come giue mee some of this that poysons by the
taste, but how must I vse it?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl,</SPEAKER>
<P>Put it into a little wine, and drinke it, twill bring you
into a long sleepe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pis.</SPEAKER>
<P>But art sure twill poyson a man?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle.</SPEAKER>
<P>Am I sure on't? why tak't vpon my credit, twil poi∣son
any vermine, except it be a woman, for twill poyson a
Cat sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni,</SPEAKER>
<P>Why a Cat hath nine liues sir, and wilt not poyson
a woman, seeing twill poyson a Cat?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl.</SPEAKER>
<P>O no, why a woman hath nine Cats liues, a woman
hath more liues then a horse hath diseases, and she wil bee
sometimes in as many mindes in an houre, as shee has
liues.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pis,</SPEAKER>
<P>What times are those?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl.</SPEAKER>
<P>When shee's left a rich Marchants Widdow, com∣monly,
and hath many suiters, she will in her minde marrie
three or foure and fiftie of a'm in an afternoone, and three∣score
more, when she goes to bed, yet in the morning sheele
haue none of them all, but goe to Church before day, and
marry her Prentice for the good seruice a did her in her
Husbands time.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pis,</SPEAKER>
<P>VVell, but whats the price of your poyson?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Theres an ounce will cost you a French crowne sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="26"/>
<SPEAKER>Kni:</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis verie deere.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle.</SPEAKER>
<P>O sir tis verie cheape, considering the goodnesse
on't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pis.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yea? is there good in ill?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl,</SPEAKER>
<P>O sir, I, in many thinges the better the worser.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>As how?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle:</SPEAKER>
<P>As in poyson, or in a punck, for the better whore
the worser woman euer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pis,</SPEAKER>
<P>Well honest fellowe, there's thy money and far∣well.</P>
<STAGE>Exit</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle:</SPEAKER>
<P>I thanke you sir, I haue sold you a poyson my old
elders, twil make an<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> sleep indeede, and I thank God that's
the worst twill doe, well, farwell Maister Apothecarie. I
must now like a friend intreate your shop to haue a special
care of it selfe.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Sparke, Ruffell and Petoune.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff,</SPEAKER>
<P>And shall wee dine with this Honorable Lord, &amp;
Knight to day?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spa,</SPEAKER>
<P>Theile take it vnkindely else.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff,</SPEAKER>
<P>Signior will you goe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet▪</SPEAKER>
<P>Not I, I was not bid.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff,</SPEAKER>
<P>Thats all one, shalt be my guest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp,</SPEAKER>
<P>Come, a shall goe, for there will bee his Mistresse
Madam <HI>Fromaga.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff,</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay then I knowe the Iet of her complexion will
draw the straw of his loue thither.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith I, poore Signior, I see the Springle of her beau∣tie
hath alreadie caught the Woodcocke of his affections.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet,</SPEAKER>
<P>Wel, I see he that wil haue the commoditie of good
wits in his companie, must indure the discommoditie of
ieastes, wit is like the heate of blood in youth 'twil breake
out.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff,</SPEAKER>
<P>True Signior, though it bee but on a Scab, but
come shall we goe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet:</SPEAKER>
<P>I my Heroique spirits, ile followe yee.</P>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="27"/>
<HEAD>Actus Quintus.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Petoune one way, and Nan the Page
another way.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan,</SPEAKER>
<P>O Signior <HI>Petoune,</HI> what newes?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith ill newes, the two Florentine Ladies, with
Maister <HI>Sparke</HI> and Maister <HI>Ruffell</HI> were all poysoned yest∣erday
at a feast by your Lord <HI>Piso</HI> and the Knight, but the
Ladies haue recouered their health, but <HI>Sparke</HI> and <HI>Ruffell</HI>
are dead, and their burial is committed to <HI>Fleire:</HI> your Lord
&amp; the Knight are committed to prison, &amp; shal to morrow
be arraign'd for the murther, and tride by the Ciuill-lawe,
because your Lord is a stranger, and claimes to be tride by
the law of nations.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan:</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith Signior I am very sorry for my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet,</SPEAKER>
<P>I protest sir so am I for them both.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan,</SPEAKER>
<P>Well Signior ile commit you to God.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pet,</SPEAKER>
<P>Let the whole band of Angels be centinells to your
safetie sweet sir.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Fleire at one doore: and a Seruingman at another.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle,</SPEAKER>
<P>I pray sir doth Iustice <HI>Ferrio</HI> dwell heere?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser,</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes sir a dwells heere.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Are you towards him sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am a poore Gentleman, whose fortunes much de∣pend
vpon his fauours, and indeede sir I am his Clarke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle.</SPEAKER>
<P>I pray sir your name.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seru.</SPEAKER>
<P>My name is Mittimus sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle,</SPEAKER>
<P>Good Maister <HI>Mittimus</HI> I would very willinglie
speake with your Maister.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeede sir hee's not well, but if you please to send
by me the substance of your busines I shall very carefullie
deliuer it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle,</SPEAKER>
<P>Truely Maister <HI>Mittimus</HI> my businesse is but this:
to morrow the Italian Lord, and Sir <HI>Iohn Haue-little</HI> are to
<PB REF="27"/>
be araign'd, and your maister beeing the chiefe Iudge of
the Court, without this presence or licence, the rest can do
nothing: wherefore Doctor <HI>Caius</HI> intreates to know his
pleasure in this businesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mitti:</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir I shall deliuer your message, and will returne
his answere to you presently.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle:</SPEAKER>
<P>Good maister <HI>Mittimus</HI> therein shall you much
obleige me to be thankfull.</P>
<L>O all-directing power yeeld good aspect,</L>
<L>And to my purpose giue a blessed ende,</L>
<L>My intent is good, O let it so succeede,</L>
<L>And be auspicious still to each good deede.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ente: Seruingman with a Ring.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser:</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir my maister hath receiued your message, &amp; hath
sent this Ring as a token to Doctor <HI>Caius,</HI> desiring him,
since my maisters health will not permit him to be present,
to proceede alone to iudgement, and so commends his
loue to him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle:</SPEAKER>
<P>Good maister <HI>Mittimus,</HI> I shall both deliuer your
maisters commendations, and the Ring.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt seuerally.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Lord Piso with a Torch, a Night-cap, and his
Doublet open: In prison.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Piso.</SPEAKER>
<L>Still tonguelesse night put off thy sable robe,</L>
<L>Thou needs not mourne, my villanies were done</L>
<P>By day, thou hadst no hand in them, O I am great, as is a
woman that is neare her time:</P>
<L>And life's the burthen that I beare.</L>
<L>But t'is a bastard for that I am asha'md on't.</L>
<P>The Law I hope is a skilfull midwife, and will soone deli∣uer
me; grim Iustice doe thy worst,</P>
<L>Thy crueltie shall prooue a curtesie,</L>
<L>And baile me out of prison.</L>
<P>Lie there thou selfe-consuming Taper, true patern of my
life, I haue consumde my selfe for others, as thou hast
done for mee, and nowe shee has extinguisht my life as I
this light.</P>
<L><PB REF="28"/>
O how obedient was my bountie, still</L>
<L>To her commaund? my liberalitie</L>
<L>Did fatten mischiefe, and hath made her prowde:</L>
<L>O that too much of any thing shuld be so ill in euery thing</L>
<L>The Suns all seeng eye, with too much vntemperate heate
makes wither what it made to flourish.</L>
<L>The earth being mother to all wholsome hearbes,</L>
<L>With too much fatnesse oft produceth weedes.</L>
<L>A sute of cloath doth keepe the bodie warme,</L>
<L>When richer garments makes the wearer proude.</L>
<L>O, the meanes the sweetest Musicke;</L>
<L>Contentment reuels when that string is toucht;</L>
<L>But O, the time will come she will repent</L>
<L>My death: for when she lookes on vices face</L>
<L>Vnmaske like mine; she will detest and loath it.</L>
<L>For this is truth and euermore hath bin,</L>
<L>None can forsake before he knowes his sinne.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Fleir, Sharke, and Ruffell.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come, come, thou didst but dreame thou wert in
hell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp:</SPEAKER>
<P>I tell thee I was in hell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff.</SPEAKER>
<P>And so was I too, Ile be sworne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle.</SPEAKER>
<P>And how long was't ere thou camest thither?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Me thought t'was long, as long as a suit hangs here
in the Law ere it be ended.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle:</SPEAKER>
<P>But I prethee how broad was the way to hell?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp:</SPEAKER>
<P>As broad as the space between two lines in a Chaun∣cerie
bill.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle.</SPEAKER>
<P>O sir, there's the conscience on't, say the Plaintiffe be
in one line, and the defendant in an other, they being ene∣mies,
wer't either conscience or honestie in the Clearke
to thrust them no neare togither, that they might goe to∣gither
by th'eares? but yfaith what good fellowship was
there in hell?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp:</SPEAKER>
<P>O the diuels are excellent companions, theile drink
your Dutch captains, or Court Ladies spunges.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="28"/>
<SPEAKER>Fle:</SPEAKER>
<P>Who didst see there?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith I saw the foure sonnes of <HI>Aymon,</HI> and they were
Porters euer since there was a companie made of am.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why are there a companie of Porters in hell?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp,</SPEAKER>
<P>O I, the Diuels are but our Apes man.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle,</SPEAKER>
<P>But didst thou see more of them that were damn'd▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, I sawe a Citizen damn'd for refusing a de∣sperate
debt, because t'was tendred him on a Sabboth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle,</SPEAKER>
<P>I hope wee shall haue no more Citizens damn'd
for that fault.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spar.</SPEAKER>
<P>There was a poore mercinarie woman damn'd
because shee forsooke her Trade, and turnd Puri∣tane.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle.</SPEAKER>
<P>And good reason, why coulde not shee haue
kept her Trade, and beene a Puritane, as well as
a Puritane keepe her Religion, and yet bee of her
Trade?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spar.</SPEAKER>
<P>There was a Ladie damn'd because shee neuer
painted: a Puritane for saying Grace without turning
vppe the white of his eyes: A Tailer for neuer ha∣uing
scabbie fingers: A Vintner for making greate
two pennie-woorths of Sugar. But there was a Innes
of Court man damn'd, and I was sorie for him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why was he damn'd?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp:</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas for a small fault.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle.</SPEAKER>
<P>I prethe what wast?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spar:</SPEAKER>
<P>For hauing alwayes money in his purse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle.</SPEAKER>
<P>Were there no Lawyers in hell?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spar.</SPEAKER>
<P>There were none of your great Lawyers as your
Serieants, and Benchers, for they take counsaile of
too manie good Angells to come there: but your young
punie Lawyers, they were in swarmes like Gnats in
Summer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle,</SPEAKER>
<P>Why are there so manie of them there?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas man they seldom conuerse with a good Angell
scarce once in a whole Michaelmasse Tearme, and if a
come a stayes not long with am to feede these soules,
for they are faine to sende am away strayght to
<PB REF="29"/>
pay for the feeding of their Horses, there was a Chamber∣maide
damb'd for keeping her virginitie till shee was mar∣ryed,
and there were many Soldiers damb'd for saying
their prayers when they were drunke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl:</SPEAKER>
<P>But what didst thou see in hell?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff,</SPEAKER>
<P>O, I sawe a Scriuener damb'd for procuring a
Gentleman money Gratis, but I came in an excellent
time.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle,</SPEAKER>
<P>What time wa'st?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff,</SPEAKER>
<P>In a gossipping time, for <HI>Proserpina</HI> was newllie
brought a bed of two twins.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl:</SPEAKER>
<P>Two twins! what were they?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff,</SPEAKER>
<P>A Sergeant and a Yeoman, but shee has put them
out to nurse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle,</SPEAKER>
<P>I prithee where?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff:</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith at the Counter in Wood-street, and the slaues
will sucke alreadie like little Horsleaches.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl:</SPEAKER>
<P>But when will she haue am home, that shee may be
rid of am.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff:</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith shee's an vnnaturall Mother, shee cares not
greatlie if they neuer come home, but the deuill their Fa∣ther
hee loues am well, heele haue am home againe ere
long.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle:</SPEAKER>
<P>Which is the elder Brother?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff,</SPEAKER>
<P>O the Sergeant, the Deuill allowes him the bet∣ter
maintenance, for hee has more to the dressing of his
meate.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, Gentlemen, since by the heauens pleasure
I haue bin appointed to saue your liues, let mee intreate
you to keepe your selues secret till the sequell of this act∣ion
shall neede your presence.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff,</SPEAKER>
<P>Come lets goe, weele onely follow your directi∣ons.</P>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="29"/>
Enter two Iudges with their traine, and
sit downe.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iaylor.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVil't please yee haue the prisoners brought
foorth?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caius.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVee can doe nothing till wee heare from
Doctor <HI>Ferrio,</HI> to knowe his pleasure in these procee∣dings.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Iudges.</SPEAKER>
<P>Was any man sent to him?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caius,</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, <HI>Fleire,</HI> the Lady Floridaes man, which is
not yet returned.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter a Iaylor.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iaylor,</SPEAKER>
<P>Reuerend Iudges: heere's a Doctor at doore de∣sires
admittance.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caius,</SPEAKER>
<P>Intreate him to come in.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Fleire like a Doctor.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle,</SPEAKER>
<P>Learned Doctors, Doctor <HI>Ferrio</HI> commends him
to you, and because sicknesse hath laide so strong a hand
vpon his weake decrepit bodye, which dooth detayne
his presence, hee intreates you to accept of mee in his
place, and as assurance of his earnest desire thereof, he
has sent this well knowne ring as a token to you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caius.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, wee knowe the ring and you are verie wel∣come,
and so I pra'y assume his place.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iaylor,</SPEAKER>
<P>Is it your pleasure the Prisoners be brought
footh.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caius,</SPEAKER>
<P>I, both of them.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Piso Knight, two Ladies, two wenches, Nan and Sue, Pe∣toune,
Fromaga.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caius.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord, you are heere indited of a hatefull
crime, &amp; I am verie sorry to see you in this sort stand here.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="30"/>
<SPEAKER>Pis.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thrice Reuerend Iudges, and therefore honored
Lords, I must confesse, that like a skilfull dancer, I haue
truely footed folly, yet like a learner in my course of life,
trod much out of measure, I haue liu'd like an vnbackt colt
proud and wanton, my tree of life hath borne more leaues
then fruite, I neuer was deboash'd &amp; steard away my daies
enen in a sea of sinne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caius,</SPEAKER>
<P>And in, that sea my Lord, you bore so great a
saile as you haue ouer set your barke of life, and heere you
are accused my Lord, euen of a hatefull crime, so is the
Knight there for poisoning two Gentlemen, <HI>Sparke</HI> and
<HI>Ruffell,</HI> how doe you answere this my Lord?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pis.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas my Lord, this is soone answered, for though
that I haue surfeited on sinne, yet haue I not bin drunke
with blood.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caius:</SPEAKER>
<P>What say you Knight?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni:</SPEAKER>
<P>The crime is great I must confesse my Lord, but I
am sure the proofe can be but little.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cai:</SPEAKER>
<P>Ladies you know moste, and therefore tis fittest
most you speake.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why then my Lord, this is all we can say, this Lord
and knight feasted diuers of vs their friendes, but foure of
vs he drench'd with such a dramme which soone made two
discharge the debt they owd to nature.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pis.</SPEAKER>
<P>O conscience wonldst thou giue me leaue!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fal:</SPEAKER>
<P>And wee no doubt my Lordes, had long ere this
breath'd out our liues like them, but that we had the lesser
quantisie, for being esteemed the weaker vessels, they
thought the lesser blow would breake vs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni:</SPEAKER>
<P>O had not death arrested me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle:</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhy then my Lord, wee thus must now proceede,
they that spilt innocent blood themselues must bleed; but
Ladies I haue heard you had a man cald <HI>Fleire,</HI> what's be∣come
of him?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo:</SPEAKER>
<P>He was sent to Doctor <HI>Ferrio,</HI> and we neuer saw him
since.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl,</SPEAKER>
<P>Doe you know his hand Ladies?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Very well.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle.</SPEAKER>
<P>I pray looke heere then.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="30"/>
<SPEAKER>Flo:</SPEAKER>
<P>This is his hand indeede.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<P>I very perfectly doe know it to be his.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle</SPEAKER>
<P>Why then vppon this hand I heare arrest you both,
vpon your liues.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Both.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who, wee?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle,</SPEAKER>
<P>I, you Ladies, my Lord I pray you, reade this letter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cai:</SPEAKER>
<P><LETTER>
<P>Reuerend Iudges, God wil by some meanes punish
euerie sinne, and though against my will, yet by my consci∣ence
I am enforced to vnmaske my Ladies vilianies, the
murther for which the Lord and Knight are like to die,
was first plotted by them: the two Pages with my selfe did
heare it: the Prisoners in this action, are inforc't by Sacra∣ment
to be secret, and thus intreating heauen in Iustice,
still to ayde you.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Yours <HI>Fleere</HI> a Florentine.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</LETTER></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caius</SPEAKER>
<P>Is this true my Lord?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2, Iudg,</SPEAKER>
<P>They are sworne not to reueale it,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle.</SPEAKER>
<P>But being reueald they may affirme it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Both:</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis too true my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle,</SPEAKER>
<P>Where are the Pages?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Both,</SPEAKER>
<P>Heere my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle.</SPEAKER>
<P>How say you boyes to this letter?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Both,</SPEAKER>
<P>The letter speakes nothing but the truth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle:</SPEAKER>
<P>Wel Ladies, then we heere pronounce this sentence
that you must die among the rest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo,</SPEAKER>
<L>You powers deuine, I know doe plainely see,</L>
<L>Heauens starrie eyes sees all our villanie:</L>
<L>And God in Iustice murther will reueale,</L>
<L>But were I now, my life for to beginne,</L>
<P>Ide be an honest wife to you, wherefore forgiue me deerest
Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pis,</SPEAKER>
<L>Lady, I doe euen as I hope to be forgiuen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Show mercy heauen, my sinnes doe thee offend,</L>
<L>Theres none can say hee's happie till his end;</L>
<L>Forgiuenesse Knight, and since the law on vs,</L>
<L>Hath laid so strickt a hand, O let me be</L>
<L>Thy wife before I die, and were I now</L>
<L>A thousand yeares to liue, I would be honest</L>
<L>Louing none but thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="31"/>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>I doe forgiue you Lady with my soule.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter a Messenger with Letters to Piso.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mes.</SPEAKER>
<P>Long liue my honored Lord and mighty Duke of
Florence.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pis,</SPEAKER>
<P>So a will, as long as't please the Hang-man.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mes,</SPEAKER>
<P>My honored Lord, your Father is deceased, and
the state of Florence by me hath sent their Letters and al∣legiance.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pis.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let them call backe the banisht Signior <HI>Antifront</HI>
whome they &amp; we, and al haue wrong'd: O could I liue but
to inquire him out, in satisfaction of his wronges, ide marry
his eldest Daughter, and whilst a liu'd a should be restored
to his estate, but O hee's—</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Fleire showes himselfe to be Antifront,</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fle.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heere my Lord.</L>
<L>I taxe you to your word, Signior <HI>Antifront</HI> yet liues,</L>
<L>And heeres his elder Daughter whome himselfe</L>
<L>But now condemn'd to die: and heeres the younger</L>
<L>Left for you, the poisoned men are heere a liue againe,</L>
<L>Who did but dreame of death, but yet doe</L>
<L>Liue t' enrich a nuptiall bed to you two,</L>
<L>And now since euerie thing so well doth sort,</L>
<L>Let all be pleas'd in this our comicke sport,</L>
<L>Where's <HI>Petoune?</HI> he shal haue his Mistris too,</L>
<L>He most deserues, for he did hotly woe,</L>
<L>If we part friendes, your hands vnto vs lend,</L>
<L>What was not well, weele next striue to amend.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt. Omnes</STAGE>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
<PB REF="31"/>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

