<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2004-02-15</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Rachel Losh</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Checked for N=""s. Checked for GROUP tags. Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, CLOSER, OPENER, ARGUMENT, EPIGRAPH, SIGNED, BYLINE, etc.). Checked for signatures. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, and UNCLEARs. Corrected ** $s and $word$s etc. of **. Converted __ $$s to GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="[vendor name]". Checked spacing of foreign GAPs. Checked for LBs. Checked for startqs, endqs, oes, q;s, and Qs. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Checked for FIGUREs and decorated initials. Checked for missing-page GAPs. Revalidated. </ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A12149">
<STC T="S">22453</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99852583</BIBNO>
<VID>17910</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>A
PASTORALL
CALLED
THE
ARCADIA.</P>
<P>Acted by her Majesties Servants
at the <HI>Phaenix</HI> in <HI>Drury</HI>
Lane.</P>
<P>Written by <HI>Iames Shirly</HI> GENT.</P>
<P><HI>LONDON,</HI>
Printed by <HI>I. D.</HI> for <HI>Iohn Williams,</HI> and <HI>F. Eglesfeild</HI>
and are to be sould at the signe of the <HI>Crane</HI>
in <HI>Pauls</HI> Church-yard. 1640.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dramatis personae">
<PB REF="2"/>
<LIST>
<HEAD>The Persons of the Comedy.</HEAD>
<ITEM>BAsilius King of Arcadia</ITEM>
<ITEM>Musidorus a Prince disguisd as a shepheard, lover of Pamela,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Pyrocles a Prince disguisd as an Amazon, lover of Philoclea.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Evarchus father to Pyrocles</ITEM>
<ITEM><LIST>
<HEAD>3. Arcadian Lords.</HEAD>
<ITEM>Calander</ITEM>
<ITEM>Philonax</ITEM>
<ITEM>Simpathus</ITEM>
</LIST></ITEM>
<ITEM>Caladolous servant to Musidorus,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Dametas a Rustick shepbeard and Guardian to Pamela and</ITEM>
<ITEM>Philoclea. Cupid.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Masquers.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Thumbe a miller Captaine of the Rebells.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Rebells.</ITEM>
<ITEM>A Messenger</ITEM>
<ITEM>Gynecia the Queene.</ITEM>
<ITEM><LIST>
<HEAD>Daughters to Basilius
and Gynecia.</HEAD>
<ITEM>Pamela</ITEM>
<ITEM>Philoclea</ITEM>
</LIST></ITEM>
<ITEM>Miso wife to Dametas.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Mopsa daughter to Dametas and Miso.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<STAGE>The Scene Arcadia.</STAGE>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="play">
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>A
PASTORALL
CALLED
THE ARCADIA.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus Primus.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Basilius, Philonax and Calander.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Philon.</SPEAKER>
<L><SEG REND="decorInit">S</SEG>Ir yet be gracious and heare them pray</L>
<L>That beg not for their owne, but for your safety</L>
<L>And honor of your state which eclipse</L>
<L>In your long darke and melancholly life,</L>
<L>We want you at the helme.</L>
<L>Our duties bind us tell you tis unnaturall</L>
<L>To bury your selfe alive, the people call</L>
<L>For their owne King to governe, the'ile forget</L>
<L>To pray for you if you continue thus</L>
<L>A stranger to em</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or if not for them</L>
<L>Which every good king makes his care as being</L>
<L>A steward to provide them all earthly blessings,</L>
<L>

<PB REF="3"/>Yet for the other part of you, our Mistris</L>
<L>That sleepes within your boosome, and not made</L>
<L>For such a conversation, returne</L>
<L>And warme your thoughts agen, about which all</L>
<L>Your servants like so many pictures gaze</L>
<L>At one another, but want motion, and take up</L>
<L>Roome ith Chambers of your Court, like Arras</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Philon</SPEAKER>
<L>Have a compassion to our daughters sir</L>
<L>Kill not your hopes in their restraint</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>What cage</L>
<L>Can please the birds Created for skie freedome?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Philon.</SPEAKER>
<L>How can you see your eldest child <HI>Pamel<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI></L>
<L>Spend her best part of time with such a rude</L>
<L>And ignorant hinde as the unbred <HI>Dametas?</HI></L>
<L>A Lady of a high and active soule,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Philon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our duties bids us tell you this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hast thou forgotten</L>
<L><HI>Philonax,</HI> or made a better glosse upon the Oracle?</L>
<L>Should we remaine in Court and let our daughters</L>
<L>Be in the sight of the admiring world</L>
<L>Reade that paper, and be not partiall <HI>Philonax</HI></L>
<STAGE>Philonax reads</STAGE>
<Q><L>Thy eldest Care shall from thy carefull face</L>
<L>By princely meane be stolne and yet not lost</L>
<L>The younger shall with natur<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es blisse embrace</L>
<L>An uncoch love, which nature hateth most</L>
<L>Both these themselves unto two such shall wed</L>
<L>That at a Beere, as at a barre shall plead</L>
<L>Why ile thee a living man they have made dead,</L>
<L>In thine owne seate a forralgne state shall sit</L>
<L>And ere that all these blowes thy head shall sit</L>
<L>Thou with thy wife adultery shall commit.</L></Q>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Canst blame me now? I should reioyce to see</L>
<L>My daughters happy mothers, but since their</L>
<L>Fate must be ripened with my blood, their pride</L>
<L>Rooted in my grave, and that untimely, tis</L>
<L>

<PB REF="3"/>Wisdome to keepe 'em vrigins. I me resolu'd</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Gynaecia, Philoclea and Pyrocles.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your queene and Ladies</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vanish all discontent, Madam this place</L>
<L>Is emptie of all royall entertainement</L>
<L>Your worth may Challenge, but since fate allowes not</L>
<L>A Courtly life which best may answer your</L>
<L>High birth spirit, let your vertue guide you</L>
<L>To accept of what we tender,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>This my Lord</L>
<L>Exceeds all merrit heere, it was the blisse</L>
<L>I aimd at to be acquainted with your goodnesse</L>
<L>I am your humble servant</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Such a title</L>
<L>Would rather become me, call me so Lady</L>
<L>And stile me above Kings, while I write yours</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Philon.</SPEAKER>
<L>If your grace</L>
<L>Could call him from this life you'd melt the hearts</L>
<L>Of your subjects into prayers for you</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gyne.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thanke your care but hees mexorable</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas deere princesse can you brooke these grove:</L>
<L>Has not a pallace something more of pleasure?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>This shall be so to mee while tis n<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y fathers,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>I ha not seene a goodlier person, how</L>
<L>Came she admitted▪ <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> gracious with the king</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>She has a charme to win from all the world</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Philon.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have read the <HI>Amazons</HI> discrib'd so</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<L>These lippes had he that robd the dragon of</L>
<L>The golden Apples, but once seene he would</L>
<L>Ha wish'd to ha gatherd fruit heere, and esteemd</L>
<L>The gaine of one sweet kifse reward sufficient</L>
<L>For all his twelve hard labors</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir your grace</L>
<L>Is pleasantly dispos'd to make my person</L>
<L>The subject of your mirth</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas</SPEAKER>
<L>And had those Creatures,</L>
<L>Booke blinded men, that dreame of other worlds</L>
<L>

<PB REF="4"/>Tell of <HI>Elizian</HI> blessings, know the joyes</L>
<L>Are in your love they would have lost themselves</L>
<L>As I have done in speculation</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>You make me blush to heare you</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Theres no action</L>
<L>Dares so affright your blood, to talke, why Lady</L>
<L>There be those men and women great and good</L>
<L>Have found no shame in telling of their loves</L>
<L>Nay in the acting</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Give me leave to tell you</L>
<L>You are not modest if I understand you</L>
<L>A King give breath to such foule thoughts,</L>
<L>Your every action should be a starr</L>
<L>To guide your subjects, if you loose your piety</L>
<L>What wickednesse have they not heence for</L>
<L>If the devotion of your service be</L>
<L>To such a friend as Lust (as what name else</L>
<L>Can it deserve) let those whose hearts are lost</L>
<L>In sinne be tempted to dishonor, I</L>
<L>Abhor the thought, pardon me royall sir</L>
<L>I hope these are but trialls, if I thought</L>
<L>There had been such a levity in men</L>
<L>Thus to provoke you</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Smooth thy brow agen</L>
<L>Or I shall neede no other punishment</L>
<L>Theres death too much in that; <HI>Philocle<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>That name sounds all my comfort, and I must</L>
<L>Dispaire to tell her so, I was to blame</L>
<L>To be so peremptorie, would I were agen;</L>
<L>To shape my answer</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Noble Lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<L>That smile has put me out, oh looke thus ever</L>
<L>I was studying a new complement to begg</L>
<L>Thy excuse</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you brought no offence there needes none sir</L>
<L>I must suppose your love, love is noble chaste</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<L>You will finde that hereafter, oh <HI>Zelmane.</HI></L>
<L>

<PB REF="4"/>Would thou couldst tell the meaning of my sighes</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>You can expresse them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not I</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Choose another to speake them for you</L>
<L>And yet I want an or at or to tell you</L>
<L>What I would say, how ere I seeme</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dost blesse me</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Theres something wants a tongue, but for your passions</L>
<L>I should not thinke they would carry so much discord</L>
<L>To any virgin care delivered by a woman</L>
<L>There is a Way to meete a gentle audience.</L>
<L>At least not harsh disdaine, did your faire daughter</L>
<L><HI>Philo<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lea</HI> the volume of all sweetnes</L>
<L>Pleade halfe your suit, altho it borderd on</L>
<L>Something not altogether just, her tongue</L>
<L>Might perchance guide it, but I am confident</L>
<L>Your ends are noble</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Theres a lightening yet</L>
<L>Of comsort, happiest Lady I will study.</L>
<L>How to be worthy of this grace,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gyne.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are expected at the pastoralls</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Philon.</SPEAKER>
<L>We take our leaves my Lord againe beseeching</L>
<L>Your pardon for our bouldnesse to reduce you</L>
<L>To your owne spheare of greatnes</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe you continue</L>
<L>Faithfull to your employments, and deserve of us</L>
<L>And of your Country; come <HI>Zelmane</HI></L>
<L>There are some sports which you must grace</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>I waite a servant to your commands</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come sweete <HI>Zelmane</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come sweetest of thy sex</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis pittie nature.</L>
<L>Made thee not a man, this complement</L>
<L>Would then become you</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt▪</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Pamela and Mopsa.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pam.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Mopsa</HI> you are to coy in my opinion</L>
<L>Tho I confesse your beauty may deserve</L>
<L>As much as any; <HI>Dorus</HI> tho he be</L>
<L>

<PB REF="5"/>Your fathers servant, hee's a hansome shepheard</L>
<L>And not to be dispised.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<P>Dispised, cannot a virgin love a young man I pray but she
must dispise him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pam.</SPEAKER>
<P>You should then with some smiles encourage him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<P>Smoyles, let me alone to smoile, and something else
when we are alone; if I thought he did not love me, I know
What I know</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas poore man he cannot sleepe for you he saies,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay and I were a bed with him he should not sleepe
so long as his eyes were open, I'de watch him for that, but doe
you thinke my father would let us couple in matrimony as they
say, he has never a sonne but I and I am his onely daughter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Make no scruple of that, if you can finde in your heart to
love him, in the name of <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>upid</HI> goe together, for ought I perceive
your father houlds a good opinion of him, marry I know not how
your mother is inclinde</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Musidorns.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whoope my mothers a scould</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heres your sweete heart▪</L>
<L>Looke you make much of him, poore Gentleman</L>
<L>How love is abie to transport, who could</L>
<L>Expect so rich a guest in that poore dwelling</L>
<L>Oh how ere the windes compell him, or the streame</L>
<L>Into whose troubled waves he has launch'd forth</L>
<L>This way he steeres his love, yet I seeme ignorant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>My deerest <HI>Mopsa</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<L>Deere; I never cost you anything</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know not</L>
<L>At what expence of fortunes were I able</L>
<L>I should be willing to make purchase of you</L>
<L>But I'me sure you have already cost my heart</L>
<L>And yet I find yours made of Marble</L>
<L>Which neither pitty nor my prayers can soften,</L>
<L>Sweete Madam pleade for me, one gracious word</L>
<L>From you would make me happie, let one beame</L>
<L>Shoot fro<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> your eye, and it will strike a spring</L>
<L>Into that frozen peece of earth, and make it</L>
<L>A bower for love to spo<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> in, 'tis in you</L>
<L>

<PB REF="5"/>To unarme her noble heart, there's too much steele</L>
<L>And gentle love in vaine attempts to fasten</L>
<L>The softer blowes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pam.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Mopsa</HI> take heed, your Shepheard can speake well</L>
<L>And if he be honest <HI>Menalcus</HI> brother</L>
<L>And heire, I know no reason why you should</L>
<L>Thinke scorne of him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<L>But for all his queint speeches Ile keepe my honestie</L>
<L>close enough I warrant you</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why should you be so cruell, nature made</L>
<L>Your face the onely object of mans wonder</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<L>Does my face looke like a flapiack?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is't possible there can be a soule so hard</L>
<L>So vnrelenting dwell in that faire body?</L>
<L>If you knew the truth of my affection and with what</L>
<L>Religion it lookes upon your vertues.</L>
<L>'T would teach your eye compassion, gracious princesse</L>
<L>Let the distressed <HI>Dorus</HI> gaine this mercy</L>
<L>From you that with the blessednes of your</L>
<L>White hand reaching to <HI>Mopsa</HI> this poore toy</L>
<L>Which late I found my love may cherish hope</L>
<L>At last to be accepted</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh fine what's that Madam?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pam.</SPEAKER>
<L>You must yet be a little coy to receive it</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<L>I wonot have it, and he wou<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d give it me</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pam.</SPEAKER>
<L>A rich Iewell the figure of a Crabfish</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>The trew emblem of my loves pace which lookes another way</L>
<L>To that it moves, she cannot but distinguish</L>
<L>Whether I would direct my heart, her eyes</L>
<L>Are fixt upon't, and my poore soule could heere</L>
<L>Star-gaze for ever</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pam.</SPEAKER>
<L>By force not choyce—all his desire is <HI>Mopsa</HI></L>
<L>Tow in your grace by my presenting it</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile take it for your sake, I wonot thanke him</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>She has no apprehension, with what</L>
<L>A calme and carelesse temper does she give it</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Dametas</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dame.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam <HI>Pamela,</HI> oh are you there, tis well</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whats the matter?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="6"/>
<SPEAKER>Dame.</SPEAKER>
<L>I me out of breath, let me walke my selfe a little</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pam.</SPEAKER>
<L>What haste does tire you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tire me, I am no woman, keepe your tires to your selfe</L>
<L>Nor am I <HI>Pericles</HI> prince of <HI>Tyre.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pam</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe beleeve it, heaven make you an honest subject,</L>
<L>For a wise one, I dispaire to see you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Am I the subject of your talke? But I give you leave to
use your tongue, y'are a woman, <HI>Dorus</HI> what make you ideling
heere? is the field dung'd as I gave Directions, and the Calfe with
the white face brought home to execution?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<P>I was carefull in my dutie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Beleeve me governor there is much hope of your servant,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, governour becomes you, I like it well when you carry
an M vnder your girdle, our govern, he will do pritty well in
time, when I have taught him the manners of the Cart, he begins
whistle in tune already, and can curry favour with the horses, but
now I remember my selfe I forgot what I came hither for,
oh dee heare tis the king your fathers pleasure and mine, that you
make haste to the lodge.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile attend</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<P>There will be gambolls to please my Lady <HI>Salamandor.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pam.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Zelmane</HI> you would say.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<P>I care not what you say, but if you meane to heare the
Dances and see the fine songs you must make haste; <HI>Dorus</HI> you
shall have leave to shake your heeles, looke you be mannerly, and
shew a cleane calf, <HI>Mopsa</HI> whats that you ha got there?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<P>A fine thing our man <HI>Dorus</HI> game, he saies tis a fish</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis a Codds head ist not, much came how you by this</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<P>Following the plow I found it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Would all my acres were sowne with such, vmh dores he
throw his stones at thee already, well set forward, if thou diest
before me <HI>Dorus</HI> Ile make some body mine heire; if I out
live thee, I wonot say what legacie I meane to bestow upon
<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hee, Continue thy dutie <HI>Dorus</HI> and follow me with a re∣verence.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Basilius, Gynecia, Pyrocles, Pamela, Philoclea,
Mopsa, Musidorus, a Shepheards.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ladies our revells wants the state and glory</L>
<L>

<PB REF="6"/>With which the Court delights might charme your senses</L>
<L>Our sceane is naturall but interpret fairely 'twas meant</L>
<L>A cure for times sicke feathers, and your mirth,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Virtue will prompt you to</L>
<L>Accept what was intended for your service</L>
<L>Yet 'tis within my wishes to salute you</L>
<L>With other testimony of your welcome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>I kisse your white hand,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Every touch conveies a firce spirit through my blood</L>
<L>I shall betray my suffering, and through my eyes</L>
<L>Let out my heart, <HI>Philoclea</HI> sit</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wilt please you rest your selfe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dwell heere for ever</L>
<L>I am now but one degree from heaven,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Since you imagine you are so neere, it is no sin</L>
<L>I hope to entreate you staie with us a little, I would</L>
<L>Wish tho to make you blest with too hastie a remove▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are all goodnes, oh that I durst but give</L>
<L>Some liberty to my imprisoned thoughts</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gy.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Philoclea</HI> you hinder the faire stranger.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pardon me that am her trouble rather</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<L>She should want vertue to call you so, but they begin</L>
<L><HI>Dametas</HI> is the steward for this dayes mirth I see.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Dametas</STAGE>
<L>And meanes to bring in the first course.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Cupid</HI> is blind some say but there are lyes</L>
<L>Abroad, for <HI>Cupid</HI> never wanted eyes</L>
<L>He is a Deity with bow and arrow</L>
<L>And he can pirce with it the very marrow</L>
<L>And never hurt the bones, ist not a wonder.</L>
<L>That flaming Ice should cut mans heart in sunder,</L>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Cupid</HI> Shepheard Musedo. Mopsa and Miso:</STAGE>
<L>Behold the Dandiprat that liv'dat Court.</L>
<L>But is come hether to make country sport</L>
<L>A wooddy god; but yet a very Coult</L>
<L>Among the maids who feele his furious boult.</L>
<L>Now <HI>Cupid</HI> speake thy selfe or while they play</L>
<L>Sing if you please I ha'not more to say.</L>
<L>

<PB REF="7"/><HI>Cupid.</HI> Tell me tydings of my mother.</L>
<L>Shepheards, and be <HI>Cupids</HI> brother</L>
<L>Downe from heaven we came together</L>
<L>With swanns speede came she not hither?</L>
<L>But what Lady have I spyde.</L>
<L>Iust so was my mother eyde</L>
<L>Such her smiles wherein I dwelt</L>
<L>In those lips have I been felt</L>
<L>Those the pillowes of her brest</L>
<L>Which gave <HI>Cupid</HI> so much rest.</L>
<L>'Tis she 'tis she make holyday</L>
<L>Shepheards Carroll Dance and play</L>
<L>'Tis <HI>Venus</HI> it can be no other</L>
<L><HI>Cupid</HI> now has found his mother</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gy.</SPEAKER>
<L>This was your poetrie, <HI>Zelmane</HI></L>
<L>You are beholding to him, he would make</L>
<L>You another I see,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gynecia</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gy.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am silent—<HI>Philoclea</HI> is too neere</L>
<L>I am not well'oth sudden, breake off your mirth</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<L>What ayles <HI>Gynecia?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gy.</SPEAKER>
<L>My heart is sicke</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Forbid it heaven</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Retire, come my <HI>Zelmane</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>I attend</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Looke to your charge <HI>Dametas</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pam.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have a pretious time; will you pace it governor?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Trot, amble or gallop Ile runne in your hand Lady.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come <HI>Dorus</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your humble servant</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art cruell.</L>
<L>To an innocent bosome love, there is no way</L>
<L>Within thy power to save me, oh <HI>Philoclea</HI></L>
<L>Where shall I coole my heart, oh if there be</L>
<L>One shaft can kill, good <HI>Cupid</HI> ayme at me.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="7"/>
<HEAD>Actus Secundus.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Gynecia and Miso.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<P>I warrant you Madam they shall have good lucke if they
whisper together in my hearing,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gy.</SPEAKER>
<P>Where is <HI>Zelmane?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Miso.</SPEAKER>
<P>In some of the Arbours, she tooke a Lute abroad with her
but I left <HI>Philoclea</HI> with her father</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gy.</SPEAKER>
<P>Prithee be carefull and watch them well good <HI>Miso</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Miso.</SPEAKER>
<P>They shano't scape me, Ile watch their waters narrow∣lie
I warrant you.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gy.</SPEAKER>
<L>I see through his disguise 'tis so, and love</L>
<L>Hath put this shape on him for <HI>Philoclea,</HI></L>
<L>In what a miserable flame I burne!</L>
<L><HI>Zelmane</HI> thou hast stolne.</L>
<L>My vertue from me, I ha'not power to thinke</L>
<L>A harmelesse thought, ha Musique,</L>
<STAGE>Musique. Song Pyrocles sings Enter Pyroclos.</STAGE>
<L>From whence breathes that sound? it is <HI>Zelmane.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>What miserable accident brought her?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Zelmane</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam I hope you'l pardon</L>
<L>The trespasse of a rude hand and voyce, I meant not</L>
<L>This for your curious care</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gy.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twas harmony</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>It was no light aire I'me sure</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeede it carried something me thought</L>
<L>Of sorrowes descant, I heard love i'nt too</L>
<L>Who is so happie to deserve a memorie</L>
<L>But in your sigh, come whoe's your servant?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have no servant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay then I see you can dissemble, my husband</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Py.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam I hope</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay I am so farre from Iealosie I should not</L>
<L>Be angry to see you both a bed together</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>How Madam</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why I can love you too, come thou sha't be my bed-fellow</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="8"/>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am not worthy</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beleeve me I could take as much delight</L>
<L>In thy imbraces as my husbands, why</L>
<L>Are we so nice to one annother, I</L>
<L>Am a woman, are not you so too?</L>
<L>Why should we not be bould then, I have a mind</L>
<L>To call thee Mistris, Yes and Ile disguise.</L>
<L>My selfe in some queint shape to court thy love:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Disguise</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay do not blush: thou shalt be a man</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your discourse appeares.</L>
<L>Strange to me Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gy.</SPEAKER>
<L>As you would to me</L>
<L>And yet you may as easily perceive</L>
<L><HI>Gynecias</HI> mindas I distinguish you</L>
<L>Through all your clouds, <HI>Cupid</HI> doth dictate rarely.</L>
<L>To those that come to schoole to him, instruct</L>
<L>With hansome shaddowes to deceive the eye</L>
<L>But cannot change my substance, I have a sense</L>
<L>Can looke beyond the superficiall barke</L>
<L>Come y'are transparen't</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam what dee meane?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gy.</SPEAKER>
<L>What meanes <HI>Zelmane</HI> to be igonrant</L>
<L>When a Queene pleads for love, my heart will not</L>
<L>Allow more circumstance; doe not question</L>
<L>How you became reveald, but pitty her</L>
<L>Whose boosome is tormented with those fires</L>
<L>Thy smiles the only greater flame can quench.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray heaven, you have your perfect senses.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then I must be plainer, and be witnesse love</L>
<L>I am compell'd, be witnesse modesty,</L>
<L>I now must blush for thee more then my selfe,</L>
<L>A man, and be so cruell to a Lady</L>
<L><HI>Zelmane</HI> either give consent I shall</L>
<L>be welcome to thee, or I vow by heaven</L>
<L>To tell <HI>Basilius</HI> what thou art, I have</L>
<L>Patience to let him court thee as a woman</L>
<L>But when he see's his love abuse his privacie</L>
<L>

<PB REF="8"/>And daughters so dishonor'd hadst thou a thousand</L>
<L>Lives they were all forfeited by this</L>
<L>So desperate in trusion, thinke uppon't</L>
<L>A woman I have lost thee, wheither will</L>
<L>Thetempest of my fate inforce my tongue</L>
<L>Yet be thou kinde <HI>Zelmane</HI> if thou takst</L>
<L>A glory in my suffering, <HI>Philoclea</HI></L>
<L>Does that name startle you? <HI>Philoclea</HI></L>
<L>My rivall now</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your rivall</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come I am familliar with every thought</L>
<L>Your deere saint shall repent it, for this hand</L>
<L>Shall take againe the unluckie life I gave her:</L>
<L>Turne not <HI>Gynecia</HI> fury</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am lost</L>
<L>In the same minute I am found, I prithee</L>
<L>Doe not forsake me heart, I never had</L>
<L>More use of thee, great Queene can you forgive?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gy.</SPEAKER>
<L>And aske thy pardon, but beleeve me t'was</L>
<L>Your strangenes did compell me to this language</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Py.</SPEAKER>
<L>I never thought that pitty of annother</L>
<L>Could be a reason to betray my selfe</L>
<L>But you have throughly charm'd me, and I must</L>
<L>Deliver up my thoughts, the truth is Madam</L>
<L>I am a man, and if you dare beleeve me</L>
<L>A prince, I must confesse beside <HI>Gynecia</HI></L>
<L>Since I came heither I have had some sprinckling of</L>
<L>I know not what affection to <HI>Philoclea</HI></L>
<L>For how could I imagine such a blessednes</L>
<L>From you, but if you mocke not</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ioyes reward your pittie</L>
<L>Oh pardon the over chardg'd <HI>Gynecia</HI></L>
<L>Whose error may be yet made more excusable</L>
<L>By the immortall name of love</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>This grace is worth more then <HI>Zelmane,</HI> and yet I</L>
<L>Have nothing but my selfe to give you for it</L>
<L>A small but free guift, bestow me as you please</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gy.</SPEAKER>
<L>My soule is narrow to receive this wide blessing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="9"/>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>But me must be wise</L>
<L>It were not safe to be observ,'d stand I</L>
<L>Discover'd to none else?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gy.</SPEAKER>
<L>To none</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Py.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then know</L>
<L>I want no apprehension of what</L>
<L>True lovers would desire, but your honor is</L>
<L>My owne, if shortly to secure 'em both</L>
<L>You let me study an opportunity</L>
<L>Ile bring your wishes home, and blesse my starrs</L>
<L>That pointed me the glorious fate, we are</L>
<L>Already interrupted</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Basilius and Philoclea.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe this my deere <HI>Philoclea,</HI> and leave</L>
<L>My cares to thee, Ile call <HI>Gynecia</HI></L>
<L>Away, and leave you both together, how</L>
<L>Faireth the best <HI>Zelmane?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Still your servant</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gynecia.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>I cannot rule my eyes they will betray</L>
<L>My cunning to <HI>Gynecia</HI> if she goe not</L>
<L>Hence quickly</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>How is it with my vertuous <HI>Amazon?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Philoclea</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let her alone, they have some busines sweete</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gy.</SPEAKER>
<L>What busines can they have together?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why art thou troubled, thou would'st be jealous</L>
<L>Of me I see, were I in privat with her,</L>
<L>Come let 'em alone a while</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay you and spare not I would imploy <HI>Philoclea</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall obay me now, I prithee walke</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi,</SPEAKER>
<L>My father sweete <HI>Zelmane</HI> to whose command</L>
<L>I owe my life</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>First let me give my life</L>
<L>Vp to these lips, and take a new one from</L>
<L>This kisse, oh deere <HI>Philoclea</HI> containe</L>
<L>All other breath I know thy fathers minde</L>
<L>Already, and must now beseech thy patience</L>
<L>

<PB REF="9"/>To a short story which I must deliver</L>
<L>Or dy before thee, if it be within</L>
<L>My desteny to be condem'd by you</L>
<L>At least know whom you sentence; I am</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>What? I feare not well</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cannot your eyes discover me, have I a shrowd</L>
<L>To hide me from <HI>Philoclea?</HI> did the kisse</L>
<L>I gave thee last convey no secret to thee?</L>
<L>There was a spirit in my lip assur'd me.</L>
<L>To save the tedious trouble of my language.</L>
<L>I heard it whisper something, did it not?</L>
<L>I would be fraine undone</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good heaven forbid</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>You wonot understand me yet <HI>Philoclea</HI></L>
<L>Then Ile undoe my selfe, I am not what</L>
<L>I seeme <HI>Zelmane;</HI> but—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>What?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L>A thing not worth the name, if you frowne on me, a man</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>A man, good heaven<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have tould you all the worst</L>
<L>If it be no offence to name a prince</L>
<L>Whose memory your owne breath oft hath sweeten'd</L>
<L>I dare be call'd <HI>Pyroclos</HI> of <HI>Macedon</HI></L>
<L>Transform'd by loving your faire selfe to this</L>
<L>Feminine shape, if now I have not sinn'd</L>
<L>Above forgivenes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh <HI>Philoclea</HI></L>
<L>Come not too neere I charge you; I would chide.</L>
<L>But dare not, would you had not tould me this</L>
<L>Indeed you were to blame, I must not heare you</L>
<L>Excuse your selfe</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>She must not leave me thus</L>
<L>But she returnes</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have lost my selfe already,</L>
<L>And love is but a blinde guide to direct</L>
<L>My virgin steps, I faine would reply something</L>
<L>But feele a tremblinge in my voyce, <HI>Zelmane</HI></L>
<L>My father, what account shall I give him</L>
<STAGE>Enter Basilius</STAGE>
<L>

<PB REF="10"/>I have said nothinge he commanded</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<L>She smiles</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord I see you can use the advantage</L>
<L>And I did arme you against my selfe; I did not</L>
<L>Thinke when I advis'd you make <HI>Philoclea</HI></L>
<L>Your advocate, she could so much have wonne</L>
<L>Vpon me, but my counsell has betray'd me,</L>
<L>Pray thinke me not immodest, if my words</L>
<L>Doe fall too rudely from me, your faire daughter</L>
<L>Whose tongue would lay a charme uppon the gods,</L>
<L>Hath gain'd all this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<L>The gods reward her for it</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Was this his plot?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<L>A thousand blessings overtake my child</L>
<L>But not a word, not a word <HI>Philoclea</HI></L>
<L>To thy mother</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have learnt my duty sir</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beshrew your haste</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Remove, convey thy selfe away deere girle, Ile follow</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>My heart is full, and tho my tongue denies</L>
<L>Him farwell, he may reade it in my eye.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<L>I knew thou couldst not choose at last but give</L>
<L>My heart an audience; I am not my selfe</L>
<L>With the imagination</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Of what?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<P>Of any thing; come I allow thee modest, it is not
fit we should say our pleasures, sweete but act them</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are to violent my Lord, I shall</L>
<L>Repent my freedome, if you give no limit</L>
<L>To your desires, if you doe love your servant,</L>
<L>Husband your flame that it may last</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<L>It shall</L>
<L>Pardon me deere <HI>Zelmane,</HI> I have a stock</L>
<L>Of blood, tho you may thinke it could is high</L>
<L>And active as the veynes of promising youth</L>
<L>I weare this snow but a disguise</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Poore winter,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<L>My haires are black at roote, and shall grow up</L>
<L>

<PB REF="10"/>Faire as the Ebony and curle themselues</L>
<L>Into a thousand pretty caves for love</L>
<L>It selfe to sit that best delights in darknes</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>This will be strange.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis you that worke these miracles</L>
<L>Vpon <HI>Basilius,</HI> as I came heither</L>
<L>I felt a score of yeares drop off, which hung</L>
<L>Vpon my locks</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>A score of haires you meane: tis molting time</L>
<L>Containe your selfe a while, you have</L>
<L>A jealous queene, and yet it goes against my Conscience</L>
<L>To wrong so sweete a Lady, pray my Lord</L>
<L>Thinke better ont</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<L>This Does inflame me more</L>
<L>Be not so cruell to remember her</L>
<L>Thou must preserve my life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Py.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well I ha thought a way</L>
<L>Shall perfect all without suspition</L>
<L>There is a cave hard by which nature made</L>
<L>Intending well to lovers, thether will I</L>
<L>With licence of your grace pretending</L>
<L>To exercise a few dayes some devotions</L>
<L>We <HI>Amazons</HI> have obligation to</L>
<L>At some convenient houre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<L>May I come to thee</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile give you notice in some evening</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Zelmane</HI> now thou dostravish me</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Py.</SPEAKER>
<L>You may with ease secure all at the lodge</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most excellent</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>I imagin sir the rest but doe not come till I desire you</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be not tedious then, I will prepare all this</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hope you doe not</L>
<L>Conclude me impudent that I encline</L>
<L>To doe this for you, by my hopes of a blest</L>
<L>Eternitie nor love nor lust ere tempted</L>
<L>My thoughts to yeild thus much to any man</L>
<L>Be carefull of my honor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh devine <HI>Zelmane</HI> keepe my soule.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="11"/>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Philoclea</HI> mine</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Musidorus</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh my deere <HI>Pyrocles</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>How ist deere Cozen</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Never till now could you salute me happy</L>
<L>The gods have beene propitious</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr,</SPEAKER>
<L>Will she know thee yet?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>There's nothing wants to make me perfect blest</L>
<L>But to heare thee pronounce thy love as fortunate</L>
<L>The envious clouds which interpose themselves</L>
<L>Like a darke Curtaine ore <HI>Pamelas</HI> face.</L>
<L>Are drawne away and I enjoy her smile</L>
<L>She does beleeve my proofes, sweetely excusing</L>
<L>Her long neglect, and promiseth as much</L>
<L>As I dare aske: sheel' trust me with her person</L>
<L>I want but opportunity to deceive</L>
<L>Our waking Dragons;—and in good time <HI>Dametas.</HI></L>
<STAGE>Enter Dame</STAGE>
<L>Away you shall know all my fate hereafter,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>I joy in thy successe, pray thou for mine.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where is this rascall <HI>Dorus</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whether were I best to tell the King ont first or seeke out</L>
<L><HI>Dametas,</HI> hee'l never be able to spend it, there may be gold</L>
<L>Enough to purchase halfe <HI>Arcadia</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vmh, what's that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile seeke him out at all adventures; oh s<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r, pray is this</L>
<L>Gold—and this and this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha gold, yes very good gold, where hadst it</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall heare more hereafter</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Dorus,</HI> honest <HI>Dorus,</HI> put on thy hat, where where, hadst it</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did you never heare of one <HI>Aristomines?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<L>He was banish'd <HI>Arcadia</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Was he rich</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Infinite rich, so rich</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis so, belike he there had all his treasure</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<L>What treasure, where i'st honest <HI>Dorus</HI> tell me</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are my Master and may be my Father</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<L>My sonne <HI>Dorus, Mopsa</HI> is thine, and she were made of
as pure gold as this, thou shouldst touch her, and melt her</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well I see it was ordained to make you rich</L>
<L>

<PB REF="11"/>In dutie Ile discover it, and yet—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Drm.</SPEAKER>
<L>Out with it good <HI>Dorus</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well—sitting beneath an oake that shall be namelesse</L>
<L>I chanc'd to turne up some turff with my mole-spade</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<L>With thy mole spade, what then</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>I saw a yellow brightnes peeping out oth' ground, which</L>
<L>when I came to examine I pr<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>v'd this mettall, I this was the first,</L>
<L>y'are sure 'tis gold, you shall pardon me for the rest but if these</L>
<L>will do you any pleasure, or twentie more</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay good honest <HI>Dorus</HI> proceede.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why the truth is I suspect where a great treasure has been</L>
<L>Long buried, these it seemes were scatter'd when the rest</L>
<L>Went to the pit-hole.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<L>But where is this place good <HI>Dorus?</HI> thou hast no more</L>
<L>About thee</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>No but if you please to furnish me with tooles Ile trye</L>
<L>The bottome; I digd till I came to a stone, whose inscription</L>
<L>Promis'd something worth a mans labour</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did it sound</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Melodiously a goulden tune</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where, where, thou maist tell me thou knowest I</L>
<L>Am secret</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>For <HI>Mopsa</HI> sake I will reveal't, you know▪</L>
<L>The oake where you first met me</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha very well</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>On the right side of that same spreading tree</L>
<L>Lies all this riches</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<L>As th'art honest</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>As I hope to be deere <HI>Mopsa's</HI> husba<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d, Ile get strong tooles</L>
<L>And bring you better proofe</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay <HI>Dorus</HI> stay, let me see</L>
<L>As I intend to be your father <HI>Dorus</HI></L>
<L>And so in <HI>Mopsas</HI> name make you my heire</L>
<L>Of all my wealth, good <HI>Dorus</HI> I am yet</L>
<L>Till things and things be done your Master <HI>Dorus</HI></L>
<L>Beside that ground is mine, the Oake is mine</L>
<L>Where under lies this treasure, I am Lord</L>
<L>Lord of the soyle my <HI>Dorus,</HI> of the soile</L>
<L>

<PB REF="12"/>I am content to be a ground for you</L>
<L>To build to hopes on <HI>Dorus,</HI> but my ground</L>
<L>No man shall dig or build on but my selfe</L>
<L>On such as this, be there a myne</L>
<L>Of Coyne or vncoyne mettall it is mine</L>
<L>All may be yours annother day my <HI>Dorus.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know my duty sir and cannot thinke</L>
<L>The gods had ere a lotted my free mind</L>
<L>To serve you but for some strange end</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<P>In this thou shewst it, keepe all close, not a word
<HI>Dorus,</HI> I take no leave be carefull my good <HI>Dorus</HI> of my
young Madam, 'tis a charge I turne over to thee, over looke her
well.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>I meane to doe it doubly</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam</SPEAKER>
<L>How, ha you a duble meaning?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>I meane with double care</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Honest <HI>Dorus</HI> 'tis the last service I shall put thee to</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hope so to</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now to the Oake my golden land marke</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Load a horse with tooles sir</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mattocks and shovells</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hookes and ladders.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Spade and Pickaxes</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ropes and daggers; youl have no helpe</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<L>No no, a mans owne toyle</L>
<L>Sweeter the profit makes in his owne soyle.</L>
<STAGE>Exit</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe thy wayes for the Lord a'th soyle</L>
<L>Theres one blocke out a'th way the golden flie,</L>
<L>Has caught this trowte, my jealous Mistris I</L>
<L>Hope she ore heard not</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mis.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh that my eares had beene long enough to have heard
some of there pretious Knaverie</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<P>It were but charitie to tell her on't, little does my Mistris
Thinke what a flesh flie my Master is,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mis.</SPEAKER>
<L>What saies the Knave</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tho she be a little stricken in yeares she is hansome enough</L>
<L>For as good a man as <HI>Dametas,</HI> and he to runne neighing</L>
<L>A this fashion after a blowse, and then put me to make excuse</L>
<L>

<PB REF="12"/>For him, 'tis not right.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh fidious Rascall, I thought there was some roguerie,</L>
<L><HI>Dorus</HI> as thou com'st of a woman tell me</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>What forsooth</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mis.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh naughty man to vse an honost woman the wrong way
thus, have I beene married so many yeares, and carried my selfe
like his lawfull wife uprising and downe lying as they say, so
even and jumpe with his desires to be thus handled, but Ile be
reveng'd it shall fall heavie vpon his head for this I warrant him,
nay I did alwaies suspect him for a co<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<P>What meane you forsooth,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mis.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come I ouer-heard somewhat to my griefe, and therefore
leaue your bogling and your trim tram tricks you must not flap
me oth mouth with fleering and with flams whilst he</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<P>Claps vp another betwixt the—a ha mistris mistris but you
say you overheard, and therefore if you know whether he is gone
you may come two houres hence time enough to prevent the
blow.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mis.</SPEAKER>
<P>If thou lookest to have my daughter with, marke what I
say</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<P>With fathers marke and mothers marke, and every mark
about her</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mis.</SPEAKER>
<P>If you conceale any thing in this case, thou knowst no case
of her, nay tho thy teeth water out the liquor of thy life, thou
shouldst not get a bit, the worst bit of her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<P>Be more charitable</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mis.</SPEAKER>
<P>Or if thou chance to get her gainst my will ile teach her
a tricke of the mother shall make thee curse her and all the brood
she came one,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<P>What is Charita to me, I know you heard him name her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mis.</SPEAKER>
<P>Charita.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will discharge my conscience and yet if you over∣heard
us without my telling, you know where hee appointed
to meet her this evening at <HI>Mantinea</HI> at her fathers in <HI>Ondemi∣on</HI>
streete,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mis</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Ondemion</HI> street?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<P>I doe not betray him now if you provide so happily to
take em at it mistris at it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="13"/>
<SPEAKER>Mis.</SPEAKER>
<P>I at it, how I itch to be at it</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<P>Saddle your mare.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mis.</SPEAKER>
<P>They shal not scape with halfe an eie betwixt them.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Pamela and Mopsa.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<P>I have given her the bells and she will flye to the de∣vill
—here comes the tother I ha given her phisicke already fit
for her constitution and now it works.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pam.</SPEAKER>
<L>How comes it <HI>Mopsa</HI> that you are so taken</L>
<L>So lifted up with high conceit?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who I</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes <HI>Mapsa</HI> you, dee thinke I cannot Iudge</L>
<L>By outward gestures and your lookes what joy</L>
<L>Doth inwardly possesse you</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who me</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes you againe, and it were not over bouldnesse</L>
<L>To request some knowledge of the cause</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<P>Rest you content; you are a Princesse borne I might
have beene so to, some body may be a Queene before you, make
what you can of that</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh fate how's this</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<P>There is a tree, and there is things worth wishing, and
some may wish and wishes may be had make what you can of
that too</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>To my wish it workes</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pam.</SPEAKER>
<L>But <HI>Mopsa</HI> may I not beseech a word</L>
<L>That may be to my understanding</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<P>You may know more hereafter, but till then I must pre∣sume
upon your Princely patience to keepe your Chamber, it is
now my raigne and doe not dare to follow</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not I, when you are drawne up to majesty</L>
<L>I can but wish you graciously would then</L>
<L>Remember the obedience of your handmaide</L>
<L>That first submits her selfe to your Command.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<P>I faith I will <HI>Pamela,</HI> and reward it, goe in sweete Lady,
on my Royall word I will,</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Pamela.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>She has spide me</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<L>Happy <HI>Dorus</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>What will my <HI>Mopsa</HI> say when she has climb'd</L>
<L>

<PB REF="13"/>The tree of happines?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<P>I I the tree, when I climbe that tree, <HI>hony Dorus</HI> tell me
it over agen, my deere bird what did <HI>Iupiter</HI> to <HI>Apollo.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<P>Vpon some falling out I tould you <HI>Jupiter</HI> threw <HI>Apollo</HI>
out of heaven and his deitie taken away he was faine to live upon
the earth and keepe <HI>Admetas</HI> Cattell, in the time of his service
being sent to fetch abreede of beasts out of <HI>Arcadia,</HI> in this very
desart he grew fainte and wearie; and would needs rest himselfe
in the boughes of an Ashen tree.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<P>The tree we wot of; on sweete bird</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Apollo</HI> in that tree calling to minde his quarrell with
<HI>Iupiter</HI> became very sorrowfull, and pittifully complayning to
his father, asking him mercie for having offended him was from
that tree receiv'd into his golden spheare, and made a god agen</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh brave</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Having the perfect nature of a god</L>
<L>Never to be ingratefull he then granted</L>
<L>A double life to <HI>Admetas,</HI> and because</L>
<L>That tree was chappell of his happy prayers</L>
<L>To it he gave this quality</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now it comes</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>That whosoever sat downe in that tree</L>
<L>In like estate and sort as he did then</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh now now now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Should forthwith have there their wish</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh the tree, the tree, the tree</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<P>The king vnderstood thus much by Oracle; and tried
himselfe but being neither heardman as then <HI>Apollo</HI> was, nor of
the race which is necessarie, delivered this secret to your father
but made him sweare to wish by his direction; for his owne bene∣fit
<HI>Dametas</HI> tould it me, and is now gon to furnish himselfe with
a scarlet Cloake for in that he must be mufled just as <HI>Apollo</HI> was,
I might now prevent'em all and be king my selfe, but what have
I to wish more then the love of <HI>Mopsa</HI> which since without
more charming force you yeild me; Ile fit you with a cloake and
then wish what you will your selfe</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile be Queene or <HI>Apollo</HI> shall never looke me in the face
agen, quickly sweet <HI>Dorus,</HI> come muffle me I long to be Queene,


<PB REF="14"/>
and my father shall aske me blessing.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus Tertius.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Rebells and Thumbe</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>COme my masters let us be resolute, is there any man
That will justifie himselfe to be sober amongst us?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>No hang sobriety</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>We must be valiant, the King I say agen has left us, and since
He scornes our company for my part I scorne to be his subject</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>I I scorne subjects, Ile be an Emperor</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>It is time to looke into the government, none but Gentle∣men
are of his Counsell, I see no reason since the Countrie is 'ours
but we should have a stroake in the state.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>That was bravely spoke my bully, stroke, heby <HI>Mars</HI> his
Gauntlet spoke like a souldier, I doe not like the Carriage of the
secret Counsells</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nor I nor any body</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Take heede my Masters</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>Lets heare <HI>Thumbe</HI> the Miller</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thu.</SPEAKER>
<P>We met together to drinke in honour of the Kings birth∣day
and tho we have tickled the Cannikins, let vs be merrie and
wise that's my opinion, no treason, the King is an honest Gentle∣man,
and so is the Queene.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>Very wisely spoken.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>But shall be govern'd by <HI>Philonax':</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who knowes but he has made away the King</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Th.</SPEAKER>
<P>Made away the King, who honest <HI>Basilius,</HI> aske the King
who has made him away, by this hand if I thought they had made
him away I would make some body away, tho I hang'd fort,
but neighbors for my owne part I will joyne with you in any
thing that is honorable, dee marke honorable; but I say still I
am cleare of opinion it is not a misse to be merry and wise
Gentlemen, my name's <HI>Thumbe,</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="14"/>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>I Tom</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Th.</SPEAKER>
<P>And Ile be a your side howsoever</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>A great spirit</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shall I speake for you</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<P>I I agreed you shall be Captaine</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why then let me alone; I will know a reason why hee
has left the government without our consents to depose him, 'tis
wisely spoken mybrave men 'oth common-wealth, we will have
other lawes and the old shall be executed</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>I I hang the old ones</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis a discredit for any subjects as we are to have a King as
if we were not able to governe our selves</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap</SPEAKER>
<P>Stroake up thy forehead thou wert borne to be a statesman,
Be rul'd by me and weel have no justice in <HI>Arcadia</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>How</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>No justice, why should we loose our liberties, and being
free men, upon any occasion suffer our selues to be bound over</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Th.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gentlemen Citizens it were very good you would take
into your consideration the statute against drunkennesse</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>It shall be lawfull for any man to be drunke without
forfeiting or paying anything to the poore</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Th.</SPEAKER>
<P>Very good, every man drinke away his estate, and then
charity begins at home,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>No man shall marrie</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>That's worse then the statute against two wives</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap,</SPEAKER>
<P>For every woman shall be common</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>Every woman common, what shall we doe withall the
proper women in <HI>Arcadia</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>They shall be common too</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh'rare, and what shall we doe withall the prisons</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Set'em a fire 'twill warme the Citie when there is cold
doings</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>What with the prisoners</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Put'em in possession of their creditors lands, they are the
only men fit for authority; for no men are us'd worst, and they
will know the better to domineere, nay weel have admirable
lawes, but who shall be this Embassador to the King</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>4.</SPEAKER>
<P>Me me choose me Captaine,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="15"/>
<SPEAKER>Th<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></SPEAKER>
<P>Choose you Captaine, Haberdasher of small wares, choose
you a Capon, Ile be the Embassador, ever while you live let a
bould man be embassador, and one that has a braine, I will not be
mealc mouth'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well said Miller</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>And because we will be wise</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Th.</SPEAKER>
<P>I I be merry and wise, ever while you live be sober and
discreete.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Say weattend heere to do our duties</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>Duties oh base</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></SPEAKER>
<P>Say so we must, heel not come forth else</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>4.</SPEAKER>
<P>What if I could his highnes there was a dance to be pre∣sented
we are furnish'd with our noise still</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Th.</SPEAKER>
<P>I I, I doe love this noise withall my heart</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>Excellent, get you behind the trees with your instruments,
and tune 'em ready, the new friske we danc'd at <HI>Enispies</HI> to day
will serve rarely as the Prologue, away; but Captaine what shall
we doe with the Kings daughters</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile have one</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<L>And Ile ha the tother our Captaine shall ha the Queene</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>And what shall we have.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thereare Ladies about the Court will content you</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thu.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will have both the Kings daughters, and he that speakes
against it—</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>They fight</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Thumbe</HI> valiant <HI>Thumbe,</HI> all spirit no mutinie no mutinie
all of a faction together by the eares for a peece of venison</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Th.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will have both the Kings daughters or else I shall not
be satisfied.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>First let vs know the Kings resolution, and if we like not
our conditions, the hares a foote; and every man take what course
he please in my Lords Parke
<STAGE>Enter Basilius, Gynecia, Pyrocles, and Philoclea.</STAGE>
But stay the King vmh</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>Speake Captaine</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>If it please your Maiesty, what was it resolu'd upon</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hees out, let me come to him, prithee doe thou tell him
thy minde, that delicome wench has made my teeth water</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>And drown'd thy tongue, a Company of bashfull shrimpes;


<PB REF="15"/>
if I but open my mouth, I say no more</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Th.</SPEAKER>
<P>King, by your leave; which is the King, my eyes twinckle,
we have beene playing the good fellowes to celebrate your
majesticall birth day, will your grace see a song</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>A dance</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Th.</SPEAKER>
<P>Or a dance, alls one, our seete are in tune, strike up behinde
the tree, you are the King and I am the Miller, ther's all the
difference, sweete Ladies my name is <HI>Thumbe</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<P>This is rudenesse</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gy.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pardon their simplicity</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Th.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile have that wench she lookes like <HI>Hercules,
Omnes,</HI> Stand</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>We have intorrogations points to put to you</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<P>Treason, treason,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Barborous Villaines</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Basilius runnes in, a bell rings, Philoclea, and Gynecia hid<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
themselves, Pyrocles fights with them, Basilius comes
in with a two handed sword, after some skirmish
Enter Philonax and Calander with a guard
the Rebells beaten off.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where is <HI>Philoclea</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heere art thou not hurt <HI>Zelmane.</HI></L>
<L>My soule at every stroake made against thee</L>
<L>Was leaving my palebody</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Py.</SPEAKER>
<L>Deere Madam are you safe</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thinke I ha pepper'd some of 'em, <HI>Philonax</HI> 'twas not
amisse you came, but <HI>Zelmane</HI> and I should have made a shift</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<P>You alone my Lord, were an army against such reeling
vallors, I did not thinke you could ha bestir'd your selfe
so well</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<P>And I were in an other place alone with thee I could best<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
my selfe better</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would you would consider yet to quit</L>
<L>This dangerous kinde of life</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Had not the valiant <HI>Amazon</HI> it seemes, defenc'd your person</L>
<L>Ere the troopes ariv'd, it might have prov'd too fatall</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gy.</SPEAKER>
<L>He plaide the man indeede, the King is troubled</L>
<L>And thinks me Iealous of him, lasse old man</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="16"/>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more</L>
<L>Waite upon our Queene and daughter, weel follow</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<L>I am wounded</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>How</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<L>By thee <HI>Zelmane</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>I see your passions are the same and I</L>
<L>This might resolue to waite for you in the Cave</L>
<L>If you when your <HI>Gynecia</HI> is a bed</L>
<L>And fast a sleepe, (be sure of that) will please</L>
<L>To put your selfe to a short travell, I</L>
<L>Shall not expresse your welcome, but</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Deere as my soule I apprehend my comfort</L>
<L>One kisse in earnest of the million</L>
<L>Thou shalt receive, but carrie it close <HI>Zelmane</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Musidorus, and Mopsa.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is the Tree</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh let me kisse it toes</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Best loose no time</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<P>Haile upon haile sweete tree, Crowne thee and all thy
wishes, Oh <HI>Dorus</HI> up womee <HI>Dorus,</HI> up womee, up womee,
up womee <HI>Dorus,</HI> teach mee to clymbe the right way prithee</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<P>You must be muffled in the cloake, so now remember
your instructions, make first your invocation to <HI>Apollo</HI> as I tould
you, which being done, imploy your minde withall devotion to
his deity, untill you heare a voyce call three times on you by your
name, tho you should thinke your father mother <HI>Pamela</HI> or my
selfe talke to you answer not they are spirits that would delude.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vnder three <HI>Mopsas</HI> Ile not talke to 'em, Ile not be cozend</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold there and youl' be happy</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile aske a king to my hus<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>and, and thou shalt be he</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your invocation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<L>Into the greate eares of Apollo</L>
<L>Now let my invocation hollow</L>
<L>Oh thou that lightest all the day</L>
<L>For some to worke and some to play</L>
<L>By owle light now</L>
<L>Incline a gracious eare to me</L>
<L>

<PB REF="16"/>Thus▪ muffled in thy wishing <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></L>
<L>Singing whoope whoope who<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></L>
<L>And pardon this my subtilty</L>
<L>That I deceive the passers by</L>
<L>I in this bough</L>
<L>Doe use the accentes of that fowle</L>
<L>Because I would be thought an Owle</L>
<L>With whoope whoope whoee</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Pamela.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>She has done her invocation</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can she not heare us</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<P>She shall heare us, but I have taken order with her eyes
and understanding too, sheel not beleeve us, thou lovely bird
Madge howlet</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's a spirit in the voyce of <HI>Dorus,</HI> but Ile not answer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>See <HI>Dorus</HI> and <HI>Pamela</HI> both are heere</L>
<L>Whilst old <HI>Dametas Miso,</HI> and their deere</L>
<L>Daughter are stragled forth, they both together</L>
<L>Are taking now their flight, and who knowes whether</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pam.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is too plaine</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh cunning Divells, but Ile not heare nor speake a sillable</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>If thou canst finde a tongue to tell <HI>Dametas,</HI></L>
<L>Make knowne unto his wisdome he is gull'd</L>
<L>Take courage Madam the way lies faire before us</L>
<L>And abarque already prepard cries come a bour'd</L>
<L>Farewell Howlet</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Musidorus and Pamela
Dametas sings within</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whoope whoope whooe—Hey I heare another singing
spirit in my fathers voyce, bee't <HI>Apollo</HI> himselfe, under three
<HI>Mopsas</HI> Ile not speake</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Dametas</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is the tree, and heere the earth is broken</L>
<L>The certaine signe left by my trusty <HI>Dorus</HI></L>
<L>The mouth of the rich treasure I salute thee</L>
<L>And kisse the hole from whence shall come my gold</L>
<L>Which being done blithly to worke I fall</L>
<L>My hand is in the moone-shine, and up goes all</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="17"/>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whoope whoope, whooe</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam,</SPEAKER>
<P>What's that; an Owle, good Mis<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>is <HI>Margerie</HI> I am busie
<Q>Art thou poore and wouldst thou be
advanc'd by wealth to Dignity
doe not thinke it then vnmeete
to stoope with hands beneath thy feete
'Tis not with hand over head to be found
no <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o thou must stoope
though thou holdst
up thy poope
and grable for't in ground</Q>
Ha what's this, my hand is in the Hony pot I thinke, vmh vmh
I doe not like the softnes, I did groape for harder stuffe, if
this be gold 'tis liquid, and yet too thicke to be potable as they
say, it has a kinde of weft me thinks if I have not lost a sence
upon the sudden, I smell, call you this gold finding</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<P>I have an extreame list now so I have saving your pre∣sence,
divell would restore your sence</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<P>What's this, a written parchment this may be the inven∣tory
of all the treasure.
<Q><L>Who hath his hire hath well his labor plac'd</L>
<L>Earth thou didst seeke, and store of earth thou hast</L></Q>
Howe's this</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whoope whoope whooe</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<P>As sure as this is my owne nose, I am stinkingly abus'd</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha ha ha,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Can Madge Howlets laugh, that laugh was like my
Daughter <HI>Mopsa</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<P>There's one time, againe againe sweete <HI>Apollo</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis her voyce what makes she there, now the dread
vengeance of my deere fatherly curse, light over th'wart thee
thou aukeward helding <HI>Mopsa</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<P>There's two times, <HI>Mopsa</HI> once more and 'tis <HI>Apollo</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="17"/>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Will you not answer in the Divells name <HI>Mopsa</HI> I say, oh
are you come</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>he strickes she falls.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes yes divine <HI>Apollo</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile unhoode yee wheres <HI>Pamela</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thanke your Deitie</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Speake now and tell me</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<P>Answer my wishes as 'thou art <HI>Phebus,</HI> as thou art
<HI>Apollo</HI> tho in the likenesse of the Clowne my father,
grant me my wishes first, I aske a King to be my husband.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<P>What talkest thou of a King; the King will hang thy
father if <HI>Pamela</HI> be gon</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let him be hang'd I care not, but let <HI>Dorus</HI> be a King,
and let him be my husband good <HI>Apollo</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shee's starke staring mad, hast thou forgot thy father,
where is thy wit</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<P>I doe not aske for wit, I tell thee, let me have a sufficient
husband and let him be a King</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou shal't have thy bellifull of husbands</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh that, that, that</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Miso</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Miso.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile at you both thou ribald villaine and thou harlot</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Miso</HI> my spouse falne mad too</L>
<L>Thou wot not beate thy mother</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Miso.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh me</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<P>I defie her and thee and thou beest not <HI>Apollo,</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh who has gulled us all, deere <HI>Miso,</HI> tender <HI>Mopsa</HI>
heare me, before I open my mouth, art not thou <HI>Miso,</HI> and
thou my daughter <HI>Mopsa,</HI> oh we are all vndone we are all
vndone</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<P>Are not you god <HI>Apollo</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<P>No as ever I hope to see him or any of his fellowes
in the face againe, I am mortall <HI>Dametas</HI> and I thinke thy fa∣ther,
I am sure I am by thy mothers side, where is <HI>Pamela</HI> all this
while, whoes at home.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<P>As sure as you are my father and you my mother, theres
No body at home</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shee's gon, shee's gon</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Dorus</HI> and <HI>Pamela,</HI> or two feends with their voyces
pastby whilst


<PB REF="18"/>
I was in <HI>Apollos</HI> tree</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Miso.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Apollos</HI> tree</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Cast off your wonder I am not such an asse, but I perceive
We are gull'd</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<P>So Divell <HI>Dorus</HI> tould me</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Miso.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh me they are gon, was this your care</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay then where was your owne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fall not at odds bout that, but goe with me</L>
<L>And helpe me to scape the gallow tree.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt▪</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Gynecia and Pyrocles, with a Taper.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did I not counterfeit an infirmitie</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rarely, how love will prompt his votarie</L>
<L>The King suspects not what we purpose</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Las poore man, how carefull he seem'd of my health</L>
<L>And councell'd me to bed</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>I smil'd to see it</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gy.</SPEAKER>
<L>So soone as he is a sleepe expect me</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay, oth suddaine I ha thought upon a way</L>
<L>Blessed blessed minute.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gy.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's the device</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shan'ot goe to bed</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not I</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>God Genius</L>
<L>I will not trust our worke to fortune if</L>
<L>You should want cunning in your passions</L>
<L>Or he should wake unhappily and finde</L>
<L>You absent, all were lost, to prevent this</L>
<L>You shall not come to me if there be danger</L>
<L>'Tis fit I be expos'd Ile take your place</L>
<L>And disaray me for <HI>Basilius</HI> bed.</L>
<L>De'e marke, muffled up for your suppos'd</L>
<L>Distemper, let me alone to counterfeit</L>
<L>Dulnes, and when his sences are chain'd up</L>
<L>In sleepe, I will come downe toth cave to you</L>
<L>But take my mantle if any of <HI>Dametas</HI></L>
<L>People meete you</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gy.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will visit bu<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> my Closet</L>
<L>And follow thy instructions,</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="18"/>
<SPEAKER>Py.</SPEAKER>
<L>If there be any starrs are kinde to love</L>
<L>This night shoote forth your golden heads, be thou</L>
<L>Bright moone propitious; on all eyes that would</L>
<L>Betray our flight, cast out a fullen mist</L>
<L>And hide thy silver cressent in a cloud,</L>
<L>But to our passage be a gentle goddesse</L>
<L>And borrow of thy brother yet more light</L>
<L>The day may spare it, <HI>Musidorus</HI> is</L>
<STAGE>Enter Gynecia with
a golden Violl.</STAGE>
<L>Embark'd already with his Mistris,</L>
<L>If I obtaine <HI>Philocleas</HI> consent</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gy.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Zelmane</HI> now I am prepar'd</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Haste to the Cave, expect,</L>
<L>Your servants visit</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gy.</SPEAKER>
<L>And my happines</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Py.</SPEAKER>
<L>How rudely vice becomes us, here's a Lady</L>
<L>Whom never fame yet blemish'd, now the example</L>
<L>Of <HI>Cupids</HI> tyranie, love transformes us all</L>
<L>And fooles our understandings, I pittie her▪</L>
<L>Now are <HI>Basilius</HI> thoughts in motion</L>
<L>And hurry him to the same licentiousnes.</L>
<L>There is warme snow I see, he delaies time.</L>
<L>In hope to finde his Queene asleepe, whose place</L>
<L>I must assume for once, love dwells upon</L>
<L>A cliffe and all the waies to our enjoying</L>
<L>Are difficult and ragged,</L>
<L>But I forget, <HI>Basilius,</HI> I must</L>
<L>Compose me for his bed, I shannot be</L>
<L>Much troubled, good old King he wishes me</L>
<STAGE>Lutes
Recorders
Exit.</STAGE>
<L>Good rest I know, and secure dreames, oh see</L>
<L><HI>Philoclea</HI> what waies I come to thee</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Basilius.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<L>These sounds may charme her into slumbers sweetly</L>
<L>Oh steale into her, hang upon her heart,</L>
<L>Come fixe your gentle raptures in her soule</L>
<L>That it may take delight to be orecome</L>
<L>And never wake the body, till <HI>Basilius</HI></L>
<L>Returne with happy Conquest from <HI>Zelmane</HI></L>
<L>Or if there be a leaden god of sleepe.</L>
<L>

<PB REF="19"/>Heere let him shake his wings and then dispatch</L>
<L>A Herra<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ld to the silent house of dreames</L>
<L>To bring one hither happier then the rest</L>
<STAGE>Enter Philoclea</STAGE>
<L>To entertaine my melancholly Queene; oh <HI>Philoclea</HI></L>
<L>Thy mother will excuse thee this nights dutie</L>
<L>Doe not disturbe her, yet your voyce and Lute</L>
<L>'Ith next Chamber may procure her sleepe</L>
<L>That done without more ceremony goe</L>
<STAGE>Exit Philoclea</STAGE>
<L>To bed, so so my bloud begins to move</L>
<L>Shee's fast, I heare her, and the musique ceast,</L>
<L>Now to <HI>Zelmane.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Agen loude
Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Philoclea.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'me troubled, and dare not goe to bed</L>
<L>There's some thing whispers to my soule this will</L>
<L>Will be a fatall night, my mother is not well</L>
<L>I must needs see her—ha, the gods protect me</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Pyrocles</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>If there were any treason meant against</L>
<L><HI>Philoclea</HI> her prayers were vainely offerd,</L>
<L>Since h<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r owne innocence is protection</L>
<L>As powerfull as the Gods, I bring no horror</L>
<L>To fright your blood, dee not know me Lady</L>
<L>I was <HI>Zelmane,</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Was<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have been</L>
<L>So watched by your Ielous mother</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>But I forget</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>What meane you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>To make fast the doores</L>
<L>If I could barre all the aire out saving what</L>
<L>Your breath should draw, for should I live by that</L>
<L>You would not chide my care</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>You make me tremble.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you cannot forgive me punish pray</L>
<L>This rudenes with my death; I prostrate to</L>
<L>Your feete my sword, and call you to my brest</L>
<L>To meete your anger, at this distance beg</L>
<L>I may behould you, but when you shall finde</L>
<L>

<PB REF="19"/>In the dissection of my heart, whose name</L>
<L>Hath fill'd it, and with what religion there</L>
<L>My thoughts adore your memory, too late</L>
<L>It may invite your teares, can faire <HI>Philoclea</HI></L>
<L>Thinke I have a soule that dare be wicked to her?</L>
<L>Such lookes would charme a ravisher, and throw</L>
<L>Ice through a Satires blood, but a man chaste</L>
<L>Already it drawes up to the simplicitie</L>
<L>And nature of an Angell, oh <HI>Philoclea</HI></L>
<L>I am so farre from being ill my selfe</L>
<L>In such a sensuall way, that although time</L>
<L>And this faire opportunity might tempt</L>
<L>And excuse wanton heate, I should repent</L>
<L>Forget to, love your selfe, if you but with</L>
<L>One thought so treacherous to your virgin honor</L>
<L>Should give consent to enioy you, it hath snow</L>
<L>Vpon my blood <HI>Philoclea,</HI> whose flowings</L>
<L>Are Chast as Christall: dare you trust me yet</L>
<L>To kisse your hand, my lips shall gently touch it</L>
<L>Nor will I leave a breath to staine the whitenesse</L>
<L>Pray be not fearefull.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sin did never yet</L>
<L>Prophane that voyce.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>When it sounds lustfully</L>
<L>Your hate, a punishment next the wrath of heaven</L>
<L>Strike my heart dead—be pleas'd to rest a little</L>
<L>And if you dare vouch safe me to sit so neere you▪</L>
<L>I have much to tell you</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know not what to say, where is my father</L>
<L>I had a mother too, this Chamber they</L>
<L>Vs'd to call their's</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are safe <HI>Philoclea,</HI></L>
<L>Let not your cheeke looke pale, their absence wrought</L>
<L>For such a minute doth encourage me</L>
<L>To tell you now or never you must shew</L>
<L>There dwells a pittle in you, oh looke smooth</L>
<L>On him whose life and fortunes you may now</L>
<L>Advance or ruine ever, if you can</L>
<L>

<PB REF="20"/>Remember who I am, and what your vertue</L>
<L>Hath made me suster, thinke me worthy of</L>
<L>A life, let it begin from your consent</L>
<L>To love poore <HI>Pyrocles,</HI> 'tis in your power</L>
<L>To be no more a prisoner to this rude</L>
<L>And solitarie dwelling, such a brightnes</L>
<L>Is lost in caves, extend your arme and reach</L>
<L>A throane where seated with becomming greatnes</L>
<L>You may disperse with moving of your eye</L>
<L>An influence beyond the starrs, and quicken</L>
<L>A world that waites to be your creature</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pyrocles</L>
<L>For so you call your selfe, and such I dare</L>
<L>Beleeve you are, for falsehood cannot dwell</L>
<L>A neighbor to that tongue although I might</L>
<L>Demand with reason, and my dutie first</L>
<L>What does concerne my parents, such a truth</L>
<L>Shines in your language, and such Innocence</L>
<L>In what you call affection, I must</L>
<L>Declare you have not plac'd one good thought heere</L>
<L>Which is not answerd with my heart, the fire</L>
<L>Which sparkled in your bosome long since leap'd</L>
<L>Into my brest and there burnes modestly</L>
<L>It would have spread into a greater flame</L>
<L>But still I curb'd it with my teares, oh <HI>Pyrocles</HI></L>
<L>I would thou wert <HI>Zelmane</HI> agen, and yet</L>
<L>I must confesse I lov'd thee then, I know not</L>
<L>With what propheticke soule but I did wish</L>
<L>Often, thou were no man, or I no woman</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou wert the comfort of my sleepes</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>And you</L>
<L>The object of my watches, when the night</L>
<L>Wanted a spell to cast me into slumber</L>
<L>Yet when the weight of my owne thoughts grew heavie</L>
<L>For my teare dropping eyes, and drew these Curtaines</L>
<L>My dreames wert still of thee, forgive my blushes</L>
<L>And the imagination thou wert then</L>
<L>My harmelesse bed fellow</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="20"/>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>I arive too soone</L>
<L>At my desires, gently oh gently drop</L>
<L>These joyes into me, least at once let fall</L>
<L>I sinke beneath the tempest of my blessings</L>
<L>And you swell my heart too fast</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>If yo<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> be <HI>Pyrocles</HI></L>
<L>You will rest satisfied with this confession</L>
<L>You onely shall obtaine my love</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Although my soule acknowledge this a blessing</L>
<L>Such as no service can reward enough</L>
<L>There remaines something, something which your honor</L>
<L>May easily consent to in this absence</L>
<L>Of both your parents whom with severall promises</L>
<L>Of my returne, I have already sent</L>
<L>To 'th Cave where they in vaine this night expect me</L>
<L>We must for sake this place, I have provided</L>
<L>For our conueiance to my fathers kingdome</L>
<L>If after all these arguments of love</L>
<L>You dare trust <HI>Pyrocles</HI> to convey you thether,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi,</SPEAKER>
<L>I dare give thee my life, but pardom me</L>
<L>This is not safe, thus seeking to assure.</L>
<L>You may vntimely happen loose <HI>Philoclea</HI></L>
<L>My dutie binds me not to rob my parents,</L>
<L>Such a departure may undoe their comfort<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>As y'are a prince perswade me not commit</L>
<L>So unnaturall a trespasse, weel expect</L>
<L>And satisfie our young desires till time</L>
<L>Mature our joy, I could content my selfe</L>
<L>To looke on <HI>Pyrocles</HI> and thinke it happines</L>
<L>Enough, or if my soule affect variety</L>
<L>Of pleasure every accent of thy voyce</L>
<L>Shall Court me with new rapture, and if these</L>
<L>Delights be narrow for us there is left</L>
<L>A modest kisse, whose every touch conveies</L>
<L>Our melting soules into each others lipes,</L>
<L>Why should not you be pleas'd to looke on me</L>
<L>To heare and sometimes kisse <HI>Philoclea</HI></L>
<L>

<PB REF="21"/>Indeed you make me blush</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>What an Ecclips</L>
<L>Hath that vaile made, it was not night till now</L>
<L>Looke if the starres have not withdrawne themselves</L>
<L>As they had waited on her richer brightnes.</L>
<L>And missing of her eyes are stolen to bed,</L>
<L>What world of beauty is behinde that cloud</L>
<L>But keepe it still conceal'd, and let the creatures</L>
<L>When they shall misse day (for the same without</L>
<L>Thine eyes will glimmer like a petty taper)</L>
<L>Feare to be lost in darkenes, and expect</L>
<L>No light to follow, but from those wide flames</L>
<L>Which heaven hath threaten'd to destroy the world,</L>
<L>When thou hast frighted us renew againe</L>
<L>Our state and cure againe the fainting vniverse</L>
<L>One looke restores all—ha, <HI>Philoclea.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>There's something that sits heavy on my forehead</L>
<L>I know you cannot but be noble, pray</L>
<L>A little sleepe, if I exceede three minutes</L>
<L>Prithee wake me</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, I doe not like</L>
<L>Her sences should be snatchd away so strangely</L>
<L>'Tis an ill omen, I should trespasse much</L>
<L>Gainst manners, to disturbe her, beside she</L>
<L>Did make it her request whose will is sacred,</L>
<L>Then gently may she sleepe, and yet if she</L>
<L>Draw out this slumber to any length my hopes</L>
<L>Are blasted, if I loose this opportunitie</L>
<L>Of flight, no hope hereafter can releeve us</L>
<L>We are both undone, she sleepes still, I was not</L>
<L>Quicke enough to perswade her resolution</L>
<L>So necessarie, yet looke up <HI>Philoclea,</HI></L>
<L>No, then enjoy thy dreame, and let us try</L>
<L>The kindnes of our fate, pitty a harsh</L>
<L>Sound should disturbe thy <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oft repose, I would</L>
<L>But dare not steale a kisse for feare to wake her,</L>
<L>And yet my loude voyce may be more offensive</L>
<L>Our soules are knit I see into one love</L>
<L>

<PB REF="21"/>Then 'tis but reason they should exercise</L>
<L>Both the same act, why doe not I sleepe too</L>
<L>The mist is falne already, if I but dreame of her</L>
<L>My slumbers shall be happy</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>he sleepes</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Dam<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tas as from a Vault.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<P>There be more wayes to the woode then one, she may
be in her sisters Chamber, I may thanke my acquaintance with the
Buttery and a trap doore for this passage; shee has shut me out of
doores of all: vmh a sword I had rather it were <HI>Pamela</HI> naked, I
durst undertake to handle her with lesse feare; vmh <HI>Philoclea;</HI> 'tis
she and this is-no—this is not <HI>Pamela,</HI> she was a woman, unlesse
she be crept into breeches since I left her, no 'tis a man, heere is no
tarrying for me; and he were not soundly a sleepe, my smell were
enough to wake him;—treason treason</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Py.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, what voyce is that, who cryes out treason?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Pyrocles</HI> what's the matter?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nothing</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Within.</SPEAKER>
<L>Treason, treason.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Harke, ist not treason, my sword, my sword</L>
<L>Is gon, we are betray'd, some theefe has been</L>
<L>Within the Chamber, yet the doores are safe▪ ha</L>
<L>Lets see, search every where, alas <HI>Philoclea</HI></L>
<L>If now I must be ravisht from thee, how</L>
<L>Can there be charity enough on earth</L>
<L>To pitty me, they die but once who still</L>
<L>Dispaire of blisse; but the Fares twise destroy</L>
<L>A lover whom they kill so neere his ioy.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus Quartus.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Rebells.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>COme my bloods since there is no hope of our pardons
let us be honest out-lawes one to another, and doe
all the mischeife we can, we are Masters of the Woods, and
we will domineere like Lords of the soyle; I say we will live,
we will eate and we will drinke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="22"/>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would I were at my forge againe</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Arcadia</HI> shall be thy Anvile smith; and thou maist live
to beate</L>
<L>Great men to dust</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<L>Some of them are so rotten they will save us a labor</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Be resolute and strike the iron while it is hot, where is the
little miller</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Thumbe</HI> the miller is cut off</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who can helpe it, be not crest falen, but shew your selues
Cockes of the game, weel make the state send for us home, and
agree to our own conditions, let vs therefore play the theeves
manfully</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>And so be hang'd honorably</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hang hang ng, we defie the lawes and we will execute
when we list in our owne quarters we will rob man woman and
child</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>Do you fight with the men, and let me alone with the women.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>And <HI>Thumbe</HI> had he beene alive he had been a fit match for
the children</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter 4. Rebell.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>4.</SPEAKER>
<P>A prise a Captaine, I see a Gentleman and a Lady
strike into a grove hard by, their horses are for their better be∣havior,
already bound to a tree, follow me and Ile conduct</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Without noyse or tumult lets steale upon them</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Musidorus and Pamela.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pam.</SPEAKER>
<L>This grove is all one bower, nature her selfe</L>
<L>Must be delighted to dwell heere, the Sunne</L>
<L>Can shoote no beame upon us through this Arbe<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Tho he does rage abroad</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>The heate betrayes</L>
<L>The Sunne is angry Madam to see you</L>
<L>Whose brightnes takes all wonder from his shine</L>
<L>And leave him a pale starr.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pam.</SPEAKER>
<L>You complement.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you not weary Madam</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pam.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall never</L>
<L>In thy societie, yet we may re<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t</L>
<L>A little in this shade, oh <HI>M<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></HI></L>
<L>He should be enemy to vertue now</L>
<L>

<PB REF="22"/>To cherrish one suspectfull thought of thee</L>
<L>Some wild licencious Prince had now <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> me</L>
<L>And carelesse of his owne ruin'd my honor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>It were not simple theft but Sacriledge</L>
<L>To rob you of one peacefull thought, if any</L>
<L>Service already have obtaind so much</L>
<L>Trust I am so familliar with mine owne</L>
<L>Desires, that hereafter Ile deserve to keepe</L>
<L>Your faire opinion of me, lust could never</L>
<L>Intrude himselfe a guest heere, I should not</L>
<L>Love mine owne eyes, had they been but tempted</L>
<L>To see an unchast picture with delight</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pam.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's that behinde the trees?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nothing, the birds are dancing on the leaves</L>
<L>Call'd heither by the musique of your tongue</L>
<L>Those that are silent doe but listen to</L>
<L>Your voyce to mend their singing</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Still methinkes I heare annother noyse</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is your feare</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pam.</SPEAKER>
<L>There's some thing whispers</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall I tell <HI>Pamela</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray if you can</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is the winde that would</L>
<L>Steale through the boughes to give you more refreshing</L>
<L>Whom the trees envie, I doe heare it murmer</L>
<L>To be kept from your lips which it would kisse</L>
<L>And mixing with your breath catch odors thence</L>
<L>Enough to sweeten all the wood, there can</L>
<L>No other danger enter heere</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>The Rebells cease upon Pamela</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pam.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are betray'd helpe</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, villaines, y'ad better lay violent hands</L>
<L>Vpon your mothers</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let your courage coole, and heare us you were best</L>
<L>If you doe love this Gentlewomans life.</L>
<L>Put up your toole, dee see this b<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>dkin sir</L>
<L>With it, Ile punch her heart, if you but offer</L>
<L>A blow at any of my traine, Ile doo't</L>
<L>As I am true Rebell and for the more security</L>
<L>

<PB REF="23"/>Deliver up your whinyard to our use<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Or Ile make an oylet-hole presently</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe not resigne your sword but use it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold heare me</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let us both die with honor, doe not give</L>
<L>Your strength and trust t'the mercy of those slaves</L>
<L>In humane villanes to us</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>But thy life,—as you are men but heare me</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Drop your steele quickly, or</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas she is my wife</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your wife, if you love her be not troublesome I tell you againe</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pam.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Pamela</HI> bids thee fight, feare not for me</L>
<L>If I die I shall not be dishonord</L>
<L>And thou shalt take a brave revenge on them,</L>
<L>Pitty not me to loose us both, weel meete</L>
<L>Again in death and love eternally</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>My soule's devided, shall I venture her?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile stay no longer</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold and take my sword</L>
<L>But sweare by some religion you will use</L>
<L>No violence to her</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<L>We sweare</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>So first and formost throw his sword out of the way, we
have no vse on't, secondly bind him to a tree</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Set her at liberty</L>
<L>And use what cruelty you please on me</L>
<L>Kill me, and Ile forgive you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<L>Forgiv'e us, heaven forgive thee, say thy prayers</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>I see there's pittie in you, if your wants</L>
<L>Councell you to this sinfull trade, we both</L>
<L>Will freely give our wealth, we have some Iewells</L>
<L>Of valew to redeeme you all, and make</L>
<L>You rich if you dare first be so in goodnes</L>
<L>And exercise no tyrany upon</L>
<L>Our bodies, what a misery it is</L>
<L>Such spirits as you are should not have fortunes</L>
<L>High as your thoughts, when every dunghill fellow</L>
<L>

<PB REF="23"/>Surfets with honors and estates, and vomits</L>
<L>In Taverns what would keepe your families,</L>
<L>But 'tis the times disease, when merrit thus</L>
<L>Disgrac'd and unrewarded by the state</L>
<L>Makes subjects desperate</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<L>He says true</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>I prithee take my cloathes, would they were rich</L>
<L>And worth your pillage, and will serve me</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas good Gentleman, let e'en strip him</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>None dare to take a skirt</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Perhaps for some offences you are banish'd</L>
<L>Your houses and estates</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<L>For nothing but being drunke</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<L>And offring to kill the King</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>4.</SPEAKER>
<L>He will not live amongst us as a good King ought.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas good men, I doe presume you, would not have kill'd
the King in any malice to him</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>I love the King withall my heart, and a pox take him that
does not, would he would but pardon us</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L>There's no hope now, we have submitted our selves too often</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet let him heare well of you, and tho</L>
<L>Necessitie compell you to be theeves,</L>
<L>Be honest theeves and ravish no body.</L>
<L>And this report ariving at his eares</L>
<L>It inclines him to have pittie on you</L>
<L>And call you to his favour</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vnhand the Gentlewoman, he that offers her</L>
<L>But a wry looke had better eate my sword</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or my scabbard tho it have been pist in</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith Captaine he hath given us good councell let us deale</L>
<L>Honestly, if we take away but all they have they will</L>
<L>Have more cause to speake well of us</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vnbinde the malefactor</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall I give him his sword?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>His sword thou ignorant theefe no so he may chance to
aske us againe for his Iewels; take thy <HI>Penelope</HI> sweete tong'd
<HI>Vlisses;</HI> and on the next back smother her in kisses—farwell</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, my <HI>Pamela.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="24"/>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>Captaine captaine comebacke he calls her <HI>Pamela</HI> that should
be the Kings daughter,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>How, vmh; now I looke better on her I have seene that
face in a maske before now</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<P>We are lost agen</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pam.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am the same <HI>Pamela</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>What ha we done, here are all your Iewells not a stone
deminish'd</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<L>If there be let me be gelded</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pam.</SPEAKER>
<L>I easily forgive all and will be</L>
<L>So far from a complaint that Ile pleade for</L>
<L>Your pardons to my father, and he sha' not</L>
<L>Be able to denie me</L>
<P><HI>Omnes</HI> A pardon, a pardon, if it please your highnes weel goe
backe with you</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not with me</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>As we are true men and theeves Madam</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pam.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are undone agen</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>At our returne Ile ioyne with her</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>Returne, why whether are you going so farre from the
lodge this is the way to the sea</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Vmh, I guest treason, are not you an't shall please your
Ladyship running away with this Gentleman</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<L>He said she was his wife</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe not like him</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Lay hands on him agen, well thought upon you shall
Iustifie your selves before the King</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dare you goe to the King without a pardon</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis the only way to procure one</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rather goe with us, and, as I am—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<L>What are you</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am—I know not</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Weel teach you to know your selfe; away with 'em
we are all made</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Villaines and Rebells.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Basilius, and Gynecia.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Zelmane</HI> has abus'd me</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Chide not her</L>
<L>'Twas mine owne plot to trie your constancie.</L>
<L>

<PB REF="24"/>Death cease upon <HI>Zelmane</HI> for his comming</L>
<L>But I will be reveng'd, when did I fall</L>
<L>From my high birth; in what lascivious action</L>
<L>Lost I my fame, that this <HI>Basilius</HI></L>
<L>should wrong his owne <HI>Gynecia</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am asham'd, I prithee chide no more.</L>
<L>She gave me sure some philter to betray</L>
<L>My bloud to this dishonor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tho your lust</L>
<L>Mist the enjoying him for whom your heart</L>
<L>Grew wanton, yet the sin cannot be purg'd</L>
<L>They are adulterate sheetes, and those embraces</L>
<L>Which lock'd mine armes thy guilt, not one warme kisse</L>
<L>But was intended for <HI>Zelmanes</HI> lips</L>
<L>Oh my fate</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prithee forgive</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gy.</SPEAKER>
<L>The silence which I vs'd</L>
<L>I wish'd might save my modesty a language</L>
<L>To accuse you now; indeede you have done ill</L>
<L>Touse me thus</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<L>My love to thee hereafter</L>
<L>Shall redeeme all, wound me no more I prithee</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gy.</SPEAKER>
<L>If vice have so possest you that my bed</L>
<L>Is now growne hatefull, make me not the scorne</L>
<L>Of all your kingdome, send me home agen</L>
<L>To <HI>Argos</HI> to weare out my life in weeping</L>
<L>My Lord has quite forsaken me</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not for</L>
<L>The crownes of Greece, and all the world deere deerest</L>
<L><HI>Gynecia</HI> pardon thou hast sau'd mine honor</L>
<L>Destroy me not agen, on what a rocke</L>
<L>(Had not thy goodnes rescued me) had I</L>
<L>Been ever ship wrack'd, take me to thy love,</L>
<L>A sad man for my fault, never, oh never</L>
<L>Shall such unworthy thoughts corrupt my heart</L>
<L>To leave a chaste wife</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gy.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe freely pardon this error</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then I am straite agen</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="25"/>
<SPEAKER>Gy.</SPEAKER>
<L>But <HI>Zelmane</HI> shall accompt</L>
<L>Deerely for this unlesse he satisfie</L>
<L>My furious bloud, new welcome to my bosome</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<L>A cup of wine would crowne our reconcilement</L>
<L>As I remember in the cave I saw</L>
<L>A golden bottle</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Majestie may taste on't, but I meant it</L>
<L>A draught for false <HI>Zelmane,</HI> it being virtuall</L>
<L>To increase affection, to me a guift</L>
<L>My mothers love bestow'd when I was married</L>
<L>To <HI>Basilius</HI> if ever he grew cold</L>
<STAGE>Enter Basilus</STAGE>
<L>To quicken his desires, I never yet</L>
<L>Made tryall</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is the gods</L>
<L>Nepenthe, or a drinke more precious</L>
<L>I prithee giv'ta name, and if my kingdome</L>
<L>Afford th'ingredients let me tast it often;</L>
<L>Ha <HI>Gynecia</HI> where am I?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here my Lord</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thinke I am deceiv'd, my tongue oth sudden
drawes backeward; and my limbes grow very feeble
Ha, oh-farwell.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Falls</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gy.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, my Lord, <HI>Basilius,</HI> oh hee's deade</L>
<L>If he be poyson'd I have made faire worke</L>
<L>Deere husband, then for ever mourne <HI>Gynecia</HI></L>
<L>The gods have punish'd thy lascivious heate</L>
<L>With hastie justice, hath my care so long</L>
<L>Almost religiously preserv'd this drinke</L>
<L>To kill thus in a minute; oh my soule</L>
<L>Doth feele a scorpion, and my lust appeares</L>
<STAGE>Enter Dametas and a Shepheard</STAGE>
<L>Circled with thousand furies</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shep.</SPEAKER>
<L>Treason treason</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doe set out your throate here; and let me alone to rore
treason in the eares of my Lord <HI>Philonax</HI>—I should ha'beene the
towne cryer</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shep.</SPEAKER>
<L>Make hast.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh yes treason,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gy.</SPEAKER>
<L>When you have spent your voyces, let your eyes</L>
<L>

<PB REF="25"/>Speake a more killing language</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, the Queene, Madam <HI>Pamela,</HI> is gon</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gy.</SPEAKER>
<L>No matter for <HI>Pamela,</HI> looke here shepheards</L>
<L>Herelies the King</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<L>No matter for <HI>Pamela?</HI> I am glad of that</L>
<L>Is his majestie a sleepe</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Never to awake, hee's deade poyson'd by this violl</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh base violl, why here is more treason then we look'd
for, this is admirable, did he dye against his will, or was he kill'd
a naturall death let vs sit upon him</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gy.</SPEAKER>
<L>For beare, I can direct you to the murderer</L>
<L>Looke heere you shepheards, it was I that kill'd him</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<L>You, your Majestie is very merry</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you not trust me</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes for more then I am worth, but if you kill'd him your
selfe, your majesty must pardon me for that, I have nothing to say
to you but, treason treason;</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet flie <HI>Gynecia</HI> and save thy life,</L>
<L>Betray not thine owne, life; why doe I talke</L>
<L>Of safety, can there be in all the World</L>
<L>A consort, when my honor and <HI>Basilius</HI></L>
<L>Have both forsaken me</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Philonax and Dametas with a guard.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Philon.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Pamela</HI> gon, how does the King take it</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<P>The King, would he could take it any way, good gentle∣man
hee's in a pittifull taking himselfe</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Philon.</SPEAKER>
<P>What sales the screech-oule</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<P>The truth is, he is sent of an errand to <HI>Erebus</HI> hee's dead,
and for my Lady <HI>Philoclea,</HI> whom I suspect</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Philon.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<P>And you make hast you may take her napping, there is a
thing in the likenes of a man with her, whom very valiantly I
dis-arm'd, and brought away his naked weapon</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Philon.</SPEAKER>
<P>What traytor? didst disarme him?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Did I and there had been twentie of 'em I would not
have car'd a rush though they had been as valiant as <HI>Hector,</HI> had I
not treason a'my side so soone as I came in</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Philon.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou dost amaze me what said he?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="26"/>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Never a word, my friend quoth to his sword</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Philon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ideot didst speake to his sword?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why he was fast a sleepe my Lord,</L>
<L>And never so much as dreamt of me</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Philon.</SPEAKER>
<P>A sleepe, we loose time goe you along with <HI>Dametas,</HI>
seize upon that Traytor, oh I am rent with sorrow</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come my Masters be not afraid as long as I have a sword</L>
<L>You shall goe before, and follow my example ther's the</L>
<L>King my Lord</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Dametas and guard,</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Philon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh <HI>Philonax</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Philon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be comforted</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gy.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shannot neede to mocke me, when you know</L>
<L>By whom he dye'd thou wilt call in thy charity</L>
<L>And curse me, it was I that poysoned him,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Philon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good Madam speake that I may understand,</L>
<L>You poysoned him? he was <HI>Basilius</HI></L>
<L>Your husband and your King, it cannot be</L>
<L>You are the Queene his wife</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gy.</SPEAKER>
<L>His murderer</L>
<L>The horror of my sinne dwells round about me</L>
<L>I neede no more accusers then my Conscience.</L>
<L>Doe with me what you please, the wicked reasons</L>
<L>That mov'd me to it you shall know hereafter</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Philon,</SPEAKER>
<L>Blesse me eternitie, Ile not beleeve</L>
<L>That any woman after this can love</L>
<L>Her husband, oh my Lord, mercilesse woman</L>
<L>For heere all other titles lost away</L>
<L>With her, see her lodg'd within the Castle.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Dametas and a guard with Philoclea and Pyrocles at
one doore, at the other Enter the Rebells with
Musidorus and Pamela.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heere they are my Lord</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where is the King?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Philon.</SPEAKER>
<L>New uprores.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<L>My charge, 'tis <HI>Pamela,</HI> my Lord <HI>Philonax</HI> 'tis <HI>Pamela
Philon, Pamela</HI> and <HI>Philoclea</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes my Lord we suspected they were running away


<PB REF="26"/>
together and therefore in hope of his maiesties pardon</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Py.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Musidorus</HI> and thy sister under guard?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Pyrocles</HI> and <HI>Philoclea</HI> prisoners too?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Philon.</SPEAKER>
<P>Looke heere unnaturall children, for I cannot
pronounce you Innocent, this circumstance
betrayes your guilt, see where your king and father
lyes a cold patterne for a tombe</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dead?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh we are miserable</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Basilus</HI> dead?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Slaine</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Philon.</SPEAKER>
<L>He was murder'd, and you are accessaries</L>
<L>Sure I have seene your face; were not you call'd</L>
<L>Zelmane <HI>the</HI> Amazon?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>I was.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Philon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Disguises, injurious villaine</L>
<L>Prophaner of all hospitable lawes</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am not loose to answer thee</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<L>And this was my man <HI>Dorus</HI> my Lord, a ha have I found
you sirra, you sent me abroad to be a gold-finder.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Philon.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have done service worthy all your pardons.</L>
<L>Now in my rage I could prevent the Law</L>
<L>And sacrifice their treachrous bloods my selfe</L>
<L>To this reverend hearse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are transported <HI>Philonax</HI></L>
<L>But that I have compassion for the death</L>
<L>Of that good King I could laugh at thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Philon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hence, load them with Irons, Ladies you must both</L>
<L>Be patient to be confinde untill</L>
<L>You cleere yourselves.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pam.</SPEAKER>
<L>What sawcie fellowe's that?</L>
<L>Meant you me <HI>Philonax,</HI> vnhand those prisoners</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Philon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away with'em I command</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet stay and heare me</L>
<L>As you did love <HI>Basilius</HI> heare his daughter,</L>
<L>This insolence doth interupt the teares</L>
<L>Due to my deere dead father, and inforces</L>
<L>Me, since he thus forgets, to declare to you</L>
<L>With confidence who I am, I am <HI>Pamela</HI></L>
<L>The eldest daughter of <HI>Basilius</HI></L>
<L>Your Queene if I mistake not, since my father</L>
<L>

<PB REF="27"/>Is dead, to whose memorie these pious dropps</L>
<L>Fall as the tribute of my griefe, who then</L>
<L>Shall be obay'd, he that was trusted with</L>
<L>My fathers power, which in his death is cancell'd</L>
<L>Or I your naturall princesse?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vmh, my charge speakes to the purpose.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Have you found so much sweetenesse in the raigne</L>
<L>You borrowed of my father, that you would</L>
<L>Vsurpe now he is dead? I have not signed</L>
<L>Any commission for your office, how</L>
<L>Dare you then in my presence command any</L>
<L>To prison, nay like a bould insolent traitor</L>
<L>Talke of confining me? we are mercifull</L>
<L>To let you keepe your proud heade on.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Reb.</SPEAKER>
<L>What will be come of us?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall have cleane halters.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pam.</SPEAKER>
<L>But in the justice to my royall father,</L>
<L>Snatch'd hence untimely from us, since you attempt</L>
<L>To charge them with his death, we give you space</L>
<L>To live and to accuse them, they shall be</L>
<L>Our prisoners, ith meane time t'will become</L>
<L>Your person to goe home and study how</L>
<L>To play the Advocate when you are call'd</L>
<L>By us, and the grave lawes, you are dismis'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Philon.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am astonish'd, doe you not wonder with me</L>
<L>To heare the daughter of our late good King</L>
<L>Lost to her filiall pietie, this comes.</L>
<L>To neere apracide <HI>Pamela.</HI> Contrie-men</L>
<L>It is apparent they have all conspird</L>
<L>The death of the old king, me thinks I heare</L>
<L>His groanes confirme it, if you suffer such</L>
<L>A treason passe <HI>Arcadia</HI> will become</L>
<L>The scorne of all the world, nor ever shall</L>
<L>Any good prince; trust his life amongest you,</L>
<L>For my Ambition, all the angells know</L>
<L>How tedious the houres have beene, since I</L>
<L>Was forc'd to take this kingdomes weight upon me.</L>
<L>But let not ceremony to the daughter.</L>
<L>

<PB REF="27"/>Whose title I dispute not shame our duties</L>
<L>To him that was her father and our Master.</L>
<L>Poyson'd, yes poyson'd by those men that have</L>
<L>No names, and will betray in our remisnes</L>
<L>The honor of these Ladies and our countrie</L>
<L>As they have done his pretious life already,</L>
<L>As you are good men let them be arraign'd</L>
<L>If they be innocent their goodnes will</L>
<L>Protect them, but if guilty let them dye</L>
<L>Like slaves unpittied.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Reb.</SPEAKER>
<L>A <HI>Philonax,</HI> a <HI>Philonax</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dare ye all be traytors then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Philon.</SPEAKER>
<L>This your great love reviues me, then convey</L>
<L>All to the Castle, but command these two</L>
<L>As traytors to be made safe, the ladies shall</L>
<L>Be vnder mild restraint.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Villaines</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>You lives shall deerely answer this.</L>
<L>We must obay the tyrant, were our hands</L>
<L>At liberty, and arm'd with our good swords</L>
<L>We should not off so tamely.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come away traytors.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Philon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well remember'd you.</L>
<L>Are not to be discharg'd, lodge himsafe too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who I, he does not meane me, my Lord these fellowes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take him a way, a traytor with the rest,</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Messenger.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away away</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Reb.</SPEAKER>
<L>So you must sir</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Would I might never see my wife and children in my
right wits, if I be a traytor that's enough my Lord, the'il carry me
away too.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Reb.</SPEAKER>
<L>De'e remember a cleane halter? come on sir.</L>
<STAGE>Exit</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>King <HI>Evarchus</HI> saist?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mess.</SPEAKER>
<L>He has but a small traine my lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas he comes to late to visit, but</L>
<L>Most seasonable to be a judgein this</L>
<L>Great cause, take gently up thatroyall body</L>
<L>Whose soules a starre already, all that we</L>
<L>Can pay is justice to his memorie.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="28"/>
<HEAD>Actus Quintus.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Smipathus, Pamela, Philoclea.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pam.</SPEAKER>
<P>GOod Master jaylor you might be so curteous in your
office to let vs see these Gentlemen,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<P>Madam I dare not,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pam.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis well you dare obay King <HI>Philonax</HI> and be a rebell to
me, the time may come you will repent.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<P>Confident that you will keepe your princely words not to
interupt or change any discourse with 'em, I have brought you
where you may tho at some distance heare 'em, they are pre∣paring
for musique, 'tis all I dare consent to, neither durst I tell
them you should be with in reach of their voyces</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well sir we are content</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Song</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Weel speake with'em but in your hearing,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doe not intreate him sister, pray have a speciall remem∣brance
to let'em want aire and necessaries, youl' forfeit your
place if you make conscience to be over honest to'em.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am sorrie Madam you accuse my nature</L>
<L>Which never yet was observ'd cruell, I</L>
<L>Would be as just to your commands.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pam.</SPEAKER>
<L>So it seemes</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Were these misfortunes over</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good sir no tedious excuses nor Apollogy but proceede
you and your great Master <HI>Philonax,</HI> and he will make you his
treasurer, or trust you with his great seale, you cannot choose but
be an excellent keeper.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<P>What will become of us?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay what will become at'h Princes, there's my feare,
would they were free againe, and had but their good swords to
second their innocence, I am mad to thinke what a condition we
are falne to, prithee <HI>Philoclea</HI> shed some teares for me, if I weepe
now it must be for anger that we cannot help 'em, but let the
gray-beards looke too't, for if they suffer, unlesse they send me of
an errand after them, not a head that nodded to their sentence,
shall know where to finde Shoulders to support'em</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Las sister I want drops for my owne greefe</L>
<L>My fathers death,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pum.</SPEAKER>
<L>My father, that that hath open'd</L>
<L>The spring agen</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ph<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L>And although guilty of his bloud, for so</L>
<L>

<PB REF="28"/>They say our mother hath confest her selfe</L>
<L>I must in dutie weepe for her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pam.</SPEAKER>
<L>My mother</L>
<L>That word strikes double sorrow, and doth call</L>
<L>A floud to drown my eyes, shall we not see her?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>She could not kill him sure, did ever greefe</L>
<L>So soone make such a paire of Orphants, our</L>
<L>Fortunes are so strange and thicke, posterity</L>
<L>Will thinke our storie fiction, and yet</L>
<L>It seemes th'are not so great to breake our hearts</L>
<L>A'th suddaine, I would willingly dye too</L>
<L>But I remember <HI>Pyrocles</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pam.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I my deere lov'd <HI>Musidorus,</HI> at which name</L>
<L>My teares dry up, and blacke revenge prepares</L>
<L>Thy throne within my bloud, but <HI>Simpathus</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are not the Princes sent for yet?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not yet</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pam.</SPEAKER>
<L>I prithee tell me how they looke; what say they to thee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe they name us?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<L>It hath been all their question, how both their</L>
<L>Princely mistrisses doe fare, for so</L>
<L>They call you Ladyes, when I answer well</L>
<L>Their joy shootes up in prayers that you may still</L>
<L>Continue safe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe they not raile sometimes and curse?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<L>I never heard'em</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Canst thou be such a foole then to beleeve</L>
<L>They are murderers?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe not beleeve they are</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doe not if thou darst be a Knave, and try if the Divell will
beare you out in't, we must not see'em</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas Madam</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor speake to our mother,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am commanded</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou shat not deny us a little discourse with <HI>Dametas</HI> my
old governor since we have no other company.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>His presence could be never more unwelcome</L>
<L>Beside his follies will but ill agree</L>
<L>With our affliction</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pam.</SPEAKER>
<L>They cannot hurt</L>
<L>Vs sister I have a brest as deepely charg'd</L>
<L>As thine although I flatter it, 'tis no sinne</L>
<L>To enable vs for bearing—how de'e Governor?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Dametas</STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="29"/>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<L>How dee Madam, 'een as you see, as ill as this iron age
can make a man</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pam.</SPEAKER>
<L>What will they doe with thee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<P>They cannot use me worse then they have; for I am
hang'd in chaines already, I have had three whippings into the
bargaine to, if they hold such a hand over me long, I shall never be
able to sleepe in a whole skin.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Had you any hand in my fathers death?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hand, I was so farre from having any hand, that I had not
so much as a finger in't, no your mother poisond him with a base
violl.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh misery!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<P>But Madam, I did not thinke you had been so dishonest,
and you had meant to runne away with any body I thought you
would have told me so, but I see a woman and a wet eele have
both slipperie tailes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pam.</SPEAKER>
<P>You ran away from me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who I runne? I was'never so good a foote man in my life,
alas I was tould by that rascall <HI>Dorus</HI> where a great deale of gold
was buried, and I went simply with a resolution after I came
home to build halfe a dozen Churches, but now I heare say there
is a Gallowes built to my hands, and I must hang ding dong like
a bell in the wodden steeple.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Speake well of <HI>Dorus</HI> sirra, you had more neede to pray
for him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heaven convert him then, and tho he live when I am
dead he may be rotten as soone as I</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who sent you sirra to my Chamber?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sent me, the Divell; and I ha thriv'd accordingly, would
my wife had broke her necke when I tooke you together.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your wife.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Or my daughter, or you or any body to save the loose of my
owne sweete Madam speake a good word for me, and Ile—
speake annother for you, my evidence will be heard, and I care
Not what I sweare; 'tis not for the King hee's dead, I looke
Every minute for a voyce to call me to the Sessions.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Within. Dametas</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hey there'tis already, as ever you hope to be married
while your maiden heads are sweete; save me from the Gal∣lowes,
for if I be once hang'd I shall never be my owne
man ag<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are very hasty to arraigne em, <HI>Pyrocles</HI></L>
<L>

<PB REF="29"/>There's nothing left me now but prayers for thee</L>
<L>With which Ile wearie heaven or tire my selfe</L>
<L>For thy successe.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Recorders,</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pam.</SPEAKER>
<L>I wo ld doe so but I</L>
<STAGE>Flourish.</STAGE>
<L>Feare my revenge will kill my charity.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt,
Enter Evarchus, Philonax and Slmpathus, The Bere.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Euax.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord your sorrow and not my ambition</L>
<L>Hath made me Iudge to day, therefore attend</L>
<L>The proofe of your election, I came</L>
<L>With purpose of a visit to your Master</L>
<L>But now salute his hearse, and weare a title</L>
<L>Of your Protector, in whch name I gave command</L>
<L>The prisoners should be sent for.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis done, and they are readie;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Philon.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord my part to day is to accuse</L>
<L>And not side in compassion.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Gynecia, Mufidorus, Pyrocles and Dam<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tas
guarded: a Barre set out.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>That the Queene?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Philon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, My Lord</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>She shewes a much deiected Lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Philon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Has she not cause?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Those the pretended Princes?</L>
<L>Of comely presence both, what's he?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Philon.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Dametas</HI> to whose trust the King gave up</L>
<L><HI>Pamela</HI> his eldest daughter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where is she?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Philon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Accompanied with her sister in the Castle</L>
<L>Their presence might occasion some tumult,</L>
<L>Nor doe the <HI>Arcadian</HI> Lawes allow proceeding</L>
<L>Against the next of bloud, as they permit not</L>
<L>She should determine anything her selfe</L>
<L>Till yeares or marriage enable her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will forgive thee <HI>Philonax</HI> for more malice then thou
hast brought against my life, for being so honest to <HI>Pamela,</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Philon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir I looke not for your thankes</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>As you are honorable, I beseech you</L>
<L>I'th name of sacred Iustice, ere you further</L>
<L>Proceed against our facts declare what you</L>
<L>Determine of <HI>Philolea,</HI> who is all Innocence</L>
<L>And most unjustly suffers, tho in thought</L>
<L>

<PB REF="30"/>You doubt ther virgin honor</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>She must become a recluse</L>
<L>And all her life with strict profession</L>
<L>Of Chastity repaire her blemish'd honor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Vestall?</L>
<L>Not if I live, yet if I die it carries</L>
<L>This comfort none hereafter shall enjoy</L>
<L>The faire <HI>Philoclea.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now to the Queene</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Philon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam stand to the barre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gy.</SPEAKER>
<L>My barr indeede which I have laide my selfe</L>
<L>To bring my honor to a fall and ruine</L>
<L>Oh my deere Lord my teares doe now enbalme thee,</L>
<L>My blood shall quickly follow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Philon.</SPEAKER>
<L>As you are just</L>
<L>Let not her sorrow tempt you to forget</L>
<L>What sin she hath committed, I want words</L>
<L>To expresse the horror of the deede which will</L>
<L>Throw shame on all her sex.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay <HI>Philonax</HI> sh'at have.</L>
<L>What thou desirest, I have been a judge already</L>
<L>Vpon my selfe and doe not desire life,</L>
<L>That am condem'd by my owne killing sentence</L>
<L>I doe againe confesse I was the murderer</L>
<L>Of your and my Lord, robd <HI>Arcadia</HI> and</L>
<L>My children of a father, I, none but I</L>
<L>Poyson'd <HI>Basilius</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Palladius</HI> dost heare?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vnfortunate Lady,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gy.</SPEAKER>
<L>And what could <HI>Philonax</HI> say more against me?</L>
<L>There remaines onely to obay your Iudgement</L>
<L>Which cannot come in any shape of death</L>
<L>Too horrid for my sinne I'me very weary</L>
<L>Of this bad world, be just and take a life</L>
<L>From me that else will groane it selfe away</L>
<L>And mocke your Iustice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Philon.</SPEAKER>
<L>You heare my Lord?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Evar.</SPEAKER>
<L>And thus proceede to sentence</L>
<L>Having confest, to spare your proofe how much</L>
<L>She hath offended, an example to all times</L>
<L>We censure thus, she shall presently</L>
<L>Be carried to prison where she may</L>
<L>Have foode but only to sustaine her life</L>
<L>Vntill her husbands buriall, with whom</L>
<L>

<PB REF="30"/>In the same vault she shall be clos'd alive</L>
<L>To keepe his body company from which</L>
<L>Her cruelty divorc'd his soule,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ya're Iust.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>My heart weepes for her</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus,</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis a severe sentence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who binds my hands? <HI>Basilius</HI> I come</L>
<L>To de a living guest in thy sad tombe.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Philon.</SPEAKER>
<L>The others to the barre</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eva.</SPEAKER>
<L>What are their names?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Daiphantas</HI> of <HI>Licia</HI> mine</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mine <HI>Palladius</HI> of <HI>Iberia.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ev.</SPEAKER>
<L>We do not dispute their titles heere, they are</L>
<L>Privat persons, you may proceede.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall, and with as much brevitie</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ev.</SPEAKER>
<L>Choose whom you'l first accuse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Philon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then first this <HI>Daiphantas,</HI> this <HI>Zelmane</HI></L>
<L>This what you will, for he hath yet no name</L>
<L>Nor shape that we can trust to, having knowledge</L>
<L>Of our late masters solitary life,</L>
<L>Came not without a purpose of this treachery</L>
<L>And by the cunning of <HI>Gynecia</HI></L>
<L>Ith habit of a woman was received</L>
<L>As an unsuspected guest, enjoy'd the freedome,</L>
<L>Of those whom the King plac'd neerest his bosome,</L>
<L>His children not more deere, treason thus fortified</L>
<L>They soone conspird the death of this good King,</L>
<L>A cave this Gentlewomans, lodging was</L>
<L>The fatall sceane where the unhappy Queene</L>
<L>By his direction forc'd his deere life from him</L>
<L>I omit what lustfull motive prompted her</L>
<L>That with more licence she might twine with this</L>
<L>Hermophrodite, and that they had appointed</L>
<L>Where they might meete when this blacke deede was done,</L>
<L>But heaven was mercifull and prevented her</L>
<L>Flight by the happy comming in of Shepheards</L>
<L>In the meane time transported with the confidence</L>
<L>Of her performance, that he might not leave</L>
<L>

<PB REF="31"/>Any revenger of this hatefull murder</L>
<L>He hastily makes up to <HI>Philocleas</HI> Chamber,</L>
<L>Whereby the mingling (what he could) her shame</L>
<L>With his offence, he easily might enforce</L>
<L>Her to be accessarie to her fathers death,</L>
<L>And under her protection, and her sisters</L>
<L>(Gainst whom they knew we were not to rebell)</L>
<L>So<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e with one gripe the state, but heaven preserv'd</L>
<L>All by the unexpected comming up</L>
<L>Of this <HI>Dametas.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes heaven and I preserv'd all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Philon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who sought then for <HI>Pamela</HI></L>
<L>Which the other Princely theefe had stolen away,</L>
<L>And finding these, I meane <HI>Philoclea</HI></L>
<L>And this young man together, found occasion</L>
<L>To inclose the ravisher till by command</L>
<L>They were apprehended: thus you have in short</L>
<L>His wicked storie, and what punishment</L>
<L>Will not be thought a mercy to that monster</L>
<L>That kills a King, dishonoreth a Queene,</L>
<L>And violates the daughter?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>In things promoted with such cunning mixture</L>
<L>'Tis hard to shape a square and direct answer.</L>
<L>My accusers sordid and malicious railing</L>
<L>More greevious to my tender sence of honor</L>
<L>Then death can be, I forget him</L>
<L>A thing beneath my anger and arm'd with</L>
<L>My owne simplicity doubt not to assure</L>
<L>How much my cause is iniur'd, know Grave Iudge</L>
<L>This prince and I drawne hither by the fame</L>
<L>Of the rare beauties in <HI>Basilius</HI> daughters</L>
<L>Knowing that with their parents they liv'd heere</L>
<L>Secluded from the world, where no accesse</L>
<L>In our owne persons was to be expected,</L>
<L>Put on these formes as soonest might conduce</L>
<L>To make our loves knowne: this <HI>Palladius</HI></L>
<L>Became so fortunate that his Princely Mistris</L>
<L>Consented to forsake, and trust his conduct</L>
<L>

<PB REF="31"/>To a happier kingdome: my fortune</L>
<L>Was not so happy, for I did not cherrish</L>
<L>A greater flame, yet modest, of <HI>Philoclea</HI></L>
<L>Then her weake father in my sex deceiv'd</L>
<L>Retain'd of me, that tyr'd with his solicites</L>
<L>I had no time to perfect my desires</L>
<L>With his faire daughter,</L>
<L>Till under collour of some devotions</L>
<L>I made a cave my lodging to invite</L>
<L><HI>Basilius</HI> thether, with full hope to enjoy me,</L>
<L>But this revealing to the Queene, she tooke</L>
<L>My place to make the old King see his follies.</L>
<L>In the meane time I must confesse I went</L>
<L>To bright <HI>Philocleas</HI> Chamber hoping to</L>
<L>Win her by all the charmes of noble love</L>
<L>To leave <HI>Arcadia;</HI> but she unhappily</L>
<L>Obeying her owne Genius gave no</L>
<L>Consent, when in the midst of my securitie</L>
<L>I know not by what meanes I was made prisoner.</L>
<L>And heere's the thred to guide through this laborinth,</L>
<L>Me thinkes your man of mightie tongue should blush</L>
<L>To have spent his rage so poorely.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ev.</SPEAKER>
<L>What ic all this to the death of the old King?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>By all the gods I am innocent</L>
<L>The Queene hath absolu'd me, as for <HI>Philoclea</HI></L>
<L>If you will call't a cryme in that I lov'd her</L>
<L>I am and shall be guiltie, but had never</L>
<L>A thought so rude to force her unstain'd chastity:</L>
<L>Or if the honor of this excellent Lady</L>
<L>Suffer it'h blind opinion of the world</L>
<L>Our marriage not my death may cure all wounds</L>
<L>Malice can fasten on her name.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Philon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh impudence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ev.</SPEAKER>
<L>If this be all you have to say proceede</L>
<L>To his confederate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Philon.</SPEAKER>
<L>The imagination how miserable</L>
<L>These juglers would have made us and our Country</L>
<L>If their disguise had prosper'd, strikes a terror</L>
<L>

<PB REF="32"/>Through all my faculties, my tongue's enfeebled.</L>
<L>Therefore to omit his practice in the murder</L>
<L>Which you may easily collect by circumstance</L>
<L>This is enough to call him a foule traytor</L>
<L>He did attempt to steale a way out princesse</L>
<L>The hope and treasure of <HI>Arcadia</HI></L>
<L>And taken in the fact dares not deny it,</L>
<L>Had he no other cry me to answer for</L>
<L>This pulls severe death on him, and to insist</L>
<L>Vpon offences of so foule a nature</L>
<L>Were to distrust your wisdome or your Iustice.</L>
<L>Thou to ther shame of mankinde speake to this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not for thy sake who in this misery</L>
<L>Hast only merrited to be my scorne</L>
<L>But for the truth I answer, pardon sir</L>
<L>If passion make me not remember language</L>
<L>That should become this place, this ill tongu'd man</L>
<L>That with such vehemence accuseth thus</L>
<L>Is himselfe guilty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Philon.</SPEAKER>
<L>How?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Of a more hatefull vice, ingratitude.</L>
<L>Is this the paiment for our services</L>
<L>Which once thy tongue acknowledged had desev'd</L>
<L>Statues to the eternall memory</L>
<L>Of the preservers of your King and Country?</L>
<L>Is all the vallor of this young man cancell'd</L>
<L>When Rebells had advanc'd their daring swords</L>
<L>High as the throat of your old King, his wife</L>
<L>And trembling daughters, is the time forgotten</L>
<L>When wild beasts had prepared their riotous mawes</L>
<L>To bury the deere pledges of your kingdome?</L>
<L>Oh where had been my treason or his rape</L>
<L>Had they been then devourd? the ground has not</L>
<L>Drunke up the blood so perfectly, but there</L>
<L>Remaines a coulour to teach impious men</L>
<L>To blush for their ingratitude, have we</L>
<L>Beene carelesse of our lives to preserve</L>
<L>The King when danger threatend horror to him</L>
<L>

<PB REF="32"/>And can a temperate man imagine we</L>
<L>Should be his murderers, we had not sav'd</L>
<L>To be our selves the hangmen? but I'me charg'd</L>
<L>For stealing of your Princesse, can your breathes</L>
<L>Acknowledge her your Soveraigne, and allow</L>
<L>No faith to what she sayes, you have degraded</L>
<L>My blood from honor, and vnlesse you make me</L>
<L>Lesse then her subject I was bound to obay</L>
<L>When she commanded I should waite upon her,</L>
<L>But you'l object I counsell'd her, I did</L>
<L>And justifie the act, she was confinde</L>
<L>Too narrowly, and I durst leade her to</L>
<L>A throane above the Majesty her birth</L>
<L>Can challenge in <HI>Arcadia,</HI> love whose force</L>
<L>The gods have not resisted may plead for me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ev.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is this all?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tho it want method'tis enough to vindicate</L>
<L>My honor from his base aspertion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ev.</SPEAKER>
<L>To him you call <HI>Dametas</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not guilty my Lord, as I hope to be sav'd not guilty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Philon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Neglect of the great charge with which the King</L>
<L>Our Master trusted him summes up his fault.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<L>I was made a gould-finder, I desire Iustice for him and</L>
<L>Mercy for my selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Philon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Silence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have heard you with attention, and whereas</L>
<L>To the Kings death (the unhappy cause of this</L>
<L>Assembly) you have answer'd with deniall</L>
<L>Which you thinke fortified by the Queenes</L>
<L>Selfes only accusation, I must tell you</L>
<L>It frees you not, for tho no manifest proofes</L>
<L>Yet circumstances well examin'd make you</L>
<L>The accidentall causes of his murder.</L>
<L>For the other part of your offence I finde not</L>
<L>You have deny'd your guilt, but onley use</L>
<L>Quallification and excuse; your services</L>
<L>In themselves high and honorable, allow you</L>
<L>No priviledge to offend, but give your blacke, faults</L>
<L>

<PB REF="33"/>A blacke die; then justly weighing your offence, you meete</L>
<L>In equall guilt, for tho you first conveid</L>
<L>Away <HI>Pamela,</HI> his intention was</L>
<L>Earely as yours, and by the rules of justice</L>
<L>The will stands for the act, both ravished</L>
<L>Although not of the Ladies from themselves</L>
<L>Yet from their parents and their countrie, which</L>
<L>By all the <HI>Grecian</HI> Lawes is paid with death.</L>
<L>Thus then I must pronounce <HI>Daiphantas</HI> shall</L>
<L>Be throwne from some high tower to meere his death,</L>
<L><HI>Palladius</HI> loose his head before Sunne-set</L>
<L>The executioner shall be <HI>Dametas</HI></L>
<L>Which office of the common hangman he</L>
<L>Shall for his whole life execute, a punishment</L>
<L>For his neglect of duty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<P>must I be hangman? oh brave, heaven preserve your
Lordship, I shall quickly learne the trade, and if ever any of your
honors have occasion to use me, I will owe you a good turne, and in
token I have beene bound to you the knot of my dutifull affection,
shall tella tale in your eare you shall thanke me when you are
hang'd, come your wayes, but I beseech your Lordship, I may be
allow'd a man some times I would be loath to hange or to behead
my selfe, my wife or my owne kindred, but if it happen there be
more worke then he can turne his hands to, I will not sticke with
him to hang my selfe, provide you malefactors and let me alone for
halters.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Callander and Calodoulus</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cala.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold stay the prisoners my Lord Protector</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Calo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh my Lord</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>My servant <HI>Calodoulus</HI> by thy duty</L>
<L>Reveale us not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Calo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me rather be dumbe eternally</L>
<L>Then two such princes be lost by my silence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ev.</SPEAKER>
<L>My sonne and Nephew are they living?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Calo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your owne <HI>Pyrocles</HI> and his Princely Nephew,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cala.</SPEAKER>
<L>Aske your father blessing, unhand'em rascalls.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Philon.</SPEAKER>
<L>The two most famous Princes in the world.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis <HI>Evarchus</HI> thy father <HI>Pyrocles,</HI> my vncle king of
<HI>Macedon,</HI> all yee gods, my heart is extaside with ioy.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="33"/>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>My father</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ev.</SPEAKER>
<L>My blessing and my teares you both divide.</L>
<L>Witnesse with me, yee immortall powers this day</L>
<L>I have done nothing, but what justice and</L>
<L>Your native lawes require, without the knowledge</L>
<L>How neere they were to my owne blood, but since</L>
<L>They are prou'd my Sonne and Nephew</L>
<L>Endow'd by nature richly, and how merriting</L>
<L>The fame and love of all the world before</L>
<L>This accident, I leave to your owne thoughts,</L>
<L>Besides these two I have no joyes of life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cala.</SPEAKER>
<L>Excellent <HI>Evarchus;</HI> why did you change your names?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>To prevent the dishonor of our blood</L>
<L>If we had suffer'd</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ev.</SPEAKER>
<L>But I have judg'd already and if right</L>
<L>I have not wrong'd, vnlesse the name</L>
<L>Of child have power to alter sacred Iustice</L>
<L>You both must dye, though when I speake your death</L>
<L>It creeps upon my heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>We dreame, is this thy father <HI>Pyrocles?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ev.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away with em.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis most tyranicall he is thy sonne.</L>
<L>Thou wot not be a murderer of thy owne?</L>
<L>Make not thy name hated of all the world</L>
<L>When it shall say hereafter <HI>Pyrocles</HI></L>
<L>Had no fault in him but he was thy sonne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>For me I am his owne and being so</L>
<L>Dispos'd of by his Iustice; to whom rather</L>
<L>I hop'd to have been a comfort then a shame</L>
<L>I kisse my sentence; but you cannot place</L>
<L>Your Kinsman in the sacrifice his mother</L>
<L>And countrie pleade a title he is theirs</L>
<L>Oh save my princely cosen</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ev.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sure I shannot live</L>
<L>Long after them, and Gentlemen if I dye</L>
<L>Before I leave <HI>Arcadia</HI> let my ashes</L>
<L>Mingle with theirs:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<L>oh oh oh</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord, Gentlemen, there's something stirs and groan<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
Come backe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="34"/>
<SPEAKER>Ev.</SPEAKER>
<L>Basilius <HI>alive, assist him</HI> Philonax.</L>
<L>He breathes, what <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> of joy runne through me?</L>
<L>Send for <HI>Gynecia</HI> and his daughters.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas</SPEAKER>
<L>Why am I supported thus like a dead man?</L>
<L>What are you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ev.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Evarc<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>us</HI> your old friend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<L>I ha seene that face before,'tis like sweete <HI>Zelmane.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ev.</SPEAKER>
<L>My sonne</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>But was a conterfeit <HI>Zelmane.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wonders, and you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ev.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Nephew, prince of <HI>Thessaly</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Gynecia, Pamela
and Philoclea,</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tho <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> your servant <HI>Doru<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Very strange; <HI>Gynecia</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gy.</SPEAKER>
<L>My deere Lord return'd</L>
<L>A thousand kisses welcome him to life</L>
<L>Which I was wearie of in thy losse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<L>My daughters</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh my father</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you <HI>Philonax?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ev.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your trusty servant</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Philon.</SPEAKER>
<L>The oracle is accomplish'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<L>You amase me, let me collect</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh my sweet <HI>Pyrocles</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pam.</SPEAKER>
<L>We shall not be divor'd I hope agen</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am your servant ever</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Devinest Mistris</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ev.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your soules I see are married</L>
<L>Let me present these princes to be your sonnes</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is this reall?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gy.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis dangerous to expect the storie.</L>
<L>I fear'd the drinke, but it may be his vertue</L>
<L>To encrease his love to me, Ile tell you more within sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Philon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me obtaine your pardons</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ev.</SPEAKER>
<L>To his Chamber <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> him gently</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<L>All is strange.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Never was day so full of happy change</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Florish:</STAGE>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<PB REF="34"/>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

