<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2005-02-24</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Rachel Losh</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Checked for N=""s. Checked for GROUP tags. Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, CLOSER, OPENER, ARGUMENT, EPIGRAPH, SIGNED, BYLINE, etc.). Checked for signatures. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, and UNCLEARs. Corrected ** $s and $word$s etc. of **. Converted __ $$s to GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="[vendor name]". Checked spacing of foreign GAPs. Checked for LBs. Checked for startqs, endqs, oes, q;s, and Qs. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Checked for FIGUREs and decorated initials. Checked for missing-page GAPs. Revalidated. </ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A12135">
<STC T="S">22441B</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99838003</BIBNO>
<VID>2360</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>

<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
THE DVKES MISTRIS, <HI>As</HI> IT VVAS PRESEN∣ted by her <HI>Majesties</HI> Servants, At the private House in <HI>Drury-Lane.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Written by</HI> IAMES SHIRLY.</P>
<P><FIGURE>
</FIGURE></P>
<P><HI>LONDON,</HI> Printed by JOHN NORTON, for ANDREVV CROOKE and WILLIAM COOKE. 1638. 6</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="prologue">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>The Prologue.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L>SO various are the pallates of our Age</L>
<L>That nothing is presented on the Stage,</L>
<L>Though nere so square, and apted to the Lawes</L>
<L>Of poesy, that ean winne full applause,</L>
<L>This likes a story, that a cunning plot</L>
<L>This wit, that lines, here one, he know's not what.</L>
<L>But after all this looking severall wayes,</L>
<L>We do obserue the generall guests to Playes,</L>
<L>Meet in opinion of two straines: that please</L>
<L>Satire, and wantonnes, the last of these</L>
<L>Though old, if in new dressing it appeare</L>
<L>Will move a smile from all, but shall not heare.</L>
<L>Our Author hath no guilt of scurrile friends.</L>
<L>For Satire they do know best what it meanes,</L>
<L>That dare apply, and if a Poets Pen,</L>
<L>Ayming at generall errors not the men,</L>
<L>'Tis not his fault, the safest cure is, they</L>
<L>That purge their bosomes, may see any Play.</L>
<L>But here we quit your feare of Satire too,</L>
<L>And with these disadvantages to you</L>
<L>Thus humbly bow, to such helpes tane away</L>
<L>What hope is there many will like the Play,</L>
<L>But good or bad, have patience but two howers,</L>
<L>The Poets credit is at stake with ours.</L>
</LG>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="play">
<PB REF="3" MS="y"/>
<PB REF="3"/>
<HEAD>THE DVKES MISTRIS</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus Primus.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Silvio, and Valerio.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Si.</SPEAKER>
<L><SEG REND="decorInit">W</SEG>Ee are like to have a brave, and jolly time on't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Court looks now as't should be, after such</L>
<L>A tempest, what should follow but a calme,</L>
<L>And Sun-beames? wher's the <HI>Dutchesse?</HI></L>
<L>And yet as the case stands, we can scarce give her</L>
<L>That title, all her glory is eclips'd, </L>
<L>Shee's i'th west, poore gentle-woman I can</L>
<L>But pity her, I meane <HI>Euphemia.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>I dare not speake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou mayst speake any thing</L>
<L>That's Courtly, and in fashion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>But the <HI>Duke.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Is <HI>Duke,</HI> and Heaven preserve him, let him have</L>
<L>His humor, and his Mistresses, what are we</L>
<L>The worse, nay lets consider like wise-men</L>
<L>We are the better for't, it gives us liberty,</L>
<L>And matter for our dutifull imitation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>But she was his <HI>Dutchesse.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>What then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>

<PB REF="4"/>
Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Lady of,</L>
<L>A flowing sweetnes, and but in his eyes</L>
<L>Can want no beauty, how her nature may</L>
<L>Thus cruelly affronted, keepe that soft,</L>
<L>And noble temper.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take heede, and be wise,</L>
<L>We are or should be Courtiers, if it please</L>
<L>The <HI>Duke</HI> for reasons best knowne to himselfe</L>
<L>To have more Wives, I say 'tis sit he have 'em,</L>
<L>I make it my owne ease.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art not married.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, I dare not for that reason, cause I hold it</L>
<L>Unfit my conscience should be limited,</L>
<L>But we are private men, and though the Lawes</L>
<L>Have power on us, the State, and <HI>Dukedome</HI> may</L>
<L>Suffer, if he that is the soule of all,</L>
<L>I meane the <HI>Duke,</HI> should wast his life with one,</L>
<L>One melancholy wife, come let me tell thee</L>
<L>Since he has chosen one, that he thinks fayrer</L>
<L>'Tis happy for his first to keepe her head on,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Coulst thou have thought so cruell, las <HI>Euphemia</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>No thou art deceiv'd, if I were <HI>Duke</HI></L>
<L>'Tis ten to one I'de have noe Wife at all,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>How?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not of mine owne, while any of my subjects</L>
<L>Had those I could affect; whom I wo'd have</L>
<L>Presented by their husbands, they should doe</L>
<L>Themselves that curtesie, none would denie,</L>
<L>Considering what may follow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Besides Hornes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Right, if the toy be gamesome, the husbands made</L>
<L>For ever.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cuckold.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>And his Wife a great one,</L>
<L>Hornes excuse for all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>The old mind still.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know my constitution</L>
<STAGE>Enter Leontio.</STAGE>
<L>His countenance weares some sore of discontent</L>
<L>Do'es he not appeare Cloudy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>

<PB REF="4"/>
Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lett's speake to him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord,—my Lord.</L>
<L>Not answer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>He does not heare.</L>
<L>My noblest Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>If I did thinke he were proud now of a suddaine,</L>
<L>I wod not aske him how he do'es, to save</L>
<L>His life—I'le speake once more, my worthiest Lord,</L>
<L><HI>Leontio.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>I ha waken'd him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Valerio,</HI> and <HI>Siluio.</HI></L>
<L>I am your servants.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not that we grudge our duties to your Lordship</L>
<L>Or breath, for without flattery, I dare</L>
<L>Be hoarse with praysing, and with praying for you,</L>
<L>But we would willingly have your Lordship take</L>
<L>Notice, when we expresse our hearts to serve you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your pardon gentlemen, I am confident</L>
<L>You have more vertue then to let me suffer in your opinions</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>You looke sad.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>And talke as you had but started from a dreame,</L>
<L>I dare not be too bold to enquire the cause,</L>
<L>But your face will teach others melancholie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now in this generall mirth it must appeare,</L>
<L>The greater wonder to behold your trouble.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall betray my selfe, keepe in my passions.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ther's something in't more then we apprehend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>What should distract the freedome of your sole</L>
<L>Kinsman, and onely favourite to the <HI>Duke,</HI></L>
<L>The peoples love too, and these seldome meete,</L>
<L>The minion of the Souldiers, who honour you</L>
<L>Most infinitly for your valour, and your bounty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Flatter not gentlemen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le be your hinde first.</L>
<L>Ecclipse not, S<SUP>r</SUP>, the glories of your minde</L>
<L>with this strange melancholy, I wod not for</L>
<L>My hopes the <HI>Duke</HI> should see this dulnes, he</L>
<L>May with unhappy jealousie interpret—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>

<PB REF="5"/>
Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>What Jealousie?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is my heart transparent?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now ioy revels in the Court,</L>
<L>By his command, and his example too;</L>
<L>Doe not affront his pleasure, I am bold,</L>
<L>But 'tis my zeale, that wo'd not have you suffer,</L>
<L>And you may give it pardon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must thanke</L>
<L>Thy love <HI>Valerio,</HI> thy heart does speake</L>
<L>A noble ftiendship, you shall witnesse Gentlemen</L>
<L>I will be very pleasant, keepe, keepe in</L>
<L>Yee rebell thoughts, and take some other time</L>
<L>To shew your wildnes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Observ'd you that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall I be bold to aske your Lordship a que-stion?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Any thing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ual.</SPEAKER>
<L>You will pardon the folly on't?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>What is't? be cleare with me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you not in love, my Lord?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>In Love?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have shrewd coniectures.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>From what?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>From these dull Symptomes, if you be</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>What then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ual.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me be your Physition, 'tis a woman</L>
<L>I must presume.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>What does a man love else?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>There be those men are in love with their own cloathes</L>
<L>Their wits, their follies, their estates, themselves,</L>
<L>But if you love a woman, let me advise you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heare him my Lord, his practise upon that sex</L>
<L>Has made him learn'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Something I have observ'd</L>
<L>After a hundred Mistresses, I had beene dull else,</L>
<L>But to the point.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>How would you advise mee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would not counsell you not to love at all,</L>
<L>As some that are all Satyr, 'gainst the sex,</L>
<L>

<PB REF="5"/>
Love me a hansome Lady, but so love her</L>
<L>That still your heart finde roome for a fresh beautie,</L>
<L>For twentie, for a thousand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is inconstancie</L>
<L>So easie, and so pardonable.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ual.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why dee' shift</L>
<L>Your shirt, the linnen's sine, but not so cleane</L>
<L>And sweete after a Journey, 'tis a Justice</L>
<L>To change: and a security a woman</L>
<L>Is Tyrant, when she finds a dotage, Love</L>
<L>But wisely, to delight our hearts, not ruine 'em</L>
<L>With too severe impression.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prethee tell me,</L>
<L>What doe most men desire that are in love?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>In this wise love I meane? why, my Lord, they</L>
<L>Desire to enioy their Mistresses, what else</L>
<L>Can be expected? and 'tis necessary</L>
<L>In my opinion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hadst thou beene woman,</L>
<L>Thou wod'st not have beene so cruell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Troth, my Lord,</L>
<L>I know not how the sex might have corrupted mee</L>
<L>But had I beene <HI>Adonis,</HI> without question</L>
<L>My Lady <HI>Venus</HI> should have had no cause</L>
<L>To accuse my bashfullnesse, I should have left</L>
<L>The Forrest to have hunted—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I beleeve it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>But I must be content.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nothing will much trouble thy head <HI>Ualerio.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe not vex my selfe with much inquirie</L>
<L>What men doe in the <HI>Indies,</HI> or what Trade</L>
<L>The great Turke's on, nor what his designe is,</L>
<L>Nor does the State at home much trouble me,</L>
<L>After the warres I enioy my limbs, and can</L>
<L>Boast some activitie, untill some woman</L>
<L>In kindnesse take me downe, be rul<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d by me,</L>
<L>Employ your spring and youth upon those Joyes</L>
<L>They are fit for, beget a new <HI>Elizium,</HI></L>
<L>Under some pleasing shade lets lie and laugh</L>
<L>

<PB REF="6"/>
Our Temples crown'd with Roses, with the choyse,</L>
<L>And richest blood of Grapes, quicken our veines,</L>
<L>Some faire cheek'd boyes skinking our swelling Cups,</L>
<L>And we with Joviall soules shooting them round</L>
<L>At each mans lip a Mistresse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>I did looke for this before.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>They in this Bower</L>
<L>Shall with their Songs, and Musicke charme our eares,</L>
<L>And nimbly dance, their bright haire loosely spread;</L>
<L>Nor shall they more their amorous beauties hide</L>
<L>Then those contended for the golden Ball.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou wod'st imagine many fine devices</L>
<L>But after all these pleasures, as there is</L>
<L>A limit, and a period set, what will</L>
<L>Succeed these raptures, when they are past enjoyings</L>
<L>But leave so many stings upon our thoughts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>We wo'not thinke of that, or if we do,</L>
<L>Wee'le venture upon Fortunes curtesie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art resolute <HI>Valerio,</HI> if ere sorrow</L>
<L>Lay seige to me, i'le wish thee my companion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am your humble creature, and shall be honord</L>
<L>In your commands.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Ascanio.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>As.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, the Duke</L>
<L>Ask'd for you.</L>
<STAGE>Ascanio whispers with Valerio, and Silvio. Ardelia.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le attend. Whither in hast?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are commanded to attend</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is his pleasure, we should waite upon her</L>
<L>To his presence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ardelia,</L>
<L>It will become you, and but that his highnes</L>
<L>Exacts my person, I should be a part</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<L>Of her attendance, but not serve her with</L>
<L>Halfe the devotion, I would pay <HI>Euphemia</HI></L>
<L>The too much injur'd <HI>Dutchesse,</HI> now a stranger</L>
<L>To the <HI>Dukes</HI> bosome, while another sits,</L>
<L>And rules his heart, but this prepares my happines,</L>
<L>My hopes grow from her misery, which may</L>
<L>Encline <HI>Euphemia</HI> to pity me.</L>
<L>

<PB REF="6"/>
I must use art.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Euphemia, and Macrina.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good Madam have more comfort.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is not that she? her habite like her Fortune</L>
<L>Most blacke, and ominous, heer's a change of State,</L>
<L>Noe noyse of waiters, and officious troopes,</L>
<L>Of Courtiers futter here, where are the traine</L>
<L>Of Ladies, with more blossome then the Spring,</L>
<L>Ambitious to present their duties to her,</L>
<L>Where be those Jewells, whose proud blaze did use</L>
<L>To vye with Sun-beames, and strike gazers blind?</L>
<L>All gone behind a Cloud? how she observes</L>
<L>The Structures, which more soft then <HI>Dionisio</HI></L>
<L>seeme to incline their marble heads, and sweate</L>
<L>In the compassion of her iniury,</L>
<L>My heart is labouring for breath, and yet</L>
<L>I dare not speake to her, the <HI>Duke</HI> has spies</L>
<L>Upon her; and his anger carries ruine.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Courtiers, who passe by neglectfully.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eup.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sure I should know this place.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis the Court Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eup.</SPEAKER>
<L>And those were Courtiers that past by?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<L>They were.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eup.</SPEAKER>
<L>Some of them serv'd me once, but now the <HI>Duke</HI></L>
<L>Has discharg'd all, why dost not thou forsake me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<L>I serv'd you Madam, for your selfe, and cannot</L>
<L>Thinke on you with lesse reverence, for your change:</L>
<L>Of Fortune.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eup.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is not that <HI>Leontio?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eup.</SPEAKER>
<L>Does he decline me too? though I am miserable,</L>
<L>My griefe wo'd not infect him, but he must</L>
<L>Compose himselfe to please, the <HI>Duke,</HI> whose creature</L>
<L>He has beene alwayes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will speake to her,</L>
<L>Though death in the <HI>Dukes</HI> eye threatens to kill me,</L>
<L>Great Mistresse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eup.</SPEAKER>
<L>You doenot well <HI>Leontio</HI> to insult</L>
<L>Upon my misery, <HI>Dionisios</HI> frowne</L>
<L>

<PB REF="7"/>
May make your feild as barren.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>By all vertue,</L>
<L>And by your selfe the Mistris, I have not</L>
<L>One thought so irreligious in my soule</L>
<L>I weepe for your misfortune, and shall Study</L>
<L>All humble wayes to serve you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eup.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have beene noble.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your titles are all sacred still with me,</L>
<L>The <HI>Dukes</HI> neglect cannot unprince you here;</L>
<L>Oh let not hasty sorrow boast a triumph</L>
<L>Over so great a mind, let not that beauty</L>
<L>Whither with apprehension of your wrong</L>
<L>That may be soone repented, and the Storme</L>
<L>That cowardly would shake that comliest building</L>
<L>Make for your happines, some lament your fate.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Strozzi.</STAGE>
<L>Whose lookes speake mirth, be confident, the <HI>Duke</HI></L>
<L>Will chide the unlawfull flame, that like rude</L>
<L>And wandring meteor, led him from your vertues</L>
<L>With so much danger to embrace <HI>Ardelia.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Str.</SPEAKER>
<L>The <HI>Duke</HI> shall know your complements.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eup.</SPEAKER>
<L>Noe more, least for your charity to me,</L>
<L>For I must call it so, you ruine not</L>
<L>Your favour with the <HI>Duke,</HI> farewell <HI>Leontio</HI></L>
<L>Yet I would pray one favour from you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Me?</L>
<L>My life's your servant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eup.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you heare the <HI>Duke</HI></L>
<L>Speake of me, as I feare he never will</L>
<L>But in displeasure, tell him I will thinke it</L>
<L>Noe cruelty to take this poore life from me,</L>
<L>Rather then let me draw a wretched breath</L>
<L>With generall scorne, let him command me dead,</L>
<L>And I forgive him, otherwise farewell.</L>
<STAGE>Eexeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>That close snew<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d something, like a will to be,</L>
<L>Reveng'd her brest heav'd up, and fell againe,</L>
<L>While both her eyes shot a contention upward,</L>
<L>As they would seeme to put just Heaven in mind</L>
<L>How much she suffers.</L>
<STAGE>

<PB REF="7"/>
Enter Pallante.</STAGE>
<L>If griefe thus become her,</L>
<L>What magicke will not love put on? <HI>I</HI> must</L>
<L>Stifle my passion. <HI>Pallante,</HI> welcome,</L>
<L>You are well met in Court;</L>
<L>Where dost thou live <HI>Pallante?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pall.</SPEAKER>
<L>Every where,</L>
<L>Yet no where to any purpose, we are out</L>
<L>Of use, and like our Engines are laid by</L>
<L>To gather dust, the Court I ha'not skill in,</L>
<L>I want the tricke of flatterie, my Lord,</L>
<L>I cannot bow to Scarlet, and Gold-lace,</L>
<L>Embroiderie is not an <HI>Idoll</HI> for my worship,</L>
<L>Give me the warres agen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>But yet remember we fight for peace,</L>
<L>The end of warre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pall.</SPEAKER>
<L>I never did, my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>What?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pall.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fight for peace, I fought for pay, and honour,</L>
<L>Peace will undoe us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis the corruption of our peace, that men</L>
<L>Glorious in Spirit, and desert, are not</L>
<L>Encourag'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pall.</SPEAKER>
<L>The faults somewhere.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I presume</L>
<L>Thou art not of so tyrannous a nature,</L>
<L>But thou couldst be content to weare rich cloathes,</L>
<L>Feed high, and want no fortune without venturing</L>
<L>To buy them at the price of blood.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pall.</SPEAKER>
<L>I could.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>And ile engage thou sha't, be this the Prologue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pall.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not I, keepe, keepe your money.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>You doe not scorne my bounty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pall.</SPEAKER>
<L>You may guesse</L>
<L>That fortune has not doted much upon mee,</L>
<L>And yet I must refuse it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your reason pray?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pall.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why ten to one I shall spend it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>So tis meant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>

<PB REF="8"/>
Pall.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twill make me gay a while, but I shall pawne</L>
<L>My Robes, and put on these agen,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou sha't not</L>
<L>While I have Fortune to preserve thee otherwise,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pall.</SPEAKER>
<L>I say out of my love to you I must not,</L>
<L>I never yet tooke money upon charity,</L>
<L>I earn'd it in the Warre, and i'le deserue't</L>
<L>In peace, of you I cannot, tis my misery</L>
<L>To be unserviceable.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is that your Scruple?</L>
<L>But that <HI>I</HI> know thy humor, <HI>I</HI> should thinke</L>
<L>This cunning, but you shall not, S<SUP>r</SUP>, despaire,</L>
<L>I shall find wayes to have mention'd</L>
<L>In your accounts for merrits, doubt not, <HI>I</HI></L>
<L>Will give you occasion to deserve more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pall.</SPEAKER>
<L>On those conditions i'le take more, and thinke the better</L>
<L>Of my owne life, honour'd by your imployments.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>The <HI>Duke.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Duke, Strozzi, Ascanio.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha? <HI>Leontio.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Str.</SPEAKER>
<L>If <HI>I</HI> have any braynes, he shew'd a passion</L>
<L>Did not become him to your <HI>Dutches,</HI> S<SUP>r</SUP>.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Presumes he on his blood, above our favour?</L>
<L>Dares he but in a thought controule our pleasure,</L>
<L>No more, wee'le take noe knowledge, oh my Lord</L>
<L>You absent your selfe too much, though we confesse</L>
<L>Our State must owe much to your care, we would not</L>
<L>Your offices should wast you with imployments</L>
<L>Preserve your health <HI>I</HI> pray—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I never did</L>
<L>Enioy it more then when <HI>I</HI> studied service,</L>
<L>And duties to your grace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Musicke, the minuits</L>
<L>Are sad i'th absence of <HI>Ardelia,</HI></L>
<L>And moove too slow, quicken their pace with Luts,</L>
<L>And voices.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>A Song.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more; we will be Musicke of our selves,</L>
<L>And spare your Arts, thought of <HI>Ardelia,</HI></L>
<L>

<PB REF="8"/>
Should strike a harmony through every heart,</L>
<L>What brow lookes sad, when we command delight?</L>
<L>We shall account that man a Traytor to us,</L>
<L>That weares one sullen Cloud upon his face,</L>
<L>I'le read his soule in't, and by our bright Mistresse,</L>
<L>Then which the World containes noe richer beauty,</L>
<L>Punish his daring sinne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>He will deserve it</L>
<L>Great Sir, that shall offend with the least sadnes,</L>
<L>Or were it so possest, yet your command</L>
<L>That stretches to the soule, would make it smile,</L>
<L>And force a bravery, severe old age</L>
<L>Shall lay aside his sullen gravity,</L>
<L>And revell like a youth, the froward Matrons</L>
<L>For this day, shall repent their yeares, and coldnes</L>
<L>Of blood, and wish agen their tempting beauties</L>
<L>To dance like wanton Lovers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>My <HI>Leontio,</HI></L>
<L>In this then thou dost present our bosome to thee,</L>
<L>What's he?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Gentleman that has deserv'd</L>
<L>For service in your late warres, Sir, a Captaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>He may turne Courtier now, we have no use</L>
<L>Of noyse, we can march here without a Drumme,</L>
<L>I hope we are not in arreares to him,</L>
<L>He haunts us for noe pay?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your bounty beside that, hath wonne their hearts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why has he noe better cloathes? this is a day</L>
<L>Of Triumph.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pall.</SPEAKER>
<L>I beseech your highnes pardon,</L>
<L>I ha' drunke your health in better cloathes, dispise</L>
<L>My Christian Buffe; this is the fruits of peace,</L>
<L>I'le waite on you agen.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wher's my <HI>Ardelia?</HI></L>
<L>How at the name my spirits leape within me,</L>
<L>And the amorous winds doe catch it from my lips</L>
<L>To sweeten the Ayre—heaven at the sound</L>
<L>Lookes cleare, and lovely, and the earth put's on</L>
<L>A spring to welcome it, speake <HI>Leontio</HI></L>
<L>

<PB REF="9"/>
<HI>Strozzi,</HI> Gentlemen, but she appeares.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Ardelia, Valerio, Silvio.</STAGE>
<L>For whom the World shall weare eternall shiue,</L>
<L>Brightest <HI>Ardelia,</HI> Queene of love, and me,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>The onely honor, my ambition climes too,</L>
<L>Is to be held your highnes humblest hand-maid.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Call me thy servant, what</L>
<L>New charmes her lookes does throw upon my soule.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>How the <HI>Duke</HI> gazes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>There is some strange divinity within her,</L>
<L>Is there not <HI>Valerio?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am not read so farre yet as divinity,</L>
<L>Mine is but humane learning.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speake agen,</L>
<L>And at thy lipps the quires shall hang to learne</L>
<L>New tunes, and the dull spheres but coldly imitate,</L>
<L>I am transform'd with my excesse of rapture,</L>
<L>Frowne, frowne <HI>Ardelia</HI> I shall forget</L>
<L>I am mortall else, and when thou hast throwne downe</L>
<L>Thy servant, with one smile exalt agen</L>
<L>His heart to heaven, and with a kisse breath in me</L>
<L>Another soule fit for thy love, but all</L>
<L>My language is too could, and we wast time,</L>
<L>Lead on, ther's something of more ceremony</L>
<L>Expects our presence, <HI>Italy</HI> is barren</L>
<L>Of what we wish to entertaine <HI>Ardelia.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>May all the pleasures thought can reach attend you.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
<TRAILER>Finis Actus primi.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="9"/>
<HEAD>Actus Secundus.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Bentivolio, Horatio.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>BE counsell'd yet without being too ambitious</L>
<L>To buy a deere repentance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now we are.</L>
<L>Arriv'd at Court, shame to our resolution,</L>
<L>I prethee do'nt tempt me to such cowardise,</L>
<L><HI>Horatio</HI> I must see her, sheele not blast us,</L>
<L>She was lovely when our eyes saluted last,</L>
<L>And at my fare-well many innocent teares</L>
<L>Wittness'd her sorrow, cleere as <HI>Aprill</HI> weepes</L>
<L>Into the bosome of the Spring, not see</L>
<L><HI>Ardelia?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have travel'd since, and she</L>
<L>Wanting noe beauty, was not over willing</L>
<L>To languish in your absence, how I pity thee,</L>
<L>But that I wod not too much vexe your folly,</L>
<L>Do'st thinke ther's faith in any womans eyes,</L>
<L>She wept at parting, a strong obligation</L>
<L>When they can thread their teares, and make a chaino</L>
<L>Of water, let me weare one o' their bracelets;</L>
<L>I will convince thy madnes in six words,</L>
<L>Admit she said she lov'd you, and to your thinking</L>
<L>Vow'd it, for you say you were contracted</L>
<L>All this is nothing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<L>No.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not this; although</L>
<L>You had beene married, and i'th Sheets together,</L>
<L>And chaffer'd earnest for a boy, 'tis nothing</L>
<L>It binds not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<L>How?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not with a thousand witnesses.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<L>How not bind her?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor any woman living, that's possest</L>
<L>

<PB REF="10"/>
With a wandring spirit, clap her in a dungeon,</L>
<L>Pile three Castles on her, yet she shall</L>
<L>Breake prison when she has but the least minde too't;</L>
<L>She le worke through a Steele-mine, to meete a friend</L>
<L>That she likes better, with more ease throw up</L>
<L>A quarrie of Marble, than a Mole shall dust,</L>
<L>They worke with spirits, man, and can doe wonders,</L>
<L>Especially a hansome woman, from whose false</L>
<L>And sly temptations, all my wits defend me.</L>
<L>There were some dealing with an Elvish female,</L>
<L>That had but a course face, or say but halfe a one,</L>
<L>Emnaticke eyes, with no more sight than could</L>
<L>Distinguish well, man from a horse, or beare,</L>
<L>To keepe her from mistake in procreation,</L>
<L>A nose of many fashions, and as many</L>
<L>Water-workes in 'em, lips of honest hide,</L>
<L>And made to last, teeth of a Moores complexion,</L>
<L>A chinne, without all controversie, good</L>
<L>To goe a fishing with, a witches beard on't,</L>
<L>With twentie other commendations, such a thing</L>
<L>Were no mischiefe, and a man might trust</L>
<L>Her with no scruple in his Conscience.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is plaine madnesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>You may call it so,</L>
<L>But Ile be bound to travell further with</L>
<L>This Night-mare, than the finest flesh and blood</L>
<L>You court, and call your mistresse, why the Devill</L>
<L>With all his art, and malice will nere cuckold me,</L>
<L>And I should leave her in hell, and goe a journey,</L>
<L>I should be sure at my returne to find her</L>
<L>Safe, and untouch'd, sound of her winde, and limbs;</L>
<L>A faire, and hansome woman would not scape so:</L>
<L>You have my opinion now, and 'twere lesse evill</L>
<L>To practise it, you mind not my instructions.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>These Lectures have L read toth' City</L>
<L>With the same successe, that Gentlemen might live honest,</L>
<L>And men have lucke to father their owne children,</L>
<L>But 'twill not be, you are resolv'd to try it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>

<PB REF="10"/>
Ben.</SPEAKER>
<L>Am I engag'd thus farre to fall backe now?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Remember where you are yet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am i'th Court.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where you expect to complement with the <HI>Dukes</HI>—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<L>What?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>What doe you thinke? the <HI>Dukes</HI> married,</L>
<L>They say although he love <HI>Ardelia,</HI></L>
<L>And without question, in these parts may want</L>
<L>No intelligence of your purpose, and your person,</L>
<L>And theres no doubt, but if he find you quaile-catching,</L>
<L>He has power enough to coole your blood, and hers,</L>
<L>Should she remember what has past betweene you,</L>
<L>In that respect be caution'd, doe not worke</L>
<L>A double ruine, to sooth one vaine humour;</L>
<L>Eyes will beget an appetite of more neerenesse,</L>
<L>And how that may succed, 'tis better feare, than prove.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<L>I prethee fright me not with shadowes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are then for her substance—ile not leave you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile see her did the Duke proclaime it death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>I Had rather see the Cow, with her five legges,</L>
<L>And all the Monsters in the market, then</L>
<L>Be troubled with the spectacle, but on,</L>
<L>Stay, yet will you but see her? will her face content you,</L>
<L>A farre off, without multiplying twinckles,</L>
<L>Ridiculous sighes, or crost armes pinion'd thus,</L>
<L>As the Kinght-Templers leggs are, whollie buried,</L>
<L>Like Taylors, no djected lookes, as y'ad</L>
<L>Your father alive agen to send you out</L>
<L>To sea, with pention to maintaine you in bisket,</L>
<L>Poore John, and halfe a livery, which should be</L>
<L>Part of your governor, to read morrall vertue</L>
<L>And lenton Lectures to you, or if she frowne</L>
<L>As much as say my friend, <HI>I</HI> am not for you,</L>
<L>The Dukes the better Gentleman, and shall pay for't</L>
<L>Will you returne then with a handsome patience,</L>
<L>And wisely love where no man els will rivall you,</L>
<L>A Witch or some old woman,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<L>I prethee leave</L>
<L>Thy phrenzy, thou shal't witnes ile be temperate.</L>
<STAGE>

<PB REF="11"/>
Enter Valerio.</STAGE>
<L>Who's this? Signior <HI>Valerio.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Bentivolio,</HI> welcome to</L>
<L><HI>Pavie,</HI> and the Court.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<L>My friend, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>You both divide me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then <HI>I</HI> am no stranger,</L>
<L>In confidence of that friendship we both seal'd</L>
<L>In Travell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>What affaires brought you to <HI>Pavie?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<L>Being at large, I had curiositie</L>
<L>To observe what might improve my knowledge here</L>
<L>With some taste of your Court.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>And <HI>I</HI> am happie</L>
<L><HI>I</HI> have some power to serve your wish, nor could you</L>
<L>Arrive to see it shine with more delight,</L>
<L>It is compos'd of revells, now all ayrc,</L>
<L>Let me present you to the Duke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall be honour'd to kisse his hand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sha't see his Mistresse,</L>
<L>The faire <HI>Ardelia,</HI> the Dukes no saint,</L>
<L>I may tell thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray Sir, with your favour,</L>
<L>Cannot the Court furnish a Gentleman,</L>
<L>And need be, with an uglie face or two,</L>
<L>Such as would turne your stomacke, would content</L>
<L>My fancie best.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>What meanes your friend?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<L>A humour he playes withall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ual.</SPEAKER>
<L>He would not play with such a woman, wo'd he?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, and if the place be not</L>
<L>Too barren to afford me one ill-favoured</L>
<L>Enough.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nere feare it, they are common here</L>
<L>As Crowes, and something of a hue by moone-shine</L>
<L>Promise to keepe your wits, and ile present you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have a lease Sir, of my braines, and dare</L>
<L>

<PB REF="11"/>
Enconnter with an armie out of <HI>Lapland.</HI></L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Musicke, and Song in Dialogue.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter the Duke, Ardelia, Fiametta, Leontio, Strozzi, Ascanio, Silvio, Ladies.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duk.</SPEAKER>
<L>How likes <HI>Ardelia</HI> this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ard.</SPEAKER>
<L>If it affect</L>
<L>Your highnesse eare, dutie hath so compos'd</L>
<L>My will to obedience, I must praise the musicke,</L>
<L>And wish no other object to that sence,</L>
<L>Unlesse you please to expresse more harmonie</L>
<L>By some commands from your owne voice, that will</L>
<L>Challenge my more religious attention.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>What charme is in her language? cease all other</L>
<L>(But discord to her accents) what a sweet,</L>
<L>And winning soule she has, is it not pity</L>
<L>She should be lesse than Dutchesse, farre above</L>
<L><HI>Euphemia</HI> in beautie, and rare softnesse</L>
<L>Of nature, I could wonder, gaze for ever;</L>
<L>But I expose my passion too much</L>
<L>To censure, yet who dares dispute our will?</L>
<L><HI>Leontio</HI> looke upon <HI>Ardelia,</HI></L>
<L>And tell me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>What Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duk.</SPEAKER>
<L>Canst see nothing there?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I see a spacious field of beautie Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duk.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis poore, and short of her perfection,</L>
<L>Beare her this other Jewell, I will have her</L>
<L>Shine like a volumne of bright constellations,</L>
<L>Till all the world turne her Idolater:</L>
<L>When did <HI>Euphemia</HI> looke thus?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Never sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duk.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be Judge thy selfe <HI>Leontio,</HI> if my Dutches</L>
<L>Lov'd me, could she denie her <HI>Dionisio</HI></L>
<L>This happinesse, but she has a stubborne soule.</L>
<L>She has, and shall repent it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, remember</L>
<L>

<PB REF="12"/>
Shee is a princesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>You were best remember her,</L>
<L>Perhaps sheele take it kindlie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, I hope</L>
<L>You have more assurance of my faith to you</L>
<L>Then to interpret—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nothing, come, all's well,</L>
<L>Name her noe more, how ere she has displeas'd</L>
<L>Us, you can violate noe duty still</L>
<L>To love her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>This infects delight,</L>
<L>Let's dance my sweete <HI>Ardelia.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>The <HI>Dukes</HI> jealous</L>
<L>Or i'me batraid.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Leontio, Silvio, Strozzi,</HI></L>
<L>The Ladies blush for you, they have breath'd too much.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>While the Dance is Enter Valerio, Bentivolio, Horatio.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, here are gentlemen desire the grace</L>
<L>To kisse your highnesse hand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Ardelia</HI> supply our Dutchesse absence,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is the <HI>Dukes</HI> desire by his example, you extend your</L>
<L>Faire hand to a payre of strangers, ambitions of the</L>
<L>Honour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ard.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Bentivolio?</HI></L>
<L>Tis he, how my heart trembles as my frame</L>
<L>Would fall to peeces, doe you know that gentleman?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let him attend me in my lodgings</L>
<L>It will be worth your friend-ship to conduct him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your countenance changes, I observ'd</L>
<L>Your eyes upon that Stranger.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>He revewes</L>
<L>The memory of a brother, I lov'd dearely,</L>
<L>

<PB REF="12"/>
That died at Sea: I ne're saw two so like.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>For representing one so neare <HI>Ardelia,</HI></L>
<L>Receive another welcome, and what favours</L>
<L>Your thoughts can study from our Court, possesse 'em.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<L>You oblige my humblest services—how now, how dost like this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why scuruily, you flatter</L>
<L>Your selfe into distruction, I see</L>
<L>The Arrow will peirce thy heart, decline it yet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<L>Still frantickely opposing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>I ha' done</L>
<L>Be mad, i'le give my braine to somewhat els,</L>
<L>Sir, I'wod see a phisnomy, though it looke</L>
<L>As big as the fower winds, I ha' court-ship for it,</L>
<L>And wo not he blowne off with an Hericano,</L>
<L>Yet trust me i'le be honest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va.</SPEAKER>
<L>I beleeve you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Onely to please my eye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va.</SPEAKER>
<L>What thinke you of</L>
<L>That Divells lans-schape, you observ'd not her,</L>
<L>Notwithstanding her complexion, she is a Lady</L>
<L>Usefull at Court, to set of other faces,</L>
<L>Especially the <HI>Dukes</HI> Mistres, whom for that,</L>
<L>And some thing else his grace has recommended</L>
<L>To be her companion, will she serve turne?</L>
<L>Did you ever see a more excellent wall-eye</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>I marry, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay let me prepare you,</L>
<L>Madam dee observe that Gentleman,</L>
<L>The <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>aring Stranger, he has busines to you,</L>
<L>And you will bid it welcome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Does he know me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va.</SPEAKER>
<L>He inquir'd for you</L>
<L>By all discriptions—and I guesse he may</L>
<L>Be worth your favour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mine?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val</SPEAKER>
<L>If ever man</L>
<L>Were an Jdolater, he is yours, i'le bring him</L>
<L>To your lodgings Madam, if you please.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fia.</SPEAKER>
<L>You'le honour me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>

<PB REF="13"/>
Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Agen to our revells, ther's noe life without being active,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not now? you shall have opportunity, </L>
<L>And I have commission to informe you something,</L>
</SP>
<L>Away here's like to be a Storme.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Euphemia.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's shee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va.</SPEAKER>
<L>Euphemia.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Str.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your <HI>Dutches,</HI> Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>How dares shee interrupt us?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>A guard about my heart, I am undone e'ls.</L>
<L>Each looke, and motion in her greife present</L>
<L>Such a commanding sweetnes, if I observe</L>
<L>With the same eyes I shall betray my selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eup.</SPEAKER>
<L>I come not Sir, with rudenes of my language,</L>
<L>Or person to offend your mirth, although</L>
<L>the nature of my sorrow is so wild</L>
<L>It may infect weake minds, and such as have not</L>
<L>Some proofe in their owne bosomes, but to make</L>
<L>One, and my last suite, which when you have heard</L>
<L>It may appeare so reasonable, and proportion'd</L>
<L>To what your thoughts allow me, that you will</L>
<L>Find easily a consent to make it fortunate,</L>
<L>And me in the prevailing.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ardelia offers to depart.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe not moove.</L>
<L><HI>Ardelia,</HI> I am full protection here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eup.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ther's something sir in my request to make her happy too,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ard.</SPEAKER>
<L>I dare not heare the <HI>Dutchesse,</HI></L>
<L>Her lookes wound me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speake your promising wishes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eup.</SPEAKER>
<L>Although I know not for what guilt in me</L>
<L>Of more then my obedience, and some lesse</L>
<L>Beauty then dwells upon <HI>Ardelias</HI> cheeke,</L>
<L>You have exild me from your love, and bosome,</L>
<L>And worse then one condemn<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d by force of lawes,</L>
<L>For sinne against your bed have sentenc'd me</L>
<L>To wander with disgrace, carv'd in my brow</L>
<L>The Fable of a <HI>Dutchesse,</HI> and your anger;</L>
<L>My desires are you would have so much charity</L>
<L>

<PB REF="13"/>
Though you have made me an out-law by your doome,</L>
<L>Not to compell me after all my shames</L>
<L>To be a murderer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Treason, our Guard.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eup.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall not trouble Sir your feares I bring</L>
<L>the least blacke thought against your person, heaven</L>
<L>Avert so foule à sinne, the danger all</L>
<L>Doth threaten me, and my life, which I thus</L>
<L>Most humbly beg may not be forc'd through blood</L>
<L>By my owne hands <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>urgd by your heavy wrongs</L>
<L>To such a desperate mutiny, which you may</L>
<L>Prevent by your revenge of Law upon me.</L>
<L>To which, and your displeasure I would yeild</L>
<L>My life your welcome sacrifice, i'le praise</L>
<L>Your mercy for my death, and blesse the stroake</L>
<L>Devids my sad soule from me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>This your project?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did you heare the <HI>Dutches</HI> suite?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ard.</SPEAKER>
<L>Noe, but i'le beg</L>
<L>It may be granted, doe not sir deny</L>
<L>Your <HI>Dutches</HI> her desires so just, and reasonable;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>How's this? shee'le pray to be rid on her,</L>
<L>Audacious woman</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eup.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me rise with horror.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Ardelia</HI> knowes not what <HI>Euphemia</HI> ask'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>She'le appeare cunning.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ard.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am confident</L>
<L>She hath propounded nothing ill becoming.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nothing, a very trifle, wearied with</L>
<L>Her injuries she onely begs the <HI>Duke</HI></L>
<L>Would be so kind to order with as much</L>
<L>Conveniency as he please, her head to be</L>
<L>Chop'd of, that all, and you were charitable</L>
<L>To joyne so modestly in the advancement</L>
<L>Of her desires.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ard.</SPEAKER>
<L>Defend it heaven,</L>
<L>Madam your pardon, I imagin'd not</L>
<L>You aym'd such cruelty upon your selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eup.</SPEAKER>
<L>Proud, and dissembling woman, at such impudence</L>
<L>

<PB REF="14"/>
I take my spirit to me, and no more</L>
<L>Will put my breath to the expence of prayer</L>
<L>To be short-liv'd, I will desire to live</L>
<L>To see heaven drop downe justice, with such loud,</L>
<L>And publicke noyse of my revenge on thee,</L>
<L>And thy adulterate arts, as the world naming</L>
<L>But once <HI>Ardelia,</HI> shall be palsey-strucke.</L>
<L>I feele a new, and fiery soule within me,</L>
<L>Apt to disperse my rage, which feare and my</L>
<L>Religion would ha' stifled. Oh my fate!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>She raves, to prison with her, we are not safe</L>
<L>While she enjoyes the freedome of our ayre:</L>
<L>Stay (my good Genius) she carries yet</L>
<L>The title of our Dutches; tis our pleasure</L>
<L><HI>Leontio,</HI> she be your prisoner,</L>
<L>But see her narrowlie confind, till we</L>
<L>Determine what shall follow, in what we</L>
<L>Limit, you not make your owne reason guide,</L>
<L>But on your life secure her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your commands</L>
<L>In all things I obey, most blest occasion!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Foole, thou dost entertain what must undo thee,</L>
<L>And make you both ripe for eternall absence;</L>
<L>Hug <HI>Juno</HI> in the clouds, and court her smiles,</L>
<L>Though she consent not, tis enough youl stand</L>
<L>Suspected, and expos'd to equall danger.</L>
<L>You sha'not lose your ayre to plead for death,</L>
<L>Thus wele secure <HI>Ardelia.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eup.</SPEAKER>
<L>I heare,</L>
<L>And with all chearefullnesse resigne my will</L>
<L>To imprisonment, or death; forgive the wildnesse,</L>
<L>And furie of my language, I repent</L>
<L>My wish upon <HI>Ardelia,</HI> may she live</L>
<L>To doe so too, and you to be possest</L>
<L>Of all joyes, Earth and Heaven can blesse your heart with</L>
<L>May danger never in a dreame affright you,</L>
<L>And if you thinke I live too long, tis possible,</L>
<L>Before you send death to conclude my sufferings,</L>
<L>Some thoughts of you may wither my poore heart,</L>
<L>

<PB REF="14"/>
And make your path smooth, to what most you joy in</L>
<L>Be not a tyrant when i'me dead, upon</L>
<L>My fame, although you wish me not alive,</L>
<L>Yet say I was <HI>Euphemia,</HI> let that sticke</L>
<L>Upon my Tombe, if you will grace my shade</L>
<L>With so much cost, in that name is supplied</L>
<L>Enough to tell the world for whom I died.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>We heare too much, away with her.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
<TRAILER>Finis Actus Secundi.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus Tertius.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Bentivolio, Valerio, Horatio.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<L>I Have given a treasure to your bosome Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shannot friend repent it, and this act</L>
<L>Of so much confidence, new binds my faith to you;</L>
<L>Contracted to <HI>Ardelia?</HI> I may chance make use of this.</L>
<L>Your pilgrimage ends here—</L>
<STAGE>Exit Ualerio</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe you know</L>
<L>What you have done?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have told him what</L>
<L>Concern'd <HI>Ardelia,</HI> and my selfe; thou wod'st</L>
<L>Suspect, and chide my credulous nature, come,</L>
<L>Ile trust him with my life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's done already,</L>
<L>He has a secret, much good doe him wo't,</L>
<L>Should ha' burnt a passage through my heart, and left</L>
<L>It ashes, ere th'ad wandred from me thus,</L>
<L>And if you never did before, pray now</L>
<L>He may be honost to you, tis too late</L>
<L>To finde compunction for it, pray, and heartily</L>
<L>He may be dumbe.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Valerio and Ardelia.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>

<PB REF="15"/>
Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Signior <HI>Bentivolio?</HI></L>
<STAGE>Exit Ardelia, and Bentivolio.</STAGE>
<L>So, so, thats over, now ile conduct you</L>
<L>To your pretious Saint, unlesse your bloud turne</L>
<L>Coward.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ob, never feare it, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>But would you did</L>
<L>First tell me and discharge me of some wonder,</L>
<L>You have an humor of the newest fashion</L>
<L>I ere yet saw, and how the Court may follow't</L>
<L>I know not, how long have you beene possest Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Possest? what Divell doe you meane? </L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>With these ilfavour'd, deform'd women, y'are bewitchd sure?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou dost not know the fiends I have convers'd with.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ual.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have no ambition to be acquainted</L>
<L>With any Goblins, further then their knowledge</L>
<L>Might make me understand the ground of your</L>
<L>Inchantment.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh a world, Legions, Legions.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Of what?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Of hansome women.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>They the cause of this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Their false, and periur'd natures, I nere met with</L>
<L>One hansome Face that made a conscience of me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>And dee' thinke to finde</L>
<L>More Faith in those that looke all ore like Devills?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis possible they may have soules, who knowes?</L>
<L>Howe're in my revenge, ile love, and doate on 'em,</L>
<L>And iustifie thy are the Sexes glorie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have enough.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Ardelia, and Bentivolio.</STAGE>
<L>They are return'd, this way Sir, to your Fayrie.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>My dearest <HI>Bentivolio,</HI> why dost stand</L>
<L>At so much gaze, and distance, as thou wod'st</L>
<L>Teach love unkindnesse, can these out ward formes</L>
<L>Disguise me from thy knowledge, lets salute,</L>
<L>My lips retaine their softnesse, and unles</L>
<L>

<PB REF="15"/>
Thy love be chang'd, our breath may meet, and we</L>
<L>Convey the heartie meaning of our soules,</L>
<L>As we once did.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'are very brave <HI>Ardelia,</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>But have no pride without you, these are no</L>
<L>Glories compar'd to what I weare within,</L>
<L>To see thee safe, whom my feares gave up lost,</L>
<L>And after so much absence, doe <HI>I</HI> live</L>
<L>To embrace my <HI>Bentivolio?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<L>You would have me</L>
<L>Beleeve <HI>J</HI> am welcome hither, faire <HI>Ardelia,</HI></L>
<L>Pardon, I know not yet what other name</L>
<L>To call you by, and if <HI>I</HI> wrong your titles,</L>
<L>Be gentle to my ignorance; this hand</L>
<L>You gave me once, when no ambition frighted</L>
<L>The troth we vow'd, our chast simplicity</L>
<L>Durst kisse without a shame, or feare to be</L>
<L>Divorc'd by greatnes, tell me, sweet <HI>Ardelia,</HI></L>
<L>When <HI>I</HI> did court thy Virgin faith, and paid</L>
<L>An innocent tribute to thy most chast lip,</L>
<L>When we had spent the day with our discourse,</L>
<L>And night came rudely in to part us, what</L>
<L>Were then thy usuall dreames? how many visions</L>
<L>Were let into thy sleepe, thou shouldst be great,</L>
<L>Torne from my bosome, to enrich thy selfe,</L>
<L>And a Dukes armes? and that a time should come,</L>
<L>When I, the promisd Master of this wealth,</L>
<L>Should thus present my selfe a beggar to thee,</L>
<L>And count thy smiles a charitie?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ard.</SPEAKER>
<L>What meanes</L>
<L>My <HI>Bentivolio</HI> by this passionate language?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe confesse <HI>I</HI> was compell'd to be</L>
<L>An exile from thee, in obedience to</L>
<L>My father, who would trust me to the Seas,</L>
<L>Or any land, ere leave me to this shipwracke,</L>
<L>For so his anger sinn'd against thy beautie,</L>
<L>Whilst the Idoll Gold grac'd not thy fairer Temple,</L>
<L>Yet when we plighted hearts, <HI>Ardelia,</HI></L>
<L><HI>I</HI> tied with mine an everlasting contract,</L>
<L>

<PB REF="16"/>
And did expect at my returne to have found</L>
<L>Thine spotles.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ard.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis the same.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<L>The same to me?</L>
<L>What makes you here then? doe not, doe not flatter</L>
<L>Thy guilt so much. Is not this <HI>Pavias</HI> Court?</L>
<L><HI>Ardelias</HI> Court indeed, for she rules here,</L>
<L>The Lady <HI>Paramount</HI> whilst the <HI>Duke</HI> himselfe</L>
<L>Bowes like a subject!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be not, Sir too credulous,</L>
<L>And with too apprehensive thoughts doe injury</L>
<L>To that which you should cherish, the <HI>Duke</HI> is—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<L>Youle say none of your subiect,</L>
<L>He is a prince,</L>
<L>Prince of your Province, writs <HI>Ardelia</HI> his,</L>
<L>Tis ravish'd all from me, and I am become</L>
<L>A stranger to my owne, nay stand, and see</L>
<L>My treasure rifled, all my wealth tane from me,</L>
<L>And dare not question the injurious power</L>
<L>That revells in my glory, but canst thinke</L>
<L>I will be cold for ever, that all seeds</L>
<L>Of man lie dead within me, and my soule</L>
<L>Sunke in my phlegme, will never rise to forme</L>
<L>Some iust revenge? thinke there are then noe furies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ard.</SPEAKER>
<L>You come to threaten not to love, and having</L>
<L>Already by long absence made a fault,</L>
<L>To quit your selfe would lay astaine on me,</L>
<L>Tis not well done.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter a Servant.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>The <HI>Duke.</HI></L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<L>The <HI>Duke?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ard.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis possible</L>
<L>He may not feare your anger.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le squat then</L>
<L>Behind this Hedge, this Garden hath quient shades,</L>
<L>I hope you'le not betray me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ard.</SPEAKER>
<L>This the forme</L>
<L>Of your revenge,</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>

<PB REF="16"/>
Enter Duke.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>My faire <HI>Ardelia</HI></L>
<L>Excuse me if I presse upon thy private</L>
<L>Walkes, love gives a bouldnes to meane spirits,</L>
<L>But in a Princes brest: tis much more active,</L>
<L>And feares noe imputation, what doth fright</L>
<L>Thy countenance? I hope <HI>Ardelia</HI></L>
<L>My presence brings noe horror.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ard.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, much comfort,</L>
<L>Whether it were my fancie or a truth</L>
<L>I know not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's the matter?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ard.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have noe satires</L>
<L>Within this ground, doe any haunte this Garden?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Satiers?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ard.</SPEAKER>
<L>As I have read 'em character'd,</L>
<L>So one appear'd, or I imagin'd so,</L>
<L>And as you entred hid himselfe, they are</L>
<L>Halfe men——</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Halfe beasts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ard.</SPEAKER>
<L>With Goats hornes in their fore-head,</L>
<L>The thought on't troubles me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>The effect onely of melancholie thoughts,</L>
<L>Noe such things are</L>
<L>In nature, yet i'le search, and—strange apprehension.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twas more then shape, sure it did talke to me,</L>
<L>And threaten me sor your sake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>How? for mine?</L>
<L>I'le have the Trees, and Arbors all torne up,</L>
<L>Divels lurke here? the earth shall not secure 'em,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ard.</SPEAKER>
<L>He said he lov'd me, and accus'd my heart</L>
<L>Of periury, as we had beene contracted.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>More strange! my guard!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ard.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay sir, before you goe</L>
<L>Let me beseech your iustice in defence</L>
<L>Of my much iniur'd honour, as you are</L>
<L>A Prince, I doe beseech you speake all truth,</L>
<L>For let him be the Divell, I'le not have</L>
<L>

<PB REF="17"/>
My innocence abus'd, I know not from</L>
<L>What fame, or fond opinion voic'd of me,</L>
<L>By some that had more thought to serve your will</L>
<L>Then vertue, I was made beleeve you lov'd me,</L>
<L>Which though my force resisted by some practises,</L>
<L>You gaind my person hither, and in Court</L>
<L>Command my stay.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Entreat, my best <HI>Ardelia.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>You may Sir, smooth your cause, but I can fetch</L>
<L>A witnes from my bosome to convince</L>
<L>The truth I urge, yet let me not be lost</L>
<L>To gratitude, my soule bids me acknowledge</L>
<L>Never was subiect to a Prince more bound</L>
<L>For free, and beauteous graces, then <HI>Ardelia</HI></L>
<L>To your highnes, and with many lives to wast</L>
<L>In service for them, I were still in debt to you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis in thy power to satisfie for all,</L>
<L>And leave me ten times more oblig'd to thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me for this time beg on answer from you,</L>
<L>Although I am not ignorant, what price</L>
<L>Your wild bloud would exact, speake in the eare</L>
<L>Of silent heaven, have you obteyn'd so much</L>
<L>As one stoope to your wanton avarice,</L>
<L>One bend to please your inflam'd appetite.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du</SPEAKER>
<L>Not any yet, the more unkind <HI>Ardelia.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speake clearely by the honour of a Prince.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>By better hopes I sweare, and by thy selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>You doe me Sir, but Justice, I will study</L>
<L>To pay my humblest duty, and i'le tell</L>
<L>When next <HI>I</HI> see the Satire——</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>To discharge those feares, i'le presently destroy,</L>
<L>This Garden, and not leave shelter,</L>
<L>For a Bird.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar</SPEAKER>
<L>Your pardon,</L>
<L>To what wo'd my immagination lead me?</L>
<L>I see all was but melancholie, here was nothing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fruits of a troubled fancie, come be pleasant,</L>
<L>And tell me when you will redeeme your cruelty,</L>
<L>

<PB REF="17"/>
It may incline you somewhat to remember</L>
<L>By what soft wayes I have persued your love,</L>
<L>How nobly <HI>I</HI> would serue you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Love, your grace</L>
<L>Knowes, never was compelld.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>But love should find</L>
<L>Compassion to the wound it makes, I bleed,</L>
<L>And court thy gentle pity to my sufferings,</L>
<L>All Princes are not of so calme a temper,</L>
<L>Thinke of it my <HI>Ardelia,</HI> and reward</L>
<L>The modest expectations of a heart,</L>
<L>That in thy absence withers, but i'le have thee</L>
<L>To chide thy cruell thoughts, and till our lipps</L>
<L>Salute agen, flatter my selfe with hope</L>
<L>Thy nature will be wise, and kind to love,</L>
<L>Where tis so fairely courted.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is he gone?</L>
<L>With what acknowledgment of my fault <HI>Ardelia</HI></L>
<L>Shall I beseech thy pardon, I am lost</L>
<L>In wonder of thy innocence; 'twere just</L>
<L>I should suspect the truth of my owne bosome,</L>
<L>Thou hast too rich a goodnes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now you flatter,</L>
<L>I knew noe way o'th suddaine to convince you,</L>
<L>But by the <HI>Dukes</HI> confession, I am yet</L>
<L>Preseru'd my <HI>Bentivolio,</HI> but with what</L>
<L>Danger of being lost to thee, and honour</L>
<L>I shall remaine here, may concerne our Jealousie,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<L>Together with the knowledge of thy vertue</L>
<L>Like balsome powr'd into my eare, I tooke</L>
<L>A poyson from the <HI>Duke,</HI> I find he loves thee</L>
<L>With a blacke purpose, and within his language</L>
<L>Was something worth our feare indeede, it will</L>
<L>Require our study, and much art, <HI>Ardelia.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let's retire into my chamber, and mature</L>
<L>Some course for both our safeties.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<L>I attend you.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>

<PB REF="18"/>
Enter Valerio, Horatio, Fiametta.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<P>I wo'not stay three minutes, ile but step aside for di∣stillation. I leave you the pleasure of your eyes.</P>
<STAGE>Exit</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, goe thy waies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe you not mocke me Sir, shall I beleeve</L>
<L>A Gentleman of your neate, and elegant making,</L>
<L>Can stoope to such a creature as I am.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you have me sweare?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fia.</SPEAKER>
<L>By no meanes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then I wo'not,</L>
<L>But I will give it thee under my hand,</L>
<L>Read that.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fia.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Something to shew I hate all hansome women.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is't a song?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>It may be, with a voice, and tune put too't,</L>
<L>Ile reade it.</L>
<STAGE>He reads.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Ualerio, with Aurelia, and Macrina veild.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>L am come agen Sir, and choose, rather then</L>
<L>To afflict you with expectation,</L>
<L>To bring my company along, you may</L>
<L>Salute 'em if you please.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are not welcome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you beleeve me now?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>If we may trust our eies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ladies you must excuse me, I affect</L>
<L>No vulgar beauties, give me a complexion</L>
<L>Cannot be match'd agen in twenty kingdomes,</L>
<L>You have eies, and nose, and lips, and other parts</L>
<L>Proportion'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sure the Gentlemans distracted.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, I am recover'd, <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> thanke my starres,</L>
<L>To know, and heartily abhorre such faces,</L>
<L>What come they hither for? dee' know 'em Madam?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>

<PB REF="18"/>
Fia.</SPEAKER>
<L>I had no purpose they should be my guests</L>
<L>At this time, th'are court Ladies, I confesse,</L>
<L>Signior <HI>Valerio</HI> this was your plot.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ual.</SPEAKER>
<L>My pure intention, Madam, to doe you</L>
<L>Service, I knew they were not for his pallate,</L>
<L>These will inflame his appetite to you,</L>
<L>And set you off, meere foiles to you doe they</L>
<L>Looke as they were ambitious to be</L>
<L>Compar'd with you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Noble sir, although</L>
<L>I have not beautie like these Ladies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho</SPEAKER>
<L>How? you ha' not beautie, take heed doe not shew</L>
<L>Your selfe unthankfull to wise nature, do not</L>
<L>They ha' not wealth enough in all their bodies</L>
<L>To purchase such a nose.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mac.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, ha.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, ha, good Madam Kick shaw,</L>
<L>That laugh to shew how many teeth you have.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be not uncivill Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why does that Fayrie grin then?</L>
<L>I'le justifie there is more worth, and beautie,</L>
<L>Consider d wisely, and as it preserves</L>
<L>Man in his wits, and sence, than can be read</L>
<L>I'th volumne of their flattering Generations.</L>
<L>Good Madam looke a squint, a little more,</L>
<L>So, keepe but that cast with your eies, and tell me</L>
<L>Whose sight is best, hers that can see at once</L>
<L>More severall waies then there are points i'th Com-passe,</L>
<L>Or theirs that lookes but point-blancke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mac.</SPEAKER>
<L>A new way</L>
<L>To commend the eies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>You thinke your fore-head pleases.</L>
<L>Whose top with frizled, and curld haire beset,</L>
<L>Appeares like a white cliffe, with reeds upon't;</L>
<L>Your nose, which like an <HI>Isthmus</HI> parts two Seas.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Seas? you meane eies agen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ual.</SPEAKER>
<L>What of their nose?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will be in danger, with continuall beating</L>
<L>Of waves, to wash the paint off, and in time</L>
<L>

<PB REF="19"/>
May fall, and put you to the charge of building</L>
<L>A silver bridge for praises to passe over.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mac.</SPEAKER>
<L>We'l barre your commendations.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>It sha'not need,</L>
<L>I doe not melt my wits to verse upon</L>
<L>Such subject, here's an instrument to smell with,</L>
<L>Tough as an Elephants trunke, and will hold water.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>It has a comely length, and is well studded</L>
<L>With gems of price, the gold-smith wo'd bid money for't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is he not mad?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>I can assure you no,</L>
<L>And by this token I would rather be</L>
<L>Condemn'd to'th Gallies, then be once in love</L>
<L>With either of your phisnomies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mac.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is't possible?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>You may put your whole faith upon't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dee' beleeve him?</L>
<L>Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Methinkes this is the prettiest mirth,</L>
<L>You have a mighty wit, could you be angry</L>
<L>I love you for't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mac.</SPEAKER>
<L>His humor takes me infinitely.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>It does, and you doe love me for't?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mac.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most strangely.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>I</HI> would you did, and heartily.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mac.</SPEAKER>
<L>What?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Love me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mac.</SPEAKER>
<L>So well, <HI>I</HI> could be happy in thy wife.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Could Fate make me so miserable if <HI>I</HI> did not</L>
<L>In lesse than a sennight breake thy heart, shu'dst</L>
<L>Cuck old me at my owne perill.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>This Lady has</L>
<L>A mightie estate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis all the fault she has,</L>
<L>Would she had none, had she no house, nor clothes,</L>
<L>Nor meanes to feed, yet <HI>I</HI> would sooner marry,</L>
<L>Observe, this naked salvage, then embrace</L>
<L>The fairest woman of the earth, with power</L>
<L>To make me Lord of <HI>Italy, I</HI> should alwayes</L>
<L>

<PB REF="19"/>
Enjoy my health.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Her very face would keepe</L>
<L>Your bodie soluble.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>No feares compell me</L>
<L>To be a prisoner to my dining-roome,</L>
<L>I might hawke, hunt, and travell to both <HI>Indies.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Give any Doctor leave to give her Phisicke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mac.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or change of Ayre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Save much in your owne diet,</L>
<L>Which else would call for Amber-greece, and rootes,</L>
<L>And stirring cullices.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>You might allow her</L>
<L>To visit Maskes and Playes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ual.</SPEAKER>
<L>And the Bordellos,</L>
<L>I thinke she would be honest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>And thats more</L>
<L>Then any Christian conscience dare assure</L>
<L>By oath on your behalfe to be short Ladies,</L>
<L>Howe're you may interpret it my humour,</L>
<L>Mine'sa <HI>Platonicke</HI> love, give me the soule,</L>
<L>I care not what course flesh, and blood inshrine it;</L>
<L>Preserve your beauties, this will feare no blasting:</L>
<L>I beg you call me servant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did you heare him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fia.</SPEAKER>
<L>You must acknowledge then <HI>I</HI> am your Mistresse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile weare your Perriwig for my Plume, and boast</L>
<L>More honour int, than to be minion</L>
<L>To all the Ladies of the Court, deere Mistresse</L>
<L>If you can love a man, jeere 'em a little.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faire Ladies will you in, and taste a banquet,</L>
<L>Be not discountenanc'd that this Gentleman</L>
<L>Is merrie with your beauties the Spring lasts</L>
<L>Not all the yeare, when nature that commands</L>
<L>Our regiment will say, faces about,</L>
<L>We may bee in fashion, no controwling destiny.</L>
<L>Passion, who curld your haire? here wanteth powder,</L>
<L>Who is your Mercer, Madam? <HI>I</HI> would know</L>
<L>What your cheeke stands you in a weeke in Taffata?</L>
<L>Your face at distance shewes like spotted Ermine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>

<PB REF="20"/>
Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or like a dish of white-broth strew'd with Currains.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Right servant, that was a more proper simily,</L>
<L>Discretion should ha put more ceruse here,</L>
<L>Your fucus was ill made, d'ee you not lie</L>
<L>In a maske all night, Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou dost in a vizard</L>
<L>I will be sworne how the rude Gipsie triumphs</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Enough, they now begin to swell, and sweate,</L>
<L>Let's leave 'em.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va.</SPEAKER>
<L>What a <HI>Hecate</HI> was this?</L>
<L>Will you not be reveng'd?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, if we knew</L>
<L>By what convenient stratagem.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have it,</L>
<L>There is another creature of my acquaintance,</L>
<L>If you have faith more monstrous then this beldam,</L>
<L>I will possesse her with this gentlemans humor,</L>
<L>And skrew her up to be this witches rivall, what thinke you of that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Au.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will it not make her mad?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>I wo'd goe a pilgrimage to see't, 'twill be</L>
<L>A mirth beyond the Beares.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Au.</SPEAKER>
<L>Loose no time then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le fit him with a female fury, such</L>
<L>As the Divell with a pitch-forke will not touch.</L>
<L>Come Madam.</L>
<STAGE>Exit,</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Leontio, Euphemia.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Have comfort Madam,</L>
<L>I prophecy your sufferings are short-liv'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eup.</SPEAKER>
<L>You meane I shall die shortly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>We shall find</L>
<L>Lesse want of all the Starres, the aged World</L>
<L>May spare their light, while 'tis possest of yours,</L>
<L>Which once extinguish'd, let those golden fires</L>
<L>Quite burne themselves to ashes, in whose heape</L>
<L>Day may be lost, and frighted heaven weare blacke</L>
<L>Before the generall doome, have bolder thoughts,</L>
<L>And bid us all live in your onely safety.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>

<PB REF="20"/>
Eup.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let not your fancy mocke the lost <HI>Euphemia?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let not the apprehension of your sorrow</L>
<L>Destroy your hope, should the <HI>Duke</HI> never wake</L>
<L>His sences steep'd in his adulterate lethargy</L>
<L>You cannot want protection, nor your will</L>
<L>To be reveng'd, an arme to punish his</L>
<L>Contempt of so much beauty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eup.</SPEAKER>
<L>How my Lord?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>What <HI>Scithian</HI> can behold an outrage done</L>
<L>Upon these eyes, and not melt his rough nature</L>
<L>In soft compassion to attend your teares?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eup.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord I know not with what words to thanke</L>
<L>Your feeling of my sufferings. I will now</L>
<L>Beleeve I am not lost to all the World;</L>
<L>You are noble, and I must be confident</L>
<L>These streames flow from your charity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Loe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe not injure</L>
<L>The unvalued wealth of your owne honour Madam,</L>
<L>Let pore deserts be worth our charity,</L>
<L>All sacrifice of greife for you is Justice,</L>
<L>And duty to the Alter of your merrit,</L>
<L>These drops are pale, and poorely speake my heart,</L>
<L>Which should dissolve into a purple flood,</L>
<L>And drowne this little Iland in your service,</L>
<L>Name some imployment that you may beleeve</L>
<L>With what true soule I honour you, oh Madam</L>
<L>If you could read the Volume of my heart,</L>
<L>You would find such a story of you there.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eup.</SPEAKER>
<L>Of me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis that keepes me alive, I have noe use</L>
<L>Of memory or reason, but in both</L>
<L>To exercise devotion to your excellence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eup.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord I understand you not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are</L>
<L>More apprehensive if you wod but thinke so,</L>
<L>In vaine I still suppreste my darke thoughts Madam,</L>
<L>Which in their mutiny to be reveal'd</L>
<L>Have left a heape of ruines worth your pity.</L>
<L>Oh doe not hide that beauty should repaire</L>
<L>

<PB REF="21"/>
What my love to it hath decay'd within me,</L>
<L>For I must say I love, although you kill</L>
<L>My ambition with a frowne; and with one angry</L>
<L>Lightning, shot from your eye, turne me to ashes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eup.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good heaven!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo</SPEAKER>
<L>I know what you will urge against me,</L>
<L>You shannot need to arme your passion,</L>
<L>I will accuse my selfe, how much I have</L>
<L>Forgot the distance of one place beneath you,</L>
<L>And wounded my obedience, that I am</L>
<L>False to the <HI>Duke,</HI> the trust impos'd upon me,</L>
<L>And to his favor which have made me shine</L>
<L>A Starre, on whom the other emulous lights</L>
<L>Looke pale, and wast their envies, I confesse</L>
<L>I have not in the stocke of my desert</L>
<L>Enough to call one bounteous smile upon me,</L>
<L>My whole life is not worth your liberall patience,</L>
<L>Of one, one minute spent in prayer to serue it,</L>
<L>Yet after all wish'd destiny commands</L>
<L>The poore <HI>Leontio</HI> to love <HI>Euphemia.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eup.</SPEAKER>
<L>What doe I heare? consider sir againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Le.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have had contentions with my blood, &amp; forc'd</L>
<L>Nature retire, and tremble with the guilt</L>
<L>Of her proud thoughts, seeking to make escape</L>
<L>Through some ungentlebreatch made by our conflict</L>
<L>But noe prevailing against love, and fate,</L>
<L>Which both decree, me lost without your mercie.</L>
<L>Oh bid me live, who but in your acceptance</L>
<L>Shall grone away my breath, and whither till</L>
<L>I turne my owne sad monument.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fup.</SPEAKER>
<L>Noe more,</L>
<L>Ist possible new miseries should oretake</L>
<L><HI>Euphemia?</HI> Oh my Lord I with what offence</L>
<L>Have I deserv'd, after my weight of sorrow,</L>
<L>Your wounds upon my honour? call agen</L>
<L>Your noble thoughts, and let me not reply</L>
<L>To your vnjust desires, if I must answer them,</L>
<L>Take my most fixt resolve, er'e I consent</L>
<L>To wrong <HI>Diovisio.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>

<PB REF="21"/>
Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eup.</SPEAKER>
<L>May: be blasted,</L>
<L>Though with contempt he looke upon me now,</L>
<L>His blood may cleare, and he returne to challenge</L>
<L><HI>Euphemias</HI> prety, our vow was made</L>
<L>For life my Lord, and heaven shall sooner fall,</L>
<L>And mixing with the elements make new <HI>Chaos,</HI></L>
<L>Then all mans violence, and wrath upon me</L>
<L>Betray one thought to breake it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Loofe not all</L>
<L>Your peace at once, vouchsafe I may waite on you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eup.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know my prison.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me hope in this,</L>
<STAGE>Enter Pallante.</STAGE>
<L>My pardon seal'd <HI>Pallante?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pall.</SPEAKER>
<L>My good Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your humble creature Madam, though the <HI>Duke</HI></L>
<L>Confine your person, thinke upon your prisoner.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt Euphemia, and Pall.</STAGE>
<L>Our vow was made for life, 'twas so how swift</L>
<L>An apprehension love has? but hee's <HI>Duke;</HI></L>
<L>Conscience be waking, I shall lanch into</L>
<L>A Sea of blood els, steere my desperate soule</L>
<L>Diviner goodnes.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Pallante agen.</STAGE>
<L>How I start at shaddowes?</L>
<L>Love take me to thy charmes, and prosper me</L>
<L><HI>Pallante</HI> thou art faithfull.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pall.</SPEAKER>
<L>To you my Lord,</L>
<L>May I be ever els condemn'd to an Hospitall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>And darst assist to make me happy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pall.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes,</L>
<L>Though with the hazard of my throat-cutting,</L>
<L>I hope Sir, you suspect not, name an action</L>
<L>Though it looke n<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ere so gastly, see how much</L>
<L>I'le tremble at it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>

<PB REF="22"/>
Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>In thy eare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pall.</SPEAKER>
<L>Once more</L>
<L>Tough service i'th beginning, may I not thinke on't?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pall.</SPEAKER>
<L>And aske my selfe a question ere I answere.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>You may.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pal.</SPEAKER>
<L>At first dash kill the Duke, no lesse</L>
<L>To begin withall, how now <HI>Leontio?</HI></L>
<L>Was there no other life but this, for saving</L>
<L>Of mine so often? he has trusted me,</L>
<L>To whom shall I turne traitor? pray my Lord,</L>
<L>Are you in earnest? would you have this done?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Aske one, whom tyrannie hath chain'd to'th oare</L>
<L>For ever forfeited to slaverie.</L>
<L>Whether he would not file off his owne bondage,</L>
<L>And in the blood of him that ownes the Gally</L>
<L>Swimme to his freedome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pall.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe you apprehend it</L>
<L>So necessary? why ile doe my poore endeavour,</L>
<L>Nay, tis but modest, if't concerne your Lordship</L>
<L>In that degree, ile doo't, you will have some</L>
<L>Convenient care of me, when tis dispatchd,</L>
<L>He scorn'd my valiant Buffe, I thought upon't,</L>
<L>You are the next in blood, when <HI>Dionisio</HI></L>
<L>Visits the wormes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou giv<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st me a new life,</L>
<L>With the same care ile cherish thee <HI>Pallante.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pall.</SPEAKER>
<L>And you doe not,</L>
<L>It is not the first onscience hath been cast</L>
<L>Away in a great mans service, cheere your heart Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is not mine <HI>Pallante,</HI> I have lost</L>
<L>The use and sway, tis to anothers growne,</L>
<L>And I have but the ruines of my owne,</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
<TRAILER>Finis Actus tertii.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="22"/>
<HEAD>Actus Quartus.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Horatio, and Fiametta, dancing a Coranto.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>SO, so, now let's releeve our lungs a while,</L>
<L>They<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l tire, <HI>I</HI> nere met with such a dancing Divell,</L>
<L>My Destinies take me to your charge, 'twill give</L>
<L>Us breath, if the Musitians exercise</L>
<L>Their voice upon the song I made, come sit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fia.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall command me servant, now, the song.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Song.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Servant.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Lady <HI>Aurelia,</HI> Madam, and <HI>Macrina</HI></L>
<L>Are come agen to visit you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fia.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am not</L>
<L>In tune for their discourse, say, <HI>I</HI> am busie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>By no meanes, she has a plot upon me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then ile meet em.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do not feare but I am fortified;</L>
<L>Here were a purchase now, and pension with</L>
<L>A Mistresse, many a proper mans profession,</L>
<L>Nature meant she should pay for't, and maintaine</L>
<L>A man in fidlers, fooles, and running-horses,</L>
<L>Here were no feare of any Lords returne</L>
<L>From Tennis, no suspition at home,</L>
<L>To force her to a politicke pilgrimage</L>
<L>To trie the vertue of some well, no kinsmen,</L>
<L>With lookes to keepe the flesh in a we, no children</L>
<L>To cry, and fright the house their mothers smother'd.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Fiametta, Aurelia, Macrina.</STAGE>
<L>They are here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>

<PB REF="23"/>
Mac.</SPEAKER>
<L>I wonder at <HI>Valerios</HI> stay.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>He wo'not be long absent, never feare madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ladies, I have no power to bid you welcome,</L>
<L>Or if I had you wod scarce thanke me for<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t,</L>
<L>You know my mind already.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Scolopendra led by Valerio.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>See hee's come,</L>
<L>And his <HI>Beare</HI> with him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Signior,</L>
<L>You see what care I have to provide for you,</L>
<L>There is not such another dapple-mare i'th Dukedome,</L>
<L>Unlesse this face content you, you may stay</L>
<L>Till the <HI>Cretan</HI> Lady goe to Bull againe,</L>
<L>Or <HI>Africke</HI> have more choice of Monsters for you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am ravish'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fia.</SPEAKER>
<L>How's that servant ha? a rivall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray whats her name?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Her name is <HI>Scolopendra.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Scolopendra?</HI> I have read of her, what kinne is she</L>
<L>To the Serpent with a hundred legges?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know not</L>
<L>But she is Cosen-germane to the <HI>Salamander</HI></L>
<L>She was a Cooke-maide once, so inu'rd to fire,</L>
<L>And tough, the flames of hell will hardly scortch her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>An admirable Dragon, can she speake?</L>
<L>Will she not spit fire if I should salute her?</L>
<L>Ile venter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>He has preservative</L>
<L>Against the odor of her lungs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>He had need</L>
<L>Of fortification for his eyes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not all</L>
<L>The spices in <HI>Arabia</HI> are like</L>
<L>Her breath.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh Sir, beleev't, right <HI>Stix,</HI> most pure <HI>Avernus.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sco.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, <HI>J</HI> did never see a Gentleman</L>
<L>Whom <HI>I</HI> did wish more heartily my husband.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>To beget Scorpions on her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>

<PB REF="23"/>
Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thanke thee my pretious <HI>Scolopendra,</HI> but</L>
<L>I have a kind of feare thou wot be unconstant,</L>
<L>Shall noe man get thee from me; here's a face</L>
<L>Is worth my jealousie, and who lookes upon't,</L>
<L>But with my eyes will be as mad as I am.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sco.</SPEAKER>
<L>The needles not more constant to the North.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>But for all that, the needles wavering</L>
<L>I would be certaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fia</SPEAKER>
<L>They conspir'd to wrong me,</L>
<L>I feare hee<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s taken with her more deformity,</L>
<L>Will you forsake me servant?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Humstand off,</L>
<L>And give my eyes play further yet, your shadowes</L>
<L>Are yet to neare—my judgment is confounded,</L>
<L>Consider one thing with another, they are both</L>
<L>Such matchles toads, I know not which to choose:</L>
<L>You have an excellent eye, but there's a pearle</L>
<L>In hers, noe Gold-smith knowes the value on't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Observe the colours in my eye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'are right Madam,</L>
<L>As many, and more bright then those i'th raine-bow</L>
<L>Delightfull as the Parrats plume, but then</L>
<L>Her for-head—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va.</SPEAKER>
<L>So like a promontory or—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Feild of Hony-suckles, and Poppy-flowers</L>
<L>Embroder'd with Dazies, and emboss'd</L>
<L>With Yellow-warts which like to Mole-hills swell,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where many Emmets hunt, and sport themselve</L>
<L>I'th Sunne, till to her haire a quick set hedge</L>
<L>I'th evening they retire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>But twixt her eyes</L>
<L>You may discerne a Forrest, some higher timber</L>
<L>Is so well growne, that fashion'd on the top</L>
<L>With scissers and cut poynted like a pyramide,</L>
<L>The World will take her for an Unicorne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good beetle-browes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sco.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, you must be my champion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va.</SPEAKER>
<L>Examine but this nose.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sco.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have a toter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>

<PB REF="24"/>
Va.</SPEAKER>
<L>Which plac'd with symmetry is like a Fountaine</L>
<L>I'th middle of her face—distilling Rhewme,</L>
<L>And at two spouts doth water all her Garden.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>But here's one soft as 'twere compos'd of wax.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>A nose of wax.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mac.</SPEAKER>
<L>It will melt presently.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not stubborne, but submits to any shape,</L>
<L>Sheele put upon't round, flat when she is pleas'd</L>
<L>She can extend, and hang it with such art</L>
<L>Over her mouth, that when she gapes into</L>
<L>The Sunne, and shewes her Teeth, you will imagine</L>
<L>You see a perfect Dyall in her Chaps,</L>
<L>To tell you what a clocke tis, then her Lips.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va.</SPEAKER>
<L>I see not so much red there, as will make</L>
<L>A Dominicall Letter, looke upon these Cheekes—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sco.</SPEAKER>
<L>I never painted, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here's red enough.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Which hideously dispos'd, and mixt with blacke,</L>
<L>The ground of her complexion will mortefie</L>
<L>The most unnaturall concupiscence,</L>
<L>While her cheekes represent in curious Land-schape,</L>
<L><HI>Gomorrah,</HI> and her sister <HI>Sodome</HI> burning.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va.</SPEAKER>
<L>That comparison was home.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>But she has a breath,</L>
<L>A more preservative then <HI>Methridate</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va.</SPEAKER>
<L>But with one kisse she will preserve you from</L>
<L>The infection, and with stronger force repell</L>
<L>The poyson of the Ayre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sco.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thanke you sir,</L>
<L>I have a strong breath 'indeed</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va.</SPEAKER>
<L>When she is moov'd</L>
<L>Sheele kill you with her phlegme, fowerscore point blancke,</L>
<L>The innocent part of it will staine a Marble,</L>
<L>Let me alone to commend thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fia.</SPEAKER>
<L>She carries not destruction like my tongue</L>
<L>Employd upon thy enemies <HI>Horatio.</HI></L>
<L>The Bells rung backwards, or the Mandrakes cry,</L>
<L>Wolves howling at the Moone, the Scritch-owles dirge,</L>
<L>The Hieus voice, the groanes of parting soules,</L>
<L>

<PB REF="24"/>
Added to these, what is in nature killing,</L>
<L>To the eare is not more fatall then my tongue</L>
<L>When it is bent on mischeife, shall I blast</L>
<L>This Witch to begin withall?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sco.</SPEAKER>
<L>Blast me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va.</SPEAKER>
<L>Belch back-wards,</L>
<L>And then shee's a dead woman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sco.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le teare your Snakes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mine <HI>Hecate.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well said <HI>Scolopendra.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>They wonot skirmish.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Divells will runne at tilt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Au.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam suffer this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Compare with me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sa, sa, sa, now sound a point of Warre.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter a servant.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam the <HI>Duke.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ua.</SPEAKER>
<L>His grace has spoild the duell,</L>
<L>And we must sound retreat.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>All goe forth but Fiam. Enter Duke, Silvio, Ascanio, Valerio returns, and falls in with the rest.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>We trusted to your art about <HI>Ardelia,</HI></L>
<L>She makes noe hast to our delight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fia.</SPEAKER>
<L>And please</L>
<L>Your highnes I have had a strange hand with her,</L>
<L>And I must tell you she was prety comming</L>
<L>Untill the stranger came.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>What stranger.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Signior <HI>Bentivolio</HI></L>
<L>Nay I know nothing by 'em, but he has</L>
<L>A most prevailing tongue upon a gentle-woman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>My feares! have I advanc'd him to supplant me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Bentivolio</HI> so gracious with the <HI>Duke?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee's courted next <HI>Ardelia.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis for her</L>
<L>We may imagine the <HI>Duke</HI> graces him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ua.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh there is noe such instrument, beleeve it</L>
<L>As a Court-Lady to advance a gentleman,</L>
<L>Or any masculine busines, they are Sticklers</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>

<PB REF="25"/>
Enter Bentivolio.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more. Signior <HI>Bentivolio.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where's <HI>Horatio.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va.</SPEAKER>
<L>He was a fraid you might kill one another,</L>
<L>And so hee's gon to hang himselfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Better all</L>
<L>Thy generation were executed, but I must to my charge</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your highnes powers</L>
<L>Such infinite graces on me I shall want</L>
<L>Life to expresse my pious duties, though</L>
<L>Time should assure me ages.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thanke <HI>Ardelia,</HI></L>
<L>Or if you would expresse your gratitude</L>
<L>To me.</L>
<L>employ your wit, and tongue, to gaine</L>
<L>That Lady to our close embrace, you have</L>
<L>A powerfull language, be it your first service</L>
<L>We doe not place this confidence on all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<L>You meane <HI>Ardelia.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Strozzi.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>That faire one, <HI>Strozzi.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ua.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well Signior <HI>Bentivolio,</HI> my quondam</L>
<L>Friend, and fellow traveller, you owe</L>
<L>To me a part of your Court exaltation,</L>
<L>And least you should forget, as few great men</L>
<L>Are guilty of good memories, I meane</L>
<L>To pay my selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must not appeare troubled.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va.</SPEAKER>
<L>I congratulate your favor with the <HI>Duke,</HI></L>
<L>And thinke it, not the least of my owne happines.</L>
<L>That I was a poore instrument—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<L>You honour'd me,</L>
<L>And shall command my services: how sped</L>
<L>My friend <HI>Horatio?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va.</SPEAKER>
<L>He gave me thankes</L>
<L>I ha fitted him, you mist excellent sport.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>

<PB REF="25"/>
Ben.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall have time to enquire, and thanke you for</L>
<L>The Storie, you know how to excuse me friend,</L>
<L>If some engagements force me hence?</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why so.</L>
<L>He has the tricke already, full of busines,</L>
<L>Court agitations, he is yet scarce warme,</L>
<L>How will he use us when his pride boyles over?</L>
<L>A nod will be a grace, while we stand bare,</L>
<L>And thanke him for the rufling of his countenance,</L>
<L>And discomposing his Court face, that's bound</L>
<L>Upon some State affaires, tis very well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Give him accesse, thou hast shew'd diligence,</L>
<L>And trust me to reward it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Str.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis my duty sir.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Strozzi.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have some intelligence wil be worth your hearing too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speake Signior <HI>Valerio.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ua.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe you know the gentleman</L>
<L>Whom you have grac'd so lately.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Signior <HI>Bentivolio.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's his name, but doe you know his nature?</L>
<L>Or his busines in these parts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prethee instruct me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va.</SPEAKER>
<L>You doe but warme a Serpent in your bosome,</L>
<L>In short he loves your Mistres.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ho's?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va.</SPEAKER>
<L>More is contracted,</L>
<L>And they both practise cunning, I ha search'd</L>
<L>His heart—your eare—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>The <HI>Duke</HI> seemes moov'd,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most strangely!</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Strozzi, Pallante.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Expect a while.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Str.</SPEAKER>
<L>Humbly your graces pleasure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ua.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your highnes shall not wast a passion,</L>
<L>I am of counsell with his thoughts, and will</L>
<L>Present him ripe to your just anger, trust me</L>
<L>To manage things a while.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>

<PB REF="26"/>
Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Honest <HI>Valerio.</HI></L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Keepe your face smooth, least he interpret Sir,</L>
<L>I ha' betraid him, ere his head be readie</L>
<L>For the execution, it were necessary</L>
<L><HI>I</HI> should examine her pulse too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duk.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ardelia's?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile creepe into her soule to bring you all</L>
<L>The best intelligence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duk.</SPEAKER>
<L>Precious <HI>Ualerio!</HI></L>
<L>Endeare me by this service, thou hast my heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>My dutie shall preserve it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duk.</SPEAKER>
<L>Strozzi.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Str.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is the gentleman, an't please</L>
<L>Your highnesse, can discover most strange things.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pall.</SPEAKER>
<L>To your private eare.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Ardelia.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duk.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Ardelia?</HI> my best health,</L>
<L>Deare as my soule, <HI>I</HI> cannot be long absent.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>So, how shall I begin now?</L>
<L>Madam, I have a suit to you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ard.</SPEAKER>
<L>To me</L>
<L>Noble <HI>Valerio,</HI> be confident</L>
<L>For your owne worth, if any power of mine</L>
<L>Can serve your wish, you shall not finde me slow</L>
<L>To exercise it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, tis in your power.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ard.</SPEAKER>
<L>Presume tis finishd then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>In your free power,</L>
<L>Without the Duke, or other to confirme it.</L>
<L>Y' are flesh, and blood.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ard.</SPEAKER>
<L>What meane you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>No other than <HI>I</HI> say, nor wish it other,</L>
<L>A woman is a partner in the frailty</L>
<L>Of humane nature, and knowes how to excuse</L>
<L>The errors of our blood, and yet you shall</L>
<L>Have cause to give me thanks, when you consider</L>
<L>My sence, and your owne state, what dee' thinke</L>
<L>

<PB REF="26"/>
Of me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ard.</SPEAKER>
<L>For what?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>For what you please to call it,</L>
<L>My persons not contemptible, though I be</L>
<L>No Duke, <HI>I</HI> can behave my selfe to please</L>
<L>Where <HI>I</HI> am accepted.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ard.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whats your purpose Signior?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>You cannot sure be ignorant of my meaning,</L>
<L>Theres not a girle of seaven yeares old, but will</L>
<L>Expound it readily, here we sucke this language</L>
<L>And our milke together, <HI>I</HI> could have us'd</L>
<L>More circumstance, have prais'd you into folly,</L>
<L>And when I had put out both your eies with Metaphors,</L>
<L>Lead you to my desires, and to your pillow:</L>
<L>But 'twas about, I could have said I lov'd you,</L>
<L>Lookd sad, and squeez'd my eies, have sigh'd perhaps,</L>
<L>And sworne my selfe quite over breath, that <HI>I</HI></L>
<L>Thought you a Saint, and my heart suffer'd more</L>
<L>Than the ten persecutions; hang't, time's precious,</L>
<L>I take the neerest way, which your discretion</L>
<L>Will like me for, yet <HI>I</HI> can love you too,</L>
<L>And would for thy embrace forget asmuch</L>
<L>Goodnesse, and tempt as many mischiefes as,</L>
<L>Another man, I hope you understand me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ard.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am lost, and see a blacke conspiracie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall see me naked. I ha' no conspiracies,</L>
<L>Carrie no private engines more then nature</L>
<L>Arm'd me withall, be wise and doe not tremble.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>How dare you be thus insolent? though my per-son</L>
<L>Move you to no regard, you shall finde one</L>
<L>Will teach you manners.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>You would meane the Duke now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Has that name no more reverence owing to it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ual.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, <HI>I</HI> desire no better judge, he'l heare</L>
<L>Us both, and equally determine all;</L>
<L>Let's to his highnesse streight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>What meanes this rudenesse?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ua.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are the Dukes game-royall, or els should</L>
<L>Be the mistris of his thoughts, whose nod does make</L>
<L>

<PB REF="27"/>
Us tremble, and in time may be the <HI>Dutchesse,</HI></L>
<L>Unles your sweete heart <HI>Bentivolio</HI></L>
<L>Snap you before him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va.</SPEAKER>
<L>What fine netts you walke in,</L>
<L>You are noe, Jugler, there has past noe contract</L>
<L>Betwixt you, and the gallant, no? and while,</L>
<L>The honest easie <HI>Duke,</HI> whose spirit raise not,</L>
<L>Doates on that face, humbled beneath a subject,</L>
<L>You have noe private meetings, change no kisses,</L>
<L>Nor hot carreers, alas hee's but a Stranger</L>
<L>Whom you respect but for the bare resemblance</L>
<L>Of a dead brother, there's noe flame in you</L>
<L>But what lights you to charity; I wast breath,</L>
<L>The <HI>Duke</HI> is yet that tame thing, you ha left him,</L>
<L>His soule in a dreame, let not your folly,</L>
<L>And peevish opposition to receive</L>
<L>Me to your armes, wake him into a tempest,</L>
<L>The lightning cannot moove more nimbly, then</L>
<L>His rage to both your deaths, your <HI>Ganimede</HI></L>
<L>Will find the <HI>Dukes</HI> revenge in his hot blood,</L>
<L>When his heart weeping the last drope shall have</L>
<L>Noe pity waite upon 'em, that durst feed</L>
<L>The rivall to a Prince, though common men</L>
<L>For want of power, and courage to revenge</L>
<L>Neglect their shame, wild Princes that know all things,</L>
<L>Beneath their feete but heaven, obey noe fate,</L>
<L>And but to be reveng'd will hazard that.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am undone for ever.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not so Madam,</L>
<L>You shall lead destiny in cords of Silke,</L>
<L>And it shall follow tame, and to your pleasure,</L>
<L>The <HI>Duke</HI> knowes nothing yet, you shall seale up</L>
<L>My lip to eternall silence of your love,</L>
<L>If I may but injoy you, you shall rule</L>
<L>With the same sway his bosome, and possesse</L>
<L>Your wealth in <HI>Bentivolio</HI> too, I'me but</L>
<L>A friend or rather servant, that shall be</L>
<L>Proud of your smile, and now, and then admitted</L>
<L>

<PB REF="27"/>
To kisse you when the Curtaines drawne, and so forth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who plac'd me on this precipice? sir, heare me,</L>
<L>Tis vaine to aske how you deriv'd the knowledge</L>
<L>Of what I thought conceal'd, you are a gentleman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va.</SPEAKER>
<L>That does appeare by my desires.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Have yet some mercy</L>
<L>On a distressed maid.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va.</SPEAKER>
<L>Maid? thanke you for that, I wo'd you were</L>
<L>Indeed, virginity is wiser then</L>
<L>Men take it for, and therefore we distinguish,</L>
<L>There is one virginity in the wedge, or bullion</L>
<L>As we may say, and this we call lunor maiden-head,</L>
<L>And there's another in the coine, the gold</L>
<L>Is not lesse gold for the impression,</L>
<L>Your maiden-head is currant in this sence.</L>
<L>And in this maiden-sence you may give Milke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>By all the goodnes that I wish were in you,</L>
<L>Not <HI>Bentivolio,</HI> whom you thinke I most</L>
<L>Affect, hath more of me then virgin knowledge,</L>
<L>Nor hath the <HI>Duke</HI> with all his flatteries</L>
<L>Wrong'd my first State, although I must confesse</L>
<L>He every day expects my fall from vertue,</L>
<L>Doe not you more sir, then the divell could,</L>
<L>Taking advantage of my wretched fortune,</L>
<L>Betray me to a shame will kill us both,</L>
<L>In fame, and soule.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va.</SPEAKER>
<L>In fame? who shall reveale it?</L>
<L>And tother may repent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, can you kill me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, no I sha'not hurt thee, women are not kil'd</L>
<L>That way, I meane to skirmish, come you may</L>
<L>Save all with little study, and lesse hazard.</L>
<L>What is the toy we talke of? eyther resolve</L>
<L>Or the <HI>Duke</HI> knowes all, and perhaps more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, yes Madam I can stay, and be till</L>
<L>Tomorrow for the sport, I am not so hot</L>
<L>But I can bath, and coole my selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can you</L>
<L>

<PB REF="28"/>
Be just hereafter if to buy my owne,</L>
<L>And my friends safety at so deare a value.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le cut my tongue out e're reveale my tongue,</L>
<L>All my concupiscence, and the cause, I will</L>
<L>Submit to thy owne carving; feare not me,</L>
<L>I hate a blab worse then an honest woman,</L>
<L>Why so? this wisdome is becoming thee,</L>
<L>Noe blubbering, kisse me, and be confident,</L>
<L>A prety rogue, tomorrow shall we meete?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Woe is me tomorrow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, thou shalt laugh tomorrow,</L>
<L>I'le come to thy owne lodgings, that's but reason,</L>
<L>Far-well, another kisse, be comforted,</L>
<L>And safe, the <HI>Duke</HI> knowes nothing, all shall live,</L>
<L>And wee'le be very loving, mighty merry.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must doe something to prevent this Divell.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Ardelia.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why so, this bargaine was well made, and timely.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Leonato.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have noe peace within me, till I heare</L>
<L>How bould <HI>Pallanto</HI> thrives, oh love upon</L>
<L>What desperate actions dost thou engage us?</L>
<L>With scorne of opposition, like a fire</L>
<L>Which till it turne all that his flame can meete with</L>
<L>Into it selfe, expires not; faire <HI>Euphemia!</HI></L>
<L>Bright in thy sorrowes, on whom every teare</L>
<L>Sits like a wealthy Diamond, and inherits</L>
<L>A Starry-lustre from the eye that shed it,</L>
<L>The <HI>Duke</HI> must die—have I betray'd my selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold, my Lord you know me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>For <HI>Valerio.</HI></L>
<L>But must hand-backe that secret, 'twas not ment</L>
<L>So early for thy knowledge, from thy bosome</L>
<L>I'le teare or drowne it in thy blood, past search</L>
<L>Of dangerous intelligence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold my Lord,</L>
<L>You shall not neede,</L>
<L>

<PB REF="28"/>
Thinke my Lord I know</L>
<L>The World, and how to keepe a secret too,</L>
<L>Though treason be contain'd in't, I am not</L>
<L>So holy as you take me, my good Lord</L>
<L>For some ends of my owne, I wish the <HI>Duke</HI></L>
<L>In another VVorld as heartely as your Lordship,</L>
<L>And will assist to his conveyance thither,</L>
<L>Though I be quarter<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d for't, that's faire, and friendly,</L>
<L>You love <HI>Euphemia,</HI> why tis not amisse,</L>
<L>I love <HI>Ardelia,</HI> (I trust you my Lord)</L>
<L>You for the wife, I for the concubine,</L>
<L>How could the <HI>Duke</HI> being in heaven, hurt me now?</L>
<L>You are his kinsman, were his favourite.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>How's that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh sir, there is a gentleman my rivall,</L>
<L>One <HI>Bentivolio</HI> got a round above you</L>
<L>In favour—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>He shall die.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, let him live</L>
<L>A litle while, to kill his highnes first,</L>
<L>And take your owne time then to turne the ladder.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Bentivolio.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou talkst a mistery.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va.</SPEAKER>
<L>It shall be cleare,</L>
<L>Be advis'd, and second me my honor'd friend,</L>
<L>You, and my Lord be more familiar.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, <HI>I</HI> shall serve you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<L>Make me happy</L>
<L>My Lord, by your commands.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ua. Ardelia</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Mistris is in health—nay be not stirrd.</L>
<L>I have done you a curtesie by acquainting</L>
<L>My Lord how things stand, and introth he pities you,</L>
<L>We have had a counsell meerely concern'd you,</L>
<L>And the poore gentlewoman, whom the <HI>Duke</HI> has not</L>
<L>Yet lur'd to fist.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know not how to thanke you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>

<PB REF="29"/>
Va.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee's next heire to'th Dukedome, and has power</L>
<L>When his grace dies—imagine, a sweet soule</L>
<L>May I perish in my hopes, if his eyes did not</L>
<L>Melt when I told thy story, and how much.</L>
<L>The innocent Lady suffered.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am bound</L>
<L>Much to his goodnes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir I would doe more</L>
<L>Then pity your just cause.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay we ha' cast it,</L>
<L>And so much above blood, and state, has vertue</L>
<L>Impression in his heart, he can forget,</L>
<L>And thinke the <HI>Duke</HI> a dead man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<L>Excellent Lord!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am ashamed, and trust me have applied</L>
<L>What my poore learning could affect, to coole</L>
<L>His riotous blood, but hee's incorrigible,</L>
<L>And now more desperately bent then ever.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<L>To Violate her?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I blush to say't, nor will</L>
<L>Your person be long safe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well interpos'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<L>He shines on me with bounteous smiles.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are dangerous,</L>
<L>And but engage you to a greater ruine.</L>
<L>You stand discover'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's my wonder sir,</L>
<L>Dee thinke your friend <HI>Horatio</HI> has not wrong'd you</L>
<L>In's drinke perhaps—some men are such spongies,</L>
<L>A child may squeeze their soule out.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<L>You fright my sences.</L>
<L>I doe now suspect, the <HI>Dukes</HI> command toward <HI>Ardelia confirmes it.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wisdome must prevent</L>
<L>I know thou hast a daring spirit, we</L>
<L>Are friends, tis clearely our opinion</L>
<L>You should by Steele or Poyson—you conceive me</L>
<L>For your owne safety, and your wives, I call her so</L>
<L>Whose life, and honour lies a bleeding, tis</L>
<L>Nothing to me, my Lord I told you, is</L>
<L>

<PB REF="29"/>
Next heire, and cannot but in conscience pardon you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Twere pity thou shouldst suffer more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<L>But dare</L>
<L>Your Lordship meane this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be confirm'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your counsells</L>
<L>Have met a spirit, apt in my revenge</L>
<L>To flie upon the world, <HI>I</HI> hope <HI>I</HI> shall</L>
<L>Be constru'd in his death, to have done your Lordship</L>
<L>Noe great discourtesie, being next heire,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis to be understood.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Dukedome made</L>
<L>Mine by his death, is nothing to the Crowne</L>
<L>Of faire <HI>Ardelias</HI> love, in whose free bosome</L>
<L>My pardon, and best wishes shall soone plant thee</L>
<L>Past the divorce of tirants.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am new</L>
<L>Create, and build my hopes upon your honour.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are secur'd dost thinke hee's firme, and daring.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va.</SPEAKER>
<L>If he kill not the <HI>Duke</HI>—i'le cut his throate,</L>
<L>He sha'not scape howe're, if <HI>I</HI> have braines</L>
<L>I must have all his venison to my selfe,</L>
<L>I'le spare nor hanuch nor humbles, oh my Lord</L>
<L>Be confident if he meete the <HI>Duke,</HI> and time</L>
<L>Though it cost him a dayes Journey, hee'le goe thorough him</L>
<L>Tis his owne cause; he was wound up discreetely,</L>
<L>You doe not by this time repent your secret.</L>
<L>I can be wicked upon good occasion,</L>
<L>The divell sha'not part us now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be constant,</L>
<L>And meete the truest friend,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va.</SPEAKER>
<L>Meete at a wench</L>
<L>Till then your humble servant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>My fate smiles</L>
<L>Conscience steeres not ambition by what's good,</L>
<L>Who lookes at crownes or lust, must smile at blood.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<TRAILER>Finis Actus quarti.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="30"/>
<HEAD>Actus Quintus.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Ardelia, Fiametta.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fia.</SPEAKER>
<L>HE will no longer be put off with ceremony,</L>
<L>You must consent this night to his embrace,</L>
<L>Or take what followes Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am lost,</L>
<L>And every minutes fild with new despaires,</L>
<L>It is in your power to perswade him yet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fia.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have said too much already.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Say <HI>I</HI> am not</L>
<L>In health, poore refuge!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not in health, the <HI>Duke</HI></L>
<L>Shall give you physicke—there be Ladies no</L>
<L>Dispraise to your beauty, wo'd be sicke a purpole</L>
<L>To have the <HI>Duke</HI> their Doctor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>What can cure</L>
<L>My sicke fate? oh my heart, poore <HI>Bentivolio,</HI></L>
<L>On what high going waves do we two faile,</L>
<L>Without a Starre or Pilot to direct</L>
<L>Our reeling barke? <HI>Valerio</HI> too expects</L>
<L>A blacke reward for silence, he is here,</L>
<STAGE>Enter Ualerio.</STAGE>
<L>Already? doe not leave me <HI>Fiametta,</HI></L>
<L>I charge thee by thy duty to his highnes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why what's the matter?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me pay a duty</L>
<L>To her white hand, whom the <HI>Duke</HI> onely honors,</L>
<L>You looke not with a cheareful countenance Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am not well my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am exelent at</L>
<L>

<PB REF="30"/>
Restoring health, send of <HI>Tosiphone</HI></L>
<L>I wo'd not have her Picture i'th roome</L>
<L>When we are at generation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee's commanded</L>
<L>To stay here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va.</SPEAKER>
<L>How? commanded? Madam <HI>I</HI> have</L>
<L>Commission to impart some private meanings</L>
<L>From his highnes to this Lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fia.</SPEAKER>
<L>And <HI>I</HI> have</L>
<L>Order, this my Lady have no such conference,</L>
<L>But <HI>I</HI> must be a witnes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va.</SPEAKER>
<L>You will not</L>
<L>Contest <HI>I</HI> hope, and dispute my authority,</L>
<L>VVhat an officious fury tis? how shall <HI>I</HI></L>
<L>Be rid on her? Madam you see this Ring,</L>
<L>A friend of yours signior <HI>Horatio</HI></L>
<L>Desires another meeting by this token.</L>
<STAGE>Whispers with Fiametta.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fia.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhere is my noble servant?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va.</SPEAKER>
<L>But you must</L>
<L>Expresse your love in making hast, <HI>I</HI> knew</L>
<L>Although for mirth <HI>I</HI> flatter'd <HI>Scolopendra,</HI></L>
<L>That you would carry him, but loose no time.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lend me thy wings sweet love to flie to him.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va.</SPEAKER>
<L>Flie to the Divell, he wants a companion,</L>
<L>I'le shut the dore after your beldamship,</L>
<L>And trust my selfe with key.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>You doe not meane</L>
<L>To play the ravisher my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va.</SPEAKER>
<L>As if</L>
<L>You mean't to putme too't, <HI>I</HI> have your promise</L>
<L>And where consents meete in the act of love,</L>
<L>The pleasures multiply to infinite.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Infinite horror! yet my Lord, be a man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall not doubt that Madam, if you will</L>
<L>Apply your selfe discreetly, we loose time,</L>
<L>Although <HI>I</HI> be no <HI>Duke, I</HI> can present thee</L>
<L>VVith all the pleasures, appetite can wish for</L>
<L>VVithin Loves empire, when you know me Madam▪</L>
<L>You will repent this tedious ignorance,</L>
<L>

<PB REF="31"/>
And not exchange my person, to claspe with</L>
<L>The greatest Prince alive, (hristian or infidell,</L>
<L>Though I commend my selfe, I ha' those wayes</L>
<L>To please a Lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wayes to please the Divell?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va.</SPEAKER>
<L>You wo'not be coy now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord I know,</L>
<L>At least I hope, howere you speake a language</L>
<L>Rather to fright then court a womans thoughts,</L>
<L>(Not yet acquainted with her owne dishonor)</L>
<L>You have some love within your heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va.</SPEAKER>
<L>Canst thou</L>
<L>Suspect it? wo't thou see my heart?</L>
<L>Give me a fort-nights warning, and let me</L>
<L>But all that while possesse thy love, and those</L>
<L>Delights i'le prompt thee too, i'le wish to live</L>
<L>No longer, get what surgeon thou wo t</L>
<L>To cut me to a <HI>Skeleton,</HI> not love thee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then by that love my Lord, I must desire you</L>
<L>At this time to deferre your expectation,</L>
<L>And leave my Chamber.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va.</SPEAKER>
<L>Quit the Chamber Madam?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>If not for love of me, for your owne safety,</L>
<L>There is danger in your stay, for every minute</L>
<L>I do expect a visite from the <HI>Duke.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is some tricke, you sha'not fright me Lady,</L>
<L>I must have that I came for.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Meete it here</L>
<STAGE>Shewes a Pistoll.</STAGE>
<L>Licentious divell, I shall do a benefit</L>
<L>To the world, in thus removing such a traytor,</L>
<L>To man, and womans honor, you shall carry</L>
<L>No tales to his highnes, if thou hast a soule.</L>
<L>Pray, tis my charity to let thee live</L>
<L>Two minutes longer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, <HI>Ardelia,</HI></L>
<L>You wo'not use me thus,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you pray sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas I have forgot, I ha'not pray'd</L>
<L>This tweny yeares at least, I am willing Madam</L>
<L>

<PB REF="31"/>
To obey, and quit the Chamber, pardon me,</L>
<L>My ghost may in revenge els, do you a mischeife,</L>
<L>And betray <HI>Bentivolio</HI> to the <HI>Duke,</HI></L>
<L>But if you let me live, I will be dumbe,</L>
<L>Madam consider a wild flesh, and blood,</L>
<L>And give me leave to spend my rest of life,</L>
<L>Onely in thinking out some fit repentance,</L>
<L>For I will never speake, if you suspect me.</L>
<STAGE>One knocks.</STAGE>
<L>The <HI>Duke</HI> is come already, I am undone</L>
<L>Mercy, and some concealment.</L>
<STAGE>Goes behinde the hangings.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Bentivolio opens the dore.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Ardelia</HI></L>
<L>Alone, I heard another voyce, with whom</L>
<L>Were you in Dialogue, and the dore so fast?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is but your suspition.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<L>This dissembling</L>
<L>I like not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>If he know who tis, I shall</L>
<L>Inflame his Jealousie—deere heart appeare</L>
<L>Lesse troubled, do not throw such busie eyes</L>
<L>About the roome, i'le whisper't in thy eare,</L>
<L>The <HI>Duke</HI>—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>There, obscur'd behind the hangings</L>
<L>Upon thy entrance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<L>Guilt has made him fearefull,</L>
<L>Oh I am lost, and thou art now not worth</L>
<L>My glorious rescue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Softly, by all goodnes</L>
<L>He has not injurd me, and if you durst</L>
<L>But trust our private conference, i'le die</L>
<L>Rather then bring thee ruines of my honor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<L>If thou beest yet white, my owne arme secures thee</L>
<L>From all his lust hereafter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh</L>
<STAGE>He wounds Valerio behind the hangings.</STAGE>
<L>I am murder'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>What have you done?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>

<PB REF="32"/>
Ben.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nothing but kild the <HI>Duke,</HI></L>
<L>You shall with me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whither?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<L>No matter where.</L>
<L>So we escape the infection of this Ayre.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Valerio falls into the Stage.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am caught in my owne toyles, by the same Engine</L>
<L>I rais'd to the <HI>Dukes</HI> death, I fall my selfe,</L>
<L>The mistery of fate, I am rewarded,</L>
<L>And that which was the ranke part of my life,</L>
<L>My blood, is met withall, and tis my wonder</L>
<L>My veines should run so cleere a red, wherein</L>
<L>so much blacke sinne was wont to bath it selfe,</L>
<L>I wo'd looke up, and beg with my best strength</L>
<L>Of voyce, and heart forgivenes, but heaven's just,</L>
<L>Thus death payes treason, and blood quencheth lust.</L>
<STAGE>Moritur</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Leontio, melancholy. Some cry treason within.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Although I love, and wish the act of treason</L>
<L>The noise yet comes to neare me.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Strozzi.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Str.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh my Lord!</L>
<L>The <HI>Duke</HI> is kil'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>The <HI>Duke?</HI> by what blacke murderer?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Str.</SPEAKER>
<L>That gives the State another wound, we cannot</L>
<L>Suspect who was the traytor, to revenge it,</L>
<L>But whosoever was guilty of this paracide,</L>
<L>Is still within the Court, the deeds so fresh</L>
<L>He cannot be farre off.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shut up the gates,</L>
<L>And plant a strong guard round about the palace,</L>
<L>Let none goe forth in paine of death, the divell</L>
<L>Sha'not obscure him here with his blacke wings,</L>
<L>Though he rob Hell to cover us with darknes,</L>
<L>Wee'le find him under twenty foggs, and drag him</L>
<L>To his just torment.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Str.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'are his pious successor.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>

<PB REF="32"/>
Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis done, and my ambition's satisfied</L>
<L>Containe my heart, but to which bold assassivate</L>
<L><HI>Pallante</HI> or <HI>Bentivolio</HI> must I owe</L>
<L>This bloody service.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Pallante</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pall.</SPEAKER>
<L>I ha' don't my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Softly, thou art my brave, and glorious villaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pall.</SPEAKER>
<L>There have beene better titles sir, bestow'd</L>
<L>On men of my desert, the killing of</L>
<L>My lawfull Prince, hath beene esteem'd an act</L>
<L>'Bove the reward of villaine, though I know</L>
<L>I am one, and a monstrous villaine too,</L>
<L>I wo d not be cal'd so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou sha't devide</L>
<L>Titles with me, dost thinke i'le not reward it?</L>
<L>Thou ar<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> sad.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pall.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am a litle melancholy</L>
<L>After my worke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dost thourepent thy service?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pall.</SPEAKER>
<L>Were he alive, i'de kill him agen for you.</L>
<L>Tis not his death that hants my conscience,</L>
<L>But the condition, and State he died in,</L>
<L>That troubles me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>What State, or what condition?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pall.</SPEAKER>
<L>When I had taught him to beleeve he was not</L>
<L>Long liv'd, and that your Lordship had by me.</L>
<L>Sent him a writ of ease, for i'le make short.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Didst thou discover me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pall.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why not? I was</L>
<L>To take an order he should n'ere reveale it,</L>
<L>Upon the mention of your name my Lord.</L>
<L>He fetch<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d a sigh, I thought would have prevented</L>
<L>My execution on his heart, as if</L>
<L>That were a greater wound then death upon him,</L>
<L>But I, whose resolute soule was deafe to his prayer,</L>
<L>Bath'd in as many teares, as would have wrought</L>
<L>A Marble to compassion, bid him choose</L>
<L>The humor he would die in, and collect</L>
<L>Some thoughts to waite upon him to eternity,</L>
<L>

<PB REF="33"/>
And what doe you thinke he made his choice?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pall.</SPEAKER>
<L>To die an honest man, no wish to part</L>
<L>The world with faire <HI>Ardelia</HI> in his armes, and give his ghost up in a wan-ton kisse.</L>
<L>But with a thousand groanes, calling upon</L>
<L><HI>Euphemia</HI> to forgive him, to whose vertue</L>
<L>His soule was going forth, to meete, and seale</L>
<L>To it, a new, and everlasting marriage,</L>
<L>Nay he had so much charity to forgive</L>
<L>You sir, and me, and would have pray'd for us,</L>
<L>But that I sent the message to his bosome</L>
<L>That made him quiet, and so left his highnes</L>
<L>Had he died obstinate in his sinnes, the wanton</L>
<L>Lascivious <HI>Duke</HI> he liv'd, I wo'd not blush for't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, dost relent for this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pall.</SPEAKER>
<L>I find some mutiny</L>
<L>In my conscience, pray my Lord tell me</L>
<L>Do not you wish it were undone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou hast</L>
<L>The tremblings of an infant, it exalts</L>
<L>My thoughts to another heaven, <HI>Pallante</HI> thou</L>
<L>Must not leave here, but make <HI>Leontio,</HI> owe</L>
<L>His perfect blessing to thy act, goe to</L>
<L><HI>Euphemia,</HI> and with thy best art drop</L>
<L>This newes into her eare.</L>
<L><HI>Within.</HI> Away with 'em.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>What tumults that?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Bentivolio, and Ardelia with officers</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Off.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord we have found the traytor</L>
<L>He does confesse he kil'd the <HI>Duke.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pall.</SPEAKER>
<L>Howes that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>He kil'd the <HI>Duke?</HI> tis <HI>Bentivolio.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<L>I did my Lord, you shannot trouble much</L>
<L>Examination, with this hand I sacrific'd</L>
<L><HI>Ferneze,</HI> and you ought to call my act</L>
<L>Pious, and thanke me for removing such</L>
<L>A tyrant, whose perfidious breath had heaven</L>
<L>Beene longer patient wo'd have blasted <HI>Parma.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>And in the confidence of this service done,</L>
<L>You present your selfe to be rewarded.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<L>I meant not to have troubled you for that</L>
<L>

<PB REF="33"/>
Had not their force compeld us backe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come neerer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I wonder at this noyse of the <HI>Dukes</HI> death,</L>
<L><HI>Valerios</HI> tragedy is all that we</L>
<L>Are guilty of, which yet I have conceal'd</L>
<L>From <HI>Bentivolio.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Had you no ayde</L>
<L>To this great execution, did you doo't alone?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alone, and tis my glory that</L>
<L>Noe hand can boast his fatall wound but mine,</L>
<L>And if you dare be just my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be confident,</L>
<L>There is some mistery in this <HI>Pallante</HI></L>
<L>Both could not kill the <HI>Duke,</HI> he does accuse,</L>
<L>himselfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pall.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am all wonder my good Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are sure tis done.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now you dishonor me,</L>
<L>Dee know blood royall, when you see't, you may</L>
<L>Beleeve that crimson evidence, I hope</L>
<L>Your Lordship will remember.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Feare it not,</L>
<L>But for a time you must be prisoner</L>
<L>To satisfie a litle forme upon</L>
<L>My life, no danger shall approach thee, trust</L>
<L>My honor, though I frowne, and call thee traitor</L>
<L>I will study thy preserving next my owne,</L>
<L>Is not this strange <HI>Pallante</HI> that heele take</L>
<L>The guilt upon himselfe, if both have kild him</L>
<L>Noe feare but hee's dead, this foole <HI>Pallante</HI></L>
<L>Shall quickly by his death secure thy Fate.</L>
<L>Put on a cunning face meane time, and narrowly</L>
<L>Observe the full behaviour of the Court,</L>
<L>But 'specially insinuate with the greatest,</L>
<L>And as they talke of me, declare my passion,</L>
<L>And with what horror, I receav'd the death</L>
<L>Of our good <HI>Duke,</HI> my pious zeale to appease</L>
<L>That blessed spirit with his murderers blood,</L>
<L>In care to their owne heads, they will proclaime</L>
<L>Me <HI>Duke,</HI> i'le to <HI>Euphemia,</HI> and by some</L>
<L>Strong art make her my owne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pall.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your grace is prudent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away to'th prison with 'em.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me beare</L>
<L>Him company my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>

<PB REF="34"/>
Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>You sha'not doubt it</L>
<L>Good Madam mischiefe, and repent together,</L>
<L>As you are like to bleed, and with full torture,</L>
<L>Howle out your wretched lives for the Dukes murder.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are deceav'd my Lord, we wo'not dye</L>
<L>For that offence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>You wo'not, glorious strumpet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'are a most</L>
<L>Uncivill Lord, thy birth had not more innocence</L>
<L>To justifie thy mother.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile be modest,</L>
<L>And say, this is not honourable.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>So Sir,</L>
<L>You will have time to talke at your arraignment,</L>
<L>Away with 'em, now to <HI>Euphemia.</HI></L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter oratio, and Fiametta.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did you not send for me, and by this token?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Follow me not, unlesse thou wo't sweare to imitate</L>
<L>What I shall lead thee too by my example,</L>
<L>For rather then not be rid of thee, at next</L>
<L>Convenient river I will drowne my selfe,</L>
<L>And thinke I goe a Martyrdome by water.</L>
<L>Cannot a Gentleman be merry w'ee,</L>
<L>But you will make him mad?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile never leave thee,</L>
<L>I will petition to the Duke, and plead</L>
<L>A contract.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou't be dam'd then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fia.</SPEAKER>
<L>What care I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>So, I shu'd have a blessing in this fiend,</L>
<L>This child of darkenesse once remov'd, I send for thee,</L>
<L>And by a token? I wo'd sooner send</L>
<L>For the hang-man, and pay him double fees</L>
<L>To strangle me, what I endur'd before,</L>
<L>Thinke twas a pennance for some mighty sinnes</L>
<L>I had committed, and be quiet now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did you not love me then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Love thee? consider</L>
<L>What thou hast said, and hang thy selfe immediatly,</L>
<L>

<PB REF="34"/>
Ile sooner dote upon a mare, dost heare me,</L>
<L>A mare with fourescore, and ninteene diseases,</L>
<L>And she the greatest to make up a hundred,</L>
<L>Then harbour one such monstrous thought, thou art</L>
<L>A thing, no Cat that comes of a good kind,</L>
<L>Will keepe the company, and yet thou lookst</L>
<L>So like a miserable ore-growne vermine,</L>
<L>Now I thinke better on't, it is my wonder</L>
<L>Th'art not devour'd quicke, leave me yet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not I Sir,</L>
<L>I know you love me still, all this is but</L>
<L>To try my constancy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Art thou so ignorant,</L>
<L>Or impudent, or both? let me intreat thee</L>
<L>But to have something of a beast about thee.</L>
<L>Thy sences in some measure, looke but how</L>
<L>I frowne upon thee, for thy safety therefore,</L>
<L>If thou hast no desire to save my credit</L>
<L>Abroad, tame thy concupiscence, we draw</L>
<L>All the spectatours but to laugh, and wonder at's,</L>
<L>And I shall be the greater prodegy</L>
<L>For talking so long with thee, wo't be rul'd,</L>
<L>And trudge from whence thou camst, good honest bruite,</L>
<L>My humours out of breath, and I ha' done,</L>
<L>But all that's ugly in thy face, or what's</L>
<L>Unseene deformity, I am now in earnest,</L>
<L>And therefore doe not tempt me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fia.</SPEAKER>
<L>My deere Signior.</L>
<L>To what?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, after all to beate thee, if</L>
<L>Thou leav'st me not the sooner.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are not you</L>
<L>My Servant?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>But in passion I forget things,</L>
<L>And if my Mistresse want discretion,</L>
<L>I shall, in my pure zeale to have her wise,</L>
<L>Beate some into her, most abhominably</L>
<L>Beate her, and make deformity to swell,</L>
<L>She sha'not get in to her chamber doore.</L>
<L>

<PB REF="35"/>
Ile bruise, and make thee up into a ball,</L>
<L>And boyes shall kick thee home, dost thou not feare me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile endure any thing from thee, my love</L>
<L>Shall thinke no paine a suffering, come, kisse me</L>
<L>But once, and I will diethy patient martyr.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>She wo'd be kild, to have me hang for her,</L>
<L>Was ever such an impudence in woman?</L>
<L>You that are hansome Ladies, I doe aske</L>
<L>Forgivenesse and beleeve it possible</L>
<L>You may be le<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>se vexations to men.</L>
<L>Dost heare? to tell thee truth, for it will out</L>
<L>By some, or other, you must here discharge</L>
<L>Your dotage, for it is but two howers since</L>
<L>I was married.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Married? to whom?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Toth' tother</L>
<L>Wild beare that courted me, to <HI>Scolopendra,</HI></L>
<L>She met i'th nicke, and wee clapt up.</L>
<L>And you know tis not conscience to abuse</L>
<L>Our honest wedlocke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fia.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall runne mad.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wo'd thou wo'dst runne into the Sea, and see</L>
<L>If I wo'd goe a fishing for thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Furies,</L>
<L>Rise in my braine, and helpe me to revenge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am afraid she'l beate me now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fia.</SPEAKER>
<L>False man,</L>
<L>I have not breath enough to raile, and curse</L>
<L>Thy apostacy, how couldst thou use me thus?</L>
<L>But seeke some sudden way to be divorc'd,</L>
<L>Or one shall dye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wo'd thou wert buried quicke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fia.</SPEAKER>
<L>But are</L>
<L>You married, tell me sweet <HI>Horatio,</HI></L>
<L>And must I weare a willow garland for thee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Weare a halter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fia.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is not possible, thou canst be so</L>
<L>Unkind to me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>You may beleeve it Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>

<PB REF="35"/>
Fia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet I must love thee till I die, and you</L>
<L>May keepe me alive, with now, and then some favour,</L>
<L>It want's no president, we may kisse I hope,</L>
<L>And thus walke arme in arme, wo'd deny</L>
<L>Thee nothing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do not vanish me good Madam.</L>
<STAGE>A noise within.</STAGE>
<L>The people hoote already, none to reskue me.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Bentivolio, and Ardelia guarded.</STAGE>
<L>Is not this <HI>Bentivolio,</HI> under guard,</L>
<L>And his faire Mistresse pinniand? how now friend,</L>
<L>Wither are you bound with such a convoy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L>To prison, they are traitors.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Traitors.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do not beleeve 'em.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L>They have kil'd the <HI>Duke.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fia.</SPEAKER>
<L>How's that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe you know him sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Deere Madam are you prisoner too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take me along,</L>
<L>Better be hang'd then hanted with that goblin.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L>Another of the conspiracy disarm'd him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me but speake a word to this old Damsell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee's of the plot too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fia.</SPEAKER>
<L>I? I defie him,</L>
<L>I know him not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hope you wo'not leave me in distresse</L>
<L>Love, Mistresse lady-bird.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fia.</SPEAKER>
<L>I defie all traitors</L>
<L>Away with 'em, the <HI>Duke</HI> kil'd! out upon 'em,</L>
<L>That Fellow alwayes had a hanging countenance</L>
<L>Blesse me, defend me.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis well treason will</L>
<L>Make her forsake me yet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dost know on what</L>
<L>Danger thou dost ingage thy selfe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Although</L>
<L>I die for company 'tis worth it gentlemen</L>
<L>

<PB REF="36"/>
You know not how you have releev'd me Madam,</L>
<L>I did expect you'd bring him into mischeife,</L>
<L>I am perfect in your sex now, come to prison.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>You may repent your malice sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>And you</L>
<L>May be a Saint, away with us, come friend,</L>
<L>Women have made me weary of the World,</L>
<L>And hanging is a helpe, we might ha' liv'd</L>
<L>If you had tane my counsell, nay i'le share w'ed</L>
<L>I ha' not lost all my good fellowship.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Duke disguis'd, with Euphemia.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eup.</SPEAKER>
<L>My sorrowes, I forgive you all, this blessing</L>
<L>Has overpaid my heart, and though it cracke</L>
<L>With weight of this so unexpected happinesse,</L>
<L>I shall die more then satisfied.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du. and Euphemia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art too mercifull, and my repentance</L>
<L>Is yet too feeble, and too short a wonder,</L>
<L>Sure thou dost slatter me, if not heaven suffred,</L>
<L>My fall with holy cunning to let thee</L>
<L>Shine the Worlds great example of forgivenes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eup.</SPEAKER>
<L>But wherefore does your grace come hither thus</L>
<L>Disguis'd, being your selfe, and mine agen, what needs</L>
<L>This cloude upon your person, truth did never</L>
<L>Shame the professor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Though I live to thee,</L>
<L>The World doe thinke me dead <HI>Euphemia,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Leonato</HI> whom I lov'd, and trusted most,</L>
<L>Design'd my everlasting far-well from thee,</L>
<L>But he that should have been my executioner,</L>
<L>Without disordering this poore heape of nature,</L>
<L>Gave me another life, and growth to vertue,</L>
<L><HI>Pallante,</HI> blest good man</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eup.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Leonates</HI> creature,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>That honest Soldier after by his counsell,</L>
<L>I put this shape on, while to my false kins-man</L>
<L>He gives relation of my death, this key</L>
<L>He lent for my accesse to thy sad chamber,</L>
<L>

<PB REF="36"/>
I hope he is return'd.</L>
<STAGE>Leonato opens the dore.</STAGE>
<L>Tis <HI>Leonato.</HI></L>
<L>My heart o'th suddaine trembles with the feare</L>
<L>Of a nere danger, I am unarm'd too,</L>
<L>For our defence—Madam you are not wise,</L>
<L>And merit not this providence to dote</L>
<L>Upon a shadow, your dead husband, when</L>
<L><HI>Leonato</HI> lives, with more ambition to</L>
<L>Succeed him in your love, then this faire Duke-dome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>What fellowes this that pleads my cause, tis some</L>
<L><HI>Pallante</HI> has appointed to prepare her,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>With pardon, you deserve him not, and were</L>
<L>I <HI>Leonato</HI>—my good Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Spare your</L>
<L>Dull Retorick sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>That I could snatch</L>
<L>His sword, I dare not call for helpe, or leave 'em</L>
<L>She may be lost within a paire of minutes,</L>
<L>My heart, my braine!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam you said your vow</L>
<L>Was made for life, <HI>Fernizes</HI> death hath canceld</L>
<L>That obligation, and in midst of teares</L>
<L>Fate smiles upon you, if you dare looke up,</L>
<L>And meete it with a will to be made happy</L>
<L>He courts you now, has power to kill all sorrow,</L>
<L>From these faire eyes, be just to your kind fortune,</L>
<L>And dresse your face with your first beauty, Madam,</L>
<L>It may become the change, why weepe you still.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eup.</SPEAKER>
<L>I weepe for you my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>For me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eup.</SPEAKER>
<L>Because</L>
<L>You cannot for your selfe, pray tell me sir,</L>
<L>Is the <HI>Duke</HI> dead in earnest, you have not</L>
<L>A mourning face, but great heires seldome dy</L>
<L>With sudden greife, or weeping for thier Father,</L>
<L>Or Kins-mens Funerall, I pray how dy'd he?</L>
<L>Although he were not kind to take his leave,</L>
<L>I wod pay my obsequie of teares upon,</L>
<L>

<PB REF="37"/>
His Hearse, and weepe a prayer to his cold dust.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>That may be time enough.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eup.</SPEAKER>
<L>How I desire</L>
<L>To kisse his lip agen, oh shew me yet</L>
<L>Where's the pale ruines of my dead Lord? stay</L>
<L>He shall have halfe my soule, where's a soft,</L>
<L>And silent breath I will convay to warme,</L>
<L>And quicken his stiffe bosome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, what's</L>
<L>All this to my reward?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eup.</SPEAKER>
<L>Reward for what.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>My love which for your sake, and let me tell you</L>
<L>Not without some encouragment from you,</L>
<L>To give your heart more freedome to meet ruine,</L>
<L>Hath sent the <HI>Duke</HI> to heaven.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eup.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art a murderer,</L>
<L>Treason?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Treason.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who was that.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Some eccho</L>
<L>Within the Chamber, nothing else my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is not the <HI>Dukes</HI> ghost hovering hereabout,</L>
<L>It has a clamour like his voyce, ha, but</L>
<L>I can take order for your silence, use</L>
<L>That tongue againe, with the least accent to</L>
<L>Affright the aire, and i'le dismisse thy soule,</L>
<L>To waite upon thy husbands angry shade.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Horror? what can preserve us but a miracle?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet i'le not so much favour you, 'tis death</L>
<L>Perhaps you have ambition too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>One word</L>
<L>My gracious Lord, it has been my trade to deale</L>
<L>With women, with your pardon you do practise</L>
<L>Too tame a court-ship for her nature, use</L>
<L>The opportunity, and force her, to your</L>
<L>Pleasures, away with Sword, and buckle with her,</L>
<L>Leave me to keepe the doore, I ha been us'd to too't</L>
<L>Shee'le thanke you when'tis done, loose no time in talke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha? do thy office.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>

<PB REF="37"/>
Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wod your Lordship know me?</L>
<L>You shall—what thinke you of this officer?</L>
<L>False to thy blood; thy honour, and thy Prince,</L>
<L>Y'are caught my precious kins-man, and I live</L>
<L>With my owne hand to be reveng'd upon thee,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha then thorow her, I will receive my mends,</L>
<L>I did suspect that voyce, had not my confidence</L>
<L>Of thy most certaine death betraid me thus,</L>
<L>I wod have made sure worke, some Fate direct</L>
<L>His Sword thorow both our hearts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>No Treason, Treason.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Pallante, Strozzi, Silvio, Ascanio, with a guard, they wound Leonato.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>So let me employ the short breath that remaines</L>
<L>To tell you I engag'd <HI>Pallante,</HI> to</L>
<L>The <HI>Dukes</HI> death with a full hope to satisfie</L>
<L>Lust, and ambition, but he jugled with me,</L>
<L>And so has <HI>Bentivolio,</HI> though he be</L>
<L>With his <HI>Ardelia</HI> in prison, for</L>
<L>Acknowledging himselfe your murderer,</L>
<L>To which <HI>Vallerio,</HI> and my selfe inflam'd him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Valerio</HI> traitor too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir he is slaine,</L>
<L>His wounded body found in <HI>Ardelias</HI> chamber.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ardelia!</L>
<L>This darke mischeife shall be cleer'd</L>
<L><HI>Strozzi,</HI> command <HI>Bentivolo,</HI></L>
<L>And <HI>Ardelia</HI> be instantly brought hither?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Str.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most ingratefull <HI>Leonato.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know I am not worth your charity,</L>
<L>And yet my Lord your cruelty upon</L>
<L><HI>Euphemia,</HI> and some licence I tooke from</L>
<L>The example of your wanton blood, was ground</L>
<L>Of these misfortunes, 't seemes Y'are reconcil'd,</L>
<L>Be worth her love hereafter, thou wert just,</L>
<L><HI>Pallante,</HI> be still faithfull to thy Prince,</L>
<L>I beg your generall pardon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>

<PB REF="38" MS="y"/>
Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>We forgive thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heaven is a great way of, and I shall be</L>
<L>Ten thousand yeeres in travell, yet twere happy</L>
<L>If I may find a lodging there at last,</L>
<L>Though my poore soule get thither upon crutches</L>
<L>It cannot stay, far-well, agen forgive me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pall.</SPEAKER>
<L>He is dead.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eup.</SPEAKER>
<L>I pity him.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Strozzi.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Str.</SPEAKER>
<L>The prisoners waite.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Admit 'em.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Bentivolio, Ardelia, Horatio.</STAGE>
<L>Was your life so great a burthen</L>
<L>That you upon the rumour of our murder,</L>
<L>Would take the act upon you, though you had</L>
<L>Promis'd to be the traitor, or did you</L>
<L>Envy another man should owne the glory,</L>
<L>And title of our bloudy executioner.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, but confest the guilt I then beleev'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is a mistery.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I can best cleere it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis my wonder how?</L>
<L><HI>Valerio</HI> was slaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<L>That I must answer,</L>
<L>Although my Sword then promis'd to another</L>
<L>Revenge, yet in the wound he met a Justice,</L>
<L>I now repent not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eup.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's that gentleman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am one Madam that do court my friend here,</L>
<L>So well that though he be in faire election</L>
<L>To loose his Head, or to be Strangled—</L>
<L>Had rather take such as I find with him,</L>
<L>Then live to be tormented with a woman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eup.</SPEAKER>
<L>What woman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Any woman, without difference,</L>
<L>I have heard your grace has a good fame, and though</L>
<L>It does become your subjects to beleeve it,</L>
<L>I was not borne here Madam, and i've had</L>
<L>Such ill luck with your sex, it does not bind</L>
<L>

<PB REF="38"/>
My faith, tis possible there may be good</L>
<L>Both faire, and honest women, but they were never</L>
<L>Under my acquaintance, no noe yet ilfavored,</L>
<L>In whom I onely look'd to find a soule,</L>
<L>But bost my labour. This is all truth Madam:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eup.</SPEAKER>
<L>His humour makes me smile.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Enough, not onely</L>
<L>Our pardon for <HI>Valerios</HI> death, I give</L>
<L>Thee back <HI>Ardelia,</HI> she was my Mistresse</L>
<L>But I returne her pure as thy owne wishes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<L>This grace is mighty sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Weele see you married,</L>
<L>And what our person, and <HI>Euphemias</HI></L>
<L>Can adde to grace you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'ave already blest us,</L>
<L>And heaven shower joyes upon you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>The next thing is to honor thee <HI>Pallante,</HI></L>
<L>Thou savest my life, and didst now marrie me,</L>
<L>Thy faith is not rewarded.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pall.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Was my duty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>What, is all well agen? and is she honest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most innocent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then shee's too good for thee,</L>
<L>Come the truth is, and now i'le speake my conscience</L>
<L>If there be few good women in the World,</L>
<L>The fault rise first from one of our owne sex,</L>
<L>By flattery in false-hood to deceave 'em,</L>
<L>And so the punishment does but descend</L>
<L>To us in justice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's some charity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come my <HI>Euphemia,</HI> this second knot</L>
<L>Shall be as firme as destiny, nor shall</L>
<L>What ever was to our chast vow a shame,</L>
<L>In my lives after Story have a name.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Omnes.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
<BACK>
<DIV1 TYPE="epilogue">
<PB REF="39"/>
<HEAD>Epil. for Horatio.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L>GEntlemen, and Ladies,</L>
<L>If I have transgrest in any language</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> hansome faces, I hope you will forgive</L>
<L>Me, and imagine, I have but plaid the part, which</L>
<L>Was most against my <HI>Genius,</HI> of any that ever I</L>
<L>Acted in my life, to speake truth,</L>
<L>Who is so simple to dote upon Witches, and hel-Cats.</L>
<L><HI>Venus</HI> deliver us, the Poet stands liftning behind the arras</L>
<L>To heare what will become on's Play, under the</L>
<L>Rose if you will seeme to like it I'le put</L>
<L>A tricke upon him.</L>
<L>For though he heare when you applaud, I'le say</L>
<L>Your hands did seale my pardon, not the Play.</L>
</LG>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
<PB REF="39"/>
</DIV1>
</BACK>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

