<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>12-20-04</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Benjamin Griffin</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM> </ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A12142">
<STC T="S">22448</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99852586</BIBNO>
<VID>17913</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>THE LADY OF PLEASVRE.</P>
<P>A COMEDIE, As it vvas Acted by her Ma¦jesties Servants, at the private House in <HI>Drury</HI> Lane.</P>
<P>Written by <HI>James Shirly.</HI></P>
<P>LONDON, Printed by <HI>Tho. Cotes,</HI> for <HI>Andrew Crooke,</HI> and <HI>William Cooke.</HI> 1637.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dramatis personae">
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>Persons of the Comedy.</HEAD>
<LIST>
<ITEM>LOrd,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Sir Thomas Bornewell.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Sir William Sentlove.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Mr. Alex. Kickshaw.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Mr. Iohn Littleworth.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Mr. Hairecut.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Mr. Fredericke.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Steward to the Lady</HI> Aretina.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Steward to the Lady</HI> Celestina.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Secretary.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Servants, &amp;c.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<ITEM>Aretina, <HI>Sir</HI> Thomas Bornwells <HI>Lady.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Celestina, <HI>a young Widow.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Isabella.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Mariana.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Madam Decoy.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<P><HI>Scene the Strand.</HI></P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>TO THE RIGHT HONO∣RABLE RICHARD LORD <HI>LOVELACE</HI> of <HI>Hurley.</HI></HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>My Lord,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P><HI><SEG REND="decorInit">I</SEG></HI> Cannot want encouragement to present a Poeme to your Lordship, while you possesse so noble a breast, in which so many seedes of honour, to the example and glory of your Name obtain'd, before your yeares a happy maturity. This Comedy fortunate in the Scene, and one that may challenge a place in the first forme of the Authors compositions, most humbly addresseth it selfe to your honour, if it meete your <PB REF="3"/>
gracious acceptance, and that you repent not to be a Patron, your Lordshipps will onely crownes the ima∣gination, and for ever by this favour oblige,</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED><HI>My Lord</HI> The most humble Services of your Honourer, <HI>IAMES SHIRLY.</HI></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="play">
<PB REF="3"/>
<HEAD>The Lady of Pleasure.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>The first Act.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Aretina <HI>and her Steward.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><SEG REND="decorInit">S</SEG>Tew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be patient Madam, you may have your pleasure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis that I came to towne for, I wo'd not</L>
<L>Endure againe the countrey conversation,</L>
<L>To be the Lady of sixe shires! the men</L>
<L>So neare the Primitive making, they retaine</L>
<L>A sence of nothing but the earth, their braines</L>
<L>And barren heads standing as much in want</L>
<L>Of plowing as their ground, to heare a fellow</L>
<L>Make himselfe merry and his horse with whisteling</L>
<L>Sellingers round, to observe with what solemnitie</L>
<L>They keepe their Wakes, and throw for pewter Candlestickes,</L>
<L>How they become the Morris, whi<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> whose bells</L>
<L>They ring all into Whitson Ales, and sweate,</L>
<L>Through twenty Scarffes and Napkins, till the Hobbyhorse</L>
<L>Tire, and the maide Marrian dissolv'd to a gelly,</L>
<L>Be kept for spoone meate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>These with your pardon are no Argument</L>
<L>To make the country life appeare so hatefull,</L>
<L>At least to your particular, who enjoy'd</L>
<L>A blessing in that calme; would you be pleasd</L>
<L>To thinke so, and the pleasure of a kingdome,</L>
<L>While your owne will commanded what should move</L>
<L>Delights, your husbands love and power joyned</L>
<L>To give your life more harmony▪ you liv'd there,</L>
<L>Secure, and innocent, beloved of all,</L>
<L>Praisd for your hospitality, and praid for▪</L>
<L><PB REF="4"/>You might be envied, but malice knew</L>
<L>Not where you dwelt, I wo'd not prophecy</L>
<L>But leave to your owne apprehension</L>
<L>What may succeede your change.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>You doe imagine,</L>
<L>No doubt, you have talk'd wisely, and confuted,</L>
<L>London past all defence, your Master should</L>
<L>Doe well to send you backe into the countrie,</L>
<L>With title of Supernitendent Baylie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>How Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>Even so sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am a Gentleman though now your servant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>A country gentleman,</L>
<L>By your affection to converse with stable,</L>
<L>His tenants will advance you wit, and plumpe it so</L>
<L>With beefe and bag-pudding.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>You may say your pleasure,</L>
<L>It becomes not me dispute.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>Complaine to the Lord of the soyle your master.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'are a woman of an ungovern'd passion, and I pitty you.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Sir Thomas Bornwell.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>How how? Whats the matter?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nothing Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Angry sweete heart?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am angry with my selfe,</L>
<L>To be so miserably restrained in things,</L>
<L>Wherein it doth concerne your love and honour</L>
<L>To see me satisfied.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>In what <HI>Aretina?</HI></L>
<L>Dost thou accuse me? have I not obeyd</L>
<L>All thy desires, against mine owne opinion,</L>
<L>Quitted the countrie, and removed the hope</L>
<L>Of our returne, by sale of that faire Lordship</L>
<L>We liv'd in, chang'd a calme and retire life</L>
<L>For this wild towne, composd of noise and charge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>What charge more than is necessarie,</L>
<L>For a Lady of my birth and education▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am not ignorant, how much Nobilitie</L>
<L><PB REF="4" MS="y"/>Flowes in your bloud, your kinsmen great and powerfull,</L>
<L>It▪h State, but with this lose not your memory</L>
<L>Of being my wife, I shall be studious</L>
<L>Madam to give the dignitie of your birth</L>
<L>All the best ornaments which become my fortune</L>
<L>But would not flatter it, to ruine both,</L>
<L>And be the fable of the towne, to teach</L>
<L>Other men losse of wit by mine, emploid</L>
<L>To serve your vaste expences.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>Am I then</L>
<L>Brought in the ballance? so Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Though you weigh</L>
<L>Me in a partiall scale my heart is honest,</L>
<L>And must take libertie to thinke you have</L>
<L>Obeyed no modest counsell to effect,</L>
<L>Nay study wayes of pride and costly ceremony,</L>
<L>Your change of gaudy furniture and pictures</L>
<L>Of this Italian Master, and that Dutchmnas,</L>
<L>Your mighty looking-glasses like Artillery;</L>
<L>Brought whom on Engins, the superfluous plate,</L>
<L>Anticke and novell, vanities of tires,</L>
<L>Fourescore pound suppers for my Lord your kinsman,</L>
<L>Banquets for tother Lady, aunt, and cozens,</L>
<L>And perfumes that exceede all traine of servants,</L>
<L>To stifle us at home and shew abroad</L>
<L>More motley than the French, or the Venetian▪</L>
<L>About your Coach whose rude Postillion</L>
<L>Must pester every narrow lane, till passengers</L>
<L>And tradsmen curse your choaking up their stalls;</L>
<L>And common cries pursue your Ladiship,</L>
<L>For hindring o'their market.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>Have you done sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>I could accuse the gayetie of your wardrobe,</L>
<L>And prodigall embroderies under which</L>
<L>Rich Sattens, Plushes, cloath of Silver, dare</L>
<L>Not shew their owne complexions, your jewells</L>
<L>Able to burne out the Spectators eyes,</L>
<L>And shew like Bonefires on you by the tapers,</L>
<L>Something might here be spar'd, which safely of</L>
<L>Your birth and honour, since the truest wealth,</L>
<L>Shines from the soule, and drawes up just admirers,</L>
<PB REF="5"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="5"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<L><PB REF="6"/>I could urge something more:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray doe I like</L>
<L>Your homilie of thrifte.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I could wish Madam</L>
<L>You would not game so much.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>A gamster too?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>But are not come to that repentance yet,</L>
<L>Should teach you skill enough to raise your profit,</L>
<L>You looke not through the subtiltie of Cards,</L>
<L>And mysteries of Dice, nor can you save</L>
<L>Charge with the boxe, buy petticotes and purles,</L>
<L>And keepe your familie by the precious income,</L>
<L>Nor doe I wish you should, my poorest servant</L>
<L>Shall not upbraid my tables, nor his hire</L>
<L>Purchasd beneath my honour, you make play</L>
<L>Not a Pastime but a tyrannie, and vexe</L>
<L>Your selfe and my estate by't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good, proceed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Another game you have, which consumes more</L>
<L>Your fame than purse, you revells in the night,</L>
<L>Your meetings cal'd the Ball, to which appeare,</L>
<L>As to the Court of Pleasure, all your gallants,</L>
<L>And Ladies thither bound by a Subpena</L>
<L>Of <HI>Venus,</HI> and small <HI>Cupids</HI> high displeasure,</L>
<L>Tis but the family of love translated</L>
<L>Into more costly sinne, there was a play on't,</L>
<L>And had the Poet not beene brib'd to a modest</L>
<L>Expression of your Anticke gambolls, in't,</L>
<L>Some darkes had beene discovered, and the deeds too,</L>
<L>In time he may repent and make some blush.</L>
<L>To see the second part danc'd on the Stage;</L>
<L>My thoughts acquit you for dishonouring me</L>
<L>By any foule act, but the vertuous know,</L>
<L>Tis not enough to cleare our selves, but the</L>
<L>Suspitions of our shame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>Have you concluded</L>
<L>Your lecture?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>I ha done, and howsoever</L>
<L>My language my appeare to you, it carries</L>
<L>No other than my faire and just intent</L>
<L>To your delights without curbe to their modest,</L>
<L>And noble freedome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile not be so tedious,</L>
<L>In my reply, but without arte or elegance,</L>
<L>Assure you I keepe still my first opinion,</L>
<L><PB REF="6"/>And though you vay'le, your avatitious meaning</L>
<L>With hansome names of modesty, and thrift,</L>
<L>I finde you would intrench and wound the liberty</L>
<L>I was borne with, were my desires unpriviledged</L>
<L>By example, while my judgement thought 'em fit,</L>
<L>You ought not to oppose, but when the practise</L>
<L>And tract of every honourable Lady,</L>
<L>Authorise me, I take it great injustice,</L>
<L>To have my pleasures circumscribed, and taught me,</L>
<L>A narrow minded husband is a theefe</L>
<L>To his owne fame, and his preferment too,</L>
<L>He shuts his parts and fortunes from the world,</L>
<L>While from the popular vote and knowledge men</L>
<L>Rise to imployment in the state.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have</L>
<L>No great ambition to buy preferment</L>
<L>At so deare rate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor I to sell my honour,</L>
<L>By living poore and sparingly, I was not</L>
<L>Bred in that ebbe of fortune, and my fate</L>
<L>Shall not compell me too't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know not Madam,</L>
<L>But you pursue these wayes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>What wayes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>In the strict sence of honestie I dare</L>
<L>Make oath, they are Innocent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do not divert,</L>
<L>By busie troubling of your braine, those thoughts</L>
<L>That should preserve em.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>How was that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis English.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>But carries some unkinde sence.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Madam Decoy.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good morrow my sweete Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Decoy</HI> welcome, this visite is a favour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas sweet Madam, I cannot stay, I came</L>
<L>But to present my service to your Ladiship;</L>
<L>I could not passe by your doore, but I must take</L>
<L>The boldnesse to tender my respects.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>You oblige me Madam, but I must</L>
<L>Not dispence so with your absence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas, the Coach Madam stayes for me at the doore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou sha't command mine, prethee sweete <HI>Decoy.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>I wou'd waite on you Madam, but I have many</L>
<L><PB REF="7"/>Visits to make this morning I beseech.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>So you will promise to dine with me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall</L>
<L>Present a guest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why then good morrow Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>A happy day shine on your Ladiship.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Steward.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whats your newes sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>St.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam two gentlemen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>What gentlemen? Have they no names.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>St.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are</L>
<L>The gentleman with his owne head of haire,</L>
<L>Whom you commended for his horsemanship</L>
<L>In Hide Parke, and becomming the saddle</L>
<L>The tother day.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>What circumstance is this,</L>
<L>To know him by.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>St.</SPEAKER>
<L>His names at my tongues end,</L>
<L>He lik'd the fashion of your pearle chaine Madam,</L>
<L>And borrowed it for his Jeweller to take</L>
<L>A coppie by it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>What cheating gallants this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>St.</SPEAKER>
<L>That never walkes without a Ladies buske,</L>
<L>And playes with fannes Mr. <HI>Alexander Kickshaw,</HI></L>
<L>I thought I should remember him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whats the other?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>St.</SPEAKER>
<L>What an unluckie memorie I have?</L>
<L>The gallant that still danceth in the streete,</L>
<L>And weares a grosse of Ribbon in his hat,</L>
<L>That carries <HI>Oringado</HI> in his pocket,</L>
<L>And Suger-plumbs to sweeten his discourse,</L>
<L>That studies complement, defies all wit</L>
<L>On blacke, and censures playes that are not bawdy,</L>
<L>Mr. <HI>Iohn littleworth.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are welcome, but</L>
<L>Pray entertaine them a small time, lest I</L>
<L>Be unprovided.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did they aske for me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>No sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>It matters not, they must be welcome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fie, how's this haire disordered? here's a curle,</L>
<L>Straddle most impiously, I must to my closet.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Waite on em: my Lady will returne agen,</L>
<L>I have to such a height fulfill d her humor,</L>
<L>All applications dangerous, these gallants</L>
<L>Must be received or shee will fall into</L>
<L>A tempest, and the house be shooke with names</L>
<L>Of all her kindred, tis a servitude,</L>
<L>I may in time shake off.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="7"/><HI>Enter Alexander and Littleworth.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al. Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Save you Sir <HI>Thomas.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Save you gentlemen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>I kisse your hand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>What day is it abroad?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>The morning rises from your Ladies eye,</L>
<L>If she looke cleare, we take the happy omen</L>
<L>Of a faire day.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sheele instantly appeare,</L>
<L>To the discredit of your complement,</L>
<L>But you expresse your wit thus.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>And you modestie,</L>
<L>Not to affect the praises of your owne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Leaving this subject, what games now on foote▪</L>
<L>What exercise carries the generall vote?</L>
<L>Oth towne now nothing moves without your knowledge,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>The cocking now has all the noise, Ile have</L>
<L>A hundred peeces of one battle, Oh,</L>
<L>These birds of <HI>Mars!</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Venus</HI> is <HI>Mars</HI> his bird too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why and the pretty Doves are <HI>Venusses,</HI></L>
<L>To show that kisses draw the Charriot.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am for that skirmish.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>When shall wee have</L>
<L>More Booths and Bag-pipes upon Bansted downes,</L>
<L>No mighty race is expected, but my Lady returnes.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Aretina.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faire morning to you gentlemen,</L>
<L>You went not late to bed by your early visit,</L>
<L>You doe me honour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>It becomes our service.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>What newes abroade? you hold precious intelligence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>All tongues are so much busie with your praise,</L>
<L>They have not time to frame other discourse,</L>
<L>Will please you Madam? tast a Sugerplum.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>What do's the Goldsmith thinke the Pearle is worth.</L>
<L>You borrowed of my Lady?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis a rich one.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>She has many other toyes whose fashion you,</L>
<L>Will like extremely, you have no intention</L>
<L>To buy any of her Iewels.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vnderstand me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>You had rather sell perhaps, but leaving this,</L>
<L>I hope you'le dine with us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>I came a purpose.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="8"/>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>And where were you last night?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>I Madam? where</L>
<L>I slept not, it had beene sin where so much</L>
<L>Delight and beauty was to keepe me waking,</L>
<L>There is a Lady Madam will be worth</L>
<L>Your free societie, my conversation</L>
<L>Nere knew so elegant and brave a soule,</L>
<L>With most incomparable flesh and bloud,</L>
<L>So spirited, so Courtly speakes the Languages,</L>
<L>Sings, Dances, playes o'th Lute to admiration,</L>
<L>Is faire and paints not, games too, keepes a table,</L>
<L>And talkes most witty Satyre, has a wit</L>
<L>Of a cleane Mercury.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is shee married?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>No.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Virgin?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Neither.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>What a widow? some∣thing.</L>
<L>Of this wide commendation might have beene</L>
<L>Excusd, this such a prodigie?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Repent</L>
<L>Before I name her, shee did never see</L>
<L>Yet full sixteene, an age in the opinion</L>
<L>Of wise men not contemptible, she ha's</L>
<L>Mourned out her yeare too for the honest Knight</L>
<L>That had compassion of her youth, and dy'd</L>
<L>So timely, such a widow is not common,</L>
<L>And now she shines more fresh and tempting</L>
<L>Then any naturall Virgin.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whats her name?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee was Christened <HI>Celestina,</HI> by her husband</L>
<L>The Lady <HI>Bellamour,</HI> this Ring was hers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>You borrowed it to coppie out the Posie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are they not pretty Rubies? twas a grace</L>
<L>She was pleasd to shew me, that I might have one</L>
<L>Made of the same fashion, for I love</L>
<L>All prettie formes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>And is she glorious?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>She is full of Jewels Madam, but I am</L>
<L>Most taken with the bravery of her minde,</L>
<L>Although her garments have all grace and ornament.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>You haue beene high in praises.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>I come short,</L>
<L>No flattery can reach her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now my Lady</L>
<L>Is troubled as she feared to be eclipsd,</L>
<L><PB REF="8"/>This newes will cost me somewhat.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>You deserve</L>
<L>Her favour for this noble character.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I possesse it by my starres benevolence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>You must bring us acquainted.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I pray doe sir.</L>
<L>I long to see her too, Madam I have</L>
<L>Thought upon't and corrected my opinion,</L>
<L>Pursue what wayes of pleasure your desires</L>
<L>Incline you too, not onely with my state,</L>
<L>But with my person I will follow you,</L>
<L>I see the folly of my thrift, and will</L>
<L>Repent in Sacke and prodigalitie</L>
<L>To your owne hearts content.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>But doe not mocke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take me to your imbraces gentlemen</L>
<L>And tutor me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>And will you kisse the Ladies?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>And sing and dance, I long to see this beauty,</L>
<L>I wood faine lose a hundred pounds at dice now,</L>
<L>Thou sha't have another gowne and petticote,</L>
<L>To morrow will you sell my running horses?</L>
<L>We have no Greeke wine in the house I thinke,</L>
<L>Pray send one of our footemen to the Merchant,</L>
<L>And throw the hogsheads of March-beare into</L>
<L>The kenell, to make roome for Sackes and Clarret,</L>
<L>What thinke you to be drunke yet before dinner?</L>
<L>We will have constant musicke and maintaine</L>
<L>Them and their Fidles in phantasticke liveries,</L>
<L>Ile tune my voyce to catches, I must have</L>
<L>My dyning roome enlarg'd to invite Embassadors,</L>
<L>Weele feast the parish in the fields, and teach</L>
<L>The Military men new discipline,</L>
<L>Who shall charge all their new Artillerie</L>
<L>With Oringes and Lemonds, boy to play</L>
<L>All dinner upon our capons.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee's exalted.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will doe any thing to please my Lady,</L>
<L>Let that suffice and kisse oth same condition,</L>
<L>I am converted, doe not you dispute</L>
<L>But patiently allow the miracle.
<STAGE>Enter Servant.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am glad to heare you sir in so good tune.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="9"/>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam the Painter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am to sit this morning.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe, while I give new directions to my Steward.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>With your favour we'le waite on you, sitting's but</L>
<L>A melancholy exercise without</L>
<L>Some company to discourse▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>It does conclude</L>
<L>A Ladies morning worke, we rise, make fine,</L>
<L>Sit for our Picture, and tis time to dine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Praying's forgot.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis out of fashion.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Celestina and her Steward.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fie, what an aire this roome has.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>St.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis persum'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>With some cheape sluffe is it your wisedomes thrift</L>
<L>To infect my nostrils thus? Or i'st to favour</L>
<L>The Gout in your worships hand? You are afraid</L>
<L>To exercise your pen in your account Booke?</L>
<L>Or doe you doubt my credit to discharge</L>
<L>Your bills.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>St.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, I hope you have not found</L>
<L>My dutie with the guilt of sloath or jealousie,</L>
<L>Vnapt to your command.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>You can extenuate</L>
<L>Your faults with language sir, but I expect</L>
<L>To be obeyed; What hangings have we here?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>St.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are Arras Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Impudence I know't,</L>
<L>I will have fresher and more rich, not wrought</L>
<L>With faces that may scandalise a Christian</L>
<L>With Iewish stories stufft with Corne and Camells,</L>
<L>You had best wrap all my chambers in wild Irish,</L>
<L>And make a nursery of Monsters here,</L>
<L>To fright the Ladies comes to visite me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>St.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam I hope.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>I say I will have other,</L>
<L>Good Master Steward of a finer loome,</L>
<L>Some silke and silver if your worship please,</L>
<L>To let me be at so much cost Ile have</L>
<L>Stories to sit the seasons of the yeare,</L>
<L>And change as often as I please.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>St.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am bound to your consent forsooth, and is</L>
<L>My coach brought home?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>St.</SPEAKER>
<L>This morning I expect it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>The inside as I gave direction,</L>
<L><PB REF="9"/>Of crimson plush.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>St.</SPEAKER>
<L>Of crimson Camell plush.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ten thousand mothes consum't, shall I ride through</L>
<L>The streets in penance wrapt up round in haire cloath,</L>
<L>Sel't to an Alderman, twill serve his wife</L>
<L>To goe a feasting to their country house,</L>
<L>Or fetch a Merchants Nurse child, and come home</L>
<L>Laden with fruite and Cheese cakes; I despise it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>St.</SPEAKER>
<L>The nailes adorne it Madam, set in method</L>
<L>And pretty formes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>But single guilt I warrant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>St.</SPEAKER>
<L>No Madam:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Another Solecisme, oh fie,</L>
<L>This fellow will bring me to a Consumption</L>
<L>With fretting at his ignorance, some Lady</L>
<L>Had rather never pray, than goe to Church in't;</L>
<L>The nailes not double guilt? to market wo't,</L>
<L>Twill hackny out to Mile-end, or convey</L>
<L>Your citie tumblers to be drunke with Creame</L>
<L>And Prunes at Islington.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>St.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good Madam heare me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile rather be beholding to my Aunt</L>
<L>The Countesse for her mourning coach, then be</L>
<L>Disparag'd so, shall any juggling tradsman</L>
<L>Be at charge to shooe his running horse with gold,</L>
<L>And shall my coach nailes be but single guilt?</L>
<L>How dare these knaves abuse me so?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>St.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vouchsafe</L>
<L>To heare me speake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is my Sedan yet finish'd?</L>
<L>And liveries for my men-Mules according</L>
<L>As I gave charge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>St.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes Madam it is finish'd,</L>
<L>But without tilting plumes at the foure corners,</L>
<L>The scarlet's pure, but not embroidered.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>What mischiefe were it to your conscience</L>
<L>Were my coach lin'd with tissue, and my harnesse</L>
<L>Cover'd with needleworke? if my Sedan</L>
<L>Had all the story of the Prodigall,</L>
<L>Embrodered with pearle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>St.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas good Madam,</L>
<L>I know tis your owne cost, I am but your Steward,</L>
<L>And wod discharge my duty the best way,</L>
<L>You have beene pleasd to heare me, tis not for</L>
<L>My profit, that I manage your estate,</L>
<L>And save expence, but for your honour Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="10"/>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>How sir, my honour?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>St.</SPEAKER>
<L>Though you heare it not</L>
<L>Mens tongues are liberall in your character,</L>
<L>Since you began to live thus high, I know</L>
<L>Your fame is precious to you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>I were best</L>
<L>Make you my governor; audacious Varlet,</L>
<L>How dare you interpose your doting counsell?</L>
<L>Mind your affaires with more obedience,</L>
<L>Or I shall ease you of an office sir,</L>
<L>Must I be limited to please your honour?</L>
<L>Or for the vulgar breath confine my pleasures,</L>
<L>I will pursue'em in what shapes I fancie,</L>
<L>Here, and abroad, my entertainements shall</L>
<L>Be oftner, and more rich, who shall controule me?</L>
<L>I live i'th strand, whether few Ladies come</L>
<L>To live, and purchase, more than fame, I will</L>
<L>Be hospitable then, and spare no cost</L>
<L>That may engage all generous report</L>
<L>To trumpet forth my bounty and my braverie,</L>
<L>Till the Court envie, and remove, Ile have</L>
<L>My house the Academy of wits, who shall</L>
<L>Exalt with rich Sacke, and Sturgeon,</L>
<L>Write Panegyricks of my feasts, and praise</L>
<L>The method of my wittie superfluities,</L>
<L>The horses shall be taught with frequent waiting</L>
<L>Vpon my gates, to stop in their careere</L>
<L>Toward Charing-crosse, spight of the Coachmans fury.</L>
<L>And not a tilter, but shall strike his plume,</L>
<L>When he failes by my window, my Balconie</L>
<L>Shall be the Courtiers Idoll, and more gaz'd at,</L>
<L>Than all the Pageantry at Temple barre,</L>
<L>By countrey Clients.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>St.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sure my Ladie's mad.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take that for your ill manners.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>St.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thanke you Ma∣dam,</L>
<L>I would there were lesse quicksilver in your fingers.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>There's more than simple honesty in a servant</L>
<L>Requi<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d to his full dutie, none should dare,</L>
<L>But with a looke, much lesse a sawcie language</L>
<L>Checke at their Mistresse pleasure, I'me resolv'd</L>
<L>To pay for some delight, my estate will beare it,</L>
<L><PB REF="10"/>Ile reine it shorter when I please.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Steward.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>St.</SPEAKER>
<L>A gentleman</L>
<L>Desires to speake with your Ladiship.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>His name?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>St.</SPEAKER>
<L>He saies you know him not, he seemes to be</L>
<L>Of qualitie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Admit him. Sir with me.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Hairecut.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam I know not, how you may receive</L>
<L>This boldnesse from me, but my faire intents</L>
<L>Knowne, will incline you to be charitable.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>No doubt sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>He must live obscurely Madam,</L>
<L>That hath not heard what vertues you possesse,</L>
<L>And I a poore admirer of your fame,</L>
<L>Am come to kisse your hand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>That all your businesse?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Though it were worth much travell, I have more</L>
<L>In my ambition.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speake it freely sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are a widow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>So.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I a Bachelor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>You come a wooing sir, and would perhaps</L>
<L>Shew me a way to reconcile these two.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>And blesse my starres for such a happinesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>I like you sir the better, that you doe not</L>
<L>Wander about, but shoote home to the meaning,</L>
<L>Tis a confidence will make a man</L>
<L>Know sooner what to trust to, but I never</L>
<L>Saw you before, and I beleeve you come not</L>
<L>With hope to finde me desperate upon marriage,</L>
<L>If maides out of their ignorance of what</L>
<L>Men, are refuse these offers, widowes may</L>
<L>Out of their knowledge be allow'd some coynesse,</L>
<L>And yet I know not how much happinesse</L>
<L>A peremptorie answer may deprive me of,</L>
<L>You may be some young Lord, and though I see not</L>
<L>Your footmen and your groome, they may not be</L>
<L>Farre off in conference with your horse, please you</L>
<L>To instruct me with your title, against which</L>
<L>I would not willingly offend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am</L>
<L>A gentleman, my name is <HI>Hairecut</HI> madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweete Mr. <HI>Hairecut,</HI> are you a Courtier?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="11"/>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>J did thinke so by your confidence,</L>
<L>Not to detaine you sir with circumstance,</L>
<L>J was not so unhappy in my husband</L>
<L>But that tis possible J may be a wife</L>
<L>Agen, but J must tell you, he that winnes</L>
<L>My affection shall deserve me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>J will hope</L>
<L>If you can love, J shanot present Madam</L>
<L>An object to displease you in my person,</L>
<L>And when time, and your patience shall possesse you</L>
<L>With further knowledge of me, and the truth</L>
<L>Of my devotion, you will not repent</L>
<L>The offer of my service.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>You say well.</L>
<L>How long doe you imagine you can love sir?</L>
<L>Is it a Quotidian, or will it hold</L>
<L>But every other day?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are pleasant Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dost take you with a burning at the first,</L>
<L>Or with a cold fit, for you gentlemen</L>
<L>Have both your Summer, and your Winter service.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>J am ignorant what you meane, but J shall never</L>
<L>Be cold in my affection to such beautie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>And twill be somewhat long ere J be warme in't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you vouchsafe me so much honour Madam,</L>
<L>That J may waite on you sometimes, J shanot</L>
<L>Despaire to see a change.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>But now J know</L>
<L>Your minde, you shall not neede to tell it, when</L>
<L>You come agen, J shall remember it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>You make me fortunate.
<STAGE>Enter Steward.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>St.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam your kinswomen</L>
<L>The Lady <HI>Novice</HI> and her sister are</L>
<L>New lighted from their coach.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>I did expect e'm,</L>
<L>They partly are my pupills, i'e attend e'm.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam I have beene too great a trespasser</L>
<L>Vpon your patience, ile take my leave,</L>
<L>You have affaires, and I have some imployment</L>
<L>Calls me to Court, I shall present agen</L>
<L>A servant to you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir you may present,
<STAGE>Exit. Ha.</STAGE></L>
<L>But not give fire I hope, now to the Ladies</L>
<L>This recreation's past, the next must be</L>
<L><PB REF="11"/>To read to them some Court Philosophie.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>The second Act.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter sir Thomas Bornewell.</STAGE>
<L>Tis a strange humour I have undertaken</L>
<L>To dance, and play, and spend as fast as she does,</L>
<L>But I am resolv'd, it may doe good upon her,</L>
<L>And fright her into thrift, nay ile endeavour</L>
<L>To make her jealous too, if this doe not</L>
<L>Allay her gamboling, shees's past a woman</L>
<L>And onely a miracle must tame her.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Steward.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>St.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis Mr. <HI>Fredericke</HI> my Ladies nephew.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>What of him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>St.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is come from the Vniversitie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>By whose directions?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>St.</SPEAKER>
<L>It seemes my Ladies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me speake with him</L>
<L>Before he see his Aunt, I doe not like it.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Mr. Fredericke.</STAGE>
<L>Mr. <HI>Fredericke</HI> welcome I expected not</L>
<L>So soone your presence, what's the hasty cause?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fr.</SPEAKER>
<L>These letters from my Tutor will acquaint you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>St.</SPEAKER>
<L>Welcome home sweet Mr. <HI>Fredericke.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where's my Aunt?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>St.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee's busie about her painting, in her closet,</L>
<L>The Outlandish man of Art, is copying out</L>
<L>Her countenance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fr.</SPEAKER>
<L>She is sitting for her picture.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>St.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes siir, and when tis drawne, she will be hang'd</L>
<L>Next the French Cardinall in the dining roome,</L>
<L>But when she heares you'r come, she will dismisse</L>
<L>The Belgicke gentleman to entertaine</L>
<L>Your worship.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Change of aire has made you witty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Tutor gives you a hansome character</L>
<L><HI>Fredericke,</HI> and is sorry your Aunts pleasure</L>
<L>Commands you from your studies, but I hope</L>
<L>You have no quarrell to the liberall arts,</L>
<L>Learning is an addition beyond</L>
<L>Nobilitie of birth, honour of bloud</L>
<L>Without the ornament of knowledge is</L>
<L>A glorious ignorance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fr.</SPEAKER>
<L>I never knew more sweet and happy houres</L>
<L><PB REF="12"/>Than I emploid upon my bookes, I heard</L>
<L>A part of my Philosophy, and was so</L>
<L>Delighted with the harmony of nature,</L>
<L>I could have wasted my whole life upon't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis pitty a rash indulgence should corrupt</L>
<L>So faire a Genius, shee's here, ile observe.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Aretina, Alexander. Littleworth. Steward.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fr.</SPEAKER>
<L>My most lov'd Aunt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>Support me, J shall faint.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>What ailes your Ladiship?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is that <HI>Fredericke,</HI></L>
<L>In blacke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes Madam, but the doublets Sattin.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>The boy's undone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fre.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam you appeare trou∣bled.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>Have J not cause? Was not J trusted with</L>
<L>Thy education boy, and have they sent thee</L>
<L>Home like a very scholler.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Twas ill done</L>
<L>How ere they usd him in the Vniversitie,</L>
<L>To send him to his friends thus.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fre.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why sir, blacke</L>
<L>(I or tis the colour that offends your eyesight)</L>
<L>Is not within my reading any blemish,</L>
<L>Sables are no disgrace in Heraldry.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis comming from the Colledge thus, that makes it</L>
<L>Dishonorable, while you ware it for</L>
<L>Your father, it was commendable, or were</L>
<L>Your Aunt dead, you might mourne and justifie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>What lucke J did not send him into France,</L>
<L>They would have given him generous education,</L>
<L>Taught him another garbe to weare his locke,</L>
<L>And shape, as gawdie as the Summer, how</L>
<L>To dance, and wagge his feather ala mode,</L>
<L>To complement, and cringe, to talke not modestly</L>
<L>Like J forsooth, and no forsooth, to blush</L>
<L>And looke so like a Chaplaine, there he might</L>
<L>Have learned a brazen confidence, and observ'd</L>
<L>So well the custome of the countrey, that</L>
<L>He might by this time have invented fashions</L>
<L>For us, and beene a benefit to the Kingdome</L>
<L>Preserv'd our Tailors in their wits, and fav'd</L>
<L>The charge of sending into forraine Courts</L>
<L>For pride and anticke fashions, observe,</L>
<L>In what a posture he does hold his hat now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="12"/>
<SPEAKER>Fr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam with your pardon, you have practisd</L>
<L>Another dialect then was taught me when</L>
<L>I was commended to your care and breeding,</L>
<L>I understand not this, Latine or Greeke</L>
<L>Are more familiar to my apprehension,</L>
<L>Logicke was not so hard in my first lectures</L>
<L>As your strange language.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>Some strong waters, oh!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Comfits will be as comfortable to your stomacke Ma∣dam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>I feare hee's spoild forever, he did name</L>
<L>Logicke, and may for ought I know be gone</L>
<L>So farre to understand it, I did alwayes</L>
<L>Suspect they would corrupt him in the Colledge,</L>
<L>Will your Greeke sawes and sentences discharge</L>
<L>The Mercer, or is Latin a fit language</L>
<L>To court a mistresse in? Mr. <HI>Alexander</HI></L>
<L>If you have any charitie, let me</L>
<L>Commend him to your breeding, I suspect</L>
<L>I must employ my Doctor first, to purge.</L>
<L>The Vniversitie that lies in's head</L>
<L>It alters his complexion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you dare</L>
<L>Trust me to serve him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mr. <HI>Littleworth</HI></L>
<L>Be you joynd in commission.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will teach him</L>
<L>Postures and rudiments.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have no patience</L>
<L>To see him in this shape, it turnes my stomacke,</L>
<L>When he has cast his Academicke skinne</L>
<L>He shall be yours, I am bound in conscience</L>
<L>To see him bred, his owne state shall maintaine</L>
<L>The charge, while hee's my Ward, come hither sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fr.</SPEAKER>
<L>What does my Aunt meane to doe with me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>St.</SPEAKER>
<L>To make you a fine gentleman, and translate you</L>
<L>Out of your learned language sir, into</L>
<L>The present Goth and Vandall, which is French.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Into what mischiefe will this humour ebbe?</L>
<L>Shee will undo the boy, I see him ruind,</L>
<L>My patience is not manly, but I must</L>
<L>Vse stratagem to reduce her, open wayes</L>
<L>Give me no hope.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>St.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall be obey'd Madam.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="13"/>
<SPEAKER>Fr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mr. <HI>Steward,</HI> are you sure we doe not dreame?</L>
<L>Was't not my Aunt you talkt to.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>St.</SPEAKER>
<L>One that loves you</L>
<L>Deare as her life, these cloathes doe not become you,</L>
<L>You must have better sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fr.</SPEAKER>
<L>These are not old.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>St.</SPEAKER>
<L>More sutable to the towne and time, we keepe</L>
<L>No Lent here, nor is't my Ladies pleasure you</L>
<L>Should fast from any thing you have a minde to,</L>
<L>Vnlesse it be your learning▪ which she would have you</L>
<L>Forget with all convenient speed that may be,</L>
<L>For the credit of your noble family,</L>
<L>The case is alter'd since we liv'd i'th country,</L>
<L>We doe not invite the poore o'th parish</L>
<L>To dinner, keepe a table for the tenants,</L>
<L>Our kitchen does not smell of beefe, the sellar</L>
<L>Defies the price of malt and hops, the footmen</L>
<L>And coachdrivers may be drunke like gentlemen</L>
<L>With wine, nor will three Fidlers upon holidayes</L>
<L>With aid of Bagge pipes, that cald in the countrey</L>
<L>To dance, and plough the hall up with their hobnailes,</L>
<L>Now make my Lady merry, wee doe feed</L>
<L>Like princes, and feast nothing but princes,</L>
<L>And are these robes fit to be seene amongst e'm.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fr.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lady keepes a court then, is Sir <HI>Thomas</HI></L>
<L>Affected with this state and cost.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>He was not,</L>
<L>But is converted, and I hope you wo'not</L>
<L>Persist in heresie, but take a course</L>
<L>Of riot to content your friends, you shall</L>
<L>Want nothing, if you can be proud and spend it</L>
<L>For my Ladies honour, here are a hundred</L>
<L>Peeces, will serve you till you have new clothes,</L>
<L>I will present you with a nag of mine</L>
<L>Poore tender of my service, please you accept,</L>
<L>My Ladies smile more than rewards me for it,</L>
<L>I must provide fit servants to attend you,</L>
<L>Monsieures for horse and foote.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fr.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall submit</L>
<L>If this be my Aunts pleasure and be rul'd</L>
<L>My eyes are open'd with this purse already,</L>
<L>And Sacke will helpe to inspire me, I must spend it,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="13"/>
<SPEAKER>St,</SPEAKER>
<L>What else sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile begin with you, to incourage</L>
<L>You, to have still a speciall care of me,</L>
<L>There is five peeces, not for your nag.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>St.</SPEAKER>
<L>No sir, I hope it is not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Buy a Beaver</L>
<L>For thy owne blocke, I shall be ruld, who does</L>
<L>Command the wineseller?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>St.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who command but you sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile try to drinke a health or two, my Aunts</L>
<L>Or any bodies, and if that foundation</L>
<L>Stagger me not too much, I will commence</L>
<L>In all the arts of London.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>St.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you finde sir</L>
<L>The operation of the wine, exalt</L>
<L>Your bloud to the desire of any femall</L>
<L>Delight, I know your Aunt wonot deny</L>
<L>Any of her chambermaides to practise on,</L>
<L>She loves you but too well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fr.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know not how</L>
<L>I may be for that exercise, farewell <HI>Aristotle,</HI></L>
<L>Prethee commend me to the Library</L>
<L>At Westminster, my bones I bequeath thither,</L>
<L>And to the learned wormes that meane to visit 'em,</L>
<L>I will compose my selfe, I beginne to thinke</L>
<L>I have lost time indeed, come to the wineseller.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Celestina, Mardana, Isabella,</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>But shall we not Madam expose our selves</L>
<L>To censure for this freedome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let them answer</L>
<L>That dare mistake us, shall we be so much</L>
<L>Cowards to be frighted from our pleasure,</L>
<L>Because men have malitious tongues, and shew</L>
<L>What miserable soules they have, no cozen,</L>
<L>We hold our life and fortunes, upon no</L>
<L>Mans charitie, if they dare shew so little</L>
<L>Discretion to traduce our fames, we will</L>
<L>Be guilty of so much wit to laugh at em.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Is.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis a becomming fortitude.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>My starres</L>
<L>Are yet kinde to me, for in a happy minute</L>
<L>Be't spoke, I'me not in love, and men shall never.</L>
<L>Make my heart leane with sighing, nor with teares</L>
<L>Draw on my eyes the infamie of spectacles,</L>
<L>Tis the chiefe principle to keepe your heart</L>
<L><PB REF="14"/>Vnder your owne obedience, jeast, but love not,</L>
<L>I say my prayers yet, can weare good clothes,</L>
<L>And onely satisfie my tailor for em.</L>
<L>I wonot lose my priviledge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>And yet they say your entertainments are,</L>
<L>Give me your pardon Madam▪ to proclaime</L>
<L>Your selfe a widow, and to get a husband.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>As if a Lady of my yeares, some beautie</L>
<L>Left by her husband rich, that had mourn'd for him</L>
<L>A twelve moneth too, could live so obscure i'th towne</L>
<L>That gallants would not know her, and invite</L>
<L>Themselves without her chargeable proclamations,</L>
<L>Then we are worse than Citizens, no widow</L>
<L>Left wealthy can be throughly warme in mourning,</L>
<L>But some one noble bloud or lusty kindred</L>
<L>Claps in, with his gilt coach, and Flandrian trotters,</L>
<L>And hurries <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> away to be a Countesse.</L>
<L>Courtiers have <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ies, and great ones with lharge titles,</L>
<L>Cold in their <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ne estates, would warme themselves</L>
<L>At a rich city <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>nefire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Is.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most true Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>No matter for corruption of the bloud,</L>
<L>Some undone Courtier made her husband rich,</L>
<L>And this new Lord receives it backe againe.</L>
<L>Admit it were my policie, and that</L>
<L>My entertainements pointed to acquaint me</L>
<L>With many sutors, that I might be safe,</L>
<L>And make the best election, could you blame me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam tis wisdome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>But I should be</L>
<L>In my thoughts miserable to be fond</L>
<L>Of leaving the sweet freedome I possesse,</L>
<L>And court my selfe into new marriage fetters,</L>
<L>I now observe mens severall wits, and windings,</L>
<L>And can laugh at their follies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have given</L>
<L>A most ingenious satisfaction.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>One thing ile tell you more, and this I give you</L>
<L>Worthy your imitation from my practise,</L>
<L>You see me merry, full of song and dancing,</L>
<L><PB REF="14"/>Pleasant in language, apt to all delights</L>
<L>That crowne a publike meeting, but you cannot</L>
<L>Accuse me of being prodigall of my favours</L>
<L>To any of my guests, I doe not summon</L>
<L>By any winke, a gentleman to follow me,</L>
<L>To my withdrawing chamber, I heare all</L>
<L>Their pleaes in Court, nor can they boast abroad</L>
<L>And doe me justice, after a salute</L>
<L>They have much conversation with my lippe,</L>
<L>I hold the kissing of my hand a courtesie,</L>
<L>And he that loves me, must upon the strength</L>
<L>Of that, expect till I renew his favour.</L>
<L>Some Ladies are so expensive in their graces,</L>
<L>To those that honour 'em, and so prodigall</L>
<L>That in a little time, they have nothing but</L>
<L>The naked sinne left to reward their servants,</L>
<L>Whereas a thrift in our rewards, will keepe</L>
<L>Men long in their devotion, and preserve</L>
<L>Our selves in stocke, to encourage those that honour us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Is.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is an art worthy a Ladies practise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>It takes not from the freedome of our mirth,</L>
<L>But seemes to advance it, when we can possesse</L>
<L>Our pleasures with security of our honour,</L>
<L>And that preservd, I welcome all the joyes</L>
<L>My fancy can let in. In this I have given</L>
<L>The copie of my minde, nor doe I blush,</L>
<L>You understand it.
<STAGE>Enter Celestinaes gentlewoman.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Is.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have honord us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, Sir <HI>William Sentlove</HI>'s come to waite on you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>There's one would be a client, make excuse</L>
<L>For a few minuts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>One that comes a woing?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Such a thing he would seeme, but in his guiltinesse</L>
<L>Of little land, his expectation is not</L>
<L>So valiant as it might be, he weares cloathes,</L>
<L>And feeds with noblemen, to some I heare</L>
<L>No better than a wanton emissarie,</L>
<L>Or scout for <HI>Venus</HI> wild foule, which made tame,</L>
<L>He thinkes no shame to stand court centinell,</L>
<L><PB REF="15"/>In hope of the reversion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have heard</L>
<L>That some of them are often my Lords tasters,</L>
<L>The first fruits they condition for, and will</L>
<L>Exact as fees for the promotion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let them agree, there's no account shall lie</L>
<L>For me among their trafficke.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Gentlewo.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mr. <HI>Hairecut</HI> Madam</L>
<L>Is new come in, to tender you his service.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let him discourse a little with sir <HI>William.</HI>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>What is this gentleman Mr. <HI>Hairecut</HI> Madam?</L>
<L>I note him very gallant, and much courted</L>
<L>By gentlemen of qualitie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know not</L>
<L>More than a trim gay man, he has some great office</L>
<L>Sure by his confident behaviour,</L>
<L>He would be entertaind under the title</L>
<L>Of servant to me, and I must confesse,</L>
<L>He is the sweetest of all men that visite me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Is.</SPEAKER>
<L>How meane you Madam?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>He is full of powder,</L>
<L>He will save much in perfume for my chamber,</L>
<L>Were he but constant here; give e'm accesse.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Sir Will. Sentlove, Mr. Hairecut.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sent.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam the humblest of your servants is</L>
<L>Exalted to a happinesse, if you smile</L>
<L>Vpon my visit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must begge your charitie</L>
<L>Vpon my rudenesse Madam, I shall give</L>
<L>That day up lost to any happinesse,</L>
<L>When I forget to tender you my service.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>You practise Courtship gentlemen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sent.</SPEAKER>
<L>But cannot</L>
<L>Find where with more desert to exercise it,</L>
<L>What Ladie's this I pray?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>A kinswoman</L>
<L>Of mine sir <HI>William.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sent.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am more her servant,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>You came from Court, now I presume.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis Ma∣dam</L>
<L>The sphere I move in, and my destinie</L>
<L>Was kinde to place me there, where J enjoy</L>
<L>All blessings that a mortall can possesse,</L>
<L><PB REF="15"/>That lives not in your presence, and J should</L>
<L>Fixe my ambition, when you would vouchsafe</L>
<L>Me so much honour, to accept from me</L>
<L>An humble entertainment there.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>But by</L>
<L>What name shall I be knowne, in what degree</L>
<L>Shall J be of kinred to you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hair.</SPEAKER>
<L>How meane you Madam?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Perhaps you'le call me sister, I shall take it</L>
<L>A speciall preferment, or it may be</L>
<L>J may passe under title of your Mistresse,</L>
<L>If I seeme rich, and faire enough, to engage</L>
<L>Your confidence to owne me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>J would hope.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>But tis not come to that yet, you will sir</L>
<L>Excuse my mirth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweet Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall J take</L>
<L>Boldnesse to aske what place you hold in Court?</L>
<L>Tis an uncivill curiositie,</L>
<L>But you'le have mercie to a womans question.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>My present condition Madam, carries</L>
<L>Honour and profit, though not to be nam'd</L>
<L>With that employment J expect ith state</L>
<L>Which shall discharge the first maturitie</L>
<L>Vpon your knowledge, untill then I begge</L>
<L>You allow a modest silence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am charmd sir,</L>
<L>And if you scape embassador, you cannot</L>
<L>Reach a preferment, wherein I'me against you,</L>
<L>But where's sir <HI>William Sentlove</HI>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Give him leave</L>
<L>To follow his nose Madam, while he hunts</L>
<L>In view, hee'le soone be at a fault.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>You know him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Know <HI>Sentlove</HI>? not a page but can decipher him,</L>
<L>The waiting women know him to a scruple,</L>
<L>Hee's cal'd the Blistermaker of the towne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whats that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Is.</SPEAKER>
<L>The laundry Ladies can resolve you,</L>
<L>And you may guesse, an arrant Epicure</L>
<L>As this day lives, borne to a prettie wit,</L>
<L>A Knight but no gentleman, J must</L>
<L>Be plaine to you, your Ladiship may have</L>
<L><PB REF="16"/>Vse of this knowledge, but conceale the author.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sen.</SPEAKER>
<L>J kisse your fairest hand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>You make a difference,</L>
<L>Pray reconcile e'm to an equall whitenesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sent.</SPEAKER>
<L>You wound my meaning Lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay sir <HI>William</HI></L>
<L>Has the art of complement.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sent.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, you honor me</L>
<L>'Bove my desert of language.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you please</L>
<L>To enrich me with your knowledge of that gentleman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sent.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe you not know him Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>What is he?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sen.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Camphire ball, you shall know more hereafter</L>
<L>He shall tell you himselfe, and save my character,</L>
<L>Till then, you see hee's proud.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>One thing gentlemen</L>
<L>I observe in your behaviour, which is rare</L>
<L>In two that court one mistresse, you preserve</L>
<L>A noble friendship, theres no gum within</L>
<L>Your hearts, you cannot fret, or shew an envy</L>
<L>Of one anothers hope, some would not governe</L>
<L>Their passions with that temper.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sent.</SPEAKER>
<L>The whole world</L>
<L>Shanot divorce our friendship. Mr <HI>Hairecut</HI></L>
<L>Would I had lives to serve him, he is lost</L>
<L>To goodnesse does not honour him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>My knight I</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is right playing at Court Shuttlecocke.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Gentlew.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, there is a gentleman desires</L>
<L>To speake w'ee, one sir <HI>Thomas Bornwell.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bornewell?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<L>He sayes he is a stranger to your Ladiship.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sen.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Haire▪</SPEAKER>
<L>Your neighbour Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Husband to the Lady, that so revells in the strand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>He has good parts they say, but cannot helpe</L>
<L>His Ladies bias.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>They have both much fame</L>
<L>'Ith towne for severall merits, pray admit him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>What comes he for?
<STAGE>Enter sir Thomas▪</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your pardon noble Lady, that I have</L>
<L>Presum'd a stranger to your knowledge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir,</L>
<L>Your worth was here before you, and your person</L>
<L>Cannot be here ingratefull.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis the bounty</L>
<L>Of your sweet disposition Madam, make me</L>
<L><PB REF="16"/>Your servant Lady by her faire example,</L>
<L>To favour me — I never knew one turne</L>
<L>Her cheeke to a gentleman that came to kisse her</L>
<L>But sha'd a stinking breath; your servant gentlemen,</L>
<L><HI>Will Sent love</HI> how ist?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am sorry Coze</L>
<L>To accuse you, we in nothing more betray</L>
<L>Our selves to censure of ridiculous pride,</L>
<L>Then answering a faire salute too rudely,</L>
<L>Oh it shewes ill upon a gentlewoman</L>
<L>Not to returne the modest lip, if she</L>
<L>Would have the world beleeve, her breath is not</L>
<L>Offensive.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, I have businesse</L>
<L>With you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sent.</SPEAKER>
<L>His lookes are pleasant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>With me sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>I heare you have an ex'lent wit Madam,</L>
<L>I see your faire</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>The first is but report,</L>
<L>And doe not trust your eyesight for the last,</L>
<L>Cause I presume y'are mortall and may erre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>He is very gamesome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'ave an ex'lent voyce;</L>
<L>They say you catch it from a dying Swan,</L>
<L>Which joyn'd to the sweete harmony of your lute,</L>
<L>You ravish all mankind.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ravish mankind?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>With their consent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>It were the stranger rape,</L>
<L>But there's the lesse inditement lies against it,</L>
<L>And there is hope; your little honesties</L>
<L>Cannot be much the worse, for men doe rather</L>
<L>Beleeve they had a maiden head, then put</L>
<L>Themselves to'th racke of memory, how long</L>
<L>Tis since they left the burden of their innocence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why you are bitter Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>So is physicke,</L>
<L>I doe not know your constitution.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall if please you Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'are too hasty,</L>
<L>I must examine what certificate</L>
<L>You have, first to preferre you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fine! certificate?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vnder your Ladies hand, and seale.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Go to,</L>
<L>I see you are a wag.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>But take heede, how</L>
<L>You trust too't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>I can love you in my wedlocke,</L>
<L>As well as that young gallant, oth first haire,</L>
<L>Or the knight Bachelor, and can returne</L>
<L><PB REF="17"/>As amorous delight to thy soft bosome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your person and your language are both strangers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>But may be more familiar, I have those</L>
<L>That dare make affidavit for my body.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>D'ee meane your Surgeon?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Surgeon Madam▪</L>
<L>I know not how you value my abilities,</L>
<L>But I dare undertake, as much, to expresse</L>
<L>My service to your Ladiship, and with</L>
<L>As fierce ambition, fly to your commands,</L>
<L>As the most valiant of these, 'lay siege to you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>You dare not sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>How Madam?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will in∣stifi't.</L>
<L>You dare not marry me, and I imagine</L>
<L>Some here should I consent, would fetch a priest</L>
<L>Out of the fire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have a wife indeede,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>And there's a statute not repeald I take it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yare in the right I must confesse y'ave hit,</L>
<L>And bled me in a master veine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>You thinke</L>
<L>I tooke you on the advantage, use your best</L>
<L>Skill at defence, Ile come up to your valour</L>
<L>And shew another worke you dare not doe,</L>
<L>You dare not sir be vertuous.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>I dare,</L>
<L>By this faire hand, I dare, and aske a pardon</L>
<L>If my rude words offend thy innocence,</L>
<L>Which in a forme so beautifull, would shine</L>
<L>To force a blush in them suspected it,</L>
<L>And from the rest draw wonder.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>I like not</L>
<L>Their secret parly, shall I interrupt em?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Is.</SPEAKER>
<L>By no meanes sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sent.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir <HI>Thomas</HI> was not wont</L>
<L>To shew so much a Courtier.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>He cannot</L>
<L>Be prejudiciall to you, suspect not</L>
<L>Your owne deserts so much, hee's married.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have other businesse Madam, you keepe musicke,</L>
<L>I came to try how you can dance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>You did? Ile trie his humour out of breath▪</L>
<L>Although boast no cunning sir in revells,</L>
<L>If you desire to shew your art that way,</L>
<L>I can waite on you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>You much honour me,</L>
<L>Nay all must joyne to make a harmony.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="17"/><HI>They dance.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have nothing now, Madam, but to beseech</L>
<L>After a pardon for my boldnesse, you</L>
<L>Would give occasion to pay my gratitude,</L>
<L>I have a house will be much honourd</L>
<L>If you vouchsafe your presence, and a wife</L>
<L>Desires to present her selfe your servant,</L>
<L>I Came with the ambition to invite you,</L>
<L>Deny me not, your person you shall trust</L>
<L>On faire securitie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, although I use not</L>
<L>This freedome with a stranger, you shall have</L>
<L>No cause to hold me obstinate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>You grace me</L>
<L>Sir <HI>William Sentlove</HI>—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must take my leave,</L>
<L>You will excuse me Madam, Court attendances —</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>By any meanes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ladies you will vouchsafe</L>
<L>Your company.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Is.</HI> M.</SPEAKER>
<L>We waite upon you sir.
<STAGE>Exunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>The third Act.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Lord unready. Hairecut preparing his Periwigge, Table, and Lookingglasse.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>What houre ist?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bout three'a clocke my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis time to rise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Lordship went but late</L>
<L>To bed last night.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Twas early in the morning.
<STAGE>Enter Secre.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>Expect a while, my Lord is busie?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whats the matter?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here is a Lady</L>
<L>Desires accesse to you upon some affaires</L>
<L>She saies may specially concerne your Lordship.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Lady? What her name?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam <HI>Decoy.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Decoy</HI>? prethee admit her.
<STAGE>Enter Decoy.</STAGE></L>
<L>Have you businesse Madam</L>
<L>With me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decoy.</SPEAKER>
<L>And such I hope as will not be</L>
<L>Offensive to your Lordship.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>I pray speake it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would desire your Lordships eare more private.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Waite i'th next chāber till I call, now Madam.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Although I am a stranger to your Lordship</L>
<L>I wo'd not lose a faire occasion offer'd.</L>
<L>To shew how much I honour, and would serve you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Please you to give me the particular</L>
<L><PB REF="18"/>That I may know the extent of my engagement,</L>
<L>I am ignorant by what desert you should</L>
<L>Be encouragd to have care of me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord,</L>
<L>I will take boldnesse to be plaine, beside</L>
<L>Your other excellent parts, you have much fame</L>
<L>For your sweet inclination to our sexe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>How dee meane Madam?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dec.</SPEAKER>
<L>I that way your Lordship</L>
<L>Hath honorably practisd upon some</L>
<L>Not to be nam'd, your noble constancie</L>
<L>To a mistresse hath deserv'd our generall vote,</L>
<L>And I a part of woman kind have thought</L>
<L>How to expresse my duty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>In what Madam?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dec.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be not so strange my Lord, I know the beauty</L>
<L>And pleasures of your eyes, that hansome creature</L>
<L>With whose faire life all your delight tooke leave,</L>
<L>And to whose memory you have paid too much▪</L>
<L>Sad tribute.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whats all this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dec.</SPEAKER>
<L>This, if your Lord∣ship</L>
<L>Accept my service, in pure zeale to cure</L>
<L>Your melancholy, I could point where you might</L>
<L>Repaire your losse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Ladiship I conceive</L>
<L>Doth trafficke in flesh marchandize.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>To men.</L>
<L>Of honour like your selfe, I am well knowne</L>
<L>To some in court and come not with ambition</L>
<L>Now to supplant your officer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>What is</L>
<L>The Lady of pleasure you preferre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Lady</L>
<L>Of birth and fortune, one upon whose vertue</L>
<L>I may presume, the Lady <HI>Aretina</HI>▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wife to sir <HI>Thomas Bornwell</HI>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dec.</SPEAKER>
<L>The same sir▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Have you prepard her?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></SPEAKER>
<L>Not for your Lordship, till I have found your pulse,</L>
<L>I am acquainted with her disposition</L>
<L>She has a very appliable nature.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>And Madam when expect you to be whipt</L>
<L>For doing these fine favors.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>How my Lord?</L>
<L>Your Lordship does but jeast I hope; you make</L>
<L>A difference betweene a Lady that</L>
<L>Does honorable offices, and one</L>
<L>They call a bawd, your Lordship was not wont</L>
<L><PB REF="18"/>To have such course opinion of our practise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Lady <HI>Aretina</HI> is my kinswoman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>What if she be my Lord? the nearer bloud</L>
<L>The dearer sympathie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile have thee carted.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Lordship wonot so much staine your honour</L>
<L>And education, to use a woman</L>
<L>Of my qualitie.—<HI>Lord.</HI>— Tis possible you may</L>
<L>Be sent off with an honorable convoy</L>
<L>Of Halberdeers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh my good Lord!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Ladiship shall be no protection</L>
<L>If thou but stai'st three minutes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am gone,</L>
<L>When next you finde rebellion in your bloud,</L>
<L>May all within ten mile o'th court turne honest.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe not finde that pronenesse since the faire</L>
<L><HI>Bella Maria</HI> died, my bloud is cold,</L>
<L>Nor is there beautie enough surviving</L>
<L>To highten me to wantonnesse, who waites?</L>
<L>And what said my Lady?
<STAGE>Enter Hairecut.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>The silent language of her face my Lord</L>
<L>Was not so pleasant, as it shewd upon</L>
<L>Her entrance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would any man that meetes</L>
<L>This Lady take her for a bawde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>She does</L>
<L>The trade an honor, credit to the profession,</L>
<L>We may in time see baldnesse, quarter noses,</L>
<L>And rotten legges to take the wall of footclothes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>I ha thought better, call the Lady backe,</L>
<L>I wonot lose this opportunitie,</L>
<L>Bid her not feare, the favour is not common,</L>
<L>And ile reward it. I doe wonder much</L>
<L><HI>Will Sentlove</HI> was not here to day.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>I heard him say this morning, he would waite</L>
<L>Vpon your Lordship.</L>
<L>She is returnd sir.
<STAGE>Enter Secre. and Decoy.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam be confident my Lords not angry.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>You returne welcome Madam, you are better</L>
<L>Read in your art I hope then to be frighted</L>
<L>With any shape of anger, when you bring</L>
<L>Such newes to gentlemen, Madam you shall</L>
<L><PB REF="19"/>Soone understand how I accept the office.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are the first Lord, since J studied carriage,</L>
<L>That shew'd such infidelity and fury</L>
<L>Vpon so kind a message, every gentleman</L>
<L>Will shew some breeding, but if one right honourable</L>
<L>Should not have noble bloud.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall returne</L>
<L>My complement in a letter to my Lady</L>
<L><HI>Aretina,</HI> favour me with a little patience,</L>
<L>Shew her that chamber.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile attend your Lordship.
<STAGE>Ex.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Write. Madam where your honour is in danger,</L>
<L>My love must not be silent.
<STAGE>Enter Sentlove and Kickshaw.</STAGE></L>
<L><HI>Sentlove</HI> and <HI>Kickshaw!</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kic.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Lordship's busie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Writing a letter, nay it shanot barre</L>
<L>Any discourse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>—Silent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Though I be no Physitian, I may prevent a feaver in your bloud.</L>
<L>And where have you spent the mornings conversation?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sent.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where you would have given the best Barbary</L>
<L>In your stable to have met on honorable termes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>What new beautie? You acquaint your selves</L>
<L>With none but wonders.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sent.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis too low a miracle▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Twill require a strong faith.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Secr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your bloud.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you be innocent preserve your fame least this <HI>Decoy</HI></L>
<L>Madam betray it to your repentance.</L>
<L>By what name is she knowne?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sent.</SPEAKER>
<L>Aske <HI>Alexander,</HI> he knowes her?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whom?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sent.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Lady <HI>Celestina.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>He has a vast knowledge of Ladies, las poore <HI>Alexander</HI>!</L>
<L>When dost thou meane thy body shall lie fallow?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al</SPEAKER>
<L>When there is mercy in a petticote,</L>
<L>I must turne pilgrime for some breath.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thinke</L>
<L>Twere cooler travell if you examine it</L>
<L>Vpon the hoofe through Spaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sent.</SPEAKER>
<L>Through <HI>Ethiopia</HI>▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay lesse laborious to serve a prentiship</L>
<L>In Peru, and dig gold out of the mine,</L>
<L>Though all the yeare were dogdayes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>To repentance,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>In briefe, this Lady, could you fall from vertue,</L>
<L>Within my knowledge will not blush to be a Bawde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="19"/>
<SPEAKER>Sent.</SPEAKER>
<L>But hang't tis honorable journey worke,</L>
<L>Thou art famous by't, and thy name's up.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>So sir▪</L>
<L>Let me aske you a question my deare knight,</L>
<L>Which is lesse servile to bring up the Pheasant,</L>
<L>And waite, or sit at table uncontrould</L>
<L>And carve to my owne appetite?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sent.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more,</L>
<L>Th'art witty, as I am—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>A bawd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sent.</SPEAKER>
<L>How's that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh you are famous by't, and your names up sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be wise, and reward my caution, with</L>
<L>Timely care of your selfe, so I shall not repent</L>
<L>To be knowne your lovings kinsman and servant.</L>
<L>Gentlemen, the Lady <HI>Celestina.</HI></L>
<L>Is she so rare a thing?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you'le have my</L>
<L>Opinion my Lord, I never saw</L>
<L>So sweete, so faire, so rich a peece of nature.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile shew thee a fairer presently, to shame</L>
<L>Thy eyes and judgement, looke o'that. — So Ile subscribe</L>
<L>Seale it, ile excuse your pen for the direction.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Bella Marias</HI> picture; she was hansome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sent.</SPEAKER>
<L>But not to be compar'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your patience gentlemen ile returne instantly.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whither is my Lord gone?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>To a Lady i'th next Chamber.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sen.</SPEAKER>
<L>What is she?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall pardon me, I am his Secretary.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sen.</SPEAKER>
<L>I was wont to be of his counsell, a new officer</L>
<L>And I'not know't? I am resolvd to 'batter</L>
<L>All other with the praise of <HI>Celestina</HI></L>
<L>I must retaine him.
<STAGE>Enter Lord.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Has not that object</L>
<L>Convinc't your erring judgements.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>What this picture?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Were but your thoughts as capable as mine</L>
<L>Of her Idea, you would wish no thought</L>
<L>That were not active in her praise, above</L>
<L>All worth and memory of her sexe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sent.</SPEAKER>
<L>She was faire</L>
<L>I must confesse, but had your Lordship look'd</L>
<L>With eyes more narrow and some lesse affection</L>
<L>Vpon her face.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe not love the copies</L>
<L><PB REF="20"/>Of any dead, they make me dreame of goblins,</L>
<L>Give me a living mistresse, with but halfe</L>
<L>The beauty of <HI>Celestina,</HI> come my Lord,</L>
<L>Tis pitty that a Lord of so much flesh</L>
<L>Should waste upon a ghost, when they are living</L>
<L>Can give you a more honourable consumption.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why doe you meane my Lord to live an Infidell?</L>
<L>Doe, and see what will come ont, observe still</L>
<L>And dote upon your vigills, build a chamber</L>
<L>Within a rocke, a tombe, among the wormes,</L>
<L>Not farre off, where you may in proofe apocryphall</L>
<L>Court em not devoure the pretty pile.</L>
<L>Of flesh your mistresse carried to the grave,</L>
<L>There are no women in the world, all eyes</L>
<L>And tongue and lippes are buried in her coffin.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why doe you thinke your selves competent Judges.</L>
<L>Of beauty gentlemen?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Both.</SPEAKER>
<L>What should hinder us?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have seene and tried as many as another</L>
<L>With a mortall bac<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lord▪</SPEAKER>
<L>Your eyes are bribd,</L>
<L>And your hearts chain'd to some desires, you cannot</L>
<L>Enjoy the freedome of a sence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Lordship</L>
<L>Has a cleare eyesight, and can judge and penetrate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>I can, and give a perfect censure of</L>
<L>Each line and point, distinguish beautie from</L>
<L>A thousand formes, which your corrupted optiks</L>
<L>Would passe for naturall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sent.</SPEAKER>
<L>I desire no other</L>
<L>Judge should determine us, and if your Lordship</L>
<L>Dare venture but your eyes upon this Lady,</L>
<L>Ile stand their justice, and be confident</L>
<L>You shall give <HI>Celestin<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> victorie,</L>
<L>And triumph ors all beauties past and living.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>J date my Lord venture a sute of clothes,</L>
<L>You will be orecome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>You doe not know my fortitude</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sent.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor frailtie, you dare not trust you selfe to see her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thinke you so gentlemen, I dare see this creature</L>
<L>To make you know your errors▪ and the difference</L>
<L>Of her, whose memory is my Saint, not trust</L>
<L>My sences? J dare see and speake with her,</L>
<L><PB REF="20"/>Which holds the best acquaintance to prepare</L>
<L>My visit to her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sent.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will doo't my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee is a Lady free in entertainements.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would give this advantage to your cause,</L>
<L>Bid him appeare in all the ornaments</L>
<L>Did ever waite on beautie, all the riches</L>
<L>Pride can put on, and teach her face more charme</L>
<L>Then ever Poet drest up <HI>Venus</HI> in,</L>
<L>Bid her be all the graces, and the queene</L>
<L>Of love in one, Ile see her <HI>Sentlove,</HI> and</L>
<L>Bring off my heart arm'd, but single thought</L>
<L>Of one that is dead, without a wound, and when</L>
<L>I have made your follie prisoner, ile laugh at you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sent.</SPEAKER>
<L>She shall expect you, trust to me for knowledge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'me for the present somewhere else engagd,</L>
<L>Let me heare from you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sent.</SPEAKER>
<L>So I am glad hee's yet</L>
<L>So neere conversion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am for <HI>Aretina.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sent.</SPEAKER>
<L>No mention of my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prepare his Lady,</L>
<L>Tis time he were reduc'd to the old sport,</L>
<L>One Lord like him more would undoe the court.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Aretina with a letter. Decoy.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>He is the ornament of your bloud Madam,</L>
<L>I am much bound to his Lordship.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>He gives you</L>
<L>A noble character.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis his goodnesse Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>I wanted such an engine, my Lord has</L>
<L>Done me a curtesie to disclose her nature,</L>
<L>I now know one to trust, and will employ her.</L>
<L>Touching my Lord, for reasons, which I shall</L>
<L>Offer to your Ladiship hereafter, I</L>
<L>Desire you would be silent, but to shew</L>
<L>How much I dare be confident in your secrecie,</L>
<L>I powre my bosome forth, I love a gentleman</L>
<L>On whom there woo'not meet much conjuration</L>
<L>To meet—your eare▪ —</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>I apprehend you, and I shall</L>
<L>Be happy to be serviceable, I am sorry</L>
<L>Your Ladiship did not know me before now,</L>
<L><PB REF="21"/>I have done offices, and not a few</L>
<L>Of the nobilitie, but have done feates</L>
<L>Within my house, which is so convenient</L>
<L>For situation, and artfull chambers,</L>
<L>Such pretty pictures to provoke the fancie.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Littleworth.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam all pleasures languish in your absence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your pardon a few minutes sir—you must</L>
<L>Contrive it thus.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>I attend, and shall account it</L>
<L>Honour to waite on your returne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>He may not</L>
<L>Have the least knowledge of my name, or person.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have practisd that already for some great ones,</L>
<L>And dare agen to satisfie you Madam;</L>
<L>I have a thousand wayes to doe sweet offices.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>If this Lady <HI>Aretina</HI> should be honest,</L>
<L>I ha lost time, shee's free as aire, J must</L>
<L>Have closer conference, and if I have art,</L>
<L>Make her affect me in revenge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>This evening</L>
<L>Leave me to manage things.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>You will oblige me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall commend my art, and thanke me after.
<STAGE>Ex.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hope the revells are maintained within.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>By sir <HI>Thomas</HI> and his Mistris.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>How? his Mistris.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Lady <HI>Celestina,</HI> I nere saw</L>
<L>Eyes shoote more amorous enterchange.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ist so?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>He weares her favor with meere pride.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Her favor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>A feather that he ravish'd from her fan.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>And is so full of courtship, which she smiles on.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>And praises her beyond all poetry.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'me glad he has so much wit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not jealous!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>This secures me, what would make other Ladies pale</L>
<L>With jealousie, gives but a licence to my wandrings,</L>
<L>Let him now taxe me if he dare—and yet</L>
<L>Her beauti's worth my envie, and I wish</L>
<L>Revenge upon it, not because he loves,</L>
<L>But that it shines above my owne.
<STAGE>Enter Alex.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Deare Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have it, you two gentlemen professe</L>
<L>Much service to me, if I have a way</L>
<L><PB REF="21"/>To employ your wit and secrecie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Both.</SPEAKER>
<L>You'le honour us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>You gave a high and worthy character</L>
<L>Of <HI>Celestina.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>I remember Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe either of you love her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor I Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>I wod not if I might.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee's now my guest,</L>
<L>And by a tricke invited by my husband</L>
<L>To disgrace me, you gentlemen are held</L>
<L>Wits of the towne, the Consulls that doe governe</L>
<L>The Senate here, whose jeeres are all authenticke,</L>
<L>The Tavernes and the Ordinaries are</L>
<L>Made academies where you come, and all</L>
<L>Your sinnes and surfets made times example,</L>
<L>Your very nods can quell a Theater,</L>
<L>No speech or Poem good without your seale,</L>
<L>You can protect scurrility, and publish</L>
<L>By your authority beleev'd, no rapture</L>
<L>Ought to have honest meaning.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Leave our characters.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>And name the emploiment.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>You must exercise</L>
<L>The strength of both your wits upon this Lady,</L>
<L>And talke her into humblenesse or anger</L>
<L>Both which are equall to my thought, if you</L>
<L>Dare undertake this slight thing for my sake,</L>
<L>My favour shall reward it, but be faithfull,</L>
<L>And seeme to let all spring from your owne freedome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ale.</SPEAKER>
<L>This all? We can defame her, if you please</L>
<L>My friend shall call her whore or any thing,</L>
<L>And never be endangerd to a duell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>How's that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>He can endure a cudgelling, and no man</L>
<L>Will fight after so faire a satisfaction,</L>
<L>But leave us to our Art, and doe not limit us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are here, begin not till I whisper you.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter sir Thomas, Celestina, Marcana, Isabella.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ie vous prie Madam d' excuser l'importunitè de mes affaires</L>
<L>Qui m' ont fait offenser, par mon, absence, une dame de laquelle</L>
<L>I'ay receu tant d' obligation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pardonnez moy Madame; vous me faictez trop a honneur.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>C'est bien de la douceur de vostre naturel que vous tenez</L>
<L>Ceste language; mais j'espere que mon mary na pas</L>
<L><PB REF="22"/>Manquè de vous entretenir en mon absence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ce.</SPEAKER>
<L>En verite Monsieur nous a fort obligè</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Il eut trop failly, s'il n'eust taschè de tout fon pouvoir à vous rendre toutes sortes de services.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cest de sa bonté qu'il nous a tant favorisé.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>De la vostre plustost Madame que vous fait donner</L>
<L>D'interpretation si benigne à ses efforts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Ie voy bien que la victoire fera toutsjours à Madame, &amp; de language, &amp; de la courtesie.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vrayement Madame, que jamais personne a plus desire,</L>
<L>L'honneur de vostre compagnie, que moy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Laissons en<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>je vous supplis, des compliments &amp; permiettoz à vostre servante de vous baiser les mains.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vous m'obligez trop.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have no more patience, lets be merry agen</L>
<L>In our owne language, Madam our mirth cooles,</L>
<L>Our Nephew!
<STAGE>Enter Fredericke.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>Passion of my braine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fre.</SPEAKER>
<L>Save you gentlemen, save you Ladies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am un∣done.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fre.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must salute, no matter at which end I begin.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>There's a complement.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is this your nephew Madam?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ie vous prie Madame d▪ execuser les habitz, &amp; le rude</L>
<L>Comportement de mon cousin. Il est tout fraischement</L>
<L>Venu de l universitiè, ou on l'a tout gastè.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel</SPEAKER>
<L>Excusez moy Madam, il est bien accomply.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fre.</SPEAKER>
<L>This language should be French, by the motions</L>
<L>Of your heads, and the mirth of your faces.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am disho∣nor'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fre.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis one of the finest tongues for Ladies to shew their</L>
<L>Teeth in, If you'le Latine I am for you, or Greeke it,</L>
<L>My tailor has not put me into French yet,</L>
<L>Mille basia, basia mille.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ie ne vous entende pas monsieur,</L>
<L>I understand you not sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fre.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why so?</L>
<L>You and I then shall be in charity,</L>
<L>For though we should be abusive, we ha the benefit</L>
<L>Not to understand one another: where's my Aunt?</L>
<L>I did heare musicke somewhere, and my braines</L>
<L><PB REF="22"/>Tun'd with a bottle of your capering claret</L>
<L>Made haste to shew their dancing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Please you Madam,</L>
<L>They are very comfortable.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>St.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas Madam</L>
<L>How would you have me helpe it, I did use</L>
<L>All meanes I could, after he heard the musicke,</L>
<L>To make him drunke in hope so to containe him,</L>
<L>But the wine made him lighter, and his head</L>
<L>Flew hi'ther, ere I mist his heeles.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ale.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay he spoke Latine to the Lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh most unpardonable! get him off</L>
<L>Quickly, and discreetely, or if I live —</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>St.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis not in my power he sweares I am</L>
<L>An absurd sober fellow, and if you keepe</L>
<L>A servant in his house to crosse his humour,</L>
<L>When the rich sword and belt comes home, hee'le kill him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>What shall I doe? Try your skill, Master <HI>Littleworth.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>He has ne're a sword, sweet Mr. <HI>Fredericke</HI>▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis pitty Madam such a syen should</L>
<L>Be lost, but you are clouded.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not I sir,</L>
<L>I never found my selfe more cleare at heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I could play with a feather, your fan Lady,</L>
<L>Gentlemen, <HI>Aretina,</HI> ta ra ra ra, come Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fre.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why my good tutor in election?</L>
<L>You might have beene a scholler.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>But I thanke</L>
<L>My friends they brought me up a little better,</L>
<L>Give me the towne wits, that deliver jeasts</L>
<L>Cleane from the bow, that whistle in the aire,</L>
<L>And cleave the pin at twelvescore, Ladies doe</L>
<L>But laugh at a gentleman that has any learning.</L>
<L>Tis sinne enough to have your clothes suspected,</L>
<L>Leave us, and I will find a time to instruct you;</L>
<L>Come here are sugar plumbes, tis a good <HI>Fredericke.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fre.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why is not this my Aunts house in the strand?</L>
<L>The noble Rendevous? Who laughes at me?</L>
<L>Go, I will root here▪ if I list, and talke</L>
<L>Of Retoricke, Logicke, Latine, Greeke, or any thing,</L>
<L>And understand 'em too, who sayes the contrary?</L>
<L>Yet in a faire way I contemne all learning,</L>
<L><PB REF="23"/>And will be ignorant as he, or he,</L>
<L>Or any taffata, satten, scarlet, plush,</L>
<L>Tissue, or cloath, a bodkin gentleman,</L>
<L>Whose manners are most gloriously infected;</L>
<L>Did you laugh at me Lady?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not I sir?</L>
<L>But if I did shew mirth upon your question,</L>
<L>I hope you wod not beate me little gentleman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fr.</SPEAKER>
<L>How little gentleman? you dare not say</L>
<L>These words to my new cloathes, and fighting sword.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nephew <HI>Fredericke</HI>!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Little gentleman,</L>
<L>This an affront both to my bloud and person,</L>
<L>I am a gentleman of as tall a birth</L>
<L>As any least nobility, though my clothes</L>
<L>Smell o'the lampe, my coate is honourable,</L>
<L>Right honourable, full, of or, and argent,</L>
<L>A little gentleman!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Coze you must be patient,</L>
<L>My Lady meant you no dishonour, and</L>
<L>You must remember shee's a woman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fre.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is she a woman, thats another matter,</L>
<L>Dee heare, my uncle tells me what you are.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>So sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fr.</SPEAKER>
<L>You cald me little gentleman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>I did sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fre.</SPEAKER>
<L>A little pinke has made a lusty ship</L>
<L>Strike her topsaile, the Crow may beard the Elephant,</L>
<L>A whelpe may tame the Tiger, spight of all</L>
<L>False decks and murderers, and a little gentleman</L>
<L>Be hard enough to grapple with your Ladiship</L>
<L>Top and top gallant; will you goe drinke uncle?</L>
<L>Tother inchanted bottle, you and I</L>
<L>Will tiple, and talke phylosophy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come Nephew,</L>
<L>You will excuse a minutes absence Madam.</L>
<L>Waite you on us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>St.</SPEAKER>
<L>My duty sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now gentlemen.
<STAGE>Ex. all but Cel. &amp; Alex. &amp; Little.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam I had rather you accuse my language</L>
<L>For speaking truth, then vertue suffer in</L>
<L>My further silence, and it is my wonder</L>
<L>That you, whose noble carriage hath deserv'd</L>
<L>All honour, and opinion should now</L>
<L><PB REF="23"/>Be guilty of ill manners.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>What was that</L>
<L>You told me sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe you not blush Madam?</L>
<L>To aske that question.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>You amaze rather</L>
<L>My cheeke to palenesse, what you meane by this?</L>
<L>I am not troubled with the hickup gentlemen,</L>
<L>You should bestow this fright upon me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then</L>
<L>Pride and ill memory goe together.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>How sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>The gentleman on whom you exercise</L>
<L>Your thin wit, was a nephew to the Lady</L>
<L>Whose guest you are, and though her modesty</L>
<L>Looke calme on the abuse of one so neare</L>
<L>Her bloud, the affront was impious.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am asham'd on't,</L>
<L>You an ingenious Lady and well mannerd?</L>
<L>Ile reach a Beare as much civility.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>You may be master of the Colledge sir</L>
<L>For ought I know.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>What Colledge? Of the Beares.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Have you a plot upon me? Dee possesse</L>
<L>Your wits, or know me gentlemen.
<STAGE>Enter Bornewell.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>How's this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Know you? yes we doe know you to an atome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Li.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam we know, what stuffe your soule is made on.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>But doe not barke so like a mastive, pray,</L>
<L>Sure they are mad, let your braines stand awhile</L>
<L>And settle gentlemen, you know not me,</L>
<L>What am I?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tha'rt a puppet, a thing made</L>
<L>Of clothes and painting, and not halfe so hansome</L>
<L>As that which plaid <HI>Susanna</HI> in the faire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>I heard you visited those canvas tragedies,</L>
<L>One of their constant audience, and so taken</L>
<L>With <HI>Susan,</HI> that you wishd your selfe a rivall</L>
<L>With the two wicked elders.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>You thinke this</L>
<L>Is wit now, come you are—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>What I beseech you?</L>
<L>Your character will be full of salt and satyre,</L>
<L>No doubt, what am I?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why you are a woman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>And that's at least a bow wide of you knowledge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wo'd be thought hansome, and might passe i'th country</L>
<L>Vpon a market day, but miserably</L>
<L>Forfeit to pride and fashions, that if heaven</L>
<L><PB REF="24"/>were a new gowne, you'd not stay in't a fortnight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>It must be miserably out of fashion then,</L>
<L>Have I no sinne but pride?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hast any vertue?</L>
<L>Or but a good face to excuse that want?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>You prais'd it yesterday.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>That made you proud.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>More pride?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>You neede not to close up the praise,</L>
<L>I have seene a better countenance in a Sibill.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>When you wore spectacles of sacke, mistooke</L>
<L>The painted cloath, and kist it for your mistresse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me aske you a question, how much</L>
<L>Have you consum'd in expectation</L>
<L>That I would love you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why? I thinke as much</L>
<L>As you have paid a way in honest debts</L>
<L>This seven yeare, tis a pretty impudence,</L>
<L>But cannot make me angry.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is there any</L>
<L>Man that will cast away his limbes upon her?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>You doe not sing so well as I imagind,</L>
<L>Nor dance, you reele in your coranto, and pinch</L>
<L>Your petticoate too hard, y ave no good eare</L>
<L>Toth' musicke, and incline too much one shoulder,</L>
<L>As you were dancing on the rope, and falling,</L>
<L>You speake abominable French, and make</L>
<L>A courtsey like a Dairie maide, not mad?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe we not sting her hansomely</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>A conspiracie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your state is not so much as tis reported</L>
<L>When you conferre notes, all your husbands debts</L>
<L>And your owne reconcild— but thats not it</L>
<L>Will so much spoile your marriage.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>As what sir?</L>
<L>Let me know all my faults.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Some men doe whisper</L>
<L>You are not over honest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>All this shall not</L>
<L>Move me to more than laughter, and some pittie,</L>
<L>Because you have the shapes of gentlemen,</L>
<L>And though you have beene insolent upon me,</L>
<L>I will engage no friend to kicke or cudgell you</L>
<L>To spoile your living, and your limbes together,</L>
<L>I leave that to diseases that offend you,</L>
<L>And spare my curse, poore silken Vermine, and</L>
<L>Hereafter shall distinguish Men from Monkies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="24"/>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Brave soule, you brace of horseleaches, I have heard</L>
<L>Their barbarous language Madam, yare too mercifull,</L>
<L>They shall be silent to your tongue, pray punish e'm.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are things not worth my character, nor mention</L>
<L>Of any cleane breath, so lost in honesty</L>
<L>They cannot satisfie for wrongs enough,</L>
<L>Though they should steale out of the world at Tiburne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are hang'd already.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet I will talke a little to the pilchards,</L>
<L>You two that have not twixt you both the hundred</L>
<L>Part of a soule, course woollen witted fellowes,</L>
<L>Without a nap, with bodies made for burdens,</L>
<L>You that are onely stuffings for apparrell</L>
<L>As you were made but engines for your Taylors</L>
<L>To frame their clothes upon, and get them custome;</L>
<L>Vntill men see you moove, yet, then you dare not</L>
<L>Out of your guilt of being the ignobler beast</L>
<L>But give a horse the wall, whom you excell</L>
<L>Onely in dancing of the brawles, because</L>
<L>The horse was not taught the French way, your two faces,</L>
<L>One fat like Christmas, tother leane like Candlemas,</L>
<L>And Prologue to a Lent, both bound together</L>
<L>Would figure <HI>Ianus,</HI> and doe many cures</L>
<L>On Agues and the greene disease by frighting,</L>
<L>But neither can with all the characters</L>
<L>And conjuring circles charme a woman, though</L>
<L>Sha'd fourescore yeares upon her, and but one</L>
<L>Tooth in her head, to love or thinke well of you;</L>
<L>And I were miserable, to be at cost</L>
<L>To court such a complexion, as your malice</L>
<L>Did impudently insinuate, but I waste time</L>
<L>And staine my breath in talking to such tadpoles.</L>
<L>Goe home and wash your tongues in Barly water</L>
<L>Drinke cleane Tobacco, be not hot i'th mouth,</L>
<L>And you may scape the Beadle; so I leave you</L>
<L>To shame and your owne garters, Sir I must</L>
<L>Entreate you for my honour doe not pennance em▪</L>
<L>They are not worth your anger, how I shall</L>
<L>Acquit your Ladies silence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="25"/>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, I</L>
<L>Am sorry to suspect, and dare revenge</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>No▪ caus<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> mine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>B<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>It must become me to attend you home.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are noble — — farewell Mushroomes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is she gone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Li.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thinke we peperd her▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am glad tis over▪</L>
<L>But I repent no service for you Madam.</L>
<STAGE>Enter servant with a letter.</STAGE>
<L>To me? from whence a Iewell a good preface,</L>
<L>Be happy the conclusion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>Some love letter —
<STAGE>He smiles upon.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>He has a hundred Mistresses, you may</L>
<L>Be charitable Madam I ha none,</L>
<L>He surfets, and I fall away <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>th kidnyes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile meete,</L>
<L>Tis some great Lady questionlesse, that has</L>
<L>Taken notice, and would satisfie her appetite.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now Mr. <HI>Alexander,</HI> you looke bright o'the suddaine,</L>
<L>Another spirit's in your eye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al▪</SPEAKER>
<L>Not <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Madam▪</L>
<L>Onely a <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> to <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> a friend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>What friend?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>By this Jewell, I know her not▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis a she friend▪ Ile follow gentlemen,</L>
<L>We may have a game <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> before you go▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall attend you <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis our duty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>I blush <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> my owne thoughts,</L>
<L>Some strange face gove<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/> me, <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></L>
<L>The wayes are east already and we thrive</L>
<L>When our sinne feares no eye nor perspective.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>The fourth Act▪</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter two men leading Alexander <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ded, and goe <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>f suddenly.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am not hurt, my patience to obey▪em</L>
<L>Not without feare to ha my throat cut else,</L>
<L>Did me a curtesie <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> ha they brought me</L>
<L>Tis devillish darke, the bottome of a well</L>
<L>At midnight, with but two starres on the top,</L>
<L>Were broad day to this darkenesse, I but thinke</L>
<L>How like a whirlewinde these rogues caught me up</L>
<L><PB REF="25"/>And smoothered my eyesight, let me see,</L>
<L>These may be spirits, and for ought I know</L>
<L>Have brought me hither over twenty steeples,</L>
<L>Pray heaven they were not Bay<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>iefes; thats more worth</L>
<L>My feare, and this a prison, all my debts</L>
<L>Reeke in my nostrill, and my bones beginne</L>
<L>To ake with feare to be made dice, and yet</L>
<L>This is too calme and quiet for a prison;</L>
<L>What if the riddle prove I am robd; and yet</L>
<L>I did not feele em search me? How now? musicke?</L>
<STAGE>Enter Decoy like an old woman with a light.</STAGE>
<L>And a light? What beldam's this, I cannot pray;</L>
<L>What art?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>A friend, feare not young man I am</L>
<L>No spirit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Off. De. Despise me not for age,</L>
<L>Or this course outside, which I weare not out</L>
<L>Of poverty; thy eyes be witnesse, tis</L>
<L>No cave or beggars cell tha'rt brought too, let</L>
<L>That gold speake here's no want, which thou maist spend,</L>
<L>And finde a spring to tire even prodigality</L>
<L>If thou beest wise▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>The devill was a coyner</L>
<L>From the beginning, yet the gold lookes currant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tha'rt still in wonder, know I am Mistresse of</L>
<L>This house, and of a fortune that shall serve</L>
<L>And feed thee with delights, twas J sent for thee,</L>
<L>The jewell and the letter came from me▪</L>
<L>It was my art, thus to contrive our meeting,</L>
<L>Because J would not trust thee with my fame,</L>
<L>Vntill J found thee worth a womans honor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Honour and fame? the devill meanes to have</L>
<L>A care on's credit, though she sent for me,</L>
<L>J hope, she has another customer</L>
<L>To doe the tricke withall, J wod not turne</L>
<L>Familiar to a witch.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>What saist? Canst thou</L>
<L>Dwell in my armes to night, shall we change kisses,</L>
<L>And entertaine the silent houres with pleasure?</L>
<L>Such as old time shall be delighted with,</L>
<L>And blame the too swifte motion of his wings</L>
<L>While we embrace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Embrace? she has had no teeth</L>
<L>This twenty yeares, and the next violent cough</L>
<L><PB REF="26"/>Brings up her tongue, it cannot possibly</L>
<L>Be sound at root, I doe not thinke but one</L>
<L>Strong sneeze upon her, and well mean't would make</L>
<L>Her quart<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rs fall away, one kicke would blow</L>
<L>Her up like gunpowder, and loose all her limbs;</L>
<L>She is so cold, an <HI>Incubus</HI> wod not heate her,</L>
<L>Her phlegme would quench a furnace, and her breath</L>
<L>Would dampe a musket bullet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Have you sir</L>
<L>Considerd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>What?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>My proposition,</L>
<L>Canst love?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>I could have done, whom doe you meane?</L>
<L>I know you are pleas'd, but to make sport.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art not</L>
<L>So dull of soule as thou appearst.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is.</L>
<L>But some device, my granam has some tricke in't:</L>
<L>Yes I can love.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>But canst thou affect me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Although to reverence so grave a matron</L>
<L>Were an ambitious word in me, yet since</L>
<L>You give me boldnesse, I doe love you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then</L>
<L>Thou art my owne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Has she no cloven foote?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I am thine, and all that I command</L>
<L>Thy servants, from this minute thou are happy,</L>
<L>And fate in thee will crowne all my desires.</L>
<L>I griev'd a proper man should be compeld</L>
<L>To bring his body to the common market,</L>
<L>My wealth shall make thee glorious, and the more</L>
<L>To encourage thee, how er<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> this forme may fright</L>
<L>Thy youthfull eyes, yet thou wo't find by light</L>
<L>Of thy owne sense, for other light is banish'd</L>
<L>My chamber, when our armes tie lovers knots,</L>
<L>And kisses seale the welcome of our lippes,</L>
<L>I shall not there af<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>right thee, nor seeme old,</L>
<L>With riveld veines, my skin is smooth and softe</L>
<L>As <HI>Ermines,</HI> with a spirit to meete thine,</L>
<L>Active and equall to the queene of Loves</L>
<L>When she did court <HI>Adonis.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>This doth more</L>
<L>Confirme she is a devill, and I am</L>
<L>Within his owne dominions, I must on,</L>
<L>Or else be torne a p<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ces, I have heard</L>
<L>These Su<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cubi must not be crost.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>We trifle</L>
<L>Too precious time away, Ile shew you a prospect</L>
<L><PB REF="26"/>Of the next chamber, and then out the candle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Have you no sacke i'th house, I would goe arm'd</L>
<L>Vpon this breach.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>It shanot need.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>One word</L>
<L>Mother, have not you beene a Cat in your dayes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am glad you are so merry sir, you observe</L>
<L>That bed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>A very brave one.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>When you are</L>
<L>Disrob'd, you can come thither in the darke,</L>
<L>You shanot stay for me, come as you wish</L>
<L>For happinesse.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am preferd, if I</L>
<L>Be modest and obey, she cannot have</L>
<L>The heart to doe me harme, and she were <HI>Hecate</HI></L>
<L>Herselfe, I will have a strong faith, and thinke,</L>
<L>I march upon a Mistris, the lesse evill,</L>
<L>If I scape fire now, I defie the devill.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Fred: Littlew. Stoward.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fre.</SPEAKER>
<L>And how dee like me now?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>St.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most excellent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fre.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your opinion Mr. <HI>Littlewor.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your French tailor</L>
<L>Has made you a perfect gentleman, I may</L>
<L>Converse now with you, and preserve my credit,</L>
<L>De'e find no alteration in your body</L>
<L>With these new clothes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fre.</SPEAKER>
<L>My body altered? No.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are not yet in fashion then, that must</L>
<L>Have a new motion garbe, and posture too,</L>
<L>Or all your pride is cast away, it is not</L>
<L>The cut of your apparrell makes a gallant,</L>
<L>But the geometricall wearing of your clothes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>St.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mr. <HI>Littleworth</HI> tells you right, you weare your <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>a<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>:</L>
<L>Too like a citizen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis like a Midwife,</L>
<L>Place it with best advantage of your haire,</L>
<L>Is halfe your feather molted? this does make</L>
<L>No shew, it should spread over like a Canopy,</L>
<L>Your hot reind Monsieur weares it for a shade,</L>
<L>And cooler to his backe, your doublet must</L>
<L>Be more unbotton'd hereabouts, you'le not</L>
<L>Be a sloven else, a foule shirt is no blemish,</L>
<L>You must be confident, and outface cleane linnen!</L>
<L>Your doublet and your breeches must be allow'd</L>
<L>No private meeting here, your cloak's too long,</L>
<L><PB REF="27"/>It reaches to your buttocke, and doth smell</L>
<L>Too much of Spanish gravitie, the fashion</L>
<L>Is to weare nothing but a Cape, a coate</L>
<L>May be allowed a covering for one elbow,</L>
<L>And some to avoid the trouble, choose to walke</L>
<L>In qui<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>po thus.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>St.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your coat, and cloak's a brushing</L>
<L>In Long-lane Lumbard.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fre.</SPEAKER>
<L>But what if it raine?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your belt about your shoulder is sufficient</L>
<L>To keepe off any storme, beside a reede</L>
<L>But wau'd discreetly, has so many pores,</L>
<L>It suckes up all the raine that falls about one,</L>
<L>With this defence▪ when other men have beene</L>
<L>Wet to the skin through all their cloakes, I have</L>
<L>Defied a tempest and walk'd by the Tavernes</L>
<L>Drie as a bone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>St.</SPEAKER>
<L>Because he had no money</L>
<L>To call for wine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why you doe walke enchanted,</L>
<L>Have you such pretty charmes in towne? But stay,</L>
<L>Who must I have to attend me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is not that</L>
<L>Yet thought upon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>St.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have laid out for servants.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are every where.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>St.</SPEAKER>
<L>I cannot yet be furnish'd</L>
<L>With such as I would put into his hands.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Of what condition must they be, and how</L>
<L>Many in number sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beside your fencing,</L>
<L>Your singing, dancing, riding, and French-master,</L>
<L>Two may serve domesticke to be constant waiters</L>
<L>Vpon a gentleman a foole, a pimpe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>St.</SPEAKER>
<L>For these two officers I have enquird,</L>
<L>And I am promisd a convenient whiskin,</L>
<L>I could save charges, and employ the Pye wench</L>
<L>That carries her intelligence in whitepots,</L>
<L>Or tis but taking order with the woman</L>
<L>That holds the ballads, she could fit him with</L>
<L>A concubin to any tune, but I</L>
<L>Have a designe to place a fellow with him</L>
<L>That has read all Sir <HI>Pandarus</HI> workes, a Trojan</L>
<L>That lies conceal'd, and is acquainted with</L>
<L>Both citty and sub<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rbian fripperies</L>
<L>Can fetch em with a spell at midnight to him,</L>
<L>And warrant which are for his turne, can for</L>
<L><PB REF="27"/>A neede supply the Surgeon too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fre.</SPEAKER>
<L>I like</L>
<L>Thy providence, — such a one deserves a livery twice a yeare▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>St.</SPEAKER>
<L>It shanot need, a cast suite of your worships</L>
<L>Will serve, he'le find a cloke to cover it</L>
<L>Out of his share with those he brings to bed to you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fre.</SPEAKER>
<L>But must I call this fellow Pimpe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is</L>
<L>Not necessary, or <HI>Iacke,</HI> or <HI>Harry,</HI></L>
<L>Or what hees knowne abroad by will sound better,</L>
<L>That men may thinke he is a Christian.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fre.</SPEAKER>
<L>But heare you Mr. <HI>Littleworth,</HI> is there not</L>
<L>A method and degrees of title in</L>
<L>Men of this a<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>According to the honour</L>
<L>Of men that do<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> employ em. An Emperour</L>
<L>May give this office to a Duke, A King</L>
<L>May have his Viceroy to negotiate for him,</L>
<L>A Duke may use a Lord, the Lord a Knight</L>
<L>A Knight may trust a gentleman, and when</L>
<L>They are abroad, and merry, gentlemen</L>
<L>May pimpe to one another.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fre.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good, good fellowship!</L>
<L>But for the foole now, that should waite on me,</L>
<L>And breake me jeasts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>A foole is necessary.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>St.</SPEAKER>
<L>By any meanes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fre.</SPEAKER>
<L>But which of these two servants</L>
<L>Must now take place.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>That question Mr. <HI>Fredericke</HI></L>
<L>The schoole of Heraldry should conclude upon;</L>
<L>But if my judgement may be heard the foole</L>
<L>Is your firstman, and it is knowne a point</L>
<L>Of state to have a foole.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>St.</SPEAKER>
<L>But sir the other</L>
<L>Is held the finer servant, his employments</L>
<L>Are full of trust, his person cleaue, and nimble,</L>
<L>And none so soone can leape into preferment</L>
<L>Where fooles are poore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not all, theres story for't,</L>
<L>Princes have beene no wi<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>er than they should be,</L>
<L>Would any noble man, that were no foole</L>
<L>Spend all in hope of the Philosophers stone,</L>
<L>To buy new Lordships in another countrey,</L>
<L>Would Knights build Colledges, or gentlemen</L>
<L>Of good states, challenge the field and fight</L>
<L>Because a whore wo'not be honest, come,</L>
<L>Fooles are a family over all the world;</L>
<L><PB REF="28"/>We doe affect one naturally, indeede</L>
<L>The foole is Leiger with us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>St.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then the Pimpe</L>
<L>Is extraordinary.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fre.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe not you fall out</L>
<L>About their places; here's my noble Aunt<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
<STAGE>Enter Aretina.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>How doe you like your nephew Madam now?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, turne about <HI>Fredericke,</HI> very well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>Am I not now a proper gentleman?</L>
<L>The vertue of rich clothes! now could I take</L>
<L>The wall of <HI>Iulius Cesar,</HI> affront</L>
<L>Great <HI>Pompeys</HI> upperlip, and defie the Senate,</L>
<L>Nay I can be as proud as your owne heart Madam,</L>
<L>You may take that for your comfort; J put on</L>
<L>That vertue with my clothes, and J doubt not</L>
<L>But in little time, J shall be impudent</L>
<L>As any Page or Players boy, J am</L>
<L>Beholding to this gentlemans good discipline,</L>
<L>But J shall doe him credit in my practise,</L>
<L>Your Steward has some pretty notions too</L>
<L>In morall mischiefe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your desert in this</L>
<L>Exceedes all other service, and shall bind me</L>
<L>Both to acknowledge, and reward.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweet Madam!</L>
<L>Thinke me but worth your favour, J wo'd creepe</L>
<L>Vpon my knees to honour you, and for every</L>
<L>Minute you lend to my reward, ile pay</L>
<L>A yeare of serviceable tribute.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>You</L>
<L>Can complement.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thus still she puts me off,</L>
<L>Vnlesse J speake the downe right word, she'le never</L>
<L>Vnderstand me, a man would thinke that creeping</L>
<L>Vpon one's knees Were English to a Lady.
<STAGE>Enter Alex.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ale.</SPEAKER>
<L>How ist <HI>Iacke</HI>? Pleasures attend you Madam,</L>
<L>How does my plant of honour?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who is this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis <HI>Alexander.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rich and glorious!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis <HI>Alexander</HI> the great.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ale.</SPEAKER>
<L>And my <HI>Bucephalus</HI></L>
<L>Waites at the doore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your case is alterd sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ale.</SPEAKER>
<L>J cannot helpe these things, the Fa<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es will have it,</L>
<L>Tis not my land does this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>But thou hast a plough</L>
<L>That brings it <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now he lookes brave and lovely.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fre.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wel <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> my gallant Macedonian.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam you gave your Nephew for my pupill,</L>
<L><PB REF="28"/>I rea'd but in a taverne, if you'le horrour us,</L>
<L>The Beare at the bridge foote shall entertaine you,</L>
<L>A drawer is my Ganim<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d, he shall skinke<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Briske <HI>Nectar</HI> to us, we will onely have</L>
<L>A dozen Partridge in a dish, as many Phesants,</L>
<L>Quailes, Cockes and Godwits, shall come marching up</L>
<L>Like the train'd band, a fort of Sturgeon</L>
<L>Shall give most bold defiance to an army,</L>
<L>And triumph ore the table.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, it will</L>
<L>But dull the appetite to heare more, and mine</L>
<L>Must be excusd, another time I may</L>
<L>Be your guest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ale.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis growne in fashion now with Ladies,</L>
<L>When you please ile attend you; <HI>Littleworth</HI></L>
<L>Come <HI>Fredericke.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fre.</SPEAKER>
<L>Weele have musicke, I love noise,</L>
<L>We will out roare the Thames and shake the bridge boy.
<STAGE>Ex.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam I kisse your hand, wod you wod thinke</L>
<L>Of your poore servant, flesh and bloud is fraile,</L>
<L>And trouble some to carry without helpe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>A coach will easily convey it, or</L>
<L>You may take water at strand bridge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>But I</L>
<L>Have taken fire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Thames will coole.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>But never quench my heart, your charitie</L>
<L>Can onely doe that!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will keepe it cold</L>
<L>Of purpose,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now you blesse me, and I date</L>
<L>Be drunke in expectation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am confident</L>
<L>He knowes me not, and I were worse than mad</L>
<L>To be my owne betrayer, hre's my husband.
<STAGE>Enter Born.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, how now <HI>Aretina?</HI> What alone?</L>
<L>The mystery of this solitude? my house</L>
<L>Turne desart o'the sudaine, all the gamsters</L>
<L>Blowne up? Why is the musicke put to silence?</L>
<L>Or ha their instruments caught a cold, since we</L>
<L>Gave e'm the last heate? I must know thy ground</L>
<L>Of Melancholy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are merry, as</L>
<L>You came from kissing <HI>Celestina.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>I</L>
<L>Feele her yet warme upon my lip, she is</L>
<L>Most excellent company, I did not thinke</L>
<L>There was that sweetnesse in her sexe, I must</L>
<L>Acknowledge twas thy cure to disinchant me</L>
<L><PB REF="29"/>From a dull husband to an active lover,</L>
<L>With such a Lady, I could spend more yeeres,</L>
<L>Than since my birth my glasse hath run <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> minutes,</L>
<L>And yet be young, her presence has a spell</L>
<L>To keepe off age, she has an eye would strike</L>
<L>Fire through an adamant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have heard as much</L>
<L>Bestow'd upon a dull fac'd chambermaid</L>
<L>Whom love and wit would thus commend, true beauty</L>
<L>Is mock'd when we compare thus, it selfe being</L>
<L>Above what can be fetch'd to make it lovely,</L>
<L>Or could our thoughts reach some thing to declare</L>
<L>The glories of a face, or bodies elegance,</L>
<L>That touches but our sense, when beauty spreads</L>
<L>Over the soule, and calls up understanding</L>
<L>To looke when thence is offer'd, and admire,</L>
<L>In both I must acknowledge <HI>Celestina</HI></L>
<L>Most excellently faire, faire above all</L>
<L>The beauties I ha seene, and one most worthy</L>
<L>Mans love and wonder.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe you speake <HI>Aretina,</HI></L>
<L>This with a pure sence to commend, or i<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></L>
<L>The mockery of my praise</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aret.</SPEAKER>
<L>Although it shame</L>
<L>My selfe, I must be just, and give her all</L>
<L>The excellency of women, and were I</L>
<L>A man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>What then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know not with what losse,</L>
<L>I should attempt her love, she is a peece</L>
<L>So angellically moving, I should thinke</L>
<L>Frailty excusd to dote upon her forme,</L>
<L>And almost vertue to be wicked with her.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>What should this meane? this is no jealousie,</L>
<L>Or she beleeves I counterfeit, I feele</L>
<L>Something within me, like a heate, to give</L>
<L>Her cause, would <HI>Celestina</HI> but consent,</L>
<L>What a fraile thing is man, it is not worth</L>
<L>Our glory to be chaste, while we deny</L>
<L>Mirth and converse with women, he is good</L>
<L>That dares the tempter, ye<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> corrects his bloud.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Celestina, Mariana, Issabella.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have told you all my knowledge since he is pleasd</L>
<L>To invite himselfe he shall be entertaind,</L>
<L><PB REF="29"/>And you shall be my witnesses.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who comes with him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir <HI>William Sentlove,</HI> that prepard me for</L>
<L>The honourable encounter, I expect</L>
<L>His Lordship every minute.
<STAGE>Enter Sentlove.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sent.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord is come.
<STAGE>Enter Lord. Hairecut.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>He has honord me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Se.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord your periwig is awry▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lo</SPEAKER>
<L>You sir —
<STAGE><HI>While Hairecut is busie about his haire, Sentlove goes to</HI> Celestina.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sent.</SPEAKER>
<L>You may guesse, at the gentleman thats with him.</L>
<L>It is his Barbar, Madam, dee observe</L>
<L>And your Ladiship want a shaver.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hai.</SPEAKER>
<L>She is here sir,</L>
<L>I am betraid <HI>Sentlove</HI> your plot, I may</L>
<L>Have opportunity to be reveng'd
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sent.</SPEAKER>
<L>She in the midst.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lo.</SPEAKER>
<L>She's faire, I must confesse,</L>
<L>But does she keepe this distance out of state.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Though I am poore in language to expresse</L>
<L>How much your Lordship honors me, my heart</L>
<L>Is rich and proud in such a guest, I shall</L>
<L>Be out of love with every aire abroad,</L>
<L>And for his grace done my unworthy house,</L>
<L>Be a fond prisoner, become anchorite,</L>
<L>And spend my houres in prayer, to reward</L>
<L>The blessing, and the bounty of this presence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Though you could turne each place you move in▪ to</L>
<L>A temple, rather than a wall should hide</L>
<L>So rich a beauty from the world, it were</L>
<L>Lesse want to lose our piety and your prayer,</L>
<L>A throne were fitter to present you to</L>
<L>Our wonder, whence your eyes more worth than all</L>
<L>They looke on, should chaine every heart a prisoner.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sent.</SPEAKER>
<L>Twas pretty well come off.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lo.</SPEAKER>
<L>By your example</L>
<L>I shall know how to complement, in this</L>
<L>You more confirme my welcome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall love</L>
<L>My lippes the better, if their silent language</L>
<L>Perswade your Lordship but to thinke so truely.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lo.</SPEAKER>
<L>You make me smile Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hope you came not</L>
<L>With feare that any sadnesse here should shake</L>
<L>One blossome from your eye, I should be miserable</L>
<L>To present any object should displease you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="30"/>
<SPEAKER>Lo.</SPEAKER>
<L>You doe not Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>As I should account</L>
<L>It no lesse sorrow, if your Lordship should</L>
<L>Lay too severe a censure on my freedome.</L>
<L>I wonot court a Prince against his justice,</L>
<L>Nor bribe him with a smile to thinke me honest,</L>
<L>Pardon my Lord this boldnesse, and the mirth</L>
<L>That may flow from me, I beleeve my father</L>
<L>Thought of no winding sheete when he begot me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>She has a merry soule, it will become</L>
<L>Me aske your pardon Madam for my rude</L>
<L>Approach so much a stranger to your knowledge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not my Lord so much stranger to my knowledge,</L>
<L>Though I have but seene your person a farre oft,</L>
<L>I am acquianted with your character,</L>
<L>Which I have heard so often, I can speake it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lo.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall doe me an honor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>If your Lordship will</L>
<L>Be patient.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lo.</SPEAKER>
<L>And glad to heare my faults.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>That as your conscience can agree upon em,</L>
<L>How ever if your Lordship give me priviledge,</L>
<L>Ile tell you whats the opinion of the world.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lo.</SPEAKER>
<L>You cannot please me better.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'are a Lord</L>
<L>Borne with as much nobilitie as would</L>
<L>Divided serve to make ten noble men</L>
<L>Without a Herald, but with so much spirit,</L>
<L>And height of soule, as well might furnish twenty.</L>
<L>You are learnd, a thing not compatible now</L>
<L>With native honour, and are master of</L>
<L>A language that doth chaine all yeares, and charme</L>
<L>All hearts, where you perswade, a wit so flowing</L>
<L>And prudence to correct it, that all men</L>
<L>Beleeve they onely meete in you, which with</L>
<L>A spacious memory make up the full wonders;</L>
<L>To these you have knowne valour, and upon</L>
<L>A noble cause, know how to use a sword</L>
<L>To honors best advantage, though you were none;</L>
<L>You are as bountifull, as the showers that fall</L>
<L>Into the Springs greene besome; as you were</L>
<L>Created Lord of fortune, not her steward;</L>
<L>So constant to the cause, in which you make</L>
<L><PB REF="30"/>Your selfe an advocate, you dare all dangers,</L>
<L>And men had rather you should be their friend,</L>
<L>Than justice or the bench, bound up together.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>But did you heare all this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>And more my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray let me have it Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>To all these vertues, there is added one,</L>
<L>(Your Lordship will remember when I name it,</L>
<L>I speake but what I gather from the voyce</L>
<L>Of others) it is growne to a full fame</L>
<L>That you have lov'd a woman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lo.</SPEAKER>
<L>But one Madam?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes many, give me leave to smile my Lord,</L>
<L>I shall not neede to interpret in what sence,</L>
<L>But you have shewd your selfe right honorable,</L>
<L>And for your love to Ladies have deserv'd,</L>
<L>If their vote might prevaile a marble statue,</L>
<L>I make no comment on the peoples text.</L>
<L>My Lord I should be sorry to offend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>You cannot Madam, these are things we owe</L>
<L>To nature for.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>And honest men will pay</L>
<L>Their debts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lo.</SPEAKER>
<L>If they be able, or compound.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>She had a hard heart, would be unmercifull,</L>
<L>And not give day to men so promising,</L>
<L>But you ow'd women nothing,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes I am</L>
<L>Still in their debt, and I must owe them love,</L>
<L>It was part of my character.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>With your Lordships</L>
<L>Pardon I onely said, you had a fame</L>
<L>For loving women, but of late men say</L>
<L>You have against the imperiall lawes of love,</L>
<L>Restraind the active flowings of your bloud,</L>
<L>And with a Mistris buried all that is</L>
<L>Hop'd for in loves succession, as all beauty</L>
<L>Had died with her, and left the world benighted!</L>
<L>In this you more dishonor all our sexe</L>
<L>Than you did grace a part, when every where</L>
<L>Love tempts your eye to admire a glorious harvest,</L>
<L>And every where as full blowne eares submit</L>
<L>Their golden heads, the laden trees bow downe</L>
<L>Their willing fruit, and court your amorous tasting.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>I see men would dissect me to a fibre,</L>
<L>But doe you beleeve this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is my wonder!</L>
<L><PB REF="31"/>I must confesse a man of nobler earth</L>
<L>Then goes to vulgar composition,</L>
<L>Borne and bred high, so unconfind, so rich</L>
<L>In fortunes, and so read in all that summe</L>
<L>Vp humane knowledge, to feed gloriously,</L>
<L>And live at court, the onely spheare wherein</L>
<L>True beauty moves, natures most wealthy garden,</L>
<L>Where every blossome is more worth, than all</L>
<L>The <HI>Hesperian</HI> fruite, by jealous Dragon watch'd</L>
<L>Where all delights doe circle appetite,</L>
<L>And pleasures multiply by being tasted,)</L>
<L>Should be so lost with thought of one, turne ashes.</L>
<L>There's nothing left my Lord that can excuse you,</L>
<L>Vnlesse you pleade, what I am asham'd to prompt</L>
<L>Your wisedome too?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lo.</SPEAKER>
<L>What that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>That you have plaid</L>
<L>The Surgeon with your selfe</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lo.</SPEAKER>
<L>And am made Eunuch.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>It were much pitty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Trouble not your selfe,</L>
<L>I could convince your feares with demonstration</L>
<L>That I am man enough, but knew not where</L>
<L>Vntill this meeting beauty dwelt; the court</L>
<L>You talk'd of must be where the queene of love is,</L>
<L>Which moves but with your person, in your eye</L>
<L>Her glory shines, and onely at that flame</L>
<L>Her wanton boy doth light his quickning torch.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay now you complement, I would it did</L>
<L>My Lord for your owne sake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>You would be kind,</L>
<L>And love me then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord I should be loving</L>
<L>Where I found worth to invite it, and should cherish</L>
<L>A constant man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then you should me Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>But is the ice about your heart fallen off,</L>
<L>Can you returne to doe what love commands?</L>
<L><HI>Cupid</HI> thou shall have instand sacrifice.</L>
<L>And I dare be the Priest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your hand, your lip,</L>
<L>Now I am proofe gainst all temptation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel</SPEAKER>
<L>Your meaning my good Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>I that have strength</L>
<L>Against thy voyce and beauty, after this</L>
<L>May dare the charmes of womankind, thou art</L>
<L><HI>Bella Maria</HI> unprophaned yet,</L>
<L>This Magicke has no power upon my bloud.</L>
<L><PB REF="31"/>Farewell Madam, if you durst be the example</L>
<L>Of chaste as well as faire, thou wert a brave one.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hope your Lordship meanes not this for earnest,</L>
<L>Be pleasd to grace a banquer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pardon Madam.</L>
<L><HI>Will Sentlove</HI> follow, I must laugh at you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord I must beseech you stay, for honour</L>
<L>For her whose memory you love best.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your pleasure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>And by that vertue you have now profest,</L>
<L>I charge you to beleeve me too, I can</L>
<L>Now glory, that you have beene worth my triall,</L>
<L>Which I beseech you pardon, had not you</L>
<L>So valiantly recoverd in this conflict,</L>
<L>You had beene my triumph, without hope of more</L>
<L>Than my just scorne upon your wanton flame;</L>
<L>Nor will I thinke these noble thoughts grew first</L>
<L>From melancholy, for some femall losse,</L>
<L>As the phantasticke world beleeves, but from</L>
<L>Truth, and your love of Innocence, which shine</L>
<L>So bright in the two royall luminaries</L>
<L>At Court, you cannot lose your way to chastitie,</L>
<L>Proceede, and speake of me as honour guides you.
<STAGE>Exit Lord.</STAGE></L>
<L>I am almost tir'd, come Ladies weele beguile</L>
<L>Dull time, and take the aire annother while.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>The fifth Act.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Aretina and Servant.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>But hath Sir <HI>Thomas</HI> lost five hundred pounds</L>
<L>Already?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>And five hundred more he borrow'd,</L>
<L>The Dice are notable devourers Madam,</L>
<L>They make no more of peeces, than of pebbles,</L>
<L>But thrust their heapes together to engender,</L>
<L>Two hundred more the Caster cries this gentleman,</L>
<L>I am w'ee. I ha that to nothing sir, the Caster</L>
<L>Agen, tis covered, and the table too,</L>
<L>With summes that frighed me, here one speakes out,</L>
<L>And with a Martyrs patience, smiles upon</L>
<L>His moneyes Executioner, the Dice,</L>
<L>Commands a pipe of good Tobacco, and</L>
<L>I'th smoke on't vanishes; another makes</L>
<L><PB REF="32"/>The bones vault ore his head, sweares that ill throwing</L>
<L>Has put his shoulder out of joynt calls for</L>
<L>A bone setter that lookes to'th boxe, to bid</L>
<L>His master send him some more hundred pounds,</L>
<L>Which lost, he takes tobacco, and is quiet;</L>
<L>Here a strong arme throwes in, and in, with which</L>
<L>He brusheth all the table, payes the Rookes</L>
<L>That went their smelts a peece upon his hand,</L>
<L>Yet sweares he has not drawne a stake this seven yeare.</L>
<L>But I was bid make haste▪ my master may</L>
<L>Lose this five hundred pound ere I come thither.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>If we both waste so fast, we shall soone finde</L>
<L>Our state is not immortall, some thing in</L>
<L>His other wayes appeare not well already.
<STAGE>Enter sir Thomas.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yee Tortoises, why make you no more haste,</L>
<L>Go pay to'th master of the house that money,</L>
<L>And tell the noble gamsters, I have another</L>
<L>Superf<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uous thousand pound, at night ile visit em.</L>
<L>Dee heare?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes and please you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor</SPEAKER>
<L>Doo't ye drudges,</L>
<L>Ta ra ra— <HI>Aretina.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have a pleasant humor sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>What should a gentleman be sad?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have lost.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>A transitory summe, as good that way</L>
<L>As another.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe you not vexe within for't?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>I had rather lose a thousand more, than one</L>
<L>Sad thought come neere my heart fort, vexe for trash,</L>
<L>Although it goe from othermen like drops.</L>
<L>Of their life bloud, we lose with the alacrity,</L>
<L>Wee drinke a cup of sacke, or kisse a Mistris,</L>
<L>No money is considerable with a gamster,</L>
<L>They have soules more spacious than Kings, did two</L>
<L>Gamsters divide the Empire of the world</L>
<L>They d make one throw for't all, and he that lost</L>
<L>Be no more melancholy, then to have plai'd for</L>
<L>A morning draught, vexe a rich soule for dirt,</L>
<L>The quiet of whose every thought is worth</L>
<L>A Province:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>But when Dice have consumd all;</L>
<L>Your patience will not pawne for as much more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hang pawning, sell outright, and the feares over.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>Say you so? I'le have another coach to morrow</L>
<L><PB REF="32"/>If there be rich above ground.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>I forgot</L>
<L>To bid the fellow aske my Jeweller,</L>
<L>Whether the chaine of Diamonds be made up,</L>
<L>I will present it to my Lady <HI>Bellamour,</HI></L>
<L>Faire <HI>Celestina.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>This gowne J have worne</L>
<L>Sixe dayes already, it lookes dull, ile give it</L>
<L>My waiting woman, and have one of cloth</L>
<L>of gold enbrodered, shooes and pantables</L>
<L>Will show well of the same.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have invited</L>
<L>A covey of Ladies, and as many gentlemen</L>
<L>To morrow to the <HI>Italian</HI> Ordinary,</L>
<L>I shall have rarities, and regalli as</L>
<L>To pay for Madam, musicke, wanton songs,</L>
<L>And tunes of silken petticotes to dance to.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>And to morrow have I invited halfe the Court</L>
<L>To dine here, what misfortune tis your company</L>
<L>And ours should be devided? after dinner</L>
<L>J entertaine e'm with a play.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>By that time</L>
<L>Your play inclines to the Epilogue, shall we</L>
<L>quit our <HI>Italian</HI> host, and whirle in coaches,</L>
<L>To the Douch Magazine of sawce, the Stillyard,</L>
<L>Where deale, and backragge, and what strange wine else,</L>
<L>They dare but give a name too in the reckoning</L>
<L>Shall flow into our roome, and drowne Westphalias,</L>
<L>Tongues, and Anchoavis, like some little towne</L>
<L>Endangered by a sluce, through whose fierce ebbe</L>
<L>We wade and wash our selves into a boate,</L>
<L>And bid our Coachmen drive their leather tenements</L>
<L>By land, while we saile home with a fresh tide</L>
<L>To some new randevous.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you have not</L>
<L>Pointed the place, pray bring your Ladies hither,</L>
<L>J meane to have a Ball to morrow night,</L>
<L>And a rich banquet for e'm, where we'le dance</L>
<L>Till morning rise, and blush to interrupt us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Have you no Ladies i'th next roome, to advance</L>
<L>A present mirth? What a dull house you governe?</L>
<L>Farewell, a wife's no company—<HI>Aretina,</HI></L>
<L>J've summ'd up my estate, and find we may have</L>
<L>A month good yet▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>What meane you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>And J do rather</L>
<L><PB REF="33"/>Be Lord one moneth of pleasures, to the height</L>
<L>And rapture of our senses, than be yeares,</L>
<L>Consuming what we have in foolish temperance,</L>
<L>Live in the darke, and no fame waite upon us,</L>
<L>I will live so, posterity shall stand</L>
<L>At gaze when I am mentioned.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>A mon'th good,</L>
<L>And what shall be done then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile over Sea,</L>
<L>And traile a pike, with watching, marching, lying</L>
<L>In trenches, with enduring cold, and hunger,</L>
<L>And taking here and there a musketshot,</L>
<L>I can earne every weeke foure shillings Madam,</L>
<L>And if the bullets favour me to snatch</L>
<L>Any superfluous limbe, when I returne</L>
<L>With good friends, I despaire not to be entold</L>
<L>Poore Knight of Windsore; for your course Madam,</L>
<L>No doubt you may doe well, your friends are great,</L>
<L>Or if your poverty, and their pride cannot</L>
<L>Agree, you neede not trouble much invention,</L>
<L>To find a trade to live by, there are customers,</L>
<L>Farewell, be frolicke Madam, if I live</L>
<L>I will feast all my senses, and not fall</L>
<L>Lesse than a <HI>Phaeton</HI> from my throne of Pleasure,</L>
<L>Though my estate flame like the world about me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis very pretty.
<STAGE>Enter Decoy.</STAGE></L>
<L>Madam <HI>Decoy.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>What melancholy
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
<L>After so sweet a nights worke? Have not I</L>
<L>Shew'd my selfe Mistris of my art.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>That title makes the credit of the act</L>
<L>A story higher, y'ave not seene him yet,</L>
<L>I wonder what hee'le say.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>He's here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ale.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beare up
<STAGE>Enter Alexander and Fredericke.</STAGE></L>
<L>My little <HI>Mirmidan,</HI> does not <HI>Iacke Littleworth</HI></L>
<L>Follow?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fre.</SPEAKER>
<L>Follow? He fell into the Thames</L>
<L>At landing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>The devill shall dive for him</L>
<L>Ere I endanger my silke stockings for him,</L>
<L>Let the Watermen alone, they have drags and engins,</L>
<L>When he has drunke his Julip, I shall laugh</L>
<L>To see him come in pickeld the next tide.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fre.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee'le never sinke, he has such a corke braine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="33"/>
<SPEAKER>Ale.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let him be hang'd or drown'd alls one to me,</L>
<L>Yet he deserves to die by water, cannot</L>
<L>Beare his wine credibly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fre.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is not this my Aunt?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ale.</SPEAKER>
<L>And another hansome Lady, I must know her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fre.</SPEAKER>
<L>My bloud is rampant too, I must court some body,</L>
<L>As good my Aunt, as any other body.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where have you beene cozen?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fre.</SPEAKER>
<L>At the bridge,</L>
<L>At the Beares foote, where our first health began</L>
<L>To the faire <HI>Aretina,</HI> whose sweet company</L>
<L>Was wished by all, we could not get a lay,</L>
<L>a Tumbler, a Device, a <HI>bona roba</HI></L>
<L>For any money, drawers were growne dull;</L>
<L>We wanted our true firkes and our vagaries;</L>
<L>When were you in drinke Aunt?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>How?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do not Ladies</L>
<L>Play the good fellowes too? there's no true mirth</L>
<L>Without e'm, I have now such tickling fancies,</L>
<L>That Doctour of the chaire of wit, has read</L>
<L>A precious lecture, how I should behave</L>
<L>My selfe to Ladies, as now for example.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would you practise upon me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fre.</SPEAKER>
<L>I first salute you,</L>
<L>You have a soft hand Madam, are you so</L>
<L>All over?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nephew.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fre.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay you should but smile,</L>
<L>And then agen I kisse you; and thus draw</L>
<L>Off your white glove, and start to see your hand</L>
<L>More excellently white, I grace my owne</L>
<L>Lip with this touch, and turning gently thus,</L>
<L>Prepare you for my skill in Palmistry,</L>
<L>Which out of curiosity no Lady</L>
<L>But easily applies too, the first line</L>
<L>I tooke with most ambition to find out,</L>
<L>Is <HI>Venus</HI> girdle, a faire semicircle</L>
<L>Enclosing both the mount of <HI>Sol</HI> and <HI>Saturne,</HI></L>
<L>If that appeare, she's for my turne, a Lady</L>
<L>Whom nature has prepar'd for the careere,</L>
<L>And <HI>Cupid</HI> at my elbow, I put forward,</L>
<L>You have this very line, Aunt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>The boy's franticke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fre.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have a Couch or Palate, I can shut</L>
<L>The Chamber doore, enrich a stranger when</L>
<L><PB REF="34"/>Your Nephew's comming into play.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fre.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you so coy to your owne flesh and bloud?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here take your playfellow, I talke of sport,</L>
<L>And she would have me marry her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fre.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heres <HI>Littleworth.</HI>
<STAGE>Enter Littleworth wet.</STAGE></L>
<L>Why how now Tutour?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>I ha beene fishing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fr.</SPEAKER>
<L>And what ha you caught?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>My belly full of water.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha ha, wheres thy rapier?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>My rapier's is drown'd,</L>
<L>And I am little better, I was up bi'th heeles,</L>
<L>And out came a tun of water beside wine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Thas made thee sober.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would you have me drunk</L>
<L>With Water?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hope your fire is quenched by this time.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fre.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is not now, as when your worship walkd</L>
<L>By all the tavernes <HI>Iacke,</HI> drie as a bone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>You had store of fish under water <HI>Iacke.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>It has made a poore <HI>Iohn</HI> of me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fre.</SPEAKER>
<L>J doe not thinke but if we cast an angle</L>
<L>Jnto his belly, we might find some Pilchards.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>And boild by this time, deere Madam a bed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Carry but the water Spaniel to a grasseplot</L>
<L>Where he may roule himselfe, let him but shake</L>
<L>His eares twice in the Sunne, and you may grind him</L>
<L>Into a posset.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fre.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come thou shalt to my bed</L>
<L>Poore pickerell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas sweete gentleman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have ill lucke, and I should smell by this time,</L>
<L>I am but new tane I am sure, sweet gentlewoman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your servant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray doe not plucke off my skin,</L>
<L>It is so wet, unlesse you have good eyes</L>
<L>You'le hardly know it from a shirt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Feare nothing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>He has sacke enough, and I may find his humor.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>And how ist with your Ladiship? you looke</L>
<L>Without a sunshine in your face.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are glorious</L>
<L>In mind and habit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ends of gold and silver.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your other clothes were not so rich, who was</L>
<L>Your tailor sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>They were made for me long since,</L>
<L>They have knowne but two bright dayes upon my backe,</L>
<L>I had a humor Madam to lay things by,</L>
<L>They will serve two dayes more, I thinke I ha gold enough</L>
<L>To goe to'th Merc<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r, Ile now allow my selfe</L>
<L><PB REF="34"/>A suite a weeke as this, with necessary</L>
<L>Dependances, Beaver, silke stockings, garters,</L>
<L>And roses in their due conformitie,</L>
<L>Bootes are forbid a cleane legge, but to ride in,</L>
<L>My linnen every morning comes in new,</L>
<L>The old goes too great bellies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are charitable.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>I may dine w'ee sometime, or at the Court</L>
<L>To meete good company, not for the table,</L>
<L>My Clarke o'th Kitchins here, a witty Epicure,</L>
<L>A spirit that to please me with whats rare</L>
<L>Can flie a hundred mile a day to market,</L>
<L>And make me Lord of Fish and Foule, I shall</L>
<L>Forget there is a butcher, and to make</L>
<L>My footmen nimble, he shall feede on nothing</L>
<L>But wings of wildfoule.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>These wayes are costly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Therefore Ile have it so, I ha sprung a mine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>You make me wonder sir, to see this change</L>
<L>Of fortune, your revenew was not late</L>
<L>So plentifull.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hang durty land and Lordships,</L>
<L>I wonot change one lodging I ha got</L>
<L>For the Chamber of London.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>Strange of such a sudden,</L>
<L>To rise to this estate, no fortunate hand</L>
<L>At dice could lift you up so, for tis since</L>
<L>Last night, yesterday, you were no such Monarke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>There be more games then dice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>It cannot be</L>
<L>A Mistris, though your person is worth love,</L>
<L>None possibly are rich enough to feed</L>
<L>As you have cast the method of your riots,</L>
<L>A Princesse, after all her Jewels must</L>
<L>Be forc'd to sell her provinces.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now you talke</L>
<L>Of Jewels? What doe you thinke of this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>A rich one.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>You'le honour me to wear't, this other toy</L>
<L>I had from you, this chaine I borrowed of you,</L>
<L>A friend had it in keeping, if your Ladiship</L>
<L>Want any summe, you know your friend and <HI>Alexander</HI>▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dare you trust my security.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>There's gold,</L>
<L>I shall have more to morrow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>You astonish me, who can supply these?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>A deare friend I have,</L>
<L><PB REF="35"/>She promisd we should meete agen i'th morning.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not that I wish to know</L>
<L>More of your happinesse, then I have aready</L>
<L>Heart to congratulate, be pleasd to lay</L>
<L>My wonder.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis a secret.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>Which ile die</L>
<L>Ere Ile betray.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have alwayes wish'd me well,</L>
<L>But you shall sweare not to reveale the partie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile lose the benefit of my tongue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor be</L>
<L>A fraid at what I say, what thinke you first</L>
<L>Of an old Witch, a strange ill favor'd hag</L>
<L>That for my company last night, has wrought</L>
<L>This cure upon my fortune? I doe sweat</L>
<L>To thinke upon her name.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are</SPEAKER>
<L>How sir a Witch?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ale.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would not fright your Ladiship too much</L>
<L>At first, but Witches are a kin to Spirits,</L>
<L>The truth is— nay if you looke pale already,</L>
<L>I ha done.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir I beseech you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ale.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you have</L>
<L>But courage then to know the truth, ile tell you</L>
<L>In one word, my chiefe friend is the devill.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>What devill? How I tremble.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ale.</SPEAKER>
<L>Have a heart,</L>
<L>Twas a shee divell too, a most insatiate</L>
<L>Abominable devill with a taile</L>
<L>Thus long.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goodnesse defend me, did you see her?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>No twas i'th darke, but she appeard first to me</L>
<L>I'th likenesse of a Bedlam, and was brought</L>
<L>I know not how, nor whither, by two Goblins,</L>
<L>More hooded than a Hawke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>But would you venter</L>
<L>Vpon a devill?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>I for meanes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>How blacke</L>
<L>An impudence is this? But are you sure</L>
<L>It was the devill you enjoy'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Say nothing,</L>
<L>I did the best to please her, but as sure</L>
<L>As you live, twas a Helcat.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>De'e not quake?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>I found my selfe the very same in i'th morning,</L>
<L>Where two of her familiars had left me.
<STAGE>Enter Servant.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord is come to visite you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>No words,</L>
<L>As you respect my safety, I ha told tales</L>
<L>Out of the devills schoole, if it be knowne</L>
<L>I lose a friend, tis now about the time</L>
<L>I promis'd her to meete agen, at my</L>
<L><PB REF="35"/>Returne Ile tell you wonders, not a word.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis a false glasse, sure I am more deform'd,</L>
<L>What have I done, my soule is miserable.
<STAGE>Enter Lord.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>I sent you a letter Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>You exprest</L>
<L>Your noble care of me my Lord.
<STAGE>Enter Bornwell, Celestina.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Lordship</L>
<L>Does me an honour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam I am glad</L>
<L>To see you here, I meant to have kist your hand</L>
<L>Ere my returne to Court.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir <HI>Thomas</HI> has</L>
<L>Prevaild to bring me to his trouble hither.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>You doe him grace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why whats the matter Ma∣dam?</L>
<L>Your eyes are tuning <HI>Lachrimae.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>As you</L>
<L>Doe hope for heaven withdraw, and give me but</L>
<L>The patience of ten minutes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Born.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wonderfull!</L>
<L>I wonot heare you above that proportion,</L>
<L>Shee talkes of heaven, come, where must we to counsell?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall conclude me when you please.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I follow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>What alteration is this? I that so late</L>
<L>Stood the temptation of her eye, and voyce,</L>
<L>Boasted a heart, 'bove all licentious flame,</L>
<L>At second veiw turne renegade, and thinke</L>
<L>I was too superstitious, and full</L>
<L>Of phlegme not to reward her amorous Courtship</L>
<L>With manly freedome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>I obey you sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile waite upon your Lordship presently.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>She could not want a cunning to seeme honest</L>
<L>When I neglected her, I am resolv'd,</L>
<L>You still looke pleasant Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have cause</L>
<L>My Lord, the rather for your presence, which</L>
<L>Hath power to charme all trouble in my thoughts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must translate that complement and owe</L>
<L>All that is cheerefull in my selfe to these</L>
<L>All quickning smiles, and rather than such bright</L>
<L>Eyes should repent their influence upon me,</L>
<L>I would release the aspects, and quit the bountie</L>
<L>Of all the other starres; Did you not thinke me</L>
<L>A strange and melancholy gentleman</L>
<L>To use you so unkindly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Me my Lord?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hope you made no loude complaint, I wod not</L>
<L><PB REF="36"/>Be tride by a Jury of Ladies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>For what my Lord?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>I did not meete that noble entertainment,</L>
<L>You were late pleasd to shew me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>I observd</L>
<L>No such defect in your Lorship, but a brave</L>
<L>And noble fortitude.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>A noble folly</L>
<L>I bring repentance fort, I know you have</L>
<L>Madam a gentle faith, and wonot ruine</L>
<L>What you have built to honour you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whats that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you can love ile tell your Ladiship.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have a stubborne soule else.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are all</L>
<L>Composd of harmony.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>What love de'e meane▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>That which doth perfect both, Madam you have heard</L>
<L>I can be constant, and if you consent</L>
<L>To grace it so, there is a spacious dwelling</L>
<L>Prepar'd within my heart for such a Mistrisse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Mistris, my good Lord?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why my good Lady?</L>
<L>Your sexe doth hold it no dishonour</L>
<L>To become Mistris to a noble servant</L>
<L>In the now court, Platonicke way, consider</L>
<L>Who tis that pleades to you, my birth, and present</L>
<L>Value can be no staine to your embrace,</L>
<L>But these are shadowes when my love appeares,</L>
<L>Which shall in his first miracle returne</L>
<L>Me in my bloome of youth, and thee a Virgin,</L>
<L>When I within some new <HI>Elisium</HI></L>
<L>Of purpose made and meant for us, shall be</L>
<L>In every thing <HI>Adonis,</HI> but in his</L>
<L>Contempt of love, and court thee from a <HI>Daphne</HI></L>
<L>Hid in the cold rinde of a bashfull tree,</L>
<L>With such warme language, and delight, till thou</L>
<L>Leape from that bayes into the queene of love,</L>
<L>And pay my conquest with composing garlands</L>
<L>Of thy owne mirtle for me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whats all this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Consent to be my Mistris <HI>Celestina,</HI></L>
<L>And we will have it Spring-time all the yeare,</L>
<L>Vpon whose invitations when we walke,</L>
<L>The windes shall play soft descant to our feete,</L>
<L>And breathe rich odors to repure the aire,</L>
<L>Greene bowers on every side shall tempt our stay,</L>
<L><PB REF="36"/>And Violets stoope to have us treade upon em.</L>
<L>The red rose shall grow pale, being neere thy cheeke,</L>
<L>And the white blush orecome with such a forehead,</L>
<L>Here laid, and measuring with our selves some banke,</L>
<L>A thousand birds shall from the woods repaire.</L>
<L>And place themselves so cunningly, behinde</L>
<L>The leaves of every tree, that while they pay</L>
<L>As tribute of their songs, thou shat imagine</L>
<L>The very trees beare musicke, and sweet voyces</L>
<L>Doe grow in every arbour, here can we</L>
<L>Embrace and kisse, tell tales, and kisse agen,</L>
<L>And none but heaven our rivall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>When we are</L>
<L>Weary of these, what if we shift our Paradise?</L>
<L>And through a grove of tall and even pine,</L>
<L>Descend into a Vally, that shall shame</L>
<L>All the delights of <HI>Tempe,</HI> upon whose</L>
<L>Greene plush the graces shall be cald to dance</L>
<L>To please us, and maintaine their Fairy revells,</L>
<L>To the harmonious murmurs of a streame</L>
<L>That gently falls upon a rocke of pearle,</L>
<L>Here doth the Nimph forsaken Eccho dwell,</L>
<L>To whom we'le tell the story of our love,</L>
<L>Till at our surfet and her want of joy,</L>
<L>We breake her heart with envy, not farre off</L>
<L>A grove shall call us to a wanton river,</L>
<L>To see a dying Swan give up the ghost,</L>
<L>The fishes shooting up their teares in bubbles</L>
<L>That they must lose the Genius of their waves,</L>
<L>And such love linsey woolsey, to no purpose.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>You chide me hansomely, pray tell me how</L>
<L>You like this language.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good my Lord forbeare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>You neede not flie out of this circle Madam,</L>
<L>These widowes so are full of circumstance,</L>
<L>Ile undertake in this time I ha courted</L>
<L>Your Ladiship for the toy, to ha broken ten,</L>
<L>Nay twenty colts, Virgins I meane, and taught em</L>
<L>The amble, or what pace I most affected.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'are not my Lord agen, the Lord I thought you.</L>
<L>And I must tell you now, you doe forget</L>
<L><PB REF="37"/>Your selfe and me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>You'le not be angry Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor rude, though gay men have a priviledge,</L>
<L>It shall appeare, there is a man my Lord</L>
<L>Within my acquaintance, rich in worldly fortunes,</L>
<L>But cannot boast any descent of bloud,</L>
<L>Would buy a coate of armes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>He may, and legges booted and spurr'd to ride into the countrey.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>But these will want antiquitie: my Lord</L>
<L>The seale of honour, whats a coate cut out</L>
<L>But yesterday to ma<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e a man a gentleman?</L>
<L>Your family as old, as the first vertue</L>
<L>That merited an Escucheon, doth owe</L>
<L>A glorious coat of armes, if you will sell now</L>
<L>All that your name doth challenge in that ensigne,</L>
<L>Il<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> helpe you to a chapman, that shall pay</L>
<L>And powre downe wealth enough fort.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sell my armes?</L>
<L>I cannot Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Give but your consent,</L>
<L>You know not how the state may be enclind</L>
<L>To dispensation, we may prevaile</L>
<L>Vpon the Heralds office afterward.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile sooner give these armess to'th hangmans axe,</L>
<L>My head, my heart, to twenty executions</L>
<L>Than sell one atome from my name.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Change that,</L>
<L>And answer him would buy my honour from me.</L>
<L>Honour that is not worne upon a flagge</L>
<L>Or pennon, that without the owners dangers,</L>
<L>An enemy may ravish, and beare from me,</L>
<L>But that which growes and withers with my soule,</L>
<L>Beside the bodies staine, think, thinke my Lord</L>
<L>To what you would unworthily betray me,</L>
<L>If you would not for price of gold, or pleasure,</L>
<L>(If that be more your idoll) lose the glory</L>
<L>And painted honour of your house — I ha done.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Enough to rectifie a Satires bloud,</L>
<L>Obscure my blushes here.
<STAGE>Enter Sentlove and Hairecut.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or this or sight with me,</L>
<L>It shall be no exception that I waite</L>
<L>Vpon my Lord, I am a gentleman,</L>
<L>You may be lesse and bea Knight, the office,</L>
<L>I doe my Lord is honest sir, how many</L>
<L><PB REF="37"/>Such you have beene guilty of, heaven knowes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sent.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis no feare of your sword, but that I wod not</L>
<L>Breake the good lawes established against duells.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oft with your periwig, and stand bare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>From this</L>
<L>Minute ile be a servant to thy goodnesse,</L>
<L>A Mistris in the wanton sence is common,</L>
<L>Ile honor you with chaste thoughts, and call you so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile study to be worth your faire opinion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Sent love,</HI> your head was usd to a covering,</L>
<L>Beside a hat, when went the haire away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sent.</SPEAKER>
<L>I laid a wager my Lord with <HI>Hairecut,</HI></L>
<L>Who thinkes I shall catch cold, that ile stand bare</L>
<L>This halfe houre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pardon my ambition</L>
<L>Madam, I told you truth, I am a gentleman,</L>
<L>And cannot feare that name is drown'd in my</L>
<L>Relation to my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>I dare not thinke so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>From henceforth call my service duty Madam,</L>
<L>That Pigges head that betraid me to your mirth,</L>
<L>Is doing penance for't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sent.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why may not I</L>
<L>My Lord begin a fashion of no haire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe you sweat sir william.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sent.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not with store of nightcaps.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Aretina, Bornwell.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heaven has dissolv'd the clouds that hung upon</L>
<L>My eyes, and if you can with mercy meet</L>
<L>A penitent, I throw my owne will off,</L>
<L>And now in all things obey yours, my nephew</L>
<L>Send backe agen to'th colledge, and my selfe</L>
<L>To what place you'le confine me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dearer now</L>
<L>Than ever to my bosome, thou shat please</L>
<L>Me best to live at thy owne choice, I did</L>
<L>But fright thee with a noise of my expences,</L>
<L>The summes are safe, and we have wealth enough,</L>
<L>If yet we use it nobly? My Lord— Madam,</L>
<L>Pray honour to night.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>I begge your presence,</L>
<L>And pardon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know not how my <HI>Aretina</HI></L>
<L>May be disposd to morrow for the country.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel</SPEAKER>
<L>You must not goe, before you both have done</L>
<L>Me honour to accept an entertainment,</L>
<L>Where I have power, on those termes I'me your guest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="38"/>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>You grace us Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>Already</L>
<L>I feele a cure upon my soule, and promise</L>
<L>My after life to vertue, pardon heaven,</L>
<L>My shame yet hid from the worlds eye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweet Madam.
<STAGE>Enter decoy.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not for the world be seene here, we are lost,</L>
<L>Ile visite you at home; but not to practise</L>
<L>What she expects, my counsell may recover her.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Alexander.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wheres Madam? pray lend me a little money,</L>
<L>My spirit has deceiv'd me, <HI>Proserpine</HI></L>
<L>Has broke her word.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe you expect to find</L>
<L>The devill true to you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not too loud.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile voyce it</L>
<L>Louder, to all the world your horrid sinne,</L>
<L>Vnlesse you promise me religiously,</L>
<L>To purge your foule bloud by repentance sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then I'me undone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Are.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not while I have power</L>
<L>To encourage you to vertue, ile endeavour</L>
<L>To find you out some nobler way at Court</L>
<L>To thrive in.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doo't, and ile forsake the devill,</L>
<L>And bring my flesh to obedience; you shall steere me,</L>
<L>My Lord — your servant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are brave agen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam your pardon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your offence requires</L>
<L>Humility.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Low as my heart. Sir <HI>Thomas</HI></L>
<L>Ile sup with you, a part of satisfaction.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our pleasures coole, musicke, and when our Ladies</L>
<L>Are tired with active motion, to give</L>
<L>Them rest in some new rapture to advance</L>
<L>Full mirth, our soules shall leape into a dance.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

