<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>7-9-08</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>John Latta</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TEMPHEAD, checked ID, and added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Checked for N=""s. Checked for GROUP tags. Proofed title page. Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure; changed several `s to 's. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, oes, --s, and UNCLEARs. Corrected $s and $Word$s. Checked for &amp;cs with incorrect spacing. Checked for LBs. Checked for startqs and endqs, q;s, abq's, Ae's, and Qs. Checked italic I / J and U / V. Checked for missing page GAPs. Checked for EPIGRAPHs and ARGUMENTS. Checked proofsheets and made corrections. Checked CLOSERs, TRAILERs, SIGNEDs, OPENERs, SALUTEs, BYLINEs. Sample: 2 minutes. Proofing: 25 minutes. Tag review and corrections: 40 minutes. DONE.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A13358">
<STC T="S">23667</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99846538</BIBNO>
<VID>11514</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>A Pleasant Conceited Historie, called The taming of a Shrew.</P>
<P>As it was sundry times acted by the <HI>Right honorable the Earle of</HI> Pembrook his seruants.</P>
<P><FIGURE>
</FIGURE></P>
<P>Printed at London by Peter Short and <HI>are to be sold by Cutbert Burbie, at his</HI> shop at the Royall Exchange. 1594.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="play">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>A Pleasant conceited Historie, called <HI>The Taming of a Shrew.</HI></HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter a Tapster, beating out of his doores <HI>Slie Droonken.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tapster.</SPEAKER>
<L>YOu whorson droonken slaue, you had best be gone,</L>
<L>And empty your droonken panch some where else</L>
<L>For in this house thou shalt not rest to night.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit <HI>Tapster.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Slie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tilly vally, by crisee Tapster Ile fese you anon.</L>
<L>Fils the tother pot and alls paid for, looke you</L>
<L>I doo drinke it of mine owne Instegation,</L>
<STAGE>Omne bene</STAGE>
<L>Heere Ile lie a while, why Tapster I say,</L>
<L>Fils a fresh cushen heere.</L>
<L>Heigh ho, heers good warme lying.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>He fals asleepe.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter a Noble man and his men from hunting.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lord.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now that the gloomie shaddow of the night,</L>
<L>Longing to view Orions drisling lookes,</L>
<L>Leapes from th'antarticke World vnto the skie</L>
<L>And dims the Welkin with her pitchie breath,</L>
<L>And darkesome night oreshades the christall heauens,</L>
<L>Here breake we off our hunting for to night,</L>
<L><PB REF="3"/>Cupple vppe the hounds and let vs hie vs home,</L>
<L>And bid the huntsman see them meated well,</L>
<L>For they haue all deseru'd it well to daie,</L>
<L>But soft, what sleepie fellow is this lies heere?</L>
<L>Or is he dead, see one what he dooth lacke?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seruingman.</SPEAKER>
<L>My lord, tis nothing but a drunken sleepe,</L>
<L>His head is too heauie for his bodie,</L>
<L>And he hath drunke so much that he can go no furder.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lord.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fie, how the slauish villaine stinkes of drinke.</L>
<L>Ho, sirha arise. What so sound asleepe?</L>
<L>Go take him vppe and beare him to my house,</L>
<L>And beare him easilie for feare he wake,</L>
<L>And in my fairest chamber make a fire,</L>
<L>And set a sumptuous banquet on the boord,</L>
<L>And put my richest garmentes on his backe,</L>
<L>Then set him at the Table in a chaire:</L>
<L>When that is doone against he shall awake,</L>
<L>Let heauenlie musicke play about him still,</L>
<L>Go two of you awaie and beare him hence,</L>
<L>And then Ile tell you what I haue deuisde,</L>
<L>But see in any case you wake him not.</L>
<STAGE><HI>Exeunt</HI> two with <HI>Slie.</HI></STAGE>
<L>Now take my cloake and giue me one of yours,</L>
<L>Al fellowes now, and see you take me so,</L>
<L>For we will waite vpon this droonken man,</L>
<L>To see his countnance when he dooth awake</L>
<L>And finde himselfe clothed in such attire,</L>
<L>With heauenlie musicke sounding in his eares,</L>
<L>And such a banquet set before his eies,</L>
<L>The fellow sure will thinke he is in heauen,</L>
<L>But we will be about him when he wakes,</L>
<L>And see you call him Lord, at euerie word,</L>
<L>And offer thou him his horse to ride abroad,</L>
<L><PB REF="3"/>And thou his hawkes and houndes to hunt the deere,</L>
<L>And I will aske what sutes he meanes to weare,</L>
<L>And what so ere he saith, see you doo not laugh,</L>
<L>But still perswade him that he is a Lord.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter one.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mes.</SPEAKER>
<L>And it please your honour your plaiers be com</L>
<L>And doo attend your honours pleasure here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lord.</SPEAKER>
<L>The fittest time they could haue chosen out,</L>
<L>Bid one or two of them come hither straight,</L>
<L>Now will I fit my selfe accordinglie,</L>
<L>For they shall play to him when he awakes.</L>
<STAGE>Enter two of the players with packs at their backs, and a boy.</STAGE>
<L>Now sirs, what store of plaies haue you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>Marrie my lord you maie haue a Tragicall</L>
<L>Or a comoditie, or what you will.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>The other.</SPEAKER>
<P>A Comedie thou shouldst say, souns thout shame vs all.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lord.</SPEAKER>
<P>And whats the name of your Comedie?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>Marrie my lord tis calde The taming of a shrew:</L>
<L>Tis a good lesson for vs my lord, for vs y are maried men</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lord.</SPEAKER>
<L>The taming of a shrew, thats excellent sure,</L>
<L>Go see that you make you readie straight,</L>
<L>For you must play before a lord to night,</L>
<L>Say you are his men and I your fellow,</L>
<L>Hees something foolish, but what so ere he saies,</L>
<L>See that you be not dasht out of countenance.</L>
<L>And sirha go you make you ready straight,</L>
<L>And dresse your selfe like some louelie ladie,</L>
<L>And when I call see that you come to me,</L>
<L>For I will say to him thou art his wife,</L>
<L>Dallie with him and hug him in thine armes,</L>
<L>And if he desire to goe to bed with thee,</L>
<L><PB REF="4"/>Then faine some scuse and say thou wilt anon.</L>
<L>Be gone I say, and see thou doost it well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>B<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="missing" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y.</SPEAKER>
<L>Feare not my Lord, Ile dandell him well enough</L>
<L>And make him thinke I loue him mightilie.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Ex.</HI> boy.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lord.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now sirs go you and make you ready to,</L>
<L>For you must play assoone as he dooth wake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>O braue, sirha Tom, we must play before</L>
<L>A foolish Lord, come lets go make vs ready,</L>
<L>Go get a dishclout to make cleane your shooes,</L>
<L>And Ile speake for the properties, My Lord, we must</L>
<L>Haue a shoulder of mutton for a propertie,</L>
<L>And a little vinegre to make our Diuell rore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lord.</SPEAKER>
<P>Very well: sirha see that they want nothing.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt omnes.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter two with a table and a banquet on it, and two other, with <HI>Slie</HI> asleepe in a chaire, richlie apparelled, &amp; the musick plaieng.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>One.</SPEAKER>
<L>So: sirha now go call my Lord,</L>
<L>And tel him that all things is ready as he wild it.</L>
<L><HI>Another.</HI> Set thou some wine vpon the boord</L>
<L>And then Ile go fetch my Lord presentlie.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter the Lord and his men.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lord.</SPEAKER>
<P>How now, what is all thinges readie?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>One.</SPEAKER>
<P>I my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lord.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then sound the musick, and Ile wake him straight,</L>
<L>And see you doo as earst I gaue in charge.</L>
<L>My lord, My lord, he sleepes soundlie: My lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Slie.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tapster, gis a little small ale. Heigh ho,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lord.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heers wine my lord, the purest of the grape.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Slie.</SPEAKER>
<P>For which Lord?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lord.</SPEAKER>
<P>For your honour my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="4"/>
<SPEAKER>Slie.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who I, am I a Lord? Iesus what fine apparell haue <HI>I</HI> got.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lord.</SPEAKER>
<L>More richer farre your honour hath to weare,</L>
<L>And if it please you I will fetch them straight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wil.</SPEAKER>
<L>And if your honour please to ride abroad,</L>
<L>Ile fetch you lustie steedes more swift of pace</L>
<L>Then winged <HI>Pegasus</HI> in all his pride,</L>
<L>That ran so swiftlie ouer the <HI>Persian</HI> plaines.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<L>And if your honour please to hunt the deere,</L>
<L>Your hounds stands readie cuppeld at the doore,</L>
<L>Who in running will oretake the Row,</L>
<L>And make the long breathde Tygre broken winded.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Slie.</SPEAKER>
<L>By the masse I thinke I am a Lord indeed,</L>
<L>Whats thy name?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lord.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Simon</HI> and it please your honour.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Slie.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Simon,</HI> thats as much to say <HI>Simion</HI> or <HI>Simon</HI></L>
<L>Put foorth thy hand and fill the pot.</L>
<L>Giue me thy hand, <HI>Sim.</HI> am I a lord indeed?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lord.</SPEAKER>
<L>I my gratious Lord, and your louelie ladie</L>
<L>Long time hath moorned for your absence heere,</L>
<L>And now with ioy behold where she dooth come</L>
<L>To gratulate your honours safe returne.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter the boy in Womans attire.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Slie.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Sim.</HI> Is this she?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lord.</SPEAKER>
<P>I my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Slie.</SPEAKER>
<P>Masse tis a prettie wench, whats her name?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh that my louelie Lord would once vouchsafe</L>
<L>To looke on me, and leaue these frantike fits,</L>
<L>Or were I now but halfe so eloquent,</L>
<L>To paint in words what ile performe in deedes,</L>
<L>I know your honour then would pittie me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Slie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Harke you mistresse, wil you eat a peece of bread,</L>
<L><PB REF="5"/>Come sit downe on my knee, <HI>Sim</HI> drinke to hir <HI>Sim,</HI></L>
<L>For she and I will go to bed anon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lord.</SPEAKER>
<L>May it please you, your honors plaiers be come</L>
<L>To offer your honour a plaie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Slie.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>A</HI> plaie <HI>Sim,</HI> O braue, be they my plaiers?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lord.</SPEAKER>
<P>I my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Slie.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is there not a foole in the plaie?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lord.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes my lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Slie.</SPEAKER>
<P>When wil they plaie <HI>Sim?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lord.</SPEAKER>
<P>Euen when it please your honor, they be readie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>My lord Ile go bid them begin their plaie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Slie.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doo, but looke that you come againe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>I warrant you my lord, I wil not leaue you thus.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> boy.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Slie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come <HI>Sim,</HI> where be the plaiers? <HI>Sim</HI> stand by</L>
<L>Me and weele flout the plaiers out of their cotes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lord.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile cal them my lord. Hoe where are you there?</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Sound Trumpets.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter two yoong Gentlemen, and a man and a boie.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Welcome to <HI>Athens</HI> my beloued friend,</L>
<L>To <HI>Platoes</HI> schooles and <HI>Aristotles</HI> walkes,</L>
<L>Welcome from <HI>Cestus</HI> famous for the loue</L>
<L>Of good <HI>Leander</HI> and his Tragedie,</L>
<L>For whom the <HI>Helespont</HI> weepes brinish teares,</L>
<L>The greatest griefe is I cannot as I would</L>
<L>Giue entertainment to my deerest friend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thankes noble <HI>Polidor</HI> my second selfe,</L>
<L>The faithfull loue which I haue found in thee</L>
<L>Hath made me leaue my fathers princelie court,</L>
<L>The Duke of <HI>Cestus</HI> thrise renowmed seate,</L>
<L>To come to <HI>Athens</HI> thus to find thee out,</L>
<L><PB REF="5"/>Which since I haue so happilie attaind,</L>
<L>My fortune now I doo account as great</L>
<L>As earst did <HI>Caesar</HI> when he conquered most,</L>
<L>But tell me noble friend where shal we lodge,</L>
<L>For I am vnacquainted in this place.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Poli.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord if you vouchsafe of schollers fare,</L>
<L>My house, my selfe, and all is yours to vse,</L>
<L>You and your men shall staie and lodge with me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurel.</SPEAKER>
<L>With all my hart, I will requite thy loue,</L>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Simon, Alphonsus,</HI> and his three daughters.</STAGE>
<L>But staie; what dames are these so bright of hew</L>
<L>Whose eies are brighter then the lampes of heauen,</L>
<L>Fairer then rocks of pearle and pretious stone,</L>
<L>More louelie farre then is the morning sunne,</L>
<L>When first she opes hir orientall gates.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alfon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Daughters be gone, and hie you to y<SUP>e</SUP> church,</L>
<L>And I will hie me downe vnto the key,</L>
<L>To see what Marchandise is come a shore.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ex. Omnes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why how now my Lord, what in a dumpe,</L>
<L>To see these damsels passe away so soone?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Trust me my friend I must confesse to thee,</L>
<L>I tooke so much delight in these faire dames,</L>
<L>As I doo wish they had not gone so soone,</L>
<L>But if thou canst, resolue me what they be,</L>
<L>And what old man it was that went with them,</L>
<L>For I doo long to see them once againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pol.</SPEAKER>
<L>I cannot blame your honor good my lord,</L>
<L>For they are both louely, wise, faire and yong,</L>
<L>And one of them the yoongest of the three</L>
<L>I long haue lou'd (sweet friend) and she lou'd me,</L>
<L>But neuer yet we could not find a meanes</L>
<L>How we might compasse our desired ioyes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="6"/>
<SPEAKER>Aurel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, is not her father willing to the match?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes trust me, but he hath solemnlie sworne,</L>
<L>His eldest daughter first shall be espowsde,</L>
<L>Before he grauntes his yoongest leaue to loue,</L>
<L>And therefore he that meanes to get their loues,</L>
<L>Must first prouide for her if he will speed,</L>
<L>And he that hath her shall be fettred so,</L>
<L>As good be wedded to the diuell himselfe,</L>
<L>For such a skould as she did neuer liue,</L>
<L>And till that she be sped none else can speed,</L>
<L>Which makes me thinke that all my labours lost,</L>
<L>And whosoere can get hir firme good will,</L>
<L>A large dowrie he shall be sure to haue,</L>
<L>For her father is a man of mightie wealth,</L>
<L>And an ancient Cittizen of the towne,</L>
<L>And that was he that went along with them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurel.</SPEAKER>
<L>But he shall keepe hir still by my aduise,</L>
<L>And yet I needs must loue his second daughter</L>
<L>The image of honor and Nobilitie,</L>
<L>In whose sweet person is comprisde the somme</L>
<L>Of natures skill and heauenlie maiestie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pol.</SPEAKER>
<L>I like your choise, and glad you chose not mine,</L>
<L>Then if you like to follow on your loue,</L>
<L>We must deuise a meanes and find some one</L>
<L>That will attempt to wed this deuilish skould,</L>
<L>And I doo know the man. Come hither boy,</L>
<L>Go your waies sirha to <HI>Ferandoes</HI> house,</L>
<L>Desire him take the paines to come to me,</L>
<L>For I must speake with him immediatlie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will sir, and fetch him presentlie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pol.</SPEAKER>
<L>A man I thinke will fit hir humor right,</L>
<L>As blunt in speech as she is sharpe of toong,</L>
<L>And he <HI>I</HI> thinke will match hir euerie waie,</L>
<L>And yet he is a man of wealth sufficient,</L>
<L><PB REF="6"/>And for his person worth as good as she,</L>
<L>And if he compasse hir to be his wife,</L>
<L>Then may we freelie visite both our loues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurel.</SPEAKER>
<L>O might I see the center of my soule</L>
<L>Whose sacred beautie hath inchanted me,</L>
<L>More faire then was the Grecian <HI>Helena</HI></L>
<L>For whose sweet sake so many princes dide,</L>
<L>That came with thousand shippes to <HI>Tenedos,</HI></L>
<L>But when we come vnto hir fathers house,</L>
<L>Tell him I am a Marchants sonne of <HI>Cestus,</HI></L>
<L>That comes for traffike vnto <HI>Athens</HI> heere,</L>
<L>And heere sirha I will change with you for once,</L>
<L>And now be thou the Duke of <HI>Cestus</HI> sonne,</L>
<L>Reuell and spend as if thou wert my selfe,</L>
<L>For I will court my loue in this disguise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>My lord, how if the Duke your father should</L>
<L>By some meanes come to <HI>Athens</HI> for to see</L>
<L>How you doo profit in these publike schooles,</L>
<L>And find me clothed thus in your attire,</L>
<L>How would he take it then thinke you my lord?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tush feare not <HI>Valeria</HI> let me alone,</L>
<L>But staie, heere comes some other companie.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Ferando</HI> and his man <HI>Saunders</HI> with a blew coat.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pol.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here comes the man that <HI>I</HI> did tel you of.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good morrow gentlemen to all at once.</L>
<L>How now <HI>Polidor,</HI> what man still in loue?</L>
<L>Euer wooing and canst thou neuer speed,</L>
<L>God send me better luck when I shall woo.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>I</HI> warrant you maister and you take my councell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why sirha, are you so cunning?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who I, twere better for you by fiue marke</L>
<L>And you could tel how to doo it as well as I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="7"/>
<SPEAKER>Pol.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would thy maister once were in the vaine,</L>
<L>To trie himselfe how he could woe a wench.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith I am euen now a going.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>I faith sir, my maisters going to this geere now.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pol.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whither in faith <HI>Ferando,</HI> tell me true.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<L>To bonie <HI>Kate,</HI> the patientst wench aliue</L>
<L>The diuel himselfe dares scarce venter to woo her,</L>
<L>Signior <HI>Alfonsos</HI> eldest daughter,</L>
<L>And he hath promisde me six thousand crownes</L>
<L>If I can win her once to be my wife,</L>
<L>And she and I must woo with skoulding sure,</L>
<L>And <HI>I</HI> will hold hir toot till she be wearie,</L>
<L>Or else Ile make her yeeld to graunt me loue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pol.</SPEAKER>
<L>How like you this <HI>Aurelius,</HI> I thinke he knew</L>
<L>Our mindes before we sent to him,</L>
<L>But tell me, when doo you meane to speake with her?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith presentlie, doo you but stand aside,</L>
<L>And I will make her father bring hir hither,</L>
<L>And she, and I, and he, will talke alone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pol.</SPEAKER>
<L>With al our heartes, Come <HI>Aurelius</HI></L>
<L>Let vs be gone and leaue him heere alone.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ho Signiour <HI>Alfonso,</HI> whose within there?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alfon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Signiour <HI>Ferando</HI> your welcome hartilie,</L>
<L>You are a stranger sir vnto my house.</L>
<L>Harke you sir, looke what I did promise you</L>
<L>Ile performe, if you get my daughters loue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then when I haue talkt a word or two with hir,</L>
<L>Doo you step in and giue her hand to me,</L>
<L>And tell her when the marriage daie shal be,</L>
<L>For I doo know she would be married faine,</L>
<L>And when our nuptiall rites be once performde</L>
<L>Let me alone to tame hir well enough,</L>
<L>Now call her foorth that I may speake with hir.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Kate.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="7"/>
<SPEAKER>Alfon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha <HI>Kate,</HI> Come hither wench &amp; list to me,</L>
<L>Vse this gentleman friendlie as thou canst.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<P>Twentie good morrowes to my louely <HI>Kate.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kate.</SPEAKER>
<P>You iest I am sure, is she yours alreadie?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<P>I tell thee <HI>Kate</HI> I know thou lou'st me well.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kate.</SPEAKER>
<P>The deuill you doo, who told you so?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<L>My mind sweet <HI>Kate</HI> doth say I am the man,</L>
<L>Must wed, and bed, and marrie bonnie <HI>Kate.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kate.</SPEAKER>
<P>Was euer seene so grose an asse as this?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, to stand so long and neuer get a kisse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kate.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hands off I say, and get you from this place;</L>
<L>Or I wil set my ten commandments in your face.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<L>I prethe doo kate; they say thou art a shrew,</L>
<L>And I like thee the better for I would haue thee so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kate.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let go my hand, for feare it reach your eare.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<P>No kate, this hand is mine and I thy loue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kate.</SPEAKER>
<P>In faith sir no the woodcock wants his taile.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<P>But yet his bil wil serue, if the other faile.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alfon.</SPEAKER>
<P>How now <HI>Ferando,</HI> what saies my daughter?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shees willing sir and loues me as hir life.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kate.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis for your skin then, but not to be your wife.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alfon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come hither <HI>Kate</HI> and let me giue thy hand</L>
<L>To him that I haue chosen for thy loue,</L>
<L>And thou to morrow shalt be wed to him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kate.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why father, what do you meane to do with me,</L>
<L>To giue me thus vnto this brainsick man,</L>
<L>That in his mood cares not to murder me?</L>
<L>She turnes aside and speakes.</L>
<L>But yet I will consent and marrie him,</L>
<L>For I methinkes haue liude too long a maid,</L>
<L>And match him to, or else his manhoods good.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alfon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Giue me thy hand <HI>Ferando</HI> loues thee wel,</L>
<L>And will with wealth and ease maintaine thy state.</L>
<L>Here <HI>Ferando</HI> take her for thy wife,</L>
<L><PB REF="8"/>And sunday next shall be your wedding day.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why so, did I not tell thee I should be the man</L>
<L>Father, I leaue my louelie <HI>Kate</HI> with you,</L>
<L>Prouide your selues against our mariage daie,</L>
<L>For I must hie me to my countrie house</L>
<L>In hast, to see prouision may be made,</L>
<L>To entertaine my <HI>Kate</HI> when she dooth come.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alfon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doo so, come <HI>Kate,</HI> why doost thou looke</L>
<L>So sad, be merrie wench thy wedding daies at hand.</L>
<L>Sonne fare you well, and see you keepe your promise.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Exit Alfonso</HI> and <HI>Kate.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<P>So, all thus farre goes well. Ho <HI>Saunder.</HI></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Saunder</HI> laughing.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Sander,</HI> I faith your a beast, <HI>I</HI> crie God hartilie</L>
<L>Mercie, my harts readie to run out of my bellie with</L>
<L>Laughing, I stood behind the doore all this while,</L>
<L>And heard what you said to hir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why didst thou think that I did not speake wel to hir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>You spoke like an asse to her, Ile tel you what,</L>
<L>And I had been there to haue woode hir, and had this</L>
<L>Cloke on that you haue, chud haue had her before she</L>
<L>Had gone a foot furder, and you talke of Woodcocks</L>
<L>with her, and I cannot tell you what.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wel sirha, &amp; yet thou seest I haue got her for all this.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>I marry twas more by hap then any good cunning</L>
<L>I hope sheele make you one of the head men of the parish shortly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wel sirha leaue your iesting and go to <HI>Polidors</HI> house,</L>
<L>The yong gentleman that was here with me,</L>
<L>And tell him the circumstance of all thou knowst,</L>
<L>Tell him on sunday next we must be married,</L>
<L>And if he aske thee whither I am gone,</L>
<L>Tell him into the countrie to my house,</L>
<L>And vpon sundaie Ile be heere againe.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ex. Ferando,</STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="8"/>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>I warrant you Maister feare not me</L>
<L>For dooing of my businesse.</L>
<L>Now hang him that has not a liuerie cote</L>
<L>To slash it out and swash it out amongst the proudest</L>
<L>On them. Why looke you now Ile scarce put vp</L>
<L>Plaine <HI>Saunder</HI> now at any of their handes, for and any</L>
<L>Bodie haue any thing to doo with my maister, straight</L>
<L>They come crouching vpon me, I beseech you good M.</L>
<L><HI>Saunder</HI> speake a good word for me, and then am I so</L>
<L>Stout and takes it vpon me, &amp; stands vpon my pantoflles</L>
<L>To them out of all crie, why I haue a life like a giant</L>
<L>Now, but that my maister hath such a pestilent mind</L>
<L>To a woman now a late, and I haue a prettie wench</L>
<L>To my sister, and I had thought to haue preferd my</L>
<L>Maister to her, and that would haue beene a good</L>
<L>Deale in my waie but that hees sped alreadie.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Polidors</HI> boie.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>Friend, well met.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>Souns, friend well met. I hold my life he sees</L>
<L>Not my maisters liuerie coat,</L>
<L>Plaine friend hop of my thum, kno you who we are.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Trust me sir it is the vse where I was borne,</L>
<L>To salute men after this manner, yet notwithstanding</L>
<L>If you be angrie with me for calling of you friend,</L>
<L>I am the more sorie for it, hoping the stile</L>
<L>Of a foole will make you amends for all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>The slaue is sorie for his fault, now we cannot be</L>
<L>Angrie, wel whats the matter that you would do with vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>Marry sir, I heare you pertain to signior <HI>Ferando.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>I</HI> and thou beest not blind thou maist see, <HI>Ecce signum,</HI> heere.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shall <HI>I</HI> intreat you to doo me a message to your Maister?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="9"/>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, it may be, &amp; you tel vs from whence you com.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>Marrie sir I serue yong <HI>Polidor</HI> your maisters friend.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>Do you serue him, and whats your name?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>My name sirha, I tell thee sirha is cald Catapie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>Cake and pie, O my teeth waters to haue a peece of thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why slaue wouldst thou eate me?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>Eate thee, who would not eate Cake and pie?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why villaine my name is Catapie,</L>
<L>But wilt thou tell me where thy maister is.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay thou must first tell me where thy maister is,</L>
<L>For I haue good newes for him, I can tell thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why see where he comes.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Polidor, Aurelius</HI> and <HI>Valeria.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come sweet <HI>Aurelius</HI> my faithfull friend,</L>
<L>Now will we go to see those louelie dames</L>
<L>Richer in beawtie then the orient pearle,</L>
<L>Whiter then is the Alpine Christall mould,</L>
<L>And farre more louelie then the terean plant,</L>
<L>That blushing in the aire turnes to a stone.</L>
<L>What <HI>Sander,</HI> what newes with you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>Marry sir my maister sends you word</L>
<L>That you must come to his wedding to morrow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pol.</SPEAKER>
<P>What, shall he be married then?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith <HI>I,</HI> you thinke he standes as long about it as you doo.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pol.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whither is thy maister gone now?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>Marrie hees gone to our house in the Countrie,</L>
<L>To make all thinges in a readinesse against my new</L>
<L>Mistresse comes thither, but heele come againe to morrowe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pol.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is suddainlie dispatcht belike,</L>
<L>Well, sirha boy, take <HI>Saunder</HI> in with you</L>
<L><PB REF="9"/>And haue him to the buttrie presentlie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will sir: come <HI>Saunder.</HI></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Saunder and the Boy.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurel.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Valeria</HI> as erste we did deuise,</L>
<L>Take thou thy lute and go to <HI>Alfonsos</HI> house,</L>
<L>And say that <HI>Polidor</HI> sent thee thither.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pol.</SPEAKER>
<L>I <HI>Valeria</HI> for he spoke to me,</L>
<L>To helpe him to some cunning Musition,</L>
<L>To teach his eldest daughter on the lute,</L>
<L>And thou I know will fit his turne so well</L>
<L>As thou shalt get great fauour at his handes,</L>
<L>Begon <HI>Valeria</HI> and say I sent thee to him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Valer</SPEAKER>
<P>I will sir and stay your comming at <HI>Alfonsos</HI> house.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Valeria</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now sweete <HI>Aurelius</HI> by this deuise</L>
<L>Shall we haue leisure for to courte our loues,</L>
<L>For whilst that she is learning on the lute,</L>
<L>Hir sisters may take time to steele abrode,</L>
<L>For otherwise shele keep them both within,</L>
<L>And make them worke whilst she hir selfe doth play,</L>
<L>But come lets go vnto <HI>Alfonsos</HI> house,</L>
<L>And see how <HI>Valeria</HI> and <HI>Kate</HI> agreese,</L>
<L>I doute his Musick skarse will please his skoller,</L>
<L>But stay here comes <HI>Alfonso.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Alfonso</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alfonso.</SPEAKER>
<L>What M. <HI>Polidor</HI> you are well mett,</L>
<L>I thanke you for the man you sent to me,</L>
<L>A good Musition I thinke he is,</L>
<L>I haue set my daughter and him togither,</L>
<L>But is this gentellman a frend of youres?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pol.</SPEAKER>
<L>He is, I praie you sir bid him welcome,</L>
<L>He's a wealthie Marchants sonne of <HI>Cestus.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alfonso.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your welcom sir and if my house aforde</L>
<L><PB REF="10"/>You any thing that may content your mind,</L>
<L>I pray you sir make bold with me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurel.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thanke you sir, and if what I haue got,</L>
<L>By marchandise or trauell on the seas,</L>
<L>Sattins or lawnes or azure colloured silke,</L>
<L>Or pretious firie pointed stones of Indie,</L>
<L>You shall command both them my selfe and all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alfon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thanks gentle sir, <HI>Polidor</HI> take him in,</L>
<L>And bid him welcome to vnto my house,</L>
<L>For thou I thinke must be my second sonne,</L>
<L><HI>Ferando, Polidor</HI> doost thou not know</L>
<L>Must marry <HI>Kate,</HI> and to morrow is the day.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pol.</SPEAKER>
<P>Such newes I heard, and <HI>I</HI> came now to know.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alfon.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Polidor</HI> tis true, goe let me alone,</L>
<L>For I must see against the bridegroome come,</L>
<L>That all thinges be according to his mind,</L>
<L>And so Ile leaue you for an houre or two.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come then <HI>Aurcleus</HI> come in with me,</L>
<L>And weele go sit a while and chat with them,</L>
<L>And after bring them foorth to take the aire.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Then <HI>Slie</HI> speakes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Slie.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Sim,</HI> when will the foole come againe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lord.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heele come againe my Lord anon.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Slie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gis some more drinke here, souns wheres</L>
<L>The Tapster, here <HI>Sim</HI> eate some of these things.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lord.</SPEAKER>
<P>So I doo my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Slie.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here <HI>Sim,</HI> I drinke to thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lord.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord heere comes the plaiers againe,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Slie.</SPEAKER>
<P>O braue, heers two fine gentlewomen.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Valeria</HI> with a Lute and <HI>Kate</HI> with him.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vale.</SPEAKER>
<L>The sencelesse trees by musick haue bin moou'd</L>
<L>And at the sound of pleasant tuned strings,</L>
<L><PB REF="10"/>Haue sauage beastes hung downe their listning heads,</L>
<L>As though they had beene cast into a trance.</L>
<L>Then it may be that she whom nought can please,</L>
<L>With musickes sound in time may be surprisde,</L>
<L>Come louely mistresse will you take your lute,</L>
<L>And play the lesson that I taught you last?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kate.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is no matter whether I doo or no,</L>
<L>For trust me <HI>I</HI> take no great delight in it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vale.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would sweet mistresse that it laie in me,</L>
<L>To helpe you to that thing thats your delight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kate.</SPEAKER>
<L>In you with a pestlence, are you so kind?</L>
<L>Then make a night cap of your fiddles case,</L>
<L>To warme your head, and hide your filthie face.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>If that sweet mistresse were your harts content,</L>
<L>You should command a greater thing then that,</L>
<L>Although it were ten times to my disgrace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kate.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your so kind twere pittie you should be hang'd,</L>
<L>And yet methinkes the foole dooth looke asquint.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why mistresse doo you mocke me?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kate.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, but I meane to moue thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, will you plaie a little?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kate.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, giue me the Lute.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>She plaies.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<P>That stop was false, play it againe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kate.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then mend it thou, thou filthy asse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<P>What, doo you bid me kisse your arse?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kate.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now iack sause, your a iollie mate,</L>
<L>Your best be still least I crosse your pate,</L>
<L>And make your musicke flie about your eares,</L>
<L>Ile make it and your foolish coxcombe meet.</L>
<L>She offers to strike him with the lute.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hold mistresse, souns wil you breake my lute?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kate.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>I</HI> on thy head, and if thou speake to me,</L>
<L><PB REF="11"/>There take it vp and fiddle somewhere else,</L>
<L>She throwes it downe.</L>
<L>And see you come no more into this place,</L>
<L>Least that I clap your fiddle on your face.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ex. Kate.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Souns, teach hir to play vpon the lute?</L>
<L>The deuill shal teach her first, I am glad shees gone,</L>
<L>For I was neare so fraid in all my life,</L>
<L>But that my lute should flie about mine eares,</L>
<L>My maister shall teach her his selfe for me,</L>
<L>For Ile keepe me far enough without hir reach,</L>
<L>For he and <HI>Polydor</HI> sent me before</L>
<L>To be with her and teach her on the lute,</L>
<L>Whilst they did court the other gentlewomen,</L>
<L>And heere methinkes they come togither.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Aurelius, Polidor, Emelia,</HI> and <HI>Philena.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pol.</SPEAKER>
<P>How now <HI>Valeria,</HI> whears your mistresse?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<P>At the vengeance I thinke and no where else.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why <HI>Valeria,</HI> will she not learne apace?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes berlady she has learnt too much already,</L>
<L>And that I had felt had I not spoke hir faire,</L>
<L>But she shall neare be learnt for me againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well <HI>Valeria</HI> go to my chamber,</L>
<L>And beare him companie that came to daie</L>
<L>From <HI>Cestus,</HI> where our aged father dwels.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ex. Valeria.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come faire <HI>Emelia</HI> my louelie loue,</L>
<L>Brighter then the burnisht pallace of the sunne,</L>
<L>The eie-sight of the glorious firmament,</L>
<L>In whose bright lookes sparkles the radiant fire,</L>
<L>Wilie <HI>Prometheus</HI> slilie stole from <HI>Ioue,</HI></L>
<L>Infusing breath, life, motion, soule,</L>
<L>To euerie obiect striken by thine eies.</L>
<L>Oh faire <HI>Emelia</HI> I pine for thee,</L>
<L>And either must enioy thy loue, or die.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="11"/>
<SPEAKER>Eme.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fie man, I know you will not die for loue:</L>
<L>Ah <HI>Polidor</HI> thou needst not to complaine,</L>
<L>Eternall heauen sooner be dissolude,</L>
<L>And all that pearseth Phebus siluer eie,</L>
<L>Before such hap befall to <HI>Polidor.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thanks faire <HI>Emelia</HI> for these sweet words,</L>
<L>But what saith <HI>Phylena</HI> to hir friend?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phyle.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why I am buying marchandise of him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mistresse you shall not need to buie of me,</L>
<L>For when I crost the bubling Canibey,</L>
<L>And sailde along the Cristall Helispont,</L>
<L>I filde my cofers of the wealthie mines,</L>
<L>Where I did cause Millions of labouring Moores</L>
<L>To vndermine the cauernes of the earth,</L>
<L>To seeke for strange and new found pretious stones,</L>
<L>And diue into the sea to gather pearle,</L>
<L>As faire as <HI>Iuno</HI> offered <HI>Priams</HI> sonne,</L>
<L>And you shall take your liberall choice of all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phyle.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>I</HI> thanke you sir and would <HI>Phylena</HI> might</L>
<L>In any curtesie requite you so,</L>
<L>As she with willing hart could well bestow.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Alfonso.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alfon.</SPEAKER>
<P>How now daughters, is <HI>Ferando</HI> come?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eme.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not yet father, I wonder he staies so long.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alfon.</SPEAKER>
<P>And wheres your sister that she is not heere?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phyle.</SPEAKER>
<L>She is making of hir readie father</L>
<L>To goe to church and if that he were come.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pol.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>I</HI> warrant you heele not be long awaie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alfon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Go daughters get you in, and bid your</L>
<L>Sister prouide her selfe against that we doo come,</L>
<L>And see you goe to church along with vs.</L>
<STAGE><HI>Exit Philena</HI> and <HI>Emelia.</HI></STAGE>
<L>I maruell that <HI>Ferando</HI> comes not away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="12"/>
<SPEAKER>Pol.</SPEAKER>
<L>His Tailor it may be hath bin too slacke,</L>
<L>In his apparrell which he meanes to weare,</L>
<L>For no question but some fantasticke sutes</L>
<L>He is determined to weare to day,</L>
<L>And richly powdered with pretious stones,</L>
<L>Spotted with liquid gold, thick set with pearle,</L>
<L>And such he meanes shall be his wedding sutes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alfon.</SPEAKER>
<L>I carde not I what cost he did bestow,</L>
<L>In gold or silke, so he himselfe were heere,</L>
<L>For I had rather lose a thousand crownes,</L>
<L>Then that he should deceiue vs heere to daie,</L>
<L>But soft I thinke I see him come.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Ferando</HI> baselie attired, and a red cap on his head.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Godmorow father, <HI>Polidor</HI> well met,</L>
<L>You wonder I know that I haue staid so long.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alfon.</SPEAKER>
<L>I marrie son, we were almost perswaded,</L>
<L>That we should scarse haue had our bridegroome heere,</L>
<L>But say, why art thou thus basely attired?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thus richlie father you should haue said,</L>
<L>For when my wife and I am married once,</L>
<L>Shees such a shrew, if we should once fal out,</L>
<L>Sheele pul my costlie sutes ouer mine eares,</L>
<L>And therefore am I thus attired awhile,</L>
<L>For manie thinges I tell you's in my head,</L>
<L>And none must know thereof but <HI>Kate</HI> and <HI>I,</HI></L>
<L>For we shall liue like lammes and Lions sure,</L>
<L>Nor lammes to Lions neuer was so tame,</L>
<L>If once they lie within the Lions pawes</L>
<L>As <HI>Kate</HI> to me if we were married once,</L>
<L>And therefore come let vs to church presently.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fie <HI>Ferando</HI> not thus atired for shame,</L>
<L>Come to my Chamber and there sute thy selfe,</L>
<L><PB REF="12"/>Of twentie sutes that I did neuer were▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tush <HI>Polidor</HI> I haue as many sutes</L>
<L>Fantasticke made to fit my humor so</L>
<L>As any in Athens and as richlie wrought</L>
<L>As was the Massie Robe that late adornd,</L>
<L>The stately legate of the Persian King,</L>
<L>And this from them haue I made choise to weare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alfon.</SPEAKER>
<L>I prethie <HI>Ferando</HI> let me intreat</L>
<L>Before thou goste vnto the church with vs,</L>
<L>To put some other sute vpon thy backe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not for the world if I might gaine it so,</L>
<L>And therefore take me thus or not at all,</L>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Kate.</HI></STAGE>
<L>But soft se where my <HI>Kate</HI> doth come,</L>
<L>I must salute hir: how fares my louely <HI>Kate?</HI></L>
<L>What art thou readie? shall we go to church?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kate.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not I with one so mad, so basely tirde,</L>
<L>To marrie such a filthie slauish groome,</L>
<L>That as it seemes sometimes is from his wits,</L>
<L>Or else he would not thus haue come to vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tush <HI>Kate</HI> these words addes greater loue in me</L>
<L>And makes me thinke thee fairrer then before,</L>
<L>Sweete <HI>Kate</HI> the louelier then Dianas purple robe,</L>
<L>Whiter then are the snowie Apenis,</L>
<L>Or icie haire that groes on Boreas chin.</L>
<L>Father I sweare by Ibis golden beake,</L>
<L>More faire and Radiente is my bonie <HI>Kate,</HI></L>
<L>Then siluer Zanthus when he doth imbrace,</L>
<L>The ruddie Simies at Idas feete,</L>
<L>And care not thou swete <HI>Kate</HI> how I be clad,</L>
<L>Thou shalt haue garments wrought of Median silke,</L>
<L>Enchast with pretious Iewells fecht from far,</L>
<L>By Italian Marchants that with Russian stemes,</L>
<L>Plous vp huge sorrowes in the <HI>Terren Maine,</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="13"/>And better farre my louely <HI>Kate</HI> shall weare,</L>
<L>Then come sweet loue and let vs to the church,</L>
<L>For this I sweare shall be my wedding sute.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt omnes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alfon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come gentlemen go along with vs,</L>
<L>For thus doo what we can he will be wed.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Polidors</HI> boy and <HI>Sander.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come hither sirha boy.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>Boy; oh disgrace to my person, souns boy</L>
<L>Of your face, you haue many boies with such</L>
<L>Pickadeuantes I am sure, souns would you</L>
<L>Not haue a bloudie nose for this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, come, I did but iest, where is that</L>
<L>Same peece of pie that I gaue thee to keepe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>The pie? I you haue more minde of your bellie</L>
<L>Then to go see what your maister dooes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tush tis no matter man I prethe giue it me,</L>
<L>I am verie hungry I promise thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why you may take it and the deuill burst</L>
<L>You with it, one cannot saue a bit after supper,</L>
<L>But you are alwaies readie to munch it vp.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why come man, we shall haue good cheere</L>
<L>Anon at the bridehouse, for your maisters gone to</L>
<L>Church to be married alreadie, and thears</L>
<L>Such cheere as passeth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>O braue, I would I had eate no meat this week,</L>
<L>For I haue neuer a corner left in my bellie</L>
<L>To put a venson pastie in, I thinke I shall burst my selfe</L>
<L>With eating, for Ile so cram me downe the tarts</L>
<L>And the marchpaines, out of all crie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, but how wilt thou doo now thy maisters</L>
<L>Married, thy mistresse is such a deuill, as sheele make</L>
<L>Thee forget thy eating quickly, sheele beat thee so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="13"/>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let my maister alone with hir for that, for</L>
<L>Heele make hir tame wel inough ere longe I warent thee</L>
<L>For he's such a churle waxen now of late that and he be</L>
<L>Neuer so little angry he thums me out of all crie,</L>
<L>But in my minde sirra the yongest is a verie</L>
<L>Prettie wench, and if I thought thy maister would</L>
<L>Not haue hir Ide haue a flinge at hir</L>
<L>My selfe, Ile see soone whether twill be a match</L>
<L>Or no: and it will not Ile set the matter</L>
<L>Hard for my selfe I warrant thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sounes you slaue will you be a Riuall with</L>
<L>My maister in his loue, speake but such</L>
<L>Another worde and Ile cut off one of thy legges.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, cruell iudgement, nay then sirra,</L>
<L>My tongue shall talke no more to you, marry my</L>
<L>Timber shall tell the trustie message of his maister,</L>
<L>Euen on the very forehead on thee, thou abusious</L>
<L>Villaine, therefore prepare thy selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come hither thou Imperfecksious slaue in</L>
<L>Regard of thy beggery, holde thee theres</L>
<L>Twoshillings for thee? to pay for the</L>
<L>Healing of thy left legge which I meane</L>
<L>Furiously to inuade or to maime at the least.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>O supernodicall foule? well Ile take your</L>
<L>two shillinges but Ile barre striking at legges.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not I, for Ile strike any where.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here here take your two shillings again</L>
<L>Ile see thee hangd ere Ile fight with thee,</L>
<L>I gat a broken shin the other day,</L>
<L>Tis not, whole yet and therefore Ile not fight</L>
<L>Come come why should we fall out?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well sirray your faire words hath something</L>
<L>Alaied my Coller: I am content for this once</L>
<L>To put it vp and be frends with thee,</L>
<L><PB REF="14"/>But soft see where they come all from church,</L>
<L>Belike they be Married allredy.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Ferando and Kate and Alfonso and Polidor and Emelia and Aurelius and Philema.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Father farwell, my <HI>Kate</HI> and I must home,</L>
<L>Sirra go make ready my horse presentlie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alfon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your horse! what son I hope you doo but iest,</L>
<L>I am sure you will not go so suddainly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kate.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let him go or tarry I am resolu'de to stay,</L>
<L>And not to trauell on my wedding day.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tut <HI>Kate</HI> I tell thee we must needes go home,</L>
<L>Villaine hast thou saddled my horse?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>Which horse, your curtall?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sounes you slaue stand you prating here?</L>
<L>Saddell the bay gelding for your Mistris.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kate</SPEAKER>
<P>Not for me: for Ile not go.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>The ostler will not let me haue him, you owe ten pence▪</L>
<L>For his meate, and 6 pence for stuffing my mistris saddle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here villaine go pay him straight.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shall I giue them another pecke of lauender.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<P>Out slaue and bring them presently to the dore</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alfon.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why son I hope at least youle dine with vs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>I pray you maister lets stay till dinner be don.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sounes villaine art thou here yet?</L>
<STAGE>Ex. Sander.</STAGE>
<L>Come <HI>Kate</HI> our dinner is prouided at home.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kate.</SPEAKER>
<L>But not for me, for here I meane to dine.</L>
<L>Ile haue my will in this as well as you,</L>
<L>Though you in madding mood would leaue your frends</L>
<L>Despite of you Ile tarry with them still.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<L>I <HI>Kate</HI> so thou shalt but at some other time,</L>
<L>When as thy sisters here shall be espousd,</L>
<L>Then thou and I will keepe our wedding day,</L>
<L>In better sort then now we can prouide,</L>
<L><PB REF="14"/>For here <HI>I</HI> promise thee before them all,</L>
<L>We will ere long returne to them againe,</L>
<L>Come <HI>Kate</HI> stand not on termes we will awaie,</L>
<L>This is my day, to morrow thou shalt rule,</L>
<L>And I will doo what euer thou commandes.</L>
<L>Gentlemen farwell, wele take our leues,</L>
<L>It will be late before that we come home.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Ferando and Kate.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pol.</SPEAKER>
<P>Farwell <HI>Ferando</HI> since you will be gone.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alfon.</SPEAKER>
<P>So mad a cupple did I neuer see.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Emel.</SPEAKER>
<P>They're euen as well macht as I would wish.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phile.</SPEAKER>
<L>And yet I hardly thinke that he can tame her.</L>
<L>For when he has don she will do what she list.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Her manhood then is good I do beleeue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pol.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Aurelius</HI> or else I misse my marke,</L>
<L>Her toung will walke if she doth hold her handes,</L>
<L><HI>I</HI> am in dout ere halfe a month be past</L>
<L>Hele curse the priest that married him so soone,</L>
<L>And yet it may be she will be reclaimde,</L>
<L>For she is verie patient grone of late.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alfon.</SPEAKER>
<L>God hold it that it may continue still,</L>
<L>I would be loth that they should disagree,</L>
<L>But he I hope will holde her in a while.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Within this two daies I will ride to him,</L>
<L>And see how louingly they do agree.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alfon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now <HI>Aurelius</HI> what say you to this,</L>
<L>What haue you sent to <HI>Cestus</HI> as you said,</L>
<L>To certifie your father of your loue,</L>
<L>For I would gladlie he would like of it,</L>
<L>And if he be the man you tell to me,</L>
<L><HI>I</HI> gesse he is a Marchant of great wealth.</L>
<L>And <HI>I</HI> haue seene him oft at <HI>Athens</HI> here,</L>
<L>And for his sake assure thee thou art welcome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pol.</SPEAKER>
<P>And so to me whilest <HI>Polidor</HI> doth liue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="15"/>
<SPEAKER>Aurel.</SPEAKER>
<L>I find it so right worthie gentlemen,</L>
<L>And of what worth your frendship I esteme,</L>
<L>I leue censure of your seuerall thoughts,</L>
<L>But for requitall of your fauours past,</L>
<L>Rests yet behind, which when occasion serues</L>
<L>I vow shalbe remembred to the full,</L>
<L>And for my fathers comming to this place,</L>
<L>I do expect within this weeke at most.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alfon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Inough <HI>Aurelieus?</HI> but we forget</L>
<L>Our Marriage dinner now the bride is gon,</L>
<L>Come let vs se what there they left behind.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Omnes</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Sanders with two or three seruing men</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come sirs prouide all thinges as fast as you can,</L>
<L>For my Masters hard at hand and my new Mistris</L>
<L>And all, and he sent me before to see all thinges redy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Welcome home <HI>Sander</HI> sirra how lookes our</L>
<L>New Mistris they say she's a plagie shrew.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>I and that thou shalt find I can tell thee and thou</L>
<L>Dost not please her well, why my Maister</L>
<L>Has such a doo with hir as it passeth and he's euen</L>
<L>like a madman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Will.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why <HI>Sander</HI> what dos he say.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why Ile tell you what: when they should</L>
<L>Go to church to be maried he puts on an olde</L>
<L>Ierkin and a paire of canuas breeches downe to the</L>
<L>Small of his legge and a red cap on his head and he</L>
<L>Lookes as thou wilt burst thy selfe with laffing</L>
<L>When thou seest him: he's ene as good as a</L>
<L>Foole for me: and then when they should go to dinner</L>
<L>He made me Saddle the horse and away he came.</L>
<L>And nere tarried for dinner and therefore you had best</L>
<L>Get supper reddy against they come, for</L>
<L><PB REF="15"/>They be hard at hand <HI>I</HI> am sure by this time.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sounes see where they be all redy.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Ferando and Kate.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now welcome <HI>Kate:</HI> wher'es these villains</L>
<L>Here, what? not supper yet vppon the borde:</L>
<L>Nor table spred nor nothing don at all,</L>
<L>Wheres that villaine that I sent before.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now, <HI>adsum,</HI> sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come hether you villaine Ile cut your nose,</L>
<L>You Rogue: helpe me of with my bootes: wilt please</L>
<L>You to lay the cloth? sounes the villaine</L>
<L>Hurts my foote? pull easely I say; yet againe.</L>
<STAGE>He beates them all. They couer the bord and fetch in the meate.</STAGE>
<L>Sounes? burnt and skorcht who drest this meate?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Will.</SPEAKER>
<L>Forsouth Iohn cooke.</L>
<L>He throwes downe the table and meate</L>
<L>and all, and beates them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Go you villaines bringe you me such meate,</L>
<L>Out of my sight I say and beare it hence,</L>
<L>Come <HI>Kate</HI> wele haue other meate prouided,</L>
<L>Is there a fire in my chamber sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>I</HI> forsooth.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Ferando and Kate.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Manent</HI> seruingmen and eate vp all the meate.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sounes? I thinke of my conscience my Masters</L>
<L>Mad since he was maried.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Will.</SPEAKER>
<L>I laft what a boxe he gaue <HI>Sander</HI></L>
<L>For pulling of his bootes.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Ferando</HI> againe.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>I hurt his foote for the nonce man.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did you so you damned villaine.</L>
<STAGE>He beates them all out againe.</STAGE>
<L>This humor must I holde me to a while,</L>
<L><PB REF="16"/>To bridle and hold backe my headstrong wife,</L>
<L>With curbes of hunger: ease: and want of sleepe,</L>
<L>Nor sleepe nor meate shall she inioie to night,</L>
<L>Ile mew her vp as men do mew their hawkes,</L>
<L>And make her gentlie come vnto the lure,</L>
<L>Were she as stuborne or as full of strength</L>
<L>As were the <HI>Thracian</HI> horse <HI>Alcides</HI> tamde,</L>
<L>That King <HI>Egeus</HI> fed with flesh of men,</L>
<L>Yet would I pull her downe and make her come</L>
<L>As hungry hawkes do flie vnto there lure.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Aurelius and Valeria.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurel.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Valeria</HI> attend: I haue a louely loue,</L>
<L>As bright as is the heauen cristalline,</L>
<L>As faire as is the milke white way of Ioue,</L>
<L>As chast as <HI>Phoebe</HI> in her sommer sportes,</L>
<L>As softe and tender as the asure downe,</L>
<L>That circles <HI>Cithereas</HI> siluer doues.</L>
<L>Her do <HI>I</HI> meane to make my louely bride,</L>
<L>And in her bed to breath the sweete content,</L>
<L>That <HI>I</HI> thou knowst long time haue aimed at.</L>
<L>Now <HI>Valeria</HI> it rests in thee to helpe</L>
<L>To compasse this, that <HI>I</HI> might gaine my loue,</L>
<L>Which easilie thou maist performe at will,</L>
<L>If that the marchant which thou toldst me of,</L>
<L>Will as he sayd go to <HI>Alfonsos</HI> house,</L>
<L>And say he is my father, and there with all</L>
<L>Pas ouer certaine deedes of land to me,</L>
<L>That I thereby may gaine my hearts desire,</L>
<L>And he is promised reward of me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Feare not my Lord Ile fetch him straight to you,</L>
<L>For hele do any thing that you command,</L>
<L>But tell me my Lord, is <HI>Ferando</HI> married then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurel.</SPEAKER>
<L>He is: and <HI>Polidor</HI> shortly shall be wed,</L>
<L>And he meanes to tame his wife erelong.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="16"/>
<SPEAKER>Vale.</SPEAKER>
<P>He saies so.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith he's gon vnto the taming schoole.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<P>The taming schoole▪ why is there such a place?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurel.</SPEAKER>
<P>I: and <HI>Ferando</HI> is the Maister of the schoole.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thats rare: but what <HI>decorum</HI> dos he vse?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith I know not: but by som odde deuise</L>
<L>Or other, but come <HI>Valeria</HI> I long to see the man,</L>
<L>By whome we must comprise our plotted drift,</L>
<L>That I may tell him what we haue to doo.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then come my Lord and I will bring you to him straight.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Agreed, then lets go.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Sander and his Mistres.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come Mistris.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kate.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Sander</HI> I prethe helpe me to some meate,</L>
<L>I am so faint that I can scarsely stande.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>I marry mistris but you know my maister</L>
<L>Has giuen me a charge that you must eate nothing,</L>
<L>But that which he himselfe giueth you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kate.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why man thy Maister needs neuer know it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>You say true indede: why looke you Mistris,</L>
<L>What say you to a peese of beeffe and mustard now?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kate.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why I say tis excellent meate, canst thou helpe me to some?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, I could helpe you to some but that</L>
<L>I doubt the mustard is too collerick for you,</L>
<L>But what say you to a sheepes head and garlick?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kate.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why any thing, I care not what it be.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>I but the garlike I doubt will make your breath</L>
<L>stincke, and then my Maister will course me for letting</L>
<L>You eate it: But what say you to a fat Capon?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kate.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thats meate for a King sweet <HI>Sander</HI> helpe</L>
<L>Me to some of it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay berlady then tis too deere for vs, we must</L>
<L><PB REF="17"/>Not meddle with the Kings meate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kate</SPEAKER>
<L>Out villaine dost thou mocke me,</L>
<L>Take that for thy sawsinesse.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>She beates him.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sounes are you so light fingerd with a murrin,</L>
<L>Ile keepe you fasting for it this two daies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kate.</SPEAKER>
<L>I tell thee villaine Ile tear the flesh of</L>
<L>Thy face and eate it and thou prates to me thus.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here comes my Maister now hele course you.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Ferando</HI> with a peece of meate vppon his daggers point and <HI>Polidor</HI> with him.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Se here <HI>Kate</HI> I haue prouided meate for thee,</L>
<L>Here take it: what ist not worthie thankes,</L>
<L>Goe sirra? take it awaie againe you shallbe</L>
<L>Thankefull for the next you haue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kate</SPEAKER>
<P>Why I thanke you for it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay now tis not worth a pin go sirray and take</L>
<L>It hence I say.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes sir Ile Carrie it hence: Maister let her</L>
<L>Haue none for she can fight as hungrie as she is.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pol.</SPEAKER>
<L>I pray you sir let it stand, for Ile eate</L>
<L>Some with her my selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well sirra set it downe againe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kate.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay nay I pray you let him take it hence,</L>
<L>And keepe it for your owne diete for Ile none,</L>
<L>Ile nere be beholding to you for your Meate,</L>
<L>I tell thee flatlie here vnto the thy teethe</L>
<L>Thou shalt not keepe me nor feede me as thou list,</L>
<L>For I will home againe vnto my fathers house.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, when you'r meeke and gentell but not</L>
<L>Before, I know your stomack is not yet come downe,</L>
<L>Therefore no maruell thou canste not eate,</L>
<L>And I will goe vnto your Fathers house,</L>
<L>Come <HI>Polidor</HI> let vs goe in againe,</L>
<L><PB REF="17"/>And <HI>Kate</HI> come in with vs I know ere longe,</L>
<L>That thou and I shall louingly agree.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ex. Omnes</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Aurelius Valeria and Phylotus the Marchant.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now Senior <HI>Phylotus,</HI> we will go</L>
<L>Vnto <HI>Alfonsos</HI> house, and be sure you say</L>
<L>As I did tell you, concerning the man</L>
<L>That dwells in <HI>Cestus,</HI> whose son I said I was,</L>
<L>For you doo very much resemble him,</L>
<L>And feare not: you may be bold to speake your mind.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phylo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I warrant you sir take you no care,</L>
<L>Ile vse my selfe so cunning in the cause,</L>
<L>As you shall soone inioie your harts delight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thankes sweet <HI>Phylotus,</HI> then stay you here,</L>
<L>And I will go and fetch him hither straight.</L>
<L>Ho, Senior <HI>Alfonso:</HI> a word with you.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Alfonso.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alfon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whose there? what <HI>Aurelius</HI> whats the matter</L>
<L>That you stand so like a stranger at the doore?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurel.</SPEAKER>
<L>My father sir is newly come to towne,</L>
<L>And I haue brought him here to speake with you,</L>
<L>Concerning those matters that <HI>I</HI> tolde you of,</L>
<L>And he can certefie you of the truth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alfon.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is this your father? you are welcome sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phylo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thankes <HI>Alfonso,</HI> for thats your name <HI>I</HI> gesse,</L>
<L>I vnderstand my son hath set his mind</L>
<L>And bent his liking to your daughters loue,</L>
<L>And for because he is my only son,</L>
<L>And I would gladly that he should doo well,</L>
<L>I tell you sir, I not mislike his choise,</L>
<L>If you agree to giue him your consent,</L>
<L>He shall haue liuing to maintaine his state,</L>
<L><PB REF="18"/>Three hundred poundes a yeere I will assure</L>
<L>To him and to his heyres, and if they do ioyne,</L>
<L>And knit themselues in holy wedlock bande,</L>
<L>A thousand massie in gots of pure gold,</L>
<L>And twise as many bares of siluer plate,</L>
<L>I freely giue him, and in writing straight,</L>
<L>I will confirme what I haue said in wordes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alfon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Trust me I must commend your liberall mind,</L>
<L>And louing care you beare vnto your son,</L>
<L>And here I giue him freely my consent,</L>
<L>As for my daughter I thinke he knowes her mind,</L>
<L>And I will in large her dowrie for your sake.</L>
<L>And solemnise with ioie your nuptiall rites,</L>
<L>But is this gentleman of <HI>Cestus</HI> too?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurel.</SPEAKER>
<L>He is the <HI>Duke</HI> of <HI>Cestus</HI> thrise renowned son,</L>
<L>Who for the loue his honour beares to me:</L>
<L>Hath thus accompanied me to this place.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alfonso.</SPEAKER>
<L>You weare to blame you told me not before,</L>
<L>Pardon me my Lord, for if I had knowne</L>
<L>Your honour had bin here in place with me,</L>
<L>I would haue donne my dutie to your honour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thankes good <HI>Alfonso:</HI> but I did come to see</L>
<L>When as these marriage rites should be performed,</L>
<L>And if in these nuptialls you vouchsafe,</L>
<L>To honour thus the prince of <HI>Cestus</HI> frend,</L>
<L>In celebration of his spousall rites,</L>
<L>He shall remaine a lasting friend to you,</L>
<L>What saies <HI>Aurelius</HI> father.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phylo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I humbly thanke your honour good my Lord,</L>
<L>And ere we parte before your honor here:</L>
<L>Shall articles of such content be drawne,</L>
<L>As twixt our houses and poste<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ities,</L>
<L>Eternallie this league of peace shall last,</L>
<L>Inuiolat and pure on either part:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="18"/>
<SPEAKER>Alfonso.</SPEAKER>
<L>With all my heart, and if your honour please,</L>
<L>To walke along with vs vnto my house,</L>
<L>We will confirme these leagues of lasting loue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come then <HI>Aurelius</HI> I will go with you.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ex. omnes.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Ferando and Kate and Sander.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>Master the haberdasher has brought my</L>
<L>Mistresse home her cappe here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come hither sirra: what haue you there?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Habar.</SPEAKER>
<P>A veluet cappe sir and it please you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who spoake for it? didst thou <HI>Kate?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kate.</SPEAKER>
<L>What if I did, come hither sirra, giue me</L>
<L>The cap, Ile see if it will fit me.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>She sets it one hir head.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<L>O monstrous: why it becomes thee not,</L>
<L>Let me see it <HI>Kate:</HI> here sirra take it hence,</L>
<L>This cappe is out of fashion quite.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kate</SPEAKER>
<L>The fashion is good inough: belike you,</L>
<L>Meane to make a foole of me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why true he meanes to make a foole of thee,</L>
<L>To haue thee put on such a curtald cappe,</L>
<L>sirra begon with it.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter the <HI>Taylor</HI> with a gowne.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here is the <HI>Taylor</HI> too with my Mistris gowne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me see it <HI>Taylor:</HI> what with cuts and iagges?</L>
<L>Sounes you villaine, thou hast spoiled the gowne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taylor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why sir I made it as your man gaue me direc∣tion,</L>
<L>You may reade the note here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come hither sirra: <HI>Taylor</HI> reade the note.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taylor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Item a faire round compast cape.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thats true.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taylor.</SPEAKER>
<P>And a large truncke sleeue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="19"/>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thats a lie maister, I sayd two truncke sleeues.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well sir goe forward.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tailor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Item a loose bodied gowne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>Maister if euer I sayd loose bodies gowne,</L>
<L>Sew me in a seame and beate me to death,</L>
<L>With a bottome of browne thred.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tailor.</SPEAKER>
<P>I made it as the note bad me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>I say the note lies in his throate and thou too,</L>
<L>And thou sayst it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taylor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay nay nere be so hot sirra, for I feare you not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doost thou heare <HI>Taylor,</HI> thou hast braued</L>
<L>Many men: braue not me.</L>
<L>Thou'st faste many men.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taylor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>Face not me Ile nether be faste nor braued</L>
<L>At thy handes I can tell thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kate.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come come I like the fashion of it well enough,</L>
<L>Heres more a do then needs Ile haue it,</L>
<L>And if you do not like it hide your eies,</L>
<L>I thinke I shall haue nothing by your will.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<P>Go I say and take it vp for your maisters vse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>Souns: villaine not for thy life touch it not,</L>
<L>Souns, take vp my mistris gowne to his</L>
<L>Maisters vse?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well sir: whats your conceit of it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue a deeper conceite in it then you</L>
<L>thinke for, take vp my Mistris gowne</L>
<L>To his maisters vse?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Tailor</HI> come hether: for this time take it</L>
<L>Hence againe, and Ile content thee for thy paines.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taylor.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thanke you sir.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Taylor.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come <HI>Kate</HI> we now will go see thy fathers house</L>
<L>Euen in these honest meane abilliments,</L>
<L>Our purses shallbe rich, our garments plaine,</L>
<L><PB REF="19"/>To shrowd our bodies from the winter rage,</L>
<L>And thats inough, what should we care for more.</L>
<L>Thy sisters <HI>Kate</HI> to morrow must be wed,</L>
<L>And I haue promised them thou shouldst be there</L>
<L>The morning is well vp lets hast away,</L>
<L>It will be nine a clocke ere we come there.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kate.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nine a clock, why tis allreadie past two</L>
<L>In the after noone by all the clocks in the towne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<P>I say tis but nine a clock in the morning.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kate.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>I</HI> say tis tow a clock in the after noone.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<L>It shall be nine then ere we go to your fathers,</L>
<L>Come backe againe, we will not go to day.</L>
<L>Nothing but crossing of me still,</L>
<L>Ile haue you say as I doo ere you go.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt omnes.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Polidor, Emelia, Aurelius and Philema.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faire <HI>Emelia</HI> sommers sun bright Queene,</L>
<L>Brighter of hew then is the burning clime,</L>
<L>Where <HI>Phoebus</HI> in his bright aequator sits,</L>
<L>Creating gold and pressious minneralls,</L>
<L>What would <HI>Emelia</HI> doo? if I were forst</L>
<L>To leaue faire <HI>Athens</HI> and to range the world.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eme.</SPEAKER>
<L>Should thou assay to scale the seate of loue,</L>
<L>Mounting the suttle ayrie regions</L>
<L>Or be snacht vp as erste was <HI>Ganimed,</HI></L>
<L>Loue should giue winges vnto my swift desires,</L>
<L>And prune my thoughts that I would follow thee,</L>
<L>Or fall and perish as did <HI>Icarus.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweetly resolued faire <HI>Emelia,</HI></L>
<L>But would <HI>Phylema</HI> say as much to me,</L>
<L>If I should aske a question now of thee,</L>
<L>What if the duke of <HI>Cestus</HI> only son,</L>
<L>Which came with me vnto your fathers house,</L>
<L>Should seeke to git <HI>Phylemas</HI> loue from me,</L>
<L><PB REF="20"/>And make thee Duches of that stately towne,</L>
<L>Wouldst thou not then forsake me for his loue?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phyle.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not for great <HI>Neptune,</HI> no nor <HI>Ioue</HI> himselfe,</L>
<L>Will <HI>Phylema</HI> leaue <HI>Aurelius</HI> loue,</L>
<L>Could he install me <HI>Empres</HI> of the world,</L>
<L>Or make me Queene and guidres of the heauens,</L>
<L>Yet would <HI>I</HI> not exchange thy loue for his,</L>
<L>Thy company is poore <HI>Philemas</HI> heauen,</L>
<L>And without thee, heauen were hell to me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eme.</SPEAKER>
<L>And should my loue as erste did <HI>Hercules</HI></L>
<L>Attempt to passe the burning valtes of hell,</L>
<L>I would with piteous lookes and pleasing wordes,</L>
<L>As once did <HI>Orpheus</HI> with his harmony,</L>
<L>And rauishing sound of his melodious harpe,</L>
<L>Intreate grim <HI>Pluto</HI> and of him obtaine,</L>
<L>That thou mightest go and safe retourne againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phyle.</SPEAKER>
<L>And should my loue as earst <HI>Leander</HI> did,</L>
<L>Attempte to swimme the boyling helispont</L>
<L>For <HI>Heros</HI> loue: no towers of brasse should hold</L>
<L>But I would follow thee through those raging flouds,</L>
<L>With lockes disheuered and my brest all bare,</L>
<L>With bended knees vpon <HI>Abidas</HI> shoore,</L>
<L>I would with smokie sighes and brinish teares,</L>
<L>Importune <HI>Neptune</HI> and the watry Gods,</L>
<L>To send a guard of siluer scaled <HI>Dolphyns,</HI></L>
<L>With sounding <HI>Tritons</HI> to be our conuoy,</L>
<L>And to transport vs safe vnto the shore,</L>
<L>Whilst I would hang about thy louely necke,</L>
<L>Redoubling kisse on kisse vpon thy cheekes,</L>
<L>And with our pastime still the swelling waues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eme.</SPEAKER>
<L>Should <HI>Polidor</HI> as great <HI>Achilles</HI> did,</L>
<L>Onely imploy himselfe to follow armes,</L>
<L>Like to the warlike <HI>Amazonian</HI> Queene,</L>
<L><HI>Pentheselea Hectors</HI> paramore,</L>
<L><PB REF="20"/>Who foyld the bloudie <HI>Pirrhus</HI> murderous greeke,</L>
<L>Ile thrust my selfe amongst the thickest throngs,</L>
<L>And with my vtmost force assist my loue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phyle.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let <HI>Eole</HI> storme: be mild and quiet thou,</L>
<L>Let <HI>Neptune</HI> swell, be <HI>Aurelius</HI> calme and pleased,</L>
<L>I care not I, betide what may betide,</L>
<L>Let fates and fortune doo the worst they can,</L>
<L>I recke them not: they not discord with me,</L>
<L>Whilst that my loue and <HI>I</HI> do well agree▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweet <HI>Phylema</HI> bewties mynerall,</L>
<L>From whence the sun exhales his glorious shine,</L>
<L>And clad the heauen in thy reflected raies,</L>
<L>And now my liefest loue, the time drawes nie,</L>
<L>That <HI>Himen</HI> mounted in his saffron robe,</L>
<L>Must with his torches waight vpon thy traine,</L>
<L>As <HI>Hellens</HI> brothers on the horned Moone,</L>
<L>Now <HI>Iuno</HI> to thy number shall I adde,</L>
<L>The fairest bride that euer Marchant had.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come faire <HI>Emelia</HI> the preeste is gon,</L>
<L>And at the church your father and the reste,</L>
<L>Do stay to see our marriage rites performde,</L>
<L>And knit in sight of heauen this <HI>Gordian</HI> knot.</L>
<L>That teeth of fretting time may nere vntwist,</L>
<L>Then come faire loue and gratulate with me,</L>
<L>This daies content and sweet solemnity.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ex. Omnes</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Slie</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Sim</HI> must they be married now?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lord.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>I</HI> my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Ferando and Kate and Sander.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Slie.</SPEAKER>
<P>Looke <HI>Sim</HI> the foole is come againe now.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sirra go fetch our horsses forth, and bring</L>
<L>Them to the backe gate presentile.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will sir <HI>I</HI> warrant you,</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Sander.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come <HI>Kate</HI> the Moone shines cleere to night methinkes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="21"/>
<SPEAKER>Kate.</SPEAKER>
<L>The moone? why husband you are deceiud</L>
<L>It is the sun.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet againe: come backe againe it shall be</L>
<L>The moone ere we come at your fathers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kate.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why Ile say as you say it is the moone.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<P>Iesus saue the glorious moone.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kate.</SPEAKER>
<P>Iesus saue the glorious moone.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am glad <HI>Kate</HI> your stomack is come downe,</L>
<L>I know it well thou knowest it is the sun,</L>
<L>But I did trie to see if thou wouldst speake,</L>
<L>And crosse me now as thou hast donne before,</L>
<L>And trust me <HI>kate</HI> hadst thou not named the moone,</L>
<L>We had gon back againe as sure as death,</L>
<L>But soft whose this thats comming here.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter the <HI>Duke of Cestus</HI> alone.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thus all alone from <HI>Cestus</HI> am I come,</L>
<L>And left my princelie courte and noble traine,</L>
<L>To come to <HI>Athens,</HI> and in this disguise,</L>
<L>To see what course my son <HI>Aurelius</HI> takes,</L>
<L>But stay, heres some it may be Trauells thether,</L>
<L>Good sir can you derect me the way to <HI>Athens?</HI></L>
<STAGE><HI>Ferando</HI> speakes to the olde man.</STAGE>
<L>Faire louely maide yoong and affable,</L>
<L>More cleere of hew and far more beautifull,</L>
<L>Then pretious <HI>Sardonix</HI> or purple rockes,</L>
<L>Of <HI>Amithests</HI> or glistering <HI>Hiasinthe,</HI></L>
<L>More amiable farre then is the plain,</L>
<L>Where glistring <HI>Cepherus</HI> in siluer boures,</L>
<L>Gaseth vpon the Giant <HI>Andromede,</HI></L>
<L>Sweet <HI>Kate</HI> entertaine this louely woman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thinke the man is mad he calles me a woman.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="21"/>
<SPEAKER>Kate.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faire louely lady, bright and Christalline,</L>
<L>Bewteous and stately as the eie-traind bird,</L>
<L>As glorious as the morning washt with dew,</L>
<L>Within whose eies she takes her dawning beames,</L>
<L>And golden sommer sleepes vpon thy cheekes,</L>
<L>Wrap vp thy radiations in some cloud,</L>
<L>Least that thy bewty make this stately towne,</L>
<L>Inhabitable like the burning <HI>Zone,</HI></L>
<L>With sweet reflections of thy louely face.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>What is she mad to? or is my shape transformd▪</L>
<L>That both of them perswade me I am a woman,</L>
<L>But they are mad sure, and therefore Ile begon,</L>
<L>And leaue their companies for fear of harme,</L>
<L>And vnto <HI>Athens</HI> hast to seeke my son.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Duke.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why so <HI>Kate</HI> this was friendly done of thee,</L>
<L>And kindly too: why thus must we two liue,</L>
<L>One minde, one heart, and one content for both,</L>
<L>This good old man dos thinke that we are mad,</L>
<L>And glad he is I am sure, that he is gonne,</L>
<L>But come sweet <HI>Kate</HI> for we will after him,</L>
<L>And now perswade him to his shape againe.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ex. omnes.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Alfonso and Phylotus and Valeria, Polidor, Emelia, Aurelius and Phylema.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alfon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come louely sonnes your marriage rites performed,</L>
<L>Lets hie vs home to see what cheere we haue,</L>
<L>I wonder that <HI>Ferando</HI> and his wife</L>
<L>Comes not to see this great solemnitie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pol.</SPEAKER>
<L>No maruell if <HI>Ferando</HI> be away,</L>
<L>His wife I think hath troubled so his wits,</L>
<L><PB REF="22"/>That he remaines at home to keepe them warme,</L>
<L>For forward wedlocke as the prouer be sayes,</L>
<L>Hath brought him to his night cappe long agoe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phylo.</SPEAKER>
<L>But <HI>Polidor</HI> let my son and you take heede,</L>
<L>That <HI>Ferando</HI> say not ere long as much to you,</L>
<L>And now <HI>Alfonso</HI> more to shew my loue,</L>
<L>If vnto <HI>Cestus</HI> you do send your ships,</L>
<L>My selfe will fraught them with <HI>Arabian</HI> silkes,</L>
<L>Rich affrick spices <HI>Arras</HI> counter poines,</L>
<L>Muske <HI>Cassia:</HI> sweet smelling <HI>Ambergreece,</HI></L>
<L>Pearle, curroll▪ christall, iett, and iuorie,</L>
<L>To gratulate the fauors of my son,</L>
<L>And friendly loue that you haue shone to him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vale.</SPEAKER>
<L>And for to honour him and this faire bride,</L>
<STAGE>Enter the <HI>Duke of Cestus.</HI></STAGE>
<L>Ile yerly send you from my fathers courte,</L>
<L>Chests of refind suger seuerally,</L>
<L>Ten tunne of tunis wine, sucket sweet druges,</L>
<L>To celibrate and solemnise this day,</L>
<L>And custome free your marchants shall conuerse:</L>
<L>And interchange the profits of your land,</L>
<L>Sending you gold for brasse, siluer for leade,</L>
<L>Casses of silke for packes of woll and cloth,</L>
<L>To binde this friendship and confirme this league.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am glad sir that you would be so franke,</L>
<L>Are you become the <HI>Duke</HI> of <HI>Cestus</HI> son,</L>
<L>And reuels with my treasure in the towne,</L>
<L>Base villaine that thus dishonorest me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sounes it is the <HI>Duke</HI> what shall I doo,</L>
<L>Dishonour thee why, knowst thou what thou saist?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Her's no villaine: he will not know me now,</L>
<L>But what say you? haue you forgot me too?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phylo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why sir, are you acquainted with my son?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>With thyson? no trust me if he be thine,</L>
<L><PB REF="22"/>I pray you sir who am I?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pardon me father: humblie on my knees,</L>
<L>I do intreat your grace to heare me speake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace villaine: lay handes on them,</L>
<L>And send them to prison straight.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Phylotus and Valeria</HI> runnes away. Then <HI>Slie</HI> speakes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Slie.</SPEAKER>
<P>I say wele haue no sending to prison.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lord.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord this is but the play, theyr but in iest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Slie.</SPEAKER>
<L>I tell thee <HI>Sim</HI> wele haue no sending,</L>
<L>To prison thats flat: why <HI>Sim</HI> am not I <HI>Don Christo Vary?</HI></L>
<L>Therefore <HI>I</HI> say they shall not go to prison.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lord.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more they shall not my Lord,</L>
<L>They be run away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Slie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are they run away <HI>Sim?</HI> thats well,</L>
<L>Then gis some more drinke, and let them play againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lord.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Slie</HI> drinkes and then falls a sleepe.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ah trecherous boy that durst presume,</L>
<L>To wed thy selfe without thy fathers leaue,</L>
<L>I sweare by fayre <HI>Cintheas</HI> burning rayes,</L>
<L>By <HI>Merops</HI> head and by seauen mouthed <HI>Nile,</HI></L>
<L>Had I but knowne ere thou hadst wedded her,</L>
<L>Were in thy brest the worlds immortall soule,</L>
<L>This angrie sword should rip thy hatefull chest,</L>
<L>And hewd thee smaller then the <HI>Libian</HI> sandes,</L>
<L>Turne hence thy face: oh cruell impious boy,</L>
<L><HI>Alfonso</HI> I did not thinke you would presume,</L>
<L>To mach your daughter with my princely house,</L>
<L>And nere make me acquainted with the cause▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alfon.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord by heauens I sweare vnto your grace,</L>
<L><HI>I</HI> knew none other but <HI>Valeria</HI> your man,</L>
<L>Had bin the <HI>Duke</HI> of <HI>Cestus</HI> nobleson,</L>
<L><PB REF="23"/>Nor did my daughter I dare sweare for her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>That damned villaine that hath deluded me▪</L>
<L>Whome I did send guide vnto my son,</L>
<L>Oh that my furious force could cleaue the earth,</L>
<L>That I might muster bands of hellish feendes,</L>
<L>To rack his heart and teare his impious soule.</L>
<L>The ceaselesse turning of celestiall orbes,</L>
<L>Kindles not greater flames in flitting aire,</L>
<L>Then passionate anguish of my raging brest,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then let my death sweet father end your griefe,</L>
<L>For I it is that thus haue wrought your woes,</L>
<L>Then be reuengd on me for here I sweare,</L>
<L>That they are innocent of what I did,</L>
<L>Oh had <HI>I</HI> charge to cut of <HI>Hydraes</HI> hed,</L>
<L>To make the toplesse <HI>Alpes</HI> a champion field,</L>
<L>To kill vntamed monsters with my sword,</L>
<L>To trauell dayly in the hottest sun,</L>
<L>And watch in winter when the nightes be colde,</L>
<L><HI>I</HI> would with gladnesse vndertake them all,</L>
<L>And thinke the paine but pleasure that I felt,</L>
<L>So that my noble father at my returne,</L>
<L>Would but forget and pardon my offence,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phile.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me intreat your grace vpon my knees,</L>
<L>To pardon him and let my death discharge</L>
<L>The heauy wrath your grace hath vowd gainst him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pol.</SPEAKER>
<L>And good my Lord let vs intreat your grace,</L>
<L>To purge your stomack of this Melancholy,</L>
<L>Taynt not your princely minde with griefe my Lord,</L>
<L>But pardon and forgiue these louers faults,</L>
<L>That kneeling craue your gratious fauor here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Emel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Great prince of <HI>Cestus,</HI> let a womans wordes,</L>
<L>Intreat a pardon in your lordly brest,</L>
<L>Both for your princely son, and vs my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Aurelius</HI> stand vp I pardon thee,</L>
<L><PB REF="23"/>I see that vertue will haue enemies,</L>
<L>And fortune willbe thwarting honour still,</L>
<L>And you faire virgin too I am content,</L>
<L>To accept you for my daughter since tis don,</L>
<L>And see you princely vsde in <HI>Cestus</HI> courte.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phyle.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thankes good my Lord and I no longer liue,</L>
<L>Then <HI>I</HI> obey and honour you in all:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alfon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me giue thankes vnto your royall grace,</L>
<L>For this great honor don to me and mine,</L>
<L>And if your grace will walke vnto my house,</L>
<L><HI>I</HI> will in humblest maner I can, show</L>
<L>The eternall seruice I doo owe your grace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke</SPEAKER>
<L>Thanks good <HI>Alfonso:</HI> but I came alone,</L>
<L>And not as did beseeme the <HI>Cestian Duke,</HI></L>
<L>Nor would I haue it knowne within the towne,</L>
<L>That I was here and thus without my traine,</L>
<L>But as I came alone so will I go,</L>
<L>And leaue my son to solemnise his feast,</L>
<L>And ere't belong Ile come againe to you,</L>
<L>And do him honour as beseemes the son</L>
<L>Of mightie <HI>Ierobell</HI> the <HI>Cestian Duke,</HI></L>
<L>Till when Ile leaue you, Farwell <HI>Aurelius.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not yet my Lord, Ile bring you to your ship.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Omnes.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Slie</HI> sleepes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lord.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whose within there? come hither sirs my Lords</L>
<L>A sleepe againe: go take him easily vp,</L>
<L>And put him in his one apparell againe,</L>
<L>And lay him in the place where we did find him,</L>
<L>Iust vnderneath the alehouse side below,</L>
<L>But see you wake him not in any case.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>It shall be don my Lord come helpe to beare him hence,</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE><PB REF="24"/>Enter <HI>Ferando, Aurelius and Polidor and his boy and Valeria and Sander.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come gentlemen now that suppers donne,</L>
<L>How shall we spend the time till we go to bed?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith if you will in triall of our wiues,</L>
<L>Who will come sownest at their husbands call.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay then <HI>Ferando</HI> he must needes sit out,</L>
<L>For he may call I thinke till he be weary,</L>
<L>Before his wife will come before she list.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis well for you that haue such gentle wiues,</L>
<L>Yet in this triall will I not sit out,</L>
<L>It may be <HI>Kate</HI> will come as soone as yours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurel.</SPEAKER>
<P>My wife comes soonest for a hundred pound.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pol.</SPEAKER>
<L>I take it: Ile lay as much to youres,</L>
<L>That my wife comes as soone as I do send.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurel.</SPEAKER>
<P>How now <HI>Ferando</HI> you dare not lay belike.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why true I dare not lay indeede;</L>
<L>But how, so little mony on so sure a thing,</L>
<L><HI>A</HI> hundred pound: why I haue layd as much</L>
<L>Vpon my dogge, in running at a Deere,</L>
<L>She shall not come so farre for such a trifle,</L>
<L>But will you lay fiue hundred markes with me,</L>
<L>And whose wife soonest comes when he doth call,</L>
<L>And shewes her selfe most louing vnto him,</L>
<L>Let him inioye the wager I haue laid,</L>
<L>Now what say you? dare you aduenture thus?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pol.</SPEAKER>
<L>I weare it a thousand pounds I durst presume</L>
<L>On my wiues loue: and <HI>I</HI> will lay with thee.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Alfonso.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alfon.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now sons what in conference so hard,</L>
<L>May I without offence, know where abouts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="24"/>
<SPEAKER>Aurel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith father a waighty cause about our wiues</L>
<L>Fiue hundred markes already we haue layd,</L>
<L>And he whose wife doth shew most loue to him,</L>
<L>He must inioie the wager to himselfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alfon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why then <HI>Ferando</HI> he is sure to lose,</L>
<L>I promise thee son thy wife will hardly come,</L>
<L>And therefore I would not wish thee lay so much.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tush father were it ten times more,</L>
<L>I durst aduenture on my louely <HI>Kate,</HI></L>
<L>But if I lose Ile pay, and so shall you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Vpon mine honour if I loose Ile pay.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pol.</SPEAKER>
<P>And so will I vpon my faith I vow.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then sit we downe and let vs send for them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alfon.</SPEAKER>
<P>I promise thee <HI>Ferando</HI> I am afraid thou wilt lose</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile send for my wife first, <HI>Valeria</HI></L>
<L>Go bid your Mistris come to me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Valeria.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now for my hundred pound.</L>
<L>Would any lay ten hundred more with me,</L>
<L>I know I should obtaine it by her loue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<P>I pray God you haue not laid too much already.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Trust me <HI>Ferando</HI> I am sure you haue,</L>
<L>For you I dare presume haue lost it all.</L>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Valeria</HI> againe.</STAGE>
<L>Now sirra what saies your mistris?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<P>She is something busie but shele come anon.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why so, did not I tell you this before,</L>
<L>She is busie and cannot come.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurel.</SPEAKER>
<L>I pray God your wife send you so good an an∣swere</L>
<L>She may be busie yet she sayes shele come.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well well: <HI>Polidor</HI> send you for your wife.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="25"/>
<SPEAKER>Pol.</SPEAKER>
<P>Agreed <HI>Boy</HI> desire your mistris to come hither.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will sir</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ex. Boy.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<P>I so so he desiers her to come.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alfon.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Polidor</HI> I dare presume for thee,</L>
<L>I thinke thy wife will not deny to come.</L>
<L>And I do maruell much <HI>Aurelius,</HI></L>
<L>That your wife came not when you sent for her.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter the <HI>Boy</HI> againe▪</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pol.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now wheres your Mistris?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<L>She bad me tell you that she will not come,</L>
<L>And you haue any businesse, you must come to her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh monstrous intollerable presumption,</L>
<L>Worse then a blasing starre, or snow at midsommer,</L>
<L>Earthquakes or any thing vnseasonable,</L>
<L>She will not come: but he must come to her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well sir <HI>I</HI> pray you lets here what</L>
<L>Answere your wife will make.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sirra, command your Mistris to come</L>
<L>To me presentlie.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Sander.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurel.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thinke my wife for all she did not come,</L>
<L>Will proue most kinde for now I haue no feare,</L>
<L>For I am sure <HI>Ferandos</HI> wife, she will not come.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<L>The mores the pittie: then I must lose.</L>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Kate</HI> and <HI>Sander.</HI></STAGE>
<L>But I haue won for see where <HI>Kate</HI> doth come.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kate.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sweet husband did you send for me?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<L>I did my loue I sent for thee to come,</L>
<L>Come hither <HI>Kate,</HI> whats that vpon thy head</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kate.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nothing husband but my cap I thinke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pull it of and treade it vnder thy feete,</L>
<L>Tis foolish I will not haue thee weare it.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>She takes of her cap and treads on it.</STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="25"/>
<SPEAKER>Pol.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh wonderfull metamorphosis.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurel.</SPEAKER>
<P>This is a wonder: almost past beleefe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is a token of her true loue to me,</L>
<L>And yet Ile trie her further you shall see,</L>
<L>Come hither <HI>Kate</HI> where are thy sisters.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kate.</SPEAKER>
<P>They be sitting in the bridall chamber.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fetch them hither and if they will not come,</L>
<L>Bring them perforce and make them come with thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kate.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alfon.</SPEAKER>
<L>I promise thee <HI>Ferando</HI> I would haue sworne,</L>
<L>Thy wife would nere haue donne so much for thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<L>But you shall see she will do more then this,</L>
<L>For see where she brings her sisters forth by force.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Kate</HI> thrusting <HI>Phylema</HI> and <HI>Emelia</HI> before her, and makes them come vnto their husbands call.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kate</SPEAKER>
<P>See husband I haue brought them both.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis well don <HI>Kate.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eme.</SPEAKER>
<L>I sure and like a louing peece, your worthy</L>
<L>To haue great praise for this attempt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phyle.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>I</HI> for making a foole of her selfe and vs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beshrew thee <HI>Phylema,</HI> thou hast</L>
<L>Lost me a hundred pound to night.</L>
<L>For I did lay that thou wouldst first haue come.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pol.</SPEAKER>
<P>But thou <HI>Emelia</HI> hast lost me a great deale more.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eme.</SPEAKER>
<L>You might haue kept it better then,</L>
<L>Who bad you lay?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now louely <HI>Kate</HI> before there husbands here,</L>
<L>I prethe tell vnto these hedstrong women,</L>
<L>What dutie wiues doo owe vnto their husbands.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kate.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then you that liue thus by your pompered wills,</L>
<L>Now list to me and marke what I shall say,</L>
<L>Theternall power that with his only breath,</L>
<L>Shall cause this end and this beginning frame,</L>
<L><PB REF="26"/>Not in time, nor before time, but with time, confusd,</L>
<L>For all the course of yeares, of ages, moneths,</L>
<L>Of seasons temperate, of dayes and houres,</L>
<L>Are tund and stopt, by measure of his hand,</L>
<L>The first world was, a forme, without a forme,</L>
<L>A heape confusd a mixture all deformd,</L>
<L>A gulfe of gulfes, a body bodiles,</L>
<L>Where all the elements were orderles,</L>
<L>Before the great commander of the world▪</L>
<L>The King of Kings the glorious God of heauen▪</L>
<L>Who in six daies did frame his heauenly worke,</L>
<L>And made all things to stand in perfit course.</L>
<L>Then to his image he did make a man.</L>
<L>Olde <HI>Adam</HI> and from his side a sleepe,</L>
<L>A rib was taken, of which the Lord did make,</L>
<L>The woe of man so termd by <HI>Adam</HI> then,</L>
<L>Woman for that, by her came sinne to vs,</L>
<L>And for her sin was <HI>Adam</HI> doomd to die,</L>
<L>As <HI>Sara</HI> to her husband, so should we,</L>
<L>Obey them, loue them, keepe, and nourish them,</L>
<L>If they by any meanes doo want our helpes,</L>
<L>Laying our handes vnder theire feete to tread,</L>
<L>If that by that we, might procure there ease,</L>
<L>And for a president Ile first begin,</L>
<L>And lay my hand vnder my husbands feete</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>She laies her hand vnder her husbands feete.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Inough sweet, the wager thou hast won,</L>
<L>And they I am sure cannot denie the same.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alfon.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>I</HI> Ferando the wager thou hast won,</L>
<L>And for to shew thee how <HI>I</HI> am pleasd in this,</L>
<L>A hundred poundes I freely giue thee more,</L>
<L>Another dowry for another daughter,</L>
<L>For she is not the same she was before.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thankes sweet father, gentlemen godnight</L>
<L><PB REF="26"/>For <HI>Kate</HI> and <HI>I</HI> will leaue you forto night,</L>
<L>Tis <HI>Kate</HI> and I am wed, and you are sped.</L>
<L>And so farwell for we will to our beds.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Ferando and Kate and Sander.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alfon.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now <HI>Aurelius</HI> what say you to this?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beleeue me father I reioice to see,</L>
<L><HI>Ferando</HI> and his wife so louingly agree.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Aurelius and Phylema and Alfonso and Valeria.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eme.</SPEAKER>
<P>How now <HI>Polidor</HI> in a dump, what sayst thou man?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pol.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>I</HI> say thou art a shrew.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eme.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thats better then a sheepe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well since tis don let it go, come lets in.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Polidor and Emelia.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Then enter two bearing of <HI>Slie</HI> in his<LB/>
Owne apparrell againe, and leaues him<LB/>
Where they found him, and then goes out.<LB/>
Then enter the <HI>Tapster.</HI></STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tapster.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now that the darkesome night is ouerpast,</L>
<L>And dawning day apeares in cristall sky,</L>
<L>Now must I hast abroad: but soft whose this?</L>
<L>What <HI>Slie</HI> oh wondrous hath he laine here allnight,</L>
<L>Ile wake him, I thinke he's starued by this,</L>
<L>But that his belly was so stuft with ale,</L>
<L>What how <HI>Slie,</HI> Awake for shame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Slie.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Sim</HI> gis some more wine: whats all the</L>
<L>Plaiers gon: am not I a Lord?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tapster.</SPEAKER>
<P>A Lord with a murrin: come art thou dronken still?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Slie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whose this? <HI>Tapster,</HI> oh Lord sirra, I haue had</L>
<L>The brauest dreame to night, that euer thou</L>
<L>Hardest in all thy life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="27"/>
<SPEAKER>Tapster.</SPEAKER>
<L>I marry but you had best get you home,</L>
<L>For your wife will course you for dreming here to night,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Slie</SPEAKER>
<L>Will she? I know now how to tame a shrew,</L>
<L>I dreamt vpon it all this night till now,</L>
<L>And thou hast wakt me out of the best dreame</L>
<L>That euer I had in my life, but Ile to my</L>
<L>Wife presently and tame her too</L>
<L>And if she anger me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tapster.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay tarry <HI>Slie</HI> for Ile go home with thee,</L>
<L>And heare the rest that thou hast dreamt to night.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Omnes.</STAGE>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
<PB REF="27"/>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

