<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2002-11-22</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Emma Leeson Huber</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, etc.). Checked for signatures. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, and UNCLEARs. Corrected 3 $s of 176. Converted 173 $s to GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech". Checked spacing of foreign GAPs. Checked for EPIGRAPHs and ARGUMENTs. Checked for startqs, endqs, oes, q;s, and Qs. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Checked for CLOSERs, TRAILERs, and BYLINEs. DONE.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="A18421">
<STC T="S">4989</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99857542</BIBNO>
<VID>23296</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>THE
REVENGE
OF
<HI>Bussy D'Ambois.</HI>
A
TRAGEDIE. As it hath beene often presented at the
priuate Play-house in the White-Fryers. Written
By GEORGE CHAPMAN, Gentleman.</P>
<P><HI>LONDON:</HI>
Printed by <HI>T. S.</HI> and are to be solde by IOHN HELME,
at his Shop in S. Dunstones Church-yard,
in <HI>Fleetstreet.</HI> 1613.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>TO THE RIGHT
VERTVOVS, AND
truely Noble Knight, S<SUP>r.</SUP>
Thomas Howard. &amp;c.</HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>Sir,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">S</SEG>Ince VVorkes of this kinde
haue beene lately estee∣med
worthy the Patro∣nage
of some of our wor∣thiest
Nobles, I haue made
no doubt to preferre this
of mine to your vndoubted Vertue, and ex∣ceeding
true Noblesse: as contayning mat∣t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r
no lesse deseruing your reading, and ex∣citation
to Heroycall life, then any such
late Dedication. Nor haue the greatest Prin∣ces
of Italie, and other Countries, conceiued
it any least diminution to their greatnesse,
<PB REF="3"/>
to haue their Names wing'd with these Tra∣gicke
Plumes, and disperst by way of Pa∣tronage,
through the most Noble Notices
of Europe.</P>
<P>Howsoeuer therefore in the Scaenicall pre∣sentation,
it might meete with some malig∣ners,
yet considering, euen therein, it past
with approbation of more worthy iudge∣ments;
the Ballance of their side (especi∣ally
being held by your impartiall hand) I
hope will to no graine abide the out-weigh∣ing.
And for the autenticall truth of eyther
person or action, who (worth the respect∣ing)
will expe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t it in a Poeme, whose sub∣iect
is not truth, but things like truth? Poore
enuious soules they are that cauill at truths
want in these naturall fictions: materiall in∣struction,
elegant and sententious excitation
to Vertue, and deflection from her contrary;
being the soule, lims, and limits of an auten∣ticall
Tragedie. But whatsoeuer merit of
your full countenance and fauour suffers
defect in this, I shall soone supply with
some other of more generall account:
wherein your right vertuous Name made
<PB REF="3"/>
famous and preserued to posteritie, your
future comfort and honour in your present
acceptation, and loue of all vertuous and
diuine expression; may be so much past
others of your Rancke encreast, as they are
short of your Iudiciall Ingenuitie, in their due
estimation.</P>
<P>For, howsoeuer those Ignoble and sowre∣brow'd
VVorldlings are carelesse of what∣soeuer
future, or present opinion spreads of
them; yet (with the most diuine Philo∣sopher,
if Scripture did not confirme it) I
make it matter of my Faith; that we truely
retaine an intellectuall feeling of Good or
Bad after this life; proportionably answera∣ble
to the loue or neglect we beare here to
all Vertue, and truely-humane Instruction:
In whose fauour and honour I wish you most
eminent; And rest euer.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Your true Vertues
most true obseruer,
Geo. Chapman.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dramatis personae">
<PB REF="4"/>
<HEAD>The Actors names.</HEAD>
<LIST>
<ITEM><HI>HEnry,</HI> the King.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Monsieur,</HI> his Brother.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Guise. D.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Renel,</HI> a Marquesse.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Mont sureau, <HI>an Earle.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Baligny,</HI> Lord Lieutenant.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Clermont, D' Ambois.
<LIST>
<HEAD>Captaines.</HEAD>
<ITEM>Maillard.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Challon.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Aumal.</ITEM>
</LIST></ITEM>
<ITEM>Espernone.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Soissone.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Perricot.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>The</HI> Guard.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Souldiers.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Seruants.
<LIST>
<HEAD>The ghost of</HEAD>
<ITEM>Bussy.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Monsieur.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Guise.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Card Guise.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Shattilion.</ITEM>
</LIST></ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<ITEM><HI>Countesse</HI> of Cambray.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Tamyra,</HI> wife to Mont sureau.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Charlotte,</HI> wife to Baligny.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Rioua,</HI> a Seruant.</ITEM>
</LIST>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<HEAD><PB REF="4"/>THE REVENGE
OF
Bussy D'Ambois.
A
TRAGEDIE.</HEAD>
<DIV1 N="1" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus primi</HEAD>
<HEAD>Scaena prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Baligny, Renel.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Baligny.</SPEAKER>
<L><SEG REND="decorInit">T</SEG>O what will this declining Kingdome turne,</L>
<L>Swindging in euery license, as in this</L>
<L>Stupide permission of braue D' Ambois Murther?</L>
<L>Murther made paralell with Law? Murther vs'd</L>
<L>To serue the Kingdome, giuen by sute to men</L>
<L>For their aduancement? suffered scarcrow-like</L>
<L>To fright adulterie? what will policie</L>
<L>At length bring vnder his capacitie?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rene.</SPEAKER>
<L>All things: for as when the high births of Kings</L>
<L>Deliuerances, and Coronations,</L>
<L>We celebrate with all the Cities Bels</L>
<L>(Iangling together in vntun'd confusion:)</L>
<L>All order'd Clockes are tyed vp: so when Glory,</L>
<L>Flatterie, and smooth applauses of things ill,</L>
<L>Vphold th'<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ordinate swindge of downe-right power,</L>
<L>Iustice, and truth, that tell th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> bounded vse,</L>
<L>Vertuous, and well distinguisht formes of Time,</L>
<L><PB REF="5"/>Are gag'd and tongue-tide, but wee haue obseru'd</L>
<L>Rule in more regular motion: things most lawfull</L>
<L>Were once most royall, Kings sought common good</L>
<L>Mens manly liberties, though ne'er so meane,</L>
<L>And had their owne swindge so▪ more free, and more,</L>
<L>But when pride enter'd them, and Rule by power,</L>
<L>All browes that smil'd beneath them, frown'd; hearts grieu'd,</L>
<L>By imitation; vertue quite was vanisht,</L>
<L>And all men stud<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'d selfe-loue, fraud, and vice,</L>
<L>Then no man could be good but he was punisht:</L>
<L>Tyrants being still more fearefull of the good</L>
<L>Then of the bad; their subiects vertues euer</L>
<L>Manag'd with curbs, and dangers, and esteem'd</L>
<L>As shadowes, and detractions to their owne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now all is peace, no danger: now what followes?</L>
<L>Idlenesse rusts vs; since no vertuous labour</L>
<L>Ends oug<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t rewarded: Ease, Securitie</L>
<L>Now all the Palme weares, wee made warre before</L>
<L>So to preuent warre, men with giuing gifts</L>
<L>More then receiuing, made our Countrey strong;</L>
<L>Our matchlesse race of Souldiers then would spend</L>
<L>In publike warres, not priuate brawles, their spirits;</L>
<L>In daring Enemies, arm'd with meanest armes;</L>
<L>Not courting strumpets, and consuming birth-rights</L>
<L>In Apishnesse, and enuy of attire.</L>
<L>No labour then was harsh, no way so deepe,</L>
<L>No rocke so steepe, but if a Bird could scale it,</L>
<L>Vp would our youth flie to. A Foe in armes</L>
<L>Stirr'd vp a much more lust of his encounter,</L>
<L>Then of a Mistresse neuer so be-painted:</L>
<L>Ambition then, was onely scaling walles;</L>
<L>And ouer-topping turrets: Fame was wealth;</L>
<L>Best parts, best deedes, were best Nobilitie;</L>
<L>Honour with worth; and wealth well got or none.</L>
<L>Countries we wonne with as few men as Countries.</L>
<L>Vertue subdu'd all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ren.</SPEAKER>
<L>Iust: and then our Nobles</L>
<L>Lou'd vertue so, they prais'd and vs'd it to;</L>
<L><PB REF="5"/>Had rather doe, then say; their owne deedes hearing</L>
<L>By others glorified, then be so barraine,</L>
<L>That their parts onely stood in praising others.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who could not doe, yet prais'd, and enui'd not;</L>
<L>Ciuile behauiour flourisht; Bountie flow'd,</L>
<L>Auarice to vpland Boores, slaues hang-men banisht.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ren.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis now quite otherwise; but to note the cause</L>
<L>Of all these foule digressions, and reuolts</L>
<L>From our first natures, this tis in a word:</L>
<L>Since good Arts faile, crafts and deceits are vs'd:</L>
<L>Men ignorant are idle; idle men</L>
<L>Most practise what they most may doe with ease,</L>
<L>Fashion, and fauour; all their studies ayming</L>
<L>At getting money, which no wise man euer</L>
<L>Fed his desires with.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet now none are wise</L>
<L>That thinke not heauens true foolish, weigh'd with that.</L>
<L>Well thou most worthy to be greatest Guise,</L>
<L>Make with thy greatnesse a new world arise.</L>
<L>Such d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>prest Nobles (followers of his)</L>
<L>As you, my selfe, my Lord will finde a time</L>
<L>When to reuenge your wrongs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ren.</SPEAKER>
<L>I make no doubt:</L>
<L>In meane time, I could wish, the wrong were righted</L>
<L>Of your slaine Brother in law, braue Bussy D' Ambois.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>That one accident was made my charge.</L>
<L>My Brother Bussy's Sister (now my wife)</L>
<L>By no suite would consent to satisfie</L>
<L>My loue of her, with marriage, till I <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ow'd,</L>
<L>To vse my vtmost to reuenge my Brother:</L>
<L>But Clermont D' Ambois (Bussy's second Brother)</L>
<L>Had (since) his apparition, and excitement,</L>
<L>To suffer none but his hand in his wreake,</L>
<L>Which hee hath vow'd, and so will needes acquite</L>
<L>Me of my vow, made to my wife, his Sister,</L>
<L>And vndertake himselfe Bussy's reuenge;</L>
<L>Yet loathing any way to giue it act,</L>
<L>But in the noblest and most manly course.</L>
<L><PB REF="6"/>(If th'Earle dares take it) he resolues to send</L>
<L>A Challenge to him, and my selfe must beare i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</L>
<L>To which deliuerie I can vse no meanes;</L>
<L>He is so barricado'd in his house,</L>
<L>And arm'd with guard still.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ren.</SPEAKER>
<L>That meanes lay on mee,</L>
<L>Which I can strangely make. My last lands sale,</L>
<L>By his great suite, stands now on price with him,</L>
<L>And hee (as you know) passing couetous,</L>
<L>(With that blinde greedinesse that followes gaine)</L>
<L>Will cast no danger, where her sweet feete tread.</L>
<L>Besides, you know, his Lady by his suite,</L>
<L>(Wooing as freshly, as when first loue shot</L>
<L>His faultlesse arrowes from her rosie eyes)</L>
<L>Now liues with him againe, and shee, I know,</L>
<L>Will ioyne with all helps, in her friends reuenge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>No doubt (my Lord) and therefore let me pray you</L>
<L>To vse all speede; for so on needels points</L>
<L>My wifes heart stands with haste of the reuenge:</L>
<L>Being (as you know) full of her brothers fire,</L>
<L>That shee imagines I neglect my vow;</L>
<L>Keepes off her kinde embraces, and still askes;</L>
<L>When, when, will this reuenge come? when perform'd</L>
<L>Will this dull vow be? And I vow to Heauen</L>
<L>So sternely, and so past her sexe she vrges</L>
<L>My vowes performance; that I almost feare</L>
<L>To see her, when I haue a while beene absent,</L>
<L>Not showing her before I speake, the bloud</L>
<L>S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e so much thirsts for, freckling hands and face,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ren.</SPEAKER>
<L>Get you the Challenge writ, and looke from me,</L>
<L>To heare your passage clear'd no long time after.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Ren.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>All restitution to your worthiest Lordship,</L>
<L>Whose errand I must carrie to the King,</L>
<L>As hauing sworne my seruice in the search</L>
<L>Of all such Malecontents, and their designes,</L>
<L>By seeming one affected with their faction,</L>
<L>And discontented humours gainst the state:</L>
<L>Nor doth my brother <HI>Clermont</HI> scape my counsaile</L>
<L><PB REF="6"/>Giuen to the King, about his Guisean greatnesse,</L>
<L>Which (as I spice it) hath possest the King</L>
<L>(Knowing his daring spirit) of much danger:</L>
<L>Charg'd in it to his person: though my conscience</L>
<L>Dare sweare him cleare of any power to be</L>
<L>Infected with the least dishonestie:</L>
<L>Yet that sinceritie, wee Politicians</L>
<L>Must say, growes out of enuie, since it cannot</L>
<L>Aspire to policies greatnesse: and the more</L>
<L>We worke on all respects of kinde, and vertue,</L>
<L>The more our seruice to the King seemes great,</L>
<L>In sparing no good that seemes bad to him:</L>
<L>And the more bad, we make the most of good,</L>
<L>The more our policie searcheth; and our seruice</L>
<L>Is wonder'd at for wisedome and sincerenesse.</L>
<L>Tis easie to make good suspected still,</L>
<L>Where good, and God, are made but cloakes for ill.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Henry, Mon<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>∣sieur, Guise, Clerm Espernone, Foisson, Monsieur taking leaue of the King.</STAGE>
<L>See Monsieur taking now his leaue for Brabant,</L>
<L>The Guise, &amp; his deare Minion, Clermont D'Ambois,</L>
<L>Whispering together, not of state affaires</L>
<L>I durst lay wagers, (though the Guise be now</L>
<L>In chiefe heate of his faction) but of some thing,</L>
<L>Sauouring of that which all men else despise,</L>
<L>How to be truely noble, truely wise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mors.</SPEAKER>
<L>See how hee hangs vpon the eare of Guise,</L>
<L>Like to his Iewell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Esper.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee's now whisp'ring in</L>
<L>Some doctrine of stabilitie, and freedome,</L>
<L>Contempt of outward greatnesse, and the guises</L>
<L>That vulgar great ones make their pride and zeale,</L>
<L>Being onely seruile traines, and sumptuous houses,</L>
<L>High places, offices.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>Contempt of these</L>
<L>Does he read to the Guise? Tis passing needfull,</L>
<L>And hee, I thinke, makes show t'affect his doctrine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Esp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Commends, admires it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>And pursues another,</L>
<L>Tis fine hypocrisie, and cheape, and vulgar,</L>
<L><PB REF="7"/>Knowne for a couert practise, yet beleeu'd</L>
<L>(By those abus'd soules, that they teach and gouerne)</L>
<L>No more then Wiues adulteries, by their Husbands,</L>
<L>They bearing it with so vnmou'd aspects,</L>
<L>Hot comming from it; as twere not all,</L>
<L>Or made by custome nothing. This same D'Ambois</L>
<L>Hath gotten such opinion of his vertues,</L>
<L>(Holding all learning but an Art to liue well,)</L>
<L>And showing hee hath learn'd it, in his life,</L>
<L>Being thereby strong in his perswading others;</L>
<L>That this ambitious Guise, embracing him,</L>
<L>Is thought t'mbrace his vertues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Esp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet in some</L>
<L>His vertues are held false for th'others vices:</L>
<L>For tis more cunning held, and much more common,</L>
<L>To suspect truth then falshood: and of both,</L>
<L>Truth still fares worse; as hardly being beleeu'd,</L>
<L>As tis vnvsuall, and rarely knowne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile part engendring vertue. Men affirme</L>
<L>Though this same Clermont hath a D'Ambois spirit,</L>
<L>And breathes his brothers valour; yet his temper</L>
<L>Is so much past his, that you cannot moue him:</L>
<L>Ile try that temper in him, Come, you two</L>
<L>Deuoure each other with your vertues zeale,</L>
<L>And leaue for other friends, no fragment of yee:</L>
<L>I wonder Guise, you will thus rauish him</L>
<L>Out of my bosome, that first gaue the life</L>
<L>His manhood breathes, spirit, and meanes and luster.</L>
<L>What doe men thinke of me, I pray thee Clermont?</L>
<L>Once giue me leaue (for tryall of that loue</L>
<L>That from thy brother Bussy thou inherit'st)</L>
<L>T'vnclaspe thy bosome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>As how sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be a true glasse to mee, in which I may</L>
<L>Behold what thoughts the many headed-beast,</L>
<L>And thou thy selfe breathes out concerning me,</L>
<L>My ends, and new vpstarted state in Brabant,</L>
<L>For which I now am bound, my higher aymes,</L>
<L>Imagin'd here in France: speake man, and let</L>
<L><PB REF="7"/>Thy words be borne as naked as thy thoughts:</L>
<L>O were braue Bussy liuing!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Liuing my Lord?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis true, thou art his brother, but durst thou</L>
<L>Haue brau'd the Guise: mauger his presence, courted</L>
<L>His wedded Lady; emptied euen the dregs</L>
<L>Of his worst thoughts of mee, euen to my te<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>th;</L>
<L>Discern'd not me his rising soueraigne</L>
<L>From any common groome: but let me heare</L>
<L>My grossest faults, as grosse-full as they were.</L>
<L>Durst thou doe this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>I cannot tell: A man</L>
<L>Does neuer know the goodnesse of his stomacke</L>
<L>Till hee sees meate before him. Were I dar'd,</L>
<L>Perhaps as he was, I durst doe like him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dare then to poure out here thy freest soule,</L>
<L>Of what I am.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis stale, he tolde you it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>He onely iested, spake of splene and enuie;</L>
<L>Thy soule more learn'd, is more ingenuous,</L>
<L>Searching, iudiciall; let me then from thee</L>
<L>Heare what I am.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>What but the sole support,</L>
<L>And most expectant hope of all our France,</L>
<L>The toward victor of the whole low Countryes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tush, thou wilt sing Encomions of my praise,</L>
<L>Is this like D'Ambois? I must vexe the Guise,</L>
<L>Or neuer looke to heare free truth; tell me,</L>
<L>For Bussy liues not: hee durst anger mee,</L>
<L>Yet for my loue, would not haue fear'd to anger</L>
<L>The King himselfe. Thou vnderstand'st me, dost not?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall my Lord, with studie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dost vnderstand thy selfe? I pray thee tell me,</L>
<L>Dost neuer search thy thoughts, what my designe</L>
<L>Might be to entertaine thee and thy brother?</L>
<L>What turne I meant to serue with you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Euen what you please to thinke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>But what thinkst thou?</L>
<L>Had I no end in't think'st?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thinke you ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>When I tooke in such two as you two were,</L>
<L><PB REF="8"/>A ragged couple of decaid Commanders,</L>
<L>When a French-crowne would plentifully serue</L>
<L>To buy you both to any thing i'th' earth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>So it would you:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay bought you both out-right,</L>
<L>You and your Trunkes: I feare me, I offend thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>No not a iot.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>The most renowmed Souldier</L>
<L><HI>Epaminondas</HI> (as good Authors say)</L>
<L>Had no more suites then backes, but you two shar'd</L>
<L>But one suite twixt you both, when both your studies</L>
<L>Were not what meate to dine with; if your Partridge,</L>
<L>Your S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ipe, your Wood-cocke, Larke, or your red Hering,</L>
<L>But where to begge it, whether at my house,</L>
<L>Or at the Guises (for you know you were</L>
<L>Ambitious beggars,) or at some Cookes-shop,</L>
<L>T' eternize the Cookes trust, and score it vp.</L>
<L>Dost not offend thee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>No sir. Pray proceede.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>As for thy Gentry, I dare boldly take</L>
<L>Thy honourable othe: and yet some say</L>
<L>Thou and thy most renowmed noble Brother,</L>
<L>Came to the Court first in a Keele of Sea-coale;</L>
<L>Dost not offend thee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Neuer doubt it, sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why doe I loue thee then? why haue I rak'd thee</L>
<L>Out of the dung-hill? cast my cast Ward-robe on thee?</L>
<L>Brought thee to Court to, as I did thy Brother?</L>
<L>Made yee my sawcy bon companions?</L>
<L>Taught yee to call our greatest Noble men</L>
<L>By the corruption of their names; Iack, Tom?</L>
<L>Haue I blowne both for nothing to this bubble?</L>
<L>Though thou art learn'd; thast no enchanting wit▪</L>
<L>Or were thy wit good, am I therefore bound</L>
<L>To keepe thee for my Table?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well Sir, 'twere</L>
<L>A good Knights place. Many a proud dubb'd Gallant</L>
<L>Seekes out a poore Knights liuing from such Emrods.</L>
<L>Or what vse else should I designe thee to?</L>
<L>Perhaps you'll answere me, to be my Pander.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="8"/>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Perhaps I shall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or did the s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ie Guise put thee</L>
<L>Into my bosome, t'vndermine my proiects?</L>
<L>I feare thee not; for though I be not sure</L>
<L>I haue thy heart, I know thy braine-pan yet</L>
<L>To be as emptie a dull piece of wainscot</L>
<L>As euer arm'd the scalpe of any Courtier;</L>
<L>A fellow onely that consists of sinewes;</L>
<L>Meere Swisser, apt for any execution.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>But killing of the King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Right: now I see</L>
<L>Thou vnderstand'st thy selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>I▪ and you better.</L>
<L>You are a Kings sonne borne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>Right.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>And a Kings brother.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>True.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>And might not any foole haue beene so too,</L>
<L>As well as you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>A poxe vpon you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>You did no Princely deedes</L>
<L>Ere you're borne (I take it) to deserue it;</L>
<L>Nor did you any sinc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> that I haue heard;</L>
<L>Nor will doe euer any, as all thinke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Diuell take him. Ile no more of him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guise.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay: stay my Lord and heare him answere you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more I sweare. Farewell.</L>
<STAGE>Ex. Mons.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guise.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more: Ill f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>tune.</L>
<STAGE>Esper. Soiss.</STAGE>
<L>I▪ would haue giuen a million to haue heard</L>
<L>His scoffes retorted: and the insolence</L>
<L>Of his high birth and greatnesse (which were neuer</L>
<L>Effects of his deserts, but of his fortune)</L>
<L>Made show to his dull eyes, beneath the worth</L>
<L>That men aspire to by their knowing vertues,</L>
<L>Without which Greatnesse is a shade, a bubble.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>But what one great man dreames of that, but you?</L>
<L>All take their births and birth-rights left to them</L>
<L>(Acquir'd by others) for their owne worths purchase,</L>
<L>When many a foole in both, is great as they:</L>
<L>And who would thinke they could winne with their worths</L>
<L>Wealthy possessions, when wonne to their hands▪</L>
<L><PB REF="9"/>They neyther can iudge iustly of their value,</L>
<L>Nor know their vse; and therefore they are puft</L>
<L>With such proud tumours as this Monsieur is:</L>
<L>Enabled onely by the goods they haue,</L>
<L>To scorne all goodnesse: none great, fill their fortunes,</L>
<L>But as those men that make their houses greater,</L>
<L>Their housholds being lesse, so Fortune raises</L>
<L>Huge heapes of out-side in these mightie men,</L>
<L>And giues them nothing in them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guise.</SPEAKER>
<L>True as truth:</L>
<L>And therefore they had rather drowne their substance</L>
<L>In superfluities of brickes and stones;</L>
<L>(Like <HI>Sysiphus,</HI> aduancing of them euer,</L>
<L>And euer pulling downe) then lay the cost</L>
<L>Of any sluttish corner, on a man,</L>
<L>Built with Gods finger, and enstil'd his Temple.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis nobly said, my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guise.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would haue these things</L>
<L>Brought vpon Stages, to let mightie Misers</L>
<L>See all their graue and serious miseries, plaid,</L>
<L>As once they were in Athens, and olde Rome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, we must now haue nothing brought on Stages,</L>
<L>But puppetry, and pide ridiculous Antickes:</L>
<L>Men thither come, to laugh, and feede foole-fat,</L>
<L>Checke at all goodnesse there, as <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ing prophan'd:</L>
<L>When wheresoeuer goodnesse comes, shee makes</L>
<L>The place still sacred; though with other feete</L>
<L>Neuer so much tis scandal'd, and polluted.</L>
<L>Let me learne any thing that fits a man,</L>
<L>In any Stables showne, as well as Stages.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why? is not all the world esteem'd a Stage?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes: and right worthily: and Stages too</L>
<L>Haue a respect due to them: if but onely,</L>
<L>For what the good Greeke Moralists sayes of them;</L>
<L>Is a man proud of greatnesse, or of riches?</L>
<L>Giue me an expert Actor; Ile shew all,</L>
<L>That can within his greatest glory fall.</L>
<L>Is a man fraid with pouertie and lownesse?</L>
<L><PB REF="9"/>Giue me an Actor, Ile shew euery eye</L>
<L>What hee laments so, and so much doth flye,</L>
<L>The best and worst of both: if but for this then,</L>
<L>To make the proudest out-side that most swels,</L>
<L>With things without him, and aboue his worth,</L>
<L>See how small cause hee has to be so blowne vp;</L>
<L>And the most poore man, to be grieu'd with poorenesse,</L>
<L>Both being so easily borne by expert Actors.</L>
<L>The Stage and Actors are not so contemptfull,</L>
<L>As euery innouating Puritane,</L>
<L>And ignorant sweater out of zealous enuie,</L>
<L>Would haue the world imagine. And besides,</L>
<L>That all things haue beene likened to the mirth,</L>
<L>Vs'd vpon Stages, and for Stages fitted.</L>
<L>The splenatiue Philosopher that euer</L>
<L>Laught at them all, were worthy the enstaging:</L>
<L>All obiects, were they ne'er so full of teares,</L>
<L>He so conceited, that he could distill thence</L>
<L>Matter that still fed his ridiculous humour.</L>
<L>Heard he a Lawyer, neuer so vehement pleading,</L>
<L>Hee stood and laught. Heard hee a Trades-man swearing</L>
<L>Neuer so thriftily (selling of his wares;)</L>
<L>Hee stood and laught. Heard hee an holy brother,</L>
<L>For hollow o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tentation at his prayers</L>
<L>Ne'er so impetuously; hee stood and laught.</L>
<L>Saw hee a great man neuer so insulting,</L>
<L>Seuerely inflicting, grauely giuing lawes,</L>
<L>Not for their good, but his; hee stood and laught.</L>
<L>Saw hee a youthfull widow</L>
<L>Neuer so weeping, wringing of her hands,</L>
<L>For her lost Lord, still the Philosopher laught:</L>
<L>Now whether hee suppos'd all these presentments,</L>
<L>Were onely maskeries, and wore false faces:</L>
<L>Or else were simply vaine, I take no care,</L>
<L>But still hee laught, how graue soere they were.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guise.</SPEAKER>
<L>And might right well (my Clermont) and for this</L>
<L>Vertuous digression, wee vvill thanke the scoffes</L>
<L>Of vicious Monsieur. But now for the maine point</L>
<L><PB REF="10"/>Of your late resolution for reuenge</L>
<L>Of your slaine friend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue here my Challenge,</L>
<L>Which I will pray my Brother Baligny</L>
<L>To beare the murtherous Earle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue prepar'd</L>
<L>Meanes for accesse to him, through all his Guard.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guise.</SPEAKER>
<L>About it then, my worthy Baligny,</L>
<L>And bring vs the successe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Tamyra sola.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tamy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Reuenge, that euer red <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>itt'st in the eyes</L>
<L>Of iniur'd Ladies, till we crowne thy browes</L>
<L>With bloudy Lawrell; and receiue from thee</L>
<L>Iustice for all our humors iniurie,</L>
<L>Whose wings none flye, that Wrath or Tyrannie</L>
<L>Haue ruthlesse made, and bloudy. Enter here,</L>
<L>Enter, O enter: and, though length of time</L>
<L>Neuer lets any scape thy constant iustice,</L>
<L>Yet now preuent that length. Flye, flye, and here</L>
<L>Fixe thy steele foot-steps: Here, O here, where still</L>
<L>Earth (mou'd with pittie) yeelded and embrac'd</L>
<L>My Loues faire figure, drawne in his deare bloud,</L>
<L>And mark'd the place, to show thee where was done</L>
<L>The cruell'st murther that ere fled the Sunne.</L>
<L>O Earth! why keep'st thou not as well his spirit,</L>
<L>To giue his forme life? No, that was not earthly:</L>
<L>That (rarefying the thinne and yeelding ayre)</L>
<L>Flew sparkling vp into the Sphaere of fire,</L>
<L>Whence endlesse flames it sheds in my desire:</L>
<L>Here be my daily pallet, here all nights</L>
<L>That can be wrested from thy riuals armes;</L>
<L>(O my deare Bussy) I will lye, and kisse</L>
<L>Spirit into thy bloud, or breathe out mine</L>
<L>In sighes, and kisses, and sad tunes to thine.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>She sings.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Mont sur.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Still on this hant? Still shall adulterous bloud</L>
<L><PB REF="10"/>Affect thy spirits? Thinke, for shame, but this,</L>
<L>This bloud that Cockatrice-like thus thou brood'st</L>
<L>To dry is to breede any quench to thine.</L>
<L>And therefore now (if onely for thy lust</L>
<L>A little couer'd with a vaile of shame)</L>
<L>Looke out for fresh life, rather then witch-like,</L>
<L>Learne to kisse horror, and with death engender.</L>
<L>Strange crosse in nature, purest virgine shame</L>
<L>Lies in the bloud, as lust lyes; and together</L>
<L>Many times mixe too: and in none more shamefull</L>
<L>Then in the shamefac't. Who can then distinguish</L>
<L>Twixt their affections; or tell when hee meetes</L>
<L>With one not common? Yet, as worthiest Poets</L>
<L>Shunne common and plebeian formes of speech,</L>
<L>Euery illiberall and affected phrase</L>
<L>To clothe their matter: and together tye</L>
<L>Matter and forme, with Art and decencie.</L>
<L>So worthiest women should shunne vulgar guises,</L>
<L>And though they cannot but flye out for change,</L>
<L>Yet modestie, the matter of their liues,</L>
<L>Be it adulterate, should be painted true</L>
<L>With modest out-parts; what they should doe still</L>
<L>Grac'd with good show, though deedes be ne'er so ill.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tamy.</SPEAKER>
<L>That is so farre from all yee seeke of vs,</L>
<L>That (though your selues be common as the ayre)</L>
<L>We must not take the ayre, wee must not fit</L>
<L>Our actions to our owne affectons:</L>
<L>But as Geometricians (you still say)</L>
<L>Teach that no lines, nor superficies,</L>
<L>Doe moue themselues, but still accompanie</L>
<L>The motions of their bodies; so poore wiues</L>
<L>Must not pursue, nor haue their owne affections,</L>
<L>But to their husbands earnests, and their iests,</L>
<L>To their austerities of lookes, and laughters,</L>
<L>(Though ne'er so foolish and iniurious)</L>
<L>Like Parasites and slaues, fit their disposures.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>I vsde thee as my soule, to moue and rule me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tamy.</SPEAKER>
<L>So said you, when you woo'd. So Souldiers tortur'd</L>
<L><PB REF="11"/>Withtedious sieges of some wel-wall'd Towne,</L>
<L>Propound conditions of most large contents,</L>
<L>Freedome of Lawes, all former gouernment;</L>
<L>But hauing once set foote within the Wals,</L>
<L>And got the reynes of power into their hands,</L>
<L>Then doe they tyrannize at their owne rude swindges,</L>
<L>Seaze all their goods, their liberties, and liues,</L>
<L>And make aduantage, and their lusts, their lawes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>But loue me, and performe a Wifes part yet,</L>
<L>(With all my loue before) I sweare forgiuenesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tamy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Forgiuenesse! that grace you should seeke of mee:</L>
<L>These tortur'd fingers, and these stab'd-through armes</L>
<L>Keepe that law in their vvounds yet, vnobseru'd,</L>
<L>And euer shall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>Remember their deserts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Those vvith faire warnings might haue beene reform'd,</L>
<L>Not these vnmanly rages. You haue heard</L>
<L>The fiction of the North winde and the Sunne,</L>
<L>Both vvorking on a Traueller, and contending</L>
<L>Which had most power to take his cloake from him:</L>
<L>Which when the Winde attempted, hee roar'd out</L>
<L>Outragious blasts at him to force it off,</L>
<L>That vvrapt it closer on. When the calme Sunne</L>
<L>(The Winde once leauing) charg'd him vvith still beames,</L>
<L>Quiet, and feruent, and therein was constant,</L>
<L>Which made him cast off both his cloake and coate:</L>
<L>Like vvhom should men doe. If yee vvish your Wiues</L>
<L>Should leaue dislik'd things, seeke it not vvith rage;</L>
<L>For that enrages: vvhat yee giue, yee haue:</L>
<L>But vse calme warnings, and kinde manly meanes,</L>
<L>And that in Wiues most prostitute will winne</L>
<L>Not onely sure amends; but make vs Wiues</L>
<L>Better then those that ne'er led faultie liues.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter a Souldier.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sould.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now; vvould any speake with me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soul.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peruerse, and traiterous miscreant:</L>
<L>Where are your other fellowes of my Guard?</L>
<L><PB REF="11"/>Haue I not told you, I will speake with none,</L>
<L>But Lord Renel?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sould.</SPEAKER>
<L>And tis hee that stayes you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, is it he? Tis well: attend him in.</L>
<L>I must be vigilant: the Furies haunt mee.</L>
<L>Doe you heare dame?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Renel, with the Souldier.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ren.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be true now, for your Ladies iniur'd sake,</L>
<L>Whose bountie you haue so much cause to honour:</L>
<L>For her respect is chiefe in this designe,</L>
<L>And therefore serue it, call out of the vvay</L>
<L>All your confederate fellowes of his Guard,</L>
<L>Till Monsieur Baligny be enter'd here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sould.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vpon your honour, my Lord shall be free</L>
<L>From any hurt you say.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ren.</SPEAKER>
<L>Free as my selfe. Watch then, and cleare his entrie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sould.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will not faile, my Lord.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Souldier.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ren.</SPEAKER>
<L>God saue your Lordship.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>My noblest Lord <HI>Renel!</HI> past all men welcome.</L>
<L>Wife, vvelcome his Lordship.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Osculatur.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ren.</SPEAKER>
<L>I much ioy in your returne here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tamy.</SPEAKER>
<L>You doe more then I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee's passionate still, to thinke we euer parted,</L>
<L>By my too sterne iniurious Ielousie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ren.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis well your Lordship will confesse your errour</L>
<L>In so good time yet.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Baligny with a Challenge.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>Death! Who haue wee here?</L>
<L>Ho! Guard! Villaines!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why exclaime you so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>Negligent Trayters! Murther, murther, murther.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ye'are mad. Had mine entent beene so, like yours,</L>
<L>It had beene done ere this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ren.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, your intent,</L>
<L>And action too▪ was rude to enter thus.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'are a decaid Lord to tell me of rudenesse,</L>
<L>As much decaid in manners as in meanes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ren.</SPEAKER>
<L>You talke of manners, that thus rudely thrust</L>
<L>Vpon a man that's busie with his Wife.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>And kept your Lordship then the dore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ren.</SPEAKER>
<L>The dore?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="12"/>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweet Lord forbeare. Show, show your purpose sir.</L>
<L>To moue such bold feete into others roofes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is my purpose sir, from Clermont D'Ambois</L>
<L>I bring this Challenge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Challenge! Ile touch none.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile leaue it here then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ren.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou shalt leaue thy life first.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Murther, murther!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ren.</SPEAKER>
<L>Retire my Lord; get off.</L>
<L>Hold, or thy death shall hold thee. Hence my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>There lye the Chalenge.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>They all fight and Bal▪ driues in M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ren.</SPEAKER>
<L>Was not this well handled?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Mont.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nobly my Lord. All thankes.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Bal.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>T<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>my.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile make him reade it.</L>
<STAGE>Exi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Tamy.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ren.</SPEAKER>
<L>This was a sleight well<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>maskt.</L>
<L>O what is man,</L>
<L>Vnlesse he be a Politician!</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<TRAILER>Finis Actus primi.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="2" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus secundi</HEAD>
<HEAD>Scaena prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Henry, Baligny.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hen.</SPEAKER>
<L>COme Baligny, we now are priuate: Say,</L>
<L>What seruice bring'st thou? make it short; the Guise</L>
<L>(Whose friend thou seem'st) is now in Court, and neare,</L>
<L>And may obserue vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>This sir, then in short.</L>
<L>The faction of the Guise (with which my policie,</L>
<L>For seruice to your Highnesse seemes to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oyne)</L>
<L>Growes ripe, and must be gather'd into hold;</L>
<L>Of which my Brother Clermont being a part</L>
<L>Exceeding capitall, deserues to haue</L>
<L>A capitall eye on him. And (as you may</L>
<L>With best aduantage, and your speediest charge,)</L>
<L>Command his apprehension: which (because</L>
<L>The Court, you know, is strong in his defence)</L>
<L>Wee must aske Country swindge and open fields.</L>
<L>And therefore I haue wrought him to goe downe</L>
<L><PB REF="12"/>To Cambray with me (of which Gouernment</L>
<L>Your Highnesse bountie made mee your Lieutenant)</L>
<L>Where when I haue him, I will leaue my house,</L>
<L>And faine some seruice out about the confines,</L>
<L>When in the meane time, if you please to giue</L>
<L>Command to my Lieutenant, by your Letters,</L>
<L>To traine him to some muster, where he may</L>
<L>(Much to his honour) see for him, your forces</L>
<L>Put into Battaile; when hee comes, hee may</L>
<L>With some close stratageme be apprehended:</L>
<L>For otherwise your whole powers there will faile</L>
<L>To worke his apprehension: and with that</L>
<L>My hand needes neuer be discern'd therein.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thankes honest Baligny.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Highnesse knowes</L>
<L>I will be honest; and betray for you</L>
<L>Brother and Father: for, I know (my Lord)</L>
<L>Treacherie for Kings is truest Loyaltie;</L>
<L>Nor is to beare the name of Treacherie,</L>
<L>But graue, deepe Policie. All acts that seeme</L>
<L>Ill in particular respects, are good</L>
<L>As they respect your vniuersall Rule.</L>
<L>As in the maine sway of the vniuerse</L>
<L>The supreame Rectors generall decrees,</L>
<L>To guard the mightie Globes of Earth and Heauen,</L>
<L>Since they make good that guard to preseruation</L>
<L>Of both those in their order and first end,</L>
<L>No mans particular (as hee thinkes) wrong</L>
<L>Must hold him wrong'd: no, not though all mens reasons,</L>
<L>All Law, all conscience, concludes it wrong.</L>
<L>Nor is comparison a flatterer</L>
<L>To liken you here to the King of kings;</L>
<L>Nor any mans particular offence</L>
<L>Against the worlds sway; to offence at yours</L>
<L>In any subiect; who as little may</L>
<L>Grudge at their particular wrong; if so it seeme</L>
<L>For th'vniuersall right of your estate.</L>
<L>As (being a Subiect of the Worlds whole sway</L>
<L><PB REF="13"/>As well as yours; and being a righteous man</L>
<L>To whom Heauen promises defence, and blessing,</L>
<L>Brought to decay, disgrace, and quite defencelesse)</L>
<L>Hee may complaine of Heauen for wrong to him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis true: the Simile at all parts holds,</L>
<L>As all good Subiects hold, that loue our fauour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Which is our Heauen here; and a miserie</L>
<L>Incomparable, and most truely Hellish</L>
<L>To liue depriu'd of our Kings grace and countenance,</L>
<L>Without which best conditions are most cursed:</L>
<L>Life of that nature, howsoeuer short,</L>
<L>Is a most lingering, and tedious life;</L>
<L>Or rather no life, but a languishing,</L>
<L>And an abuse of life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis well conceited.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thought it not amisse to yeeld your Highnesse</L>
<L>A reason of my speeches; lest perhaps</L>
<L>You might conceiue I flatter'd: which (I know)</L>
<L>Of all ils vnder heauen you most abhorre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Still thou art right, my vertuous Baligny,</L>
<L>For which I thanke and loue thee. Thy aduise</L>
<L>Ile not forget: Haste to thy Gouernment,</L>
<L>And carry D'Ambois with thee. So farewell.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Maiestie fare euer like it selfe.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Guise.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guise.</SPEAKER>
<L>My sure Friend Baligny!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Noblest of Princes!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guise.</SPEAKER>
<L>How stands the State of Cambray?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Strong, my Lord,</L>
<L>And fit for seruice: for whose readinesse</L>
<L>Your creature Clermont D'Ambois, and my selfe</L>
<L>Ride shortly downe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guise.</SPEAKER>
<L>That Clermont is my loue;</L>
<L>France neuer bred a nobler Gentleman</L>
<L>For all parts: he exceedes his Brother Bussy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, my Lord?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guise.</SPEAKER>
<L>Farre: because (besides his valour)</L>
<L><PB REF="13"/>Hee hath the crowne of man, and all his parts,</L>
<L>Which Learning is; and that so true and vertuous,</L>
<L>That it giues power to doe, as well as say</L>
<L>What euer fits a most accomplisht man;</L>
<L>Which Bussy, for his valours season, lackt;</L>
<L>And so was rapt with outrage oftentimes</L>
<L>Beyond Decorum; where this absolute Clermont,</L>
<L>Though (onely for his naturall zeale to right)</L>
<L>Hee will be fiery, when hee sees it crost;</L>
<L>And in defence of it; yet when he lists</L>
<L>Hee can containe that fire, as hid in Embers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>No question, hee's a true, learn'd, Gentleman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guise.</SPEAKER>
<L>He is as true as Tides, or any Starre</L>
<L>Is in his motion: And for his rare learning,</L>
<L>Hee is not (as all else are that seeke knowledge)</L>
<L>Of taste so much deprau'd, that they had rather</L>
<L>Delight, and satisfie themselues to drinke</L>
<L>Of the streame troubled, wandring ne'er so farre</L>
<L>From the cleare fount, then of the fount it selfe.</L>
<L>In all; Romes Brutus is reuiu'd in him,</L>
<L>Whom hee of industry doth imitate.</L>
<L>Or rather, as great Troys Euphorbus was</L>
<L>After Pithagoras; so is Brutus, Clermont.</L>
<L>And (were not Brutus a Conspirator)</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Conspirator, my Lord? Doth that empaire him?</L>
<L>Caesar beganne to tyrannize; and when vertue,</L>
<L>Nor the religion of the Gods could serue</L>
<L>To curbe the insolence of his proud Lawes,</L>
<L>Brutus would be the Gods iust instrument.</L>
<L>What said the Princesse (sweet Antigone)</L>
<L>In the graue Greeke Tragedian, when the question</L>
<L>Twixt her and Creon is, for lawes of Kings?</L>
<L>Which when he vrges, shee replies on him;</L>
<L>Though his Lawes were a Kings, they were not Gods;</L>
<L>Nor would shee value Creons written Lawes</L>
<L>With Gods vnwrit Edicts: since they last not</L>
<L>This day and the next, but euery day and euer;</L>
<L>Where Kings Lawes alter euery day and houre,</L>
<L><PB REF="14"/>And in that change imply a bounded power.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guise.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, let vs leaue these vaine disputings what</L>
<L>Is to be done, and fall to doing something.</L>
<L>When are you for your Gouernment in Cambray?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>When you command, my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guise.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, that's not fit.</L>
<L>Continue your designements with the King,</L>
<L>With all your seruice; onely if I send</L>
<L>Respect me as your friend, and loue my Clermont.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Highnesse knowes my vowes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guise.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, tis enough.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Guise.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Manet Bal.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thus must wee play on both sides, and thus harten</L>
<L>In any ill those men whose good wee hate.</L>
<L>Kings may doe what they list: and for Kings, Subiects,</L>
<L>Eyther exempt from censure or exception:</L>
<L>For,<NOTE PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>c.</NOTE> as no mans worth can be iustly iudg'd</L>
<L>But when he shines in some authoritie;<NOTE PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>possibile est <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>n cognoscere <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>entem ac vo∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>nt atem, pri∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>quam in Ma∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>stratibus appa∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>t <BIBL><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>pho Antig.</BIBL></NOTE></L>
<L>So no authoritie should suffer censure</L>
<L>But by a man of more authoritie.</L>
<L>Great vessels into lesse are emptied neuer,</L>
<L>There's a redoundance past their continent euer.</L>
<L>These <HI>virtuosi</HI> are the poorest creatures;</L>
<L>For looke how Spinners weaue out of themselues</L>
<L>Webs, whose strange matter none before can see;</L>
<L>So these, out of an vnseene good in vertue,</L>
<L>Make arguments of right, and comfort, in her,</L>
<L>That clothe them like the poore web of a Spinner.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Clermont.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now, to my Challenge. What's the place, the weapon?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Soft sir: let first your Challenge be receiued.</L>
<L>Hee would not touch, nor see it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Possible!</L>
<L>How did you then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Left it, in his despight.</L>
<L>But when hee saw mee enter so expectlesse,</L>
<L>To heare his base exclaimes of murther, murther,</L>
<L>Made me thinke Noblesse lost, in him quicke buried.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="14"/>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are the breathing Sepulchres of Noblesse:</L>
<L>No trulier noble men, then Lions pictures</L>
<L>Hung vp for signes, are Lions.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Quo molii<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> gunt <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <BIBL>E<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t.</BIBL></NOTE> Who knowes not,</L>
<L>That Lyons the more soft kept, are more seruile?</L>
<L>And looke how Lyons close kept, fed by hand,</L>
<L>Lose quite th'innatiue fire of spirit and greatnesse</L>
<L>That Lyons free breathe, forraging for prey;</L>
<L>And grow so grosse, that mastifes, curs, and mungrils</L>
<L>Haue spirit to cow them: So our soft French Nobles</L>
<L>Chain'd vp in ease and numbd securitie,</L>
<L>Their spirits shrunke vp like their couetous fists,</L>
<L>And neuer opened but Domitian-like,</L>
<L>And all his base obsequious minions</L>
<L>When they were catching, though it were but flyes.</L>
<L>Besotted with their pezzants loue of gaine,</L>
<L>Rusting at home, and on each other preying,</L>
<L>Are for their greatnesse but the greater slaues,</L>
<L>And none is noble but who scrapes and saues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis base, tis base; and yet they thinke them high.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>So Children mounted on their hobby-horse,</L>
<L>Thinke they are riding, when with wanton toile</L>
<L>They beare what should beare them. A man may well</L>
<L>Compare them to those foolish great-spleen'd Cammels,</L>
<L>That to their high heads, beg'd of Ioue hornes higher;</L>
<L>Whose most vncomely, and ridiculous pride</L>
<L>When hee had satisfied, they could not vse,</L>
<L>But where they went vpright before, they stoopt,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Simi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</NOTE></L>
<L>And bore their heads much lower for their hornes.</L>
<L>As these high men doe▪ low in all true grace,</L>
<L>Their height being priuiledge to all things base.</L>
<L>And as the foolish Poet that still writ</L>
<L>All his most selfe-lou'd verse in paper royall,</L>
<L>Or Partchment rul'd with Lead, smooth'd with the Pum<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ce;</L>
<L>Bound richly vp, and strung with Crimson strings;</L>
<L>Neuer so blest as when hee writ and read</L>
<L>The Ape-lou'd issue of his braine; and neuer</L>
<L>But ioying in himselfe; admiring euer:</L>
<L>Yet in his workes behold him, and hee show'd</L>
<L><PB REF="15"/>Like to a ditcher. So these painted men,</L>
<L>All set on out-side, looke vpon within,</L>
<L>And not a pezzants entrailes you shall finde</L>
<L>More foule and mezel'd, nor more steru'd of minde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>That makes their bodies fat. I faine would know</L>
<L>How many millions of our other Nobles</L>
<L>Would make one Guise. There is a true tenth Worthy▪</L>
<L>Who (did not one act onely blemish him.)</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>One act? what one?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>One, that (though yeeres past done)</L>
<L>Stickes by him still, and will distaine him euer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good Heauen! wherein? what one act can you name</L>
<L>Suppos'd his staine, that Ile not proue his luster?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>To satisfie you, twas the Massacre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Massacre? I thought twas some such blemish.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>O it was hainous.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>To a brutish sense,</L>
<L>But not a manly reason. Wee so tender</L>
<L>The vile part in vs, that the part diuine</L>
<L>We see in hell, and shrinke not. Who was first</L>
<L>Head of that Massacre?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Guise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis nothing so.</L>
<L>Who was in fault for all the slaughters made</L>
<L>In Ilion, and about it? Were the Greekes?</L>
<L>Was it not Paris rauishing the Queene</L>
<L>Of Lacaedemon? Breach of shame and faith?</L>
<L>And all the lawes of Hospitalitie?</L>
<L>This is the Beastly slaughter made of men,</L>
<L>When Truth is ouer-throwne, his Lawes corrupted;</L>
<L>When soules are smother'd in the flatter'd flesh,</L>
<L>Slaine bodies are no more then Oxen slaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Differ not men from Oxen?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who sayes so?</L>
<L>But see wherein; In the vnderstanding rules</L>
<L>Of their opinions, liues, and actions;</L>
<L>In their communities of faith and reason.</L>
<L>Was not the Wolfe that nourisht <HI>Romulus</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="15"/>More humane then the men that did expose him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>That makes against you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not sir, if you note</L>
<L>That by that deede, the actions difference make</L>
<L>Twixt men and beasts, and not their names nor formes.</L>
<L>Had faith, nor shame, all hospitable rights</L>
<L>Be<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ne broke by Troy, Greece had not made that slaughter.</L>
<L>Had that beene sau'd (sayes a Philosopher)</L>
<L>The Iliads and Odysses had beene lost,</L>
<L>Had Faith and true Religion beene prefer'd,</L>
<L>Religious Guise had neuer massacerd,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well sir, I cannot when I meete with you</L>
<L>But thus digresse a little, for my learning,</L>
<L>From any other businesse I entend.</L>
<L>But now the voyage, we resolu'd for Cambray,</L>
<L>I told the Guise beginnes; and wee must haste.</L>
<L>And till the Lord <HI>Renel</HI> hath found some meane</L>
<L>(Conspiring with the Countesse) to make sure</L>
<L>Your sworne wreake on her Husband (though this fail'd)</L>
<L>In my so braue Command, wee'll spend the time,</L>
<L>Sometimes in training out in Skirmishes,</L>
<L>And Battailes, all our Troopes and Companies;</L>
<L>And sometimes breathe your braue Scotch running horse,</L>
<L>That great Guise gaue you, that all th'horse in France</L>
<L>Farre ouer-runnes at euery race and hunting</L>
<L>Both of the Hare and Deere. You shall be honor'd</L>
<L>Like the great Guise himselfe, aboue the King.</L>
<L>And (can you but appease your great-spleen'd Sister,</L>
<L>For our delaid wreake of your Brothers slaughter)</L>
<L>At all parts you'll be welcom'd to your wonder.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile see my Lord the Guise againe before</L>
<L>Wee take our iourney.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>O sir, by all meanes,</L>
<L>You cannot be too carefull of his loue,</L>
<L>That euer takes occasion to be raising</L>
<L>Your virtues, past the reaches of this age,</L>
<L>And rankes you with the best of th'ancient Romanes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>That praise at no part moues mee, but the worth</L>
<L><PB REF="16"/>Of all hee can giue others spher'd in him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee yet is thought to entertaine strange aymes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r.</SPEAKER>
<L>He may be well; yet not as you thinke strange,</L>
<L>His strange Aymes are to crosse the common Custome</L>
<L>Of Seruile Nobles; in which hee's so rauisht,</L>
<L>That quite the Earth he leaues, and vp hee leapes,</L>
<L>On Atlas shoulders, and from thence lookes downe,</L>
<L>Viewing how farre off other high ones creepe:</L>
<L>Rich, poore of reason, wander; All pale looking,</L>
<L>And trembling but to thinke of their sure deaths,</L>
<L>Their liues so base are, and so rancke their breaths.</L>
<L>Which I teach Guise to heighten, and make sweet</L>
<L>With lifes deare odors, a good minde and name;</L>
<L>For which, hee onely loues me, and deserues</L>
<L>My loue and life, which through all deaths I vow:</L>
<L>Resoluing this, (what euer change can be)</L>
<L>Thou hast created, thou hast ruinde mee.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<TRAILER>Finis Actus secundi.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="3" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus tertij</HEAD>
<HEAD>Scaena prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE>A march of Captaines ouer the Stage.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Maillard, Chalon, Aumall following with Souldiers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mail.</SPEAKER>
<L>THese Troopes and companies come in with wings:</L>
<L>So many men, so arm'd, so gallant Horse,</L>
<L>I thinke no other Gouernment in France</L>
<L>So soone could bring together. With such men</L>
<L>Me thinkes a man might passe th'insulting Pillars</L>
<L>Of Bacchus and Alcides.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chal.</SPEAKER>
<L>I much wonder</L>
<L>Our Lord Lieutenant brought his brother downe</L>
<L>To feast and honour him, and yet now leaues him</L>
<L>At such an instance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mail.</SPEAKER>
<L>Twas the Kings Command:</L>
<L>For whom he must leaue Brother, Wife, friend, all things.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="16"/>
<SPEAKER>Aum.</SPEAKER>
<L>The confines of his Gouernment, whose view</L>
<L>Is the pretext of his Command, hath neede</L>
<L>Of no such sodaine expedition.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mail.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee must not argue that. The Kings Command</L>
<L>Is neede and right enough: and that he serues,</L>
<L>(As all true Subiects should) without disputing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chal.</SPEAKER>
<L>But knowes not hee of your Command to take</L>
<L>His Brother Clermont?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mail.</SPEAKER>
<L>No: the Kings will is</L>
<L>Expressely to conceale his apprehension</L>
<L>From my Lord Gouernour. Obseru'd yee not?</L>
<L>Againe peruse the Letters. Both you are</L>
<L>Made my assistants, and haue right and trust</L>
<L>In all the waightie secrets like my selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aum.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis strange a man that had, through his life past,</L>
<L>So sure a foote in vertue and true knowledge,</L>
<L>As Clermont D'Ambois, should be now found tripping,</L>
<L>And taken vp thus, so to make his fall</L>
<L>More steepe and head-long.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mail.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is Vertues fortune,</L>
<L>To keepe her low, and in her proper place.</L>
<L>Height hath no roome for her: But as a man</L>
<L>That hath a fruitfull wife, and euery yeere</L>
<L>A childe by her, hath euery yeere a month,</L>
<L>To breathe himselfe: where hee that gets no childe</L>
<L>Hath not a nights rest (if he will doe well.)</L>
<L>So, let one marry this same barraine Vertue,</L>
<L>She neuer lets him rest: where fruitfull vice</L>
<L>Spares her rich drudge, giues him in labour breath;</L>
<L>Feedes him with bane, and makes him fat with death,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chal.</SPEAKER>
<L>I see that good liues neuer can secure</L>
<L>Men from bad liuers. Worst men will haue best</L>
<L>As ill as they, or heauen to hell they'll wrest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aum.</SPEAKER>
<L>There was a merit for this, in the fault</L>
<L>That Bussy made, for which he (doing pennance)</L>
<L>Proues that these foule adulterous guilts will runne</L>
<L>Through the whole bloud, which not the cleare can shunne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mail.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile therefore take heede of the bastarding</L>
<PB REF="17"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="17"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<L><PB REF="18"/>Whole innocent races; tis a fearefull thing.</L>
<L>And as I am true Batcheler, I sweare,</L>
<L>To touch no woman (to the coupling ends)</L>
<L>Vnlesse it be mine owne wife or my friends.</L>
<L>I may make bold with him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aum.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis safe and common.</L>
<L>The more your friend dares trust, the more deceiue him.</L>
<L>And as through dewie vapors the Sunnes forme</L>
<L>Makes the gay Rainebow, girdle to a storme,</L>
<L>So in hearts hollow, Friendship (euen the Sunne</L>
<L>To all good growing in societie)</L>
<L>Makes his so glorious and diuine name hold</L>
<L>Collours for all the ill that can be told.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mail.</SPEAKER>
<L>Harke, our last Troopes are come.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Trumpets within.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Harke, our last foote.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Drums beate.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mail.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, let vs put all quickly into battaile,</L>
<L>And send for Clermont, in whose honour, all</L>
<L>This mart<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>all preparation wee pretend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee must bethinke vs ere wee apprehend him,</L>
<L>(Besides our maine strength) of some stratageme</L>
<L>To make good our seuere Command on him;</L>
<L>As well to saue bloud, as to make him sure:</L>
<L>For if hee come on his Scotch horse, all France</L>
<L>Put at the heeles of him, will faile to take him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>il.</SPEAKER>
<L>What thinke you if wee should disguise a brace</L>
<L>Of our best Souldiers in faire Lackies coates,</L>
<L>And send them for him, running by his side,</L>
<L>Till they haue brought him in some ambuscado</L>
<L>We close may lodge for him; and sodainely</L>
<L>Lay sure hand on him, plucking him from horse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m.</SPEAKER>
<L>It must be sure and strong hand: for if once</L>
<L>H<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e feeles the touch of such a stratageme,</L>
<L>Tis not the choisest brace of all our Bands</L>
<L>Can ma<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>acle, or quench his <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ery hands.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>l.</SPEAKER>
<L>When they haue seaz'd him, the ambush shal make in.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aum.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe as you please; his blamelesse spirit deserues</L>
<L>(I dare engage my life) of all this, nothing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why should all this stirre be then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="18"/>
<SPEAKER>Aum.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who knowes not</L>
<L>The bumbast politie thrusts into his Gyant,</L>
<L>To make his wisedome seeme of size as huge,</L>
<L>And all for sleight encounter of a shade,</L>
<L>So hee be toucht, hee would haue hainous made?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mail.</SPEAKER>
<L>It may be once so; but so euer, neuer;</L>
<L>Ambition is abroad, on foote, on horse;</L>
<L>Faction chokes euery corner, streete, the Court,</L>
<L>Whose faction tis you know: and who is held</L>
<L>The fautors right hand: how high his aymes reach,</L>
<L>Nought but a Crowne can measure. This must fall</L>
<L>Past shadowes waights; and is most capitall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chal.</SPEAKER>
<L>No question; for since hee is come to Cambray</L>
<L>The malecontent, decaid Marquesse Renel,</L>
<L>Is come, and new arriu'd; and made partaker</L>
<L>Of all the entertaining Showes and Feasts</L>
<L>That welcom'd Clermont to the braue Virago</L>
<L>His manly Sister. Such wee are esteem'd</L>
<L>As are our conforts. Marquesse malecontent</L>
<L>Comes where hee knowes his vaine hath safest vent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mail.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let him come at his will, and goe as free,</L>
<L>Let vs ply Clermont, our whole charge is hee.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter a Gentleman Vsher before Clermont: Renel, Char∣lotte,
with two women attendants, with others: Sh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>wes
hauing past within.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Char.</SPEAKER>
<L>This for your Lordships welcome into Cambray.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ren.</SPEAKER>
<L>Noblest of Ladies, tis beyond all power</L>
<L>(Were my estate at first full) in my meanes</L>
<L>To quit or merit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>You come something latter</L>
<L>From Court my Lord then I: And since newes there</L>
<L>Is euery day encreasing with th'affaires,</L>
<L>Must I not aske now, what the newes is there?</L>
<L>Where the Court lyes? what stirre? change? what auise</L>
<L>From England, Italie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ren.</SPEAKER>
<L>You must doe so▪</L>
<L>If you'll be cald a Gentleman well quallified,</L>
<L><PB REF="19"/>And weare your time and wits in those discourses.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Locrian Princes therefore were braue Rubers;</L>
<L>For whosoeuer there came new from Countrie,</L>
<L>And in the Citie askt, what newes? was punisht:</L>
<L>Since commonly such braines are most delighted</L>
<L>With innouations, Gossips tales, and mischiefes:</L>
<L>But as of Lyons it is said and Eagles,</L>
<L>That when they goe, they draw their seeres and tallons</L>
<L>Close vp, to shunne rebating of their sharpnesse:</L>
<L>So our wits sharpnesse, which wee should employ</L>
<L>In noblest knowledge, wee should neuer waste</L>
<L>In vile and vulgar admirations.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ren.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis right: but who, saue onely you, performes it,</L>
<L>And your great brother? Madame, where is he?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Char.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gone a day since, into the Countries confines,</L>
<L>To see their strength, and readinesse for seruice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ren.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis well: his fauour with the King hath made him</L>
<L>Most worthily great, and liue right royally.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>I: Would hee would not doe so. Honour neuer</L>
<L>Should be esteem'd with wise men, as the price</L>
<L>And value of their virtuous Seruices,</L>
<L>But as their signe or Badge: for that bewrayes</L>
<L>More glory in the outward grace of goodnesse,</L>
<L>Then in the good it selfe; and then tis said:</L>
<L>Who more ioy takes, that men his good aduance,</L>
<L>Then in the good it selfe, does it by chance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Char.</SPEAKER>
<L>My brother speakes all principle; what man</L>
<L>Is mou'd with your soule? or hath such a thought</L>
<L>In any rate of goodnesse?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cher.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis their fault.</L>
<L>We haue examples of it, cleare and many.</L>
<L>Dem<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>trius Phalerius, an Orator,</L>
<L>And (which not o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t meete) a Philosopher,</L>
<L>So great in Athens grew, that he er<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cted</L>
<L>Three hundred Statues of him; of all which,</L>
<L>No rust▪ nor length of time corrupted one;</L>
<L>But in his life time, all were ouerthrowne.</L>
<L>And Demades (that past Demosthenes</L>
<L><PB REF="19"/>For all extemporall Orations)</L>
<L>Erected many Statues, which (he liuing)</L>
<L>Were broke, and melted into Chamber-pots.</L>
<L>Many such ends haue fallen on such proud honours,</L>
<L>No more because the men on whom they fell</L>
<L>Grew insolent, and left their vertues state;</L>
<L>Then for their hugenesse, that procur'd their hate:</L>
<L>And therefore little pompe in men most great,</L>
<L>Makes mightily and strongly to the guard</L>
<L>Of what they winne by chance, or iust reward.</L>
<L>Great and immodest braueries againe,</L>
<L>Like Statues, much too high made for their bases,</L>
<L>Are ouerturn'd as soone, as giuen their places.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter a Messenger with a Letter.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Messen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here is a Letter sir deliuer'd mee,</L>
<L>Now at the fore-gate by a Gentleman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>What Gentleman?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mess.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee would not tell his name;</L>
<L>Hee said, hee had not time enough to tell it,</L>
<L>And say the little rest hee had to say.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>That was a merry saying; he tooke measure</L>
<L>Of his deare time like a most thri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tie husband.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Char.</SPEAKER>
<L>What newes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Strange ones, and fit for a Nouation;</L>
<L>Waightie, vnheard of, mischieuous enough.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ren.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heauen shield: what are they?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Read them, good my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ren.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are betraid into this Countrie. Monstrous!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Char.</SPEAKER>
<L>How's that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Read on.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ren.</SPEAKER>
<P>Maillard▪ you brothers Leiutenant, that yesterday
inu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ted you to see his Musters; hath Letters and strickt
Charge from the King to appr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hend you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Char.</SPEAKER>
<L>To apprehend him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ren.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Brother absents himselfe of purpose.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's a sound one.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Char.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's a lye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="20"/>
<SPEAKER>Ren.</SPEAKER>
<P>Get on your Scotch horse, and retire to your strength;
you know where it is, and there it expects you: Beleeue this
as your best friend had sworne it. Fare-well if you will. Ano∣nymos.
What's that?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r.</SPEAKER>
<L>Without a name.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<L>And all his notice too, without all truth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>So I conceiue it Sister: ile not wrong</L>
<L>My well knowne Brother for Anonymos,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Some foole hath put this tricke on you, yet more</L>
<L>T'vncouer your defect of spirit and valour.</L>
<L>First showne in lingring my deare Brothers wreake.</L>
<L>See what it is to giue the enuious World</L>
<L>Aduantage to diminish eminent virtue.</L>
<L>Send him a Challenge? Take a noble course</L>
<L>To wreake a murther, done so like a villaine?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall we reuenge a villanie with villanie?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Char.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is it not equall?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall wee equall be</L>
<L>With villaines?</L>
<L>Is that your reason?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Char.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cowardise euermore</L>
<L>Flyes to the shield of Reason.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nought that is</L>
<L>Approu'd by Reason, can be Cowardise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dispute when you should fight. Wrong wreaklesse</L>
<L>Makes men dye honorlesse: One borne, another (sleeping,</L>
<L>Leapes on our shoulders.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee must wreake our wrongs</L>
<L>So, as wee take not more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Char.</SPEAKER>
<L>One wreakt in time</L>
<L>Preuents all other. Then shines vertue most</L>
<L>When time is found for facts; and found, not lost.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>No time occurres to Kings, much lesse to Vertue;</L>
<L>Not can we call it Vertue that proceedes</L>
<L>From vicious Fury. I repent that euer</L>
<L>(By any instigation in th'appearance</L>
<L>My Brothers spirit made, as I imagin'd)</L>
<L>That e'er I yeelded to reuenge his murther.</L>
<L><PB REF="20"/>All worthy men should euer bring their bloud</L>
<L>To beare all ill, not to be wreakt with good:</L>
<L>Doe ill for no ill: Neuer priuate cause</L>
<L>Should take on it the part of publike Lawes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Char.</SPEAKER>
<L>A D'Ambois beare in wrong so tame a spirit!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ren.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madame, besure there will be time enough</L>
<L>For all the vengeance your great spirit can wish.</L>
<L>The course yet taken is allow'd by all,</L>
<L>Which being noble, and refus'd by th'Earle,</L>
<L>Now makes him worthy of your worst aduantage:</L>
<L>And I haue cast a proiect with the Countesse</L>
<L>To watch a time when all his wariest Guards</L>
<L>Shall not exempt him. Therefore giue him breath;</L>
<L>Sure Death delaid is a redoubled Death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good Sister trouble not your selfe with this:</L>
<L>Take other Ladyes care; practise your face.</L>
<L>There's the chaste Matron, Madame Perigot,</L>
<L>Dwels not farre hence, Ile ride and send her to you,</L>
<L>Shee did liue by retailing mayden<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>heads</L>
<L>In her minoritie: but now shee deales</L>
<L>In whole-sale altogether for the Court.</L>
<L>I tell you, shee's the onely fashion-monger,</L>
<L>For your complexion, poudring of your haire,</L>
<L>Shadowes, Rebatoes, Wires, Tyres, and such trickes,</L>
<L>That Cambray, or I thinke, the Court affords:</L>
<L>She shall attend you Sister, and with these</L>
<L>Womanly practises emply your spirit;</L>
<L>This other suites you not, nor fits the fashion.</L>
<L>Though shee be deare, lay't on, spare for no cost,</L>
<L>Ladies in these haue all their bounties lost.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ren.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madame, you see, his spirit will not checke</L>
<L>At any single danger; when it stands</L>
<L>Thus merrily firme against an host of men,</L>
<L>Threate<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'d to be armes for his surprise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Char.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's a meere Bugge-beare, an impossible mocke,</L>
<L>If hee, and him I bound by nuptiall faith</L>
<L>Had not beene dull and drossie in performing</L>
<L>Wreake of the deare bloud of my matchlesse Brother,</L>
<L><PB REF="21"/>What Prince? what King? which of the desperat'st Ruffings,</L>
<L>Outlawes in Acden, durst haue tempted thus</L>
<L>One of our bloud and name, be't true or false.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is not caus'd by that: <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>twill be as sure</L>
<L>As yet it is not, though this should be true.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Char.</SPEAKER>
<L>True? tis past thought false.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>I suppose the worst,</L>
<L>Which farre I am from thinking; and despise</L>
<L>The Armie now in battaile that should act it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would not let my bloud vp to that thought,</L>
<L>But it should cost the dearest bloud in France.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweet Sister, <STAGE>[osculatur]</STAGE> fa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re be both off as the fact</L>
<L>Of my fain'd apprehension.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Char.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would once</L>
<L>Strip off my shame with my attire, and trie</L>
<L>If a poore woman, votist of reuenge</L>
<L>Would not performe it, with a president</L>
<L>To all you bungling foggy-spirited men;</L>
<L>But for our birth-rights honour, doe not mention</L>
<L>One syllable of any word may goe</L>
<L>To the begetting of an act so tender,</L>
<L>And full of sulphure as this Letters truth:</L>
<L>It comprehends so blacke a circumstance</L>
<L>Not to be nam'd; that but to forme one thought,</L>
<L>It is, or can be so; would make me mad:</L>
<L>Come my Lord, you and I will fight this dreame</L>
<L>Out at the Chesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ren.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most gladly, worthiest Ladie.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Char▪ and Ren.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter a Messenger.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mess.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, my Lord Gouernours Lieutenant prayes</L>
<L>Accesse to you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Himselfe alone?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mess.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alone, sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Attend him in. <STAGE>[Exit Mess.]</STAGE> Now comes this plot to tryall,</L>
<L>I shall descerne (if it be true as rare)</L>
<L>Some sparkes will flye from his dissembling eyes.</L>
<L>Ile sound his depth.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="21"/>Enter Maillard with the Messenger.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Maill.</SPEAKER>
<L>Honour, and all things noble.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>As much to you good Captaine. What's th'affaire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mail.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, the poore honour we can adde to all</L>
<L>Your studyed welcome to this martiall place,</L>
<L>In presentation of what strength consists</L>
<L>My Lord your Brothers Gouernment is readie.</L>
<L>I haue made all his Troopes and Companies</L>
<L>Aduance, and put themselues randg'd in Battailia,</L>
<L>That you may see, both how well arm'd they are;</L>
<L>How strong is euery Troope and Companie;</L>
<L>How ready, and how well prepar'd for seruice,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>And must they take mee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mail.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take you, sir? O Heauen!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ss.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beleeue it sir, his count'nance chang'd in turning.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mail.</SPEAKER>
<L>What doe you meane sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you haue charg'd them,</L>
<L>You being charg'd your selfe, to apprehend mee,</L>
<L>Turne not your face: throw not your lookes about so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mail.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pardon me sir. You amaze me to conceiue</L>
<L>From whence our wils to honour you, should turne</L>
<L>To such dishonour of my Lord your Brother.</L>
<L>Dare I, without him, vendertake your taking?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why not? by your direct charge from the King?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mail.</SPEAKER>
<L>By my charge from the King? would he so much</L>
<L>Disgrace my Lord, his owne Lieutenant here,</L>
<L>To giue me his Command without his forfaite?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Acts that are done by Kings, are not askt why.</L>
<L>Ile not dispute the case, but I will search you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mail.</SPEAKER>
<L>Search mee? for what?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>For Letters.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mail.</SPEAKER>
<L>I beseech you,</L>
<L>Doe not admit one thought of such a sham<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>To a Commander.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe to: I must doo't.</L>
<L>Stand and be searcht; you know mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mail.</SPEAKER>
<L>You forget</L>
<L><PB REF="22"/>What tis to be a Captaine, and your selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stand, or I vow to heauen, Ile make you lie</L>
<L>Neuer to rise more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mail.</SPEAKER>
<L>If a man be mad</L>
<L>Reason must beare him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>So coy to be searcht?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mail.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sdeath sir, vse a Captaine like a Carrier.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, be not furious; when I haue done</L>
<L>You shall make such a Carrier of me</L>
<L>If't be your pleasure: you're my friend I know,</L>
<L>And so am bold with you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mail.</SPEAKER>
<L>You'll nothing finde</L>
<L>Where nothing is.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweare you haue nothing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mail.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nothing you seeke, I sweare, I beseech you,</L>
<L>Know I desir'd this out of great affection,</L>
<L>To th'end my Lord may know out of your witnesse,</L>
<L>His Forces are not in so bad estate</L>
<L>As hee esteem'd them lately in your hearing:</L>
<L>For which he would not trust me with the Confines;</L>
<L>But went himselfe to witnesse their estate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>I heard him make that reason, and am sorie</L>
<L>I had no thought of it before I made</L>
<L>Thus bold with you; since tis such Ruberb to you.</L>
<L>Ile therefore search no more. If you are charg'd</L>
<L>(By Letters from the King, or otherwise)</L>
<L>To apprehend me; neuer spice it more</L>
<L>With forc'd tearmes of your loue, but say: I yeeld;</L>
<L>Holde; take my sword; here; I forgiue thee freely;</L>
<L>Take; doe thine office.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mail.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sfoote, you make m'a hang-man:</L>
<L>By all my faith to you, there's no such thing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your faith to mee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mail.</SPEAKER>
<L>My faith to God: All's one,</L>
<L>Who hath no faith to men, to God hath none.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>In that sense I accept your othe, and thanke you.</L>
<L>I gaue my word to goe, and I will goe.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Cler.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mail.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile watch you whither.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Mail.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="22"/>
<SPEAKER>Mess.</SPEAKER>
<L>If hee goes, hee proues</L>
<L>How vaine are mens fore knowledges of things,</L>
<L>When heauen strikes blinde their powers of note and vse;</L>
<L>And makes their way to ruine seeme more right,</L>
<L>Then that which safetie opens to their sight.</L>
<L>Cassandra's prophecie had no more profit</L>
<L>With Troyes blinde Citizens, when shee fore-tolde</L>
<L>Troyes ruine: which succeeding, made her vse</L>
<L>This sacred Inclamation; God (said shee)</L>
<L>Would haue me vtter things vncredited:</L>
<L>For which now they approue what I presag'd;</L>
<L>They count me wise, that said before I rag'd.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Challon with two Souldiers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come Souldiers: you are downe-wards fit for lackies;</L>
<L>Giue me your Pieces, and take you these Coates,</L>
<L>To make you compleate foot-men: in whose formes</L>
<L>You must be compleate Souldiers: you two onely</L>
<L>Stand for our Armie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<L>That were much.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis true,</L>
<L>You two must doe, or enter, what our Armie</L>
<L>Is now in field for.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2</SPEAKER>
<L>I see then our guerdon</L>
<L>Must be the deede it selfe, twill be such honour:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chal.</SPEAKER>
<L>What fight Souldiers most for?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<L>Honour onely.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet here are crownes beside.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ambo.</SPEAKER>
<L>We thanke you Captaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2</SPEAKER>
<L>Now sir, how show wee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chal.</SPEAKER>
<L>As you should at all parts.</L>
<L>Goe now to Clermont D'Ambois, and informe him,</L>
<L>Two Battailes are set ready in his honour,</L>
<L>And stay his presence onely for their signall,</L>
<L>When they shall ioyne: and that t'attend him hither,</L>
<L>Like one wee so much honour, wee haue sent him</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<L>Vs two in person.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well sir, say it so.</L>
<L><PB REF="23"/>And hauing brought him to the field, when I</L>
<L>Fall in with him, saluting, get you both</L>
<L>Of one side of his horse, and plucke him downe,</L>
<L>And I with <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h'ambush laid, will second you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, we shall lay on hands of too much strength</L>
<L>To neede your secondings.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2</SPEAKER>
<L>I hope, we shall.</L>
<L>Two are enough <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o encounter Hercules.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis well said worthy Souldiers: hast, and hast him.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Clermont, Maillard close following him.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Scotch horse to their Armie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l.</SPEAKER>
<L>Please you sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sd<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ath you're passing diligent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>il.</SPEAKER>
<L>Of my soule</L>
<L>Tis onely in my loue to honour you</L>
<L>With what would grace the King: but since I see</L>
<L>You still sustaine a iealous eye on mee,</L>
<L>Ile goe before.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis well; Ile come; my hand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>il.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your hand sir? Come, your word, your choise be vs'd.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Clermont solus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>I had an auersation to this voyage,</L>
<L>When first my Brother mou'd it; and haue found</L>
<L>That natiue power in me was neuer vaine;</L>
<L>Y<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t now neglected it. I wonder much</L>
<L>At my inconstancie in these decrees,</L>
<L>I eu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ry houre set downe to guide my life.</L>
<L>When Homer made Achilles passionate,</L>
<L>Wra<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ull, reuengefull▪ and insatiate</L>
<L>In his aff<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ctions; what man will denie,</L>
<L>He did compose it all of industrie,</L>
<L>To let men see▪ that men of most renowne,</L>
<L>Strong'st, noblest, fairest, if they set not downe</L>
<L>Decrees within them, for disposing these,</L>
<L>Of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>udgement, Resolution, Vprightnesse,</L>
<L>And certaine knowledge, of their vse and ends</L>
<L><PB REF="23"/>Mishap and miserie no lesse extends</L>
<L>To their destruction; with all that they pris'd,</L>
<L>Then to the poorest, and the most despis'd.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Renel.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ren.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why▪ how now friend? retir'd? take heede you proue not</L>
<L>Dismaid with this strange fortune: all obserue you.</L>
<L>Your gouernment's as much markt as the Kings.</L>
<L>What said a friend to Pompey?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>What?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ren.</SPEAKER>
<L>The people</L>
<L>Will neuer know, vnlesse in death thou trie,</L>
<L>That thou know'st how to beare aduersitie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall approue how vile I value feare</L>
<L>Of death at all times: but to be too rash,</L>
<L>Without both will and care to shunne the worst,</L>
<L>(It being in power to doe, well and with cheere)</L>
<L>Is stupid negligence, and worse then feare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ren.</SPEAKER>
<L>Suppose this true now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, I cannot doo't.</L>
<L>My sister truely said; there hung a taile</L>
<L>Of circumstance so blacke on that supposure,</L>
<L>That to sustaine it thus, abhorr'd our mettall.</L>
<L>And I can shunne it too, in spight of all:</L>
<L>Not going to field: and there to, being so mounted</L>
<L>As I will, since I goe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ren.</SPEAKER>
<L>You will then goe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am engag'd both in my word, and hand;</L>
<L>But this is it, that makes me thus retir'd,</L>
<L>To call my selfe t'account, how this affaire</L>
<L>Is to be manag'd if the worst should chance:</L>
<L>With which I note, how dangerous it is,</L>
<L>For any man to prease beyond the place,</L>
<L>To which his birth, or meanes, or knowledge ties him;</L>
<L>For my part, though of noble birth my birth-right</L>
<L>Had little left it, and I know tis better</L>
<L>To liue with little; and to keepe within</L>
<L>A mans owne strength still, and in mans true end,</L>
<L><PB REF="24"/>Then runne a mixt course. Good and bad hold neuer</L>
<L>Any thing common: you can neuer finde</L>
<L>Things outward care, but you neglect your minde.</L>
<L>God hath the whole world perfect made and free;</L>
<L>His parts to th'vse of th'all; men then that are</L>
<L>Parts of that all, must as the generall sway</L>
<L>Of that importeth, willingly obay</L>
<L>In euery thing without their power to change.</L>
<L>Hee that vnpleas'd▪ to hold his place, will range,</L>
<L>Can in no other be contain'd that's fit,</L>
<L>And so re<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>isting th'All, is crusht with it.</L>
<L>But he that knowing how diuine a Frame</L>
<L>The whole world is: and of it all, can name</L>
<L>(Without selfe-flatterie) no part so diuine,</L>
<L>As hee himselfe; and therefore will confine</L>
<L>Freely, his whole powers, in his proper part,</L>
<L>Goes on most God-like. Hee that striues t'inuert</L>
<L>The Vniuersals course with his poore way,</L>
<L>Not onely dust-like shiuers with the sway,</L>
<L>But crossing God in his great worke; all earth</L>
<L>Beares not so cursed, and so damn'd a birth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ren.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe, on; Ile take no care what comes of you;</L>
<L>Heauen will not see it ill, how ere it show:</L>
<L>But the pretext to see these Battailes rang'd</L>
<L>Is much your honour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>As the world esteemes it.</L>
<L>But to decide that; you make me remember</L>
<L>An accident of high and noble note,</L>
<L>And fits the subiect of my late discourse,</L>
<L>Of holding on our free and proper way.</L>
<L>I ouer-tooke, comming from Italie,</L>
<L>In Germanie, a great and famous Earle</L>
<L>Of England; the most goodly fashion'd man</L>
<L>I euer <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aw: from head to foote in forme</L>
<L>Rare, and most absolute; hee had a face</L>
<L>Like one of the most ancient honour'd Romanes,</L>
<L>From whence his noblest Familie was deriu'd;</L>
<L>He was beside of spirit passing great,</L>
<L><PB REF="24"/>Valiant, and learn'd, and liberall as the Sunne,</L>
<L>Spoke and writ sweetly, or of learned subiects,</L>
<L>Or of the discipline of publike weales;</L>
<L>And t'was the Earle of Oxford: and being offer'd</L>
<L>At that time, by Duke Cassimere, the view</L>
<L>Of his right royall Armie then in field;</L>
<L>Refus'd it, and no foote was mou'd, to stirre</L>
<L>Out of his owne free fore-determin'd course:</L>
<L>I wondring at it, askt for it his reason,</L>
<L>It being an offer so much for his honour.</L>
<L>Hee, all acknowledging, said, t'was not fit</L>
<L>To take those honours that one cannot quit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ren.</SPEAKER>
<L>Twas answer'd like the man you haue describ'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>And yet he cast it onely in the way,</L>
<L>To stay and serue the world. Nor did it fit</L>
<L>His owne true estimate how much it waigh'd,</L>
<L>For hee despis'd it; and esteem'd it freer</L>
<L>To keepe his owne way straight, and swore that hee</L>
<L>Had rather make away his whole estate</L>
<L>In things that crost the vulgar, then he would</L>
<L>Be frozen vp, stiffe, like a sir Iohn Smith</L>
<L>(His Countrey-man) in common Nobles fashions;</L>
<L>Affecting, as the end of Noblesse were</L>
<L>Those seruile obseruations▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ren.</SPEAKER>
<L>It was strange.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>O tis a vexing sight to see a man</L>
<L>Out of his way, stalke, proud as hee were in;</L>
<L>Out of his way to be officious,</L>
<L>Obseruant, wary, serious, and graue,</L>
<L>Fearefull, and passionate, insulting, raging,</L>
<L>Labour with iron Flailes, to thresh downe feathers</L>
<L>Flitting in ayre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ren.</SPEAKER>
<L>What one considers this,</L>
<L>Of all that are thus out? or once endeuours,</L>
<L>Erring to enter, on mans Right-hand path?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>These are too graue for braue wits: giue them toyes,</L>
<L>Labour bestow'd on these is harsh and thriftlesse.</L>
<L>If you would Consull be (sayes one) of Rome,</L>
<L><PB REF="25"/>You must be watching, starting out of sleepes;</L>
<L>Euery way whisking; gloryfying Plebeians,</L>
<L>K<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ssing Patricians hands, Rot at their dores;</L>
<L>Speake and doe basely; eu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>y day bestow</L>
<L>Gifts and obseruance vpon one or other:</L>
<L>And what's th'<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uent of all? Twelue Rods before thee,</L>
<L>Three or f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ure times sit for the whole Tribunall.</L>
<L>Exhibite Circean Games; make publike feasts,</L>
<L>And f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r these idle outward things (sayes he)</L>
<L>Would'st thou lay on such cost, toile, spend thy spirits.</L>
<L>And to be voide of perturbation</L>
<L>For constancie: sleepe when thou would'st haue sleepe,</L>
<L>Wake wh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n thou would'st wake, feare nought, vexe for nought,</L>
<L>No paines wilt thou bestow? no cost? no thought?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ren.</SPEAKER>
<L>What should I say? as good consort with you,</L>
<L>As with an Angell: I cou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d heare you euer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r.</SPEAKER>
<L>W<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ll; in, my Lord, and spend time with my Sister;</L>
<L>And keepe her from the Field with all endeauour;</L>
<L>The Souldiers loue her so; and shee so madly</L>
<L>Would take my apprehension, if it chance,</L>
<L>That bloud would flow in riuers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ren.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heauen forbid;</L>
<L>And all with honour your arriuall speede.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ssenger with two Souldiers like Lackies.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ss.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here are two Lackies sir, haue message to you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r.</SPEAKER>
<L>What is your message? and from whom, my friends?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<L>From the Lieutenant Colonell, and the Captaines,</L>
<L>Who sent vs to informe you, that the Battailes</L>
<L>Stand ready rang'd, expecting but your presence,</L>
<L>To be their honor'd signall when to ioyne,</L>
<L>And we are charg'd to runne by, and attend you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>I come. I pray you see my running horse</L>
<L>Brought to the backe-gate to mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mess.</SPEAKER>
<L>Instantly.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Mess.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Chance what can chance mee; well or ill is equall</L>
<L>In my acceptance, since I ioy in neyther;</L>
<L>B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t goe with sway of all the world together.</L>
<L><PB REF="25"/>In all successes, Fortune and the day</L>
<L>To mee alike are; I am fixt, be shee</L>
<L>Neuer so fickle; and will there repose,</L>
<L>Farre past the reach of any Dye she throwes.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ex. cum Pedis<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</STAGE>
<TRAILER>Finis Actus tertij.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="4" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus quarti</HEAD>
<HEAD>Scaena prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Alarum within: Excursions ouer thee Stage.</STAGE>
<STAGE>The Lackies running, Maillard following them.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mail.</SPEAKER>
<L>VIllaines, not hold him when ye had him downe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<L>Who can hold lightning? Sdeath a man as well</L>
<L>Might catch a Canon Bullet in his mouth,</L>
<L>And spit it in your hands, as take and hold him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mail.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pursue; enclose him; stand, or fall on him,</L>
<L>And yee may take him. Sdeath, they make him guards.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Alarum still, and enter Chalon.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stand Cowards, stand, strike, send your bullets at him▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee came to entertaine him sir, for honour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2</SPEAKER>
<L>Did ye not say so?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Slaues, hee is a traitor;</L>
<L>Command the horse troopes to ouer-runne the traitor.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Showts within. Alarum still▪ and Chambers shot off.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Then enter Aumall.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aum.</SPEAKER>
<L>What spirit breathes thus, in this more then man,</L>
<L>Turnes flesh to ayre possest, and in a storme,</L>
<L>Teares men about the field like Autumne leaues?</L>
<L>He turnd wilde lightning in the Lackies hands,</L>
<L>Who, though their sodaine violent twitch vnhorst him,</L>
<L>Yet when he bore himselfe, their saucie fingers</L>
<L>Flew as too hot off, as hee had beene fire.</L>
<L>The ambush then made in, through all whose force,</L>
<L>Hee draue as if a fierce and fire<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> giuen Canon</L>
<L>Had spit his iron vomit out amongst them.</L>
<L><PB REF="26"/>The Battailes then, in two halfe-moones enclos'd him,</L>
<L>In which he shew'd, as if he were the light,</L>
<L>And they but earth, who wondring what hee was;</L>
<L>Shruncke their steele hornes, and gaue him glorious passe,</L>
<L>And as a great shot from a towne besieg'd,</L>
<L>At foes before it, flyes forth blacke and roring,</L>
<L>But they too farre, and that with waight opprest,</L>
<L>(As if disdaining earth) doth onely grasse,</L>
<L>Strike earth, and vp againe into the ayre;</L>
<L>Againe sinkes to it, and againe doth rise,</L>
<L>And keepes such strength that when it softliest moues,</L>
<L>It piece-meale shiuers any let it proues:</L>
<L>So flew braue Clermont forth, till breath forsooke him,</L>
<L>Then fell to earth, and yet (sweet man) euen then</L>
<L>His spirits conuulsions made him bound againe,</L>
<L>Past all their reaches; till all motion spent,</L>
<L>His fixt eyes cast a blaze of such disdaine,</L>
<L>All stood and star'd, and vntouch'd let him lie,</L>
<L>As something sacred fallen out of the skie.</L>
<STAGE>A cry within.</STAGE>
<L>O now some rude hand hath laid hold on him!</L>
<STAGE>Enter Maillard, Chalon leading Clermont, Captaines and Souldiers following.</STAGE>
<L>See, prisoner led, with his bands honour'd more,</L>
<L>Then all the freedome he enioy'd before.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mail.</SPEAKER>
<L>At length wee haue you sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>You haue much ioy too,</L>
<L>I made you sport yet, but I pray you tell mee,</L>
<L>Are not you periur'd?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mail.</SPEAKER>
<L>No: I swore for the King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet periurie I hope is periurie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mail.</SPEAKER>
<L>But thus forswearing is not periurie;</L>
<L>You are no Politician: not a fault,</L>
<L>How foule soeuer, done for priuate ends,</L>
<L>Is fault in vs sworne to the publike good:</L>
<L>Wee neuer can be of the damned crew,</L>
<L>Wee may impolitique our selues (as t'were)</L>
<L>Into the Kingdomes body politique,</L>
<L><PB REF="26"/>Whereof indeede we'are members: you misse terme▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>The things are yet the same.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mail.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis nothing so: the propertie is alter'd:</L>
<L>Y'are no Lawyer. Or say that othe and othe</L>
<L>Are still the same in number, yet their species</L>
<L>Differ extreamely, as for flat example,</L>
<L>When politique widowes trye men for their turne,</L>
<L>Before they wed them, they are harlots then,</L>
<L>But when they wed them, they are honest women▪</L>
<L>So, priuate men, when they forsweare, betray,</L>
<L>Are periur'd treachers, but being publique once,</L>
<L>That is, sworne-married to the publique good.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are married women publique?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mail.</SPEAKER>
<L>Publique good,</L>
<L>For marriage makes them, being the publique good,</L>
<L>And could not be without them. So I say</L>
<L>Men publique, that is, being sworne-married</L>
<L>To the good publique, being one body made</L>
<L>With the Realmes body politique, are no more</L>
<L>Priuate, nor can be periur'd, though forsworne,</L>
<L>More then a widow married, for the act</L>
<L>Of generation is for that an harlot,</L>
<L>Because for that shee was so, being vnmarried:</L>
<L>An argument <HI>a paribus.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis a shrow'd one.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who hath no faith to men, to God hath none:</L>
<L>Retaine you that Sir? who said so?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mail.</SPEAKER>
<L>Twas I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy owne tongue damne thy infidelitie.</L>
<L>But Captaines all you know me nobly borne,</L>
<L>Vse yee t'assault such men as I with Lackyes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chal.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are no Lackyes sir, but Souldiers,</L>
<L>Disguis'd in Lackyes coates.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, wee haue seene the enemie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Auant yee Rascols, hence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mail.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now leaue your coates.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me not see them more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aum.</SPEAKER>
<L>I grieue that vertue liues so vndistinguisht</L>
<L>From vice in any ill, and though the crowne</L>
<L>Of Soueraigne Law; shee should be yet her foot-stoole,</L>
<L><PB REF="27"/>Subiect to censure, all the shame and paine</L>
<L>Of all her rigor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet false policie</L>
<L>Would couer all, being like offenders hid,</L>
<L>That (after notice taken where they hide)</L>
<L>The more they crouch and stirre, the more are spide.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aum.</SPEAKER>
<L>I vvonder how this chanc'd you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Some informer,</L>
<L>Bloud hound to mischiefe, vsher to the Hangman,</L>
<L>Thi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>stie of honour for some huge state act▪</L>
<L>Perceiuing me great vvith the vvorthy Guise:</L>
<L>And he (I know not vvhy) held dangerous,</L>
<L>Made me the desperate organe of his danger,</L>
<L>Onely vvith that poore colour: tis the common</L>
<L>And more then vvhore-like tricke of treacherie,</L>
<L>And vermine bred to rapine, and to ruine:</L>
<L>For vvhich this▪ fault is still to be accus'd,</L>
<L>Since good acts faile, crafts and deceits are vs'd.</L>
<L>If it be other neuer pittie mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aum.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, vve are glad, beleeue it, and haue hope</L>
<L>The King vvill so conceit it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>At his pleasure.</L>
<L>In meane time, vvhat's your vvill Lord Lieutenant?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>il.</SPEAKER>
<L>To leaue your owne horse, and to mount the trumpets.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>It shall be done: this heauily preuents</L>
<L>My purpos'd recreation in these parts;</L>
<L>Which now I thinke on: let mee begge you sir,</L>
<L>To lend me some one Captaine of your Troopes,</L>
<L>To beare the message of my haplesse seruice,</L>
<L>And mis<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rie, to my most noble mistresse,</L>
<L>Countesse of Cambray: to whose house this night</L>
<L>I promist my repaire, and know most truely,</L>
<L>With all the ceremonies of her fauour,</L>
<L>She sure expects mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mail.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thinke you now on that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>On that, sir? I, and that so worthily,</L>
<L>That if the King▪ in spight of your great seruice,</L>
<L>Would send me instant promise of enlargement,</L>
<L>Condition I would set this message by,</L>
<L><PB REF="27"/>I would not take it, but had rather die.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aum.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your message shall be done sir: I my selfe</L>
<L>Will be for you a messenger of ill.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thanke you sir, and doubt not yet to liue</L>
<L>To quite your kindnesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aum.</SPEAKER>
<L>Meane space vse your spirit</L>
<L>And knowledge for the chearfull patience</L>
<L>Of this so strange and sodaine consequence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good sir, beleeue that no perticular torture</L>
<L>Can force me from my glad obedience</L>
<L>To any thing the high and generall cause,</L>
<L>To match with his whole Fabricke, hath ordainde,</L>
<L>And know yee all (though farre from all your aymes,</L>
<L>Yet worth them all, and all mens endlesse studies)</L>
<L>That in this one thing, all the discipline</L>
<L>Of manners, and of manhood is contain'd;</L>
<L>A man to ioyne himselfe with th'Vniuerse,</L>
<L>In his maine sway, and make (in all things fit)</L>
<L>One with that all, and goe on, round as it;</L>
<L>Not plucking from the whole his wretched part,</L>
<L>And into strai<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es, or into nought reuert,</L>
<L>Wishing the compleate Vniuerse might be</L>
<L>Subiect to such a ragge of it as hee:</L>
<L>But to consider great necessitie</L>
<L>All things as well refract, as voluntarie</L>
<L>Reduceth to the prime celestiall cause,</L>
<L>Which he that yeelds to with a mans applause,</L>
<L>And cheeke, by cheeke, goes; crossing it, no breath,</L>
<L>But like Gods Image, followes to the death,</L>
<L>That man is truely wise, and euery thing,</L>
<L>(Each cause, and euery part distinguishing)</L>
<L>In Nature, with enough Art vnderstands,</L>
<L>And that full glory merits at all hands,</L>
<L>That doth the whole world at all parts adorne,</L>
<L>And appe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>taines to one celestiall borne.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt omnes,</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Baligny, Renel.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>So foule a scandall neuer man sustain'd,</L>
<L><PB REF="28"/>Which caus'd by'th King, is rude and tyrannous:</L>
<L>Giu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> me a place, and my Lieutenant make</L>
<L>The filler of it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ren.</SPEAKER>
<L>I should neuer looke</L>
<L>For better of him; neuer trust a man,</L>
<L>For any Iustice, that is rapt with pleasure:</L>
<L>To order armes well, that makes smockes his ensignes,</L>
<L>And his whole Gouernments sayles: you heard of late,</L>
<L>Hee had the foure and twenty wayes of Venerie</L>
<L>Done all before him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Twas abhorr'd and beastly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ren.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis more then natures mightie hand can do<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>To make one humane and a Letcher too.</L>
<L>Looke how a Wolfe doth like a Dogge appeare,</L>
<L>So, like a friend is an Adulterer,</L>
<L>Voluptuaries, and these belly-gods;</L>
<L>No more true men are, then so many Toads.</L>
<L>A good man happy, is a common good;</L>
<L>Vile men aduanc'd liue of the common bloud.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Giue and then take like children.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ren.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bounties are</L>
<L>As soone repented as they happen rare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>What should Kings doe, and men of eminent places;</L>
<L>But as they gather, sow gifts to the graces,</L>
<L>And where they haue giuen, rather giue againe,</L>
<L>(Being giuen for vertue) then like Babes and fooles,</L>
<L>Take and repent Gifts; why are wealth and power?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ren.</SPEAKER>
<L>Power and wealth moue to tyranny, not bountie;</L>
<L>The Merchant for his wealth is swolne in minde,</L>
<L>When yet the chiefe Lord of it is the Winde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>That may so chance to our State-Merchants too:</L>
<L>Something performed, that hath not farre to goe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ren.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's the maine point, my Lord; insist on that.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>But doth this fire rage further? hath it taken</L>
<L>The tender tynder of my wifes sere bloud?</L>
<L>Is shee so passionate?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ren.</SPEAKER>
<L>So wilde, so mad,</L>
<L>Shee cannot liue, and this vnwreakt sustaine.</L>
<L><PB REF="28"/>The woes are bloudy that in women raigne.</L>
<L>The Sicile gulfe keepes feare in lesse degree;</L>
<L>There is no Tyger, not more tame then shee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>There is no looking home then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ren.</SPEAKER>
<L>Home? Medea</L>
<L>With all her hearbs, charmes, thunders, lightning,</L>
<L>Made not her presence, and blacke hants more dreadfull.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, to the King▪ if he reforme not all,</L>
<L>Marke the euent, none stand where that must fall.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Countesse, Rioua, and an Vsher.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vsh.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madame, a Captaine come from Clermont D'Ambois</L>
<L>Desires accesse to you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Count.</SPEAKER>
<L>And not himselfe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vsh.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, Madame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Coun.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's not vvell. Attend him in.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Vsh.</STAGE>
<L>The last houre of his promise now runne out</L>
<L>And hee breake, some brack in the frame of nature</L>
<L>That forceth his breach.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Vsher and Aumal.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aum.</SPEAKER>
<L>Saue your Ladiship.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Coun.</SPEAKER>
<L>All welcome. Come you from my worthy seruant?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aum.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, Madame, and conferre such newes from him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Coun.</SPEAKER>
<L>Such newes? vvhat newes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aum.</SPEAKER>
<L>Newes that I wish some other had had the charge of.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Coun.</SPEAKER>
<L>O vvhat charge? vvhat newes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aum.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Ladiship must vse some patience</L>
<L>Or else I cannot doe him that desire,</L>
<L>He vrg'd vvith such affection to your Graces.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Coun.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe it; for heauens loue doe it, if you serue</L>
<L>His kinde desires, I vvill haue patience.</L>
<L>Is hee in health?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aum.</SPEAKER>
<L>He is.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Count.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, that's the ground</L>
<L>Of all the good estate wee hold in earth;</L>
<L>All our ill built vpon that, is no more</L>
<L>Then wee may beare, and should expresse it all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aum.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madame, tis onely this; his libertie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Coun.</SPEAKER>
<L>His libertie<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Without that health is nothing.</L>
<L><PB REF="29"/>Why liue I, but to aske in doubt of that,</L>
<L>Is that bere<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aum.</SPEAKER>
<L>You'll againe preuent me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>un.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more, I sweare, I must heare, and together</L>
<L>Come all my miserie. Ile hold though I burst.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aum.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then madame, thus it fares; he was enuited</L>
<L>By vvay of honour to him, to take view</L>
<L>Of all the Powers his brother Baligny</L>
<L>Hath in his gou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rnment; vvhich rang'd in battailes,</L>
<L>Mail<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ard, Lieutenant to the Gouernour,</L>
<L>Hauing re<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>iu'd strickt Letters from the King,</L>
<L>To tr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ine him to the musters, and betray him,</L>
<L>To their supprise, which, with Chalon in chiefe,</L>
<L>And other Captaines (all the field put hard</L>
<L>By his incredible valour for his s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>pe)</L>
<L>They haplesly and guiltlesly perform'd,</L>
<L>And to Bastile hee's now led prisoner.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Coun.</SPEAKER>
<L>What change is here? how are my hopes preuented?</L>
<L>O my most faithfull seruant; thou betraid?</L>
<L>Will Kings make treason lawfull? Is Societie</L>
<L>(To keepe which onely Kings vvere first ordain'd)</L>
<L>Lesse broke in breaking faith twixt friend and friend,</L>
<L>Then twixt the King and Subiect? let them feare,</L>
<L>Kings Presidents in licence lacke no danger.</L>
<L>Kings are compar'd to Gods, and should be like them,</L>
<L>F<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ll in all right, in nought superfluous;</L>
<L>Nor nothing straining past right, for their right:</L>
<L>Raigne iustly, and raigne safely. Policie</L>
<L>Is but a Guard corrupted, and a way</L>
<L>Venter'd in Desarts, vvithout guide or path.</L>
<L>Kings punish Subiects errors vvith their owne.</L>
<L>Kings are like Archers, and their Subiects, shafts:</L>
<L>For as when Archers let their arrowes flye,</L>
<L>They call to them, and bid them flye or fall,</L>
<L>As if twere in the free power of the shaft</L>
<L>To flye or fall, when onely tis the strength,</L>
<L>Straight shooting, compasse giuen it by the Archer,</L>
<L>That makes it hit or misse; and doing eyther,</L>
<L>Hee<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s to be prais'd or blam'd, and not the shaft:</L>
<L><PB REF="29"/>So Kings to Subiects crying, doe, doe not this;</L>
<L>Must to them by their owne examples strength,</L>
<L>The straightnesse of their acts, and equall compasse,</L>
<L>Giue Subiects power t'obey them in the like;</L>
<L>Not shoote them forth with faultie ayme and strength,</L>
<L>And lay the fault in them for flying amisse,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aum.</SPEAKER>
<L>But for your seruant, I dare sweare him guiltlesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Count.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee would not for his Kingdome traitor be;</L>
<L>His Lawes are not so true to him, as he.</L>
<L>O knew I how to free him, by way forc'd</L>
<L>Through all their armie, I would flye, and doe it:</L>
<L>And had I, of my courage and resolue,</L>
<L>But tenne such more, they should not all retaine him;</L>
<L>But I will neuer die, before I giue</L>
<L>Maillard an hundred slashes with a sword,</L>
<L>Chalon an hundred breaches with a Pistoll.</L>
<L>They could not all haue taken Clermont D'Ambois,</L>
<L>Without their treacherie; he had bought his bands out</L>
<L>With their slaue blouds: but he was credulous;</L>
<L>Hee would beleeue, since he would be beleeu'd;</L>
<L>Your noblest natures are most credulous.</L>
<L>Who giues no trust, all trust is apt to breake;</L>
<L>Hate like hell mouth, who thinke not what they speake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aum.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, Madame, I must tender my attendance</L>
<L>On him againe. Will't please you to returne</L>
<L>No seruice to him by me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Count.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fetch me straight</L>
<L>My little Cabinet. <STAGE>[Exit Ancil.]</STAGE> Tis little tell him,</L>
<L>And much too little for his matchlesse loue:</L>
<L>But as in him the worths of many men</L>
<L>Are close contracted; <STAGE>[Intr. Ancil.]</STAGE> so in this are Iewels</L>
<L>Worth many Cabinets. Here, with this (good sir)</L>
<L>Commend my kindest seruice to my seruant,</L>
<L>Thanke him, with all my comforts; and, in them</L>
<L>With all my life for them: all sent from him</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n his remembrance of mee, and true loue:</L>
<L>And looke you tell him, tell him how I lye</L>
<STAGE>She kneeles downe at his feete.</STAGE>
<L>Prostrate at feet of his accurst misfortune,</L>
<L><PB REF="30"/>Pouring my teares out, which shall euer fall,</L>
<L>Till I haue pour'd for him out eyes and all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aum.</SPEAKER>
<L>O Madame, this will kill him: comfort you</L>
<L>With full assurance of his quicke acquitall;</L>
<L>Be not so passionate: rise▪ cease your teares.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Coun.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then must my life cease. Teares are all the vent</L>
<L>My life hath to scape death: Teares please me better,</L>
<L>Then all lifes comforts, being the naturall seede</L>
<L>Of heartie sorrow. As a tree fruit beares,</L>
<STAGE>Hee raises her, and leades her out. Exe.</STAGE>
<L>So doth an vndissembled sorrow, teares.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vsh.</SPEAKER>
<L>This might haue beene before, and sau'd much charge.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Henry, Guise, Baligny, Esp. Soisson.
Pericot with pen, inck<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, and paper.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guise.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now sir, I hope you're much abus'd Eyes see</L>
<L>In my word for my Clermont, what a villaine</L>
<L>Hee was that whisper'd in your iealous eare</L>
<L>His owne blacke treason in suggesting Clermonts:</L>
<L>Colour'd with nothing but being great with mee,</L>
<L>Signe then this writ for his deliuerie,</L>
<L>Your hand was neuer vrg'd with worthier boldnesse:</L>
<L>Come, pray sir, signe it: why should Kings be praid</L>
<L>To acts of Iustice? tis a reuerence</L>
<L>Makes them despis'd, and showes they sticke and tyre</L>
<L>In what their free powers should be hot as fire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, take your will sir, Ile haue mine ere long.</L>
<L>But wherein is this Clermont such a rare one?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guis<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L>In his most gentle, and vnwearied minde,</L>
<L>Rightly to vertue fram'd; in very nature;</L>
<L>In his most firme inexorable spirit,</L>
<L>To be remou'd from any thing hee chuseth</L>
<L>For worthinesse; or beare the lest perswasion</L>
<L>To what is base, or fitteth not his obiect;</L>
<L>In his contempt of riches and of greatnesse;</L>
<L>In <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>stimation of th'Idolatrous vulgar;</L>
<L>His scorne of all things seruile and ignoble,</L>
<L>Though they could gaine him neuer such aduancement;</L>
<L>His liberall kinde of speaking what is truth,</L>
<L><PB REF="30"/>In spight of temporising; the great rising,</L>
<L>and learning of his soule, so much the more</L>
<L>Against ill fortune, as shee set her selfe</L>
<L>Sharpe against him, or would present most hard,</L>
<L>To shunne the malice of her deadliest charge;</L>
<L>His detestation of his speciall friends,</L>
<L>When he perceiu'd their tyrannous will to doe,</L>
<L>Or their abiection basely to sustaine</L>
<L>Any iniustice that they could reuenge;</L>
<L>The flexibilitie of his most anger,</L>
<L>Euen in the maine careere and fury of it,</L>
<L>When any obiect of desertfull pittie</L>
<L>Offers it selfe to him; his sweet disposure</L>
<L>As much abhorring to behold, as doe</L>
<L>Any vnnaturall and bloudy action;</L>
<L>His iust <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ontempt of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>esters, Parasites,</L>
<L>Seruile obseruers, and polluted tongues:</L>
<L>In sho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>, this Senecall man is found in him,</L>
<L>Hee may with heauens immortall powers compare,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> the day and fortune equall are,</L>
<L>Come faire or foule, what euer chance can fall,</L>
<L>Fix<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> himselfe, hee still is one to all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Showes he to others thus?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Om<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es.</SPEAKER>
<L>To all that know him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hen.</SPEAKER>
<L>And apprehend I this man for a traitor?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guise.</SPEAKER>
<L>These are your Macheuilian Villaines,</L>
<L>Your bastard Teucers, that their mischiefes done,</L>
<L>Runne to your shield for shelter: Caucusses,</L>
<L>That cut their too large murtherous theueries,</L>
<L>To their dens length still: woe be to that state</L>
<L>Where treacherie guards, and ruine makes men grea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe, take my Letters for him, and release him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Om.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thankes to your Highnesse, euer liue your Highnesse.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeuent.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Better a man were buried quicke, then liue</L>
<L>A propertie for state, and spoile, to thriue.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Clermont, Mail. Chal. with Souldiers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mail.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee ioy you take a chance so ill, so well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who euer saw me differ in acceptance</L>
<L><PB REF="31"/>Of eyther fortune?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chal.</SPEAKER>
<L>What, loue bad, like good?</L>
<L>How should one learne that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>To loue nothing outward,</L>
<L>Or not within our owne powers to command;</L>
<L>And so being sure of euery thing we loue,</L>
<L>Who cares to lose the rest: if any man</L>
<L>Would neyther liue nor dye in his free choise,</L>
<L>But as hee sees necessitie will haue it,</L>
<L>(Which if hee would resist, hee striues in vaine)</L>
<L>What can come neere him, that hee doth not well,</L>
<L>And if in worst euents, his will be done;</L>
<L>How can the best be better? all is one.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mail.</SPEAKER>
<L>Me thinkes tis prettie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Put no difference</L>
<L>If you haue this, or not this; but as children</L>
<L>Playing at co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tes, euer regard their game,</L>
<L>And care not for their coites; so let a man</L>
<L>The things themselues that touch him not esteeme,</L>
<L>But his free power in well disposing them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prettie from toyes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Me thinkes this double disticke</L>
<L>Seemes prettily too, to stay superfluous longings:</L>
<L>Not to haue want, what riches doth exceede?</L>
<L>Not to be subiect, what superiour thing?</L>
<L>He that to nought aspires, doth nothing neede;</L>
<L>Who breakes no Law is subiect to no King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mail.</SPEAKER>
<L>This goes to mine eare well I promise you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chal.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, but tis passing hard to stay one thus.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis so; rancke custome raps men so beyond it,</L>
<L>And as tis hard, so well mens dores to barre</L>
<L>To keepe the cat out, and th'adulterer;</L>
<L>So tis as hard to curbe affections so,</L>
<L>Wee let in nought to make them ouer-flow.</L>
<L>And as of Homers verses, many Critickes</L>
<L>On those stand, of which times old moth hath eaten,</L>
<L>The first or last feete, and the perfect parts,</L>
<L>of his vnmatched Poeme sinke beneath,</L>
<L><PB REF="31"/>With vpright gasping, and sloath dull as death:</L>
<L>So the vnprofitable things of life,</L>
<L>And those we cannot compasse, we affect;</L>
<L>All that doth profit, and wee haue, neglect,</L>
<L>Like couetous, and basely getting men,</L>
<L>That gathering much, vse neuer vvhat they keepe;</L>
<L>But for the least they loose, extreamely vveepe,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mail.</SPEAKER>
<L>This prettie talking and our horses walking</L>
<L>Downe this steepe hill, spends time with equall profit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis well bestow'd on ye, meate and men sicke</L>
<L>Agree like this, and you; and yet euen this</L>
<L>Is th'end of all skill, power, wealth, all that is.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chal.</SPEAKER>
<L>I long to heare sir, how your Mistresse takes this.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Aumal with a Cabinet.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mail.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee soone shall know it: see Aumall return'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aum.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ease to your bands sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Welcome worthy friend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chal.</SPEAKER>
<L>How tooke his noblest Mistresse your sad message?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aum.</SPEAKER>
<L>As great rich men take sodaine pouertie,</L>
<L>I neuer witness'd a more noble loue,</L>
<L>Nor a more ruthfull sorrow: I well wisht</L>
<L>Some other had beene master of my message.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mail.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'are happy sir, in all things, but this one,</L>
<L>Of your vnhappy apprehension.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is to mee, compar'd with her much mone,</L>
<L>As one teare is to her whole passion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aum.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, shee commends her kindest seruice to you,</L>
<L>And this rich Cabinet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chal.</SPEAKER>
<L>O happy man.</L>
<L>This may enough hold to redeeme your bands.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>These clouds I doubt not, will be soone blowne ouer.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Baligny with his discharge: Renel, and others.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aum.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your hope is iust and happy, see sir both</L>
<L>In both the looks of these.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here's a discharge</L>
<L>For this your prisoner, my good Lord Lieutenant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="32"/>
<SPEAKER>Mail</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas, sir, I vsurpe that stile enforc't,</L>
<L>And hope you know it was not my aspiring.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well sir, my wrong aspir'd past all mens hopes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l.</SPEAKER>
<L>I sorrow for it sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ren.</SPEAKER>
<L>You see sir there</L>
<L>Your prisoners discharge autenticall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mail.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is sir, and I yeeld it him with gladnesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Brother, I brought you downe to much good purpose.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Repeate not that sir: the amends makes all:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ren.</SPEAKER>
<L>I ioy in it, my best and worthiest friend,</L>
<L>O y'haue a princely fautor of the Guise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thinke I did my part to.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ren.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, sir; all</L>
<L>Is in the issue vvell: and (vvorthiest Friend)</L>
<L>Here's from your friend the Guise; here from the Countesse,</L>
<L>Your Brothers Mistresse, the contents vvhereof</L>
<L>I know, and must prepare you now to please</L>
<L>Th'vnrested spirit of your slaughtered brother,</L>
<L>If it be true, as you imagin'd once,</L>
<L>His apparition show'd it▪ the complot</L>
<L>Is now laid sure betwixt vs; therefore haste</L>
<L>Both to your great friend (vvho hath some vse vvaightie</L>
<L>For your repaire to him) and to the Countesse,</L>
<L>Whose satisfaction is no lesse important.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>I see all, and vvill haste as it importeth.</L>
<L>And good friend, since I must delay a little</L>
<L>My wisht attendance on my noblest Mistresse,</L>
<L>Excuse me to her, with returne of this,</L>
<L>And endlesse protestation of my seruice;</L>
<L>And now become as glad a messenger,</L>
<L>As you vvere late a vvofull.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m.</SPEAKER>
<L>Happy change,</L>
<L>I <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uer vvill salute thee with my seruice</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet more newes Brother; the late iesting Monsieur</L>
<L>Makes now your Brothers dying prophesie equall</L>
<L>At all parts, being dead as he presag'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ren.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heauen shield the Guise from seconding that truth,</L>
<L>With what he likewise prophesied on him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="32"/>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>It hath enough, twas grac'd with truth in one,</L>
<L>To'th other falshood and confusion.</L>
<L>Leade to'th Court sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>You Ile leade no more,</L>
<L>It was to ominous and foule before.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<TRAILER>Finis Actus quarti.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="5" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus quinti</HEAD>
<HEAD>Scaena prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Ascendit Vmbra Bussi.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vmb.</SPEAKER>
<L>VP from the Chaos of eternall night,</L>
<L>(To vvhich the whole digestion of the world</L>
<L>Is now returning) once more I ascend,</L>
<L>And bide the cold dampe of this piercing ayre.</L>
<L>To vrge the iustice, whose almightie word</L>
<L>Measures the bloudy acts of impious men,</L>
<L>With equall pennance, who in th'act it selfe</L>
<L>Includes th'infliction, which like chained shot</L>
<L>Batter together still; though (as the thunder</L>
<L>Seemes, by mens duller hearing then their sight,</L>
<L>To breake a great time after lightning forth,</L>
<L>Yet both at one time teare the labouring cloud,)</L>
<L>So men thinke pennance of their ils is slow,</L>
<L>Though th'ill and pennance still together goe.</L>
<L>Reforme yee ignorant men, your manlesse liues</L>
<L>Whose lawes yee thinke are nothing but your lusts▪</L>
<L>When leauing but for supposition sake,</L>
<L>The body of felicitie (Religion)</L>
<L>Set in the midst of Christendome, and her head</L>
<L>Cleft to her bosome; one halfe one vvay swaying</L>
<L>Another th'other: all the Christian world</L>
<L>And all her lawes, vvhose obseruation,</L>
<L>Stands vpon faith, aboue the power of reason:</L>
<L>Leauing (I say) all these, this might suffice,</L>
<L>To fray yee from your vicious swindge in ill,</L>
<L><PB REF="33"/>And set you more on fire to doe more good:</L>
<L>That since the vvorld (as vvhich of you denies)</L>
<L>Stands by proportion, all may the<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ce conclude,</L>
<L>That all the ioynts and nerues sustaining nature,</L>
<L>As well may breake, and yet the vvorld abide,</L>
<L>As any one good vnrewarded die,</L>
<L>Or any one ill scape his penaltie.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>The Ghost stands close.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Guise, Clermont.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>G<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>i.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thus (friend) thou seest how all good men would thriue,</L>
<L>Did not the good thou prompt'st me with preuent,</L>
<L>The iealous ill pursuing them in others.</L>
<L>But now thy dangers are dispatc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t, note mine:</L>
<L>Hast thou not heard of that admired voyce,</L>
<L>That at the Barricadoes spake to mee,</L>
<L>(No person seene) Let's leade (my Lord) to Reimes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor could you learne the person?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guise.</SPEAKER>
<L>By no meanes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Twas but your fancie then a waking dreame:</L>
<L>For as in sleepe, which bindes both th' outward senses,</L>
<L>And the sense common to; th'imagining power</L>
<L>(Stird vp by formes hid in the memories store,</L>
<L>Or by the vapours of o'er-flowing humours</L>
<L>In bodies full and foule; and mixt vvith spirits,)</L>
<L>Faines many strange, miraculous images,</L>
<L>In which act, it so painfully applyes</L>
<L>It selfe to those formes, that the common sense</L>
<L>It actuates with his motion; and thereby</L>
<L>Those fictions true seeme, and haue reall act:</L>
<L>So, in the strength of our conceits, awake,</L>
<L>The cause alike, doth of like fictions make.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guise.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be what it vvill, twas a presage of something</L>
<L>Waightie and secret, vvhich th'aduertisements</L>
<L>I haue receiu'd from all parts, both vvithout,</L>
<L>And in this Kingdome, as from Rome and Spaine</L>
<L>Soccaine and Sauoye, giues me cause to thinke,</L>
<L>All vvriting that our plots Catastrophe,</L>
<L>For propagation of the Catholique cause,</L>
<L><PB REF="33"/>Will bloudy proue, dissoluing all our counsailes▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Retyre then from them all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guise.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must not doe so.</L>
<L>The Arch-Bishop of Lyons tels me plaine</L>
<L>I shall be said then to abandon France</L>
<L>In so important an occasion:</L>
<L>And that mine enemies (their profit making</L>
<L>Of my faint absence) soone would let that fall,</L>
<L>That all my paines did to this height exhale.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let all fall that would rise vnlawfully:</L>
<L>Make not your forward spirit in vertues right,</L>
<L>A property for vice, by thrusting on</L>
<L>Further then all your powers can fetch you off.</L>
<L>It is enough, your will is infinite</L>
<L>To all things vertuous and religious,</L>
<L>Which within limits kept, may without danger,</L>
<L>Let vertue some good from your Graces gather,</L>
<L>Auarice of all is euer nothings father.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vmb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Danger (the spurre of all great mindes) is euer</L>
<L>The curbe to your tame spirits; you respect not</L>
<L>(With all your holinesse of life and learning)</L>
<L>More then the present, like illiterate vulgars,</L>
<L>Your minde (you say) kept in your fleshes bounds,</L>
<L>Showes that mans will must rul'd be by his power:</L>
<L>When (by true doctrine) you are taught to liue</L>
<L>Rather without the body, then within;</L>
<L>And rather to your God still then your selfe:</L>
<L>To liue to him, is to doe all things fitting</L>
<L>His Image, in which, like himselfe we liue;</L>
<L>To be his Image, is to doe those things,</L>
<L>That make vs deathlesse, which by death is onely;</L>
<L>Doing those deedes that fit eternitie,</L>
<L>And those deedes are the perfecting that Iustice,</L>
<L>That makes the world last, which proportion is</L>
<L>Of punishment and wreake for euery wrong,</L>
<L>As well as for right a reward as strong:</L>
<L>Away then, vse the meanes thou hast to right</L>
<L>The wrong I suffer'd. What corrupted Law</L>
<L><PB REF="34"/>Leaues vnperform'd in Kings, doe thou supply,</L>
<L>And be aboue them all in dignitie.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guise.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why stand'st thou still thus, and applyest thine eares,</L>
<L>And eyes to nothing?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Saw you nothing here?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guise.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou dream'st, awake now; what was here to see?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Brothers spirit, vrging his reuenge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guise.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy Brothers spirit! pray thee mocke me not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, by my loue and seruice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guise.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would he rise,</L>
<L>And not be thundring threates against the Guise?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r.</SPEAKER>
<L>You make amends for enmitie to him,</L>
<L>With tenne parts more loue, and desert of mee;</L>
<L>And as you make your hate to him, no let</L>
<L>Of any loue to mee; no more beares hee</L>
<L>(Since you to me supply it) hate to you,</L>
<L>Which reason and which Iustice is perform'd</L>
<L>In Spirits tenne parts more then fleshy men.</L>
<L>To whose fore-sights our acts and thoughts lie open:</L>
<L>And therefore since hee saw the treacherie</L>
<L>Late practis'd by my brother Baligny,</L>
<L>Hee would not honor his hand with the iustice</L>
<L>(As hee esteemes it) of his blouds reuenge,</L>
<L>To which my Sister needes would haue him sworne,</L>
<L>Before she would consent to marry him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guise.</SPEAKER>
<L>O Baligny, who would beleeue there were</L>
<L>A man, that (onely since his lookes are rais'd</L>
<L>Vpwards, and haue but sacred heauen in sight)</L>
<L>Could beare a minde so more then diuellish?</L>
<L>As for the painted glory of the countenance,</L>
<L>Flitting in Kings, doth good for nought esteeme,</L>
<L>And the more ill hee does, the better seeme.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee easily may beleeue it, since we see</L>
<L>In this worlds practise few men better be.</L>
<L>Iustice to liue doth nought but Iustice neede,</L>
<L>But Policie must still on mischiefe feede.</L>
<L>Vntruth for all his ends, truths name doth sue in;</L>
<L>None safely liue, but those that study ruine.</L>
<L><PB REF="34"/>A good man happy, is a common good;</L>
<L>Ill men aduanc'd liue of the common bloud.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guise.</SPEAKER>
<L>But this thy brothers spirit startles mee,</L>
<L>These spirits seld or neuer hanting men,</L>
<L>But some mishap ensues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ensue what can:</L>
<L>Tyrants may kill, but neuer hurt a man;</L>
<L>All to his good makes, spight of death and hell.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Aumall.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aum.</SPEAKER>
<L>All the desert of good, renowne your Highnesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guise.</SPEAKER>
<L>Welcome Aumall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>My good friend, friendly welcome.</L>
<L>How tooke my noblest mistresse the chang'd newes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aum.</SPEAKER>
<L>It came too late sir, for those loueliest eyes</L>
<L>(Through which a soule look't so diuinely louing,</L>
<L>Teares nothing vttering her distresse enough)</L>
<L>She wept quite out, and like two falling Starres</L>
<L>Their dearest sights quite vanisht with her teares.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>All good forbid it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guise.</SPEAKER>
<L>What euents are these?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>All must be borne my Lord: and yet this chance</L>
<L>Would willingly enforce a man to cast off</L>
<L>All power to beare with comfort, since hee sees</L>
<L>In this, our comforts made our miseries.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guise.</SPEAKER>
<L>How strangely thou art lou'd of both the sexes;</L>
<L>Yet thou lou'st neyther, but the good of both.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>In loue of women, my affection first</L>
<L>Takes fire out of the fraile parts of my bloud;</L>
<L>Which till I haue enioy'd, is passionate,</L>
<L>Like other louers: but fruition past▪</L>
<L>I then loue out of iudgement; the desert</L>
<L>Of her I loue, still sticking in my heart,</L>
<L>Though the desire, and the delight be gone,</L>
<L>Which must chance still, since the comparison</L>
<L>Made vpon tryall twixt what reason loues,</L>
<L>And what affection, makes in mee the best</L>
<L>Euer preferd; what most loue, valuing lest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="35"/>
<SPEAKER>Guise.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy loue being iudgement then, and of the minde,</L>
<L>Marry thy worthiest mistresse now being blinde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>If there were loue in mariage so I would;</L>
<L>But I denie that any man doth loue,</L>
<L>Affecting vviues, maides, widowes, any women:</L>
<L>For neither Fly<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s loue milke, although they drowne</L>
<L>In greedy search thereof; nor doth the Bee</L>
<L>Loue honey, though the labour of her life</L>
<L>Is spent in gathering it; nor those that fat</L>
<L>Or beasts▪ or fowles, doe any thing therein</L>
<L>For any loue: for as when onely nature</L>
<L>Moues men to meate, as farre as her power rules,</L>
<L>Shee doth it with a temperate appetite,</L>
<L>The too much men deuoure, abhorring nature;</L>
<L>And in our most health, is our most disease:</L>
<L>So, when humanitie rules men and vvomen.</L>
<L>Tis for societie confinde in reason.</L>
<L>But what excites the beds desire in bloud,</L>
<L>By no meanes iustly can be construed loue;</L>
<L>For when loue kindles any knowing spirit,</L>
<L>It ends in vertue and effects diuine;</L>
<L>And is in friendship chaste, and masculine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guise.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou shalt my Mistresse be; me thinkes my bloud</L>
<L>Is taken vp to all loue vvith thy vertues.</L>
<L>And howsoeuer other men despise</L>
<L>These Paradoxes strange, and too precise,</L>
<L>Since they hold on the right way of our reason,</L>
<L>I could attend them euer. Come, away;</L>
<L>Performe thy brothers thus importun'd wreake;</L>
<L>And I will see what great affaires the King</L>
<L>Hath to employ my counsell, which he seemes</L>
<L>Much to desire, and more and more esteemes.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Henry, Baligny, with sixe of the guard.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Saw you his sawcie forcing of my hand</L>
<L>To D'Ambois freedome?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Saw, and through mine eyes</L>
<L>Le<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ire into my heart, that burn'd to beare</L>
<L><PB REF="35"/>An insolence so Giantly austere.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hen.</SPEAKER>
<L>The more Kings beare at Subiects hands, the more</L>
<L>Their lingring Iustice gathers; that resembles</L>
<L>The waightie, and the goodly-bodied Eagle,</L>
<L>Who (being on earth) before her shady wings</L>
<L>Can raise her into ayre, a mightie way</L>
<L>Close by the ground she runnes; but being aloft,</L>
<L>All shee commands, she flyes at; and the more</L>
<L>Death in her Seres beares, the more time shee stayes</L>
<L>Her thundry stoope from that on which shee preyes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>You must be then more secret in the waight</L>
<L>Of these your shadie counsels, who will else</L>
<L>Beare (where such sparkes flye as the Guise and D'Ambois)</L>
<L>Pouder about them. Counsels (as your en<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ailes)</L>
<L>Should be vnpierst and sound kept; for not those,</L>
<L>Whom you discouer, you neglect; but ope</L>
<L>A ruinous passage to your owne best hope.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee haue Spies set on vs, as we on others;</L>
<L>And therefore they that serue vs must excuse vs,</L>
<L>If what wee most hold in our hearts, take winde,</L>
<L>Deceit hath eyes that see into the minde.</L>
<L>But this plot shall be quicker then their twinckling,</L>
<L>On whose lids Fate, with her dead waight shall lie,</L>
<L>And Confidence that lightens ere she die.</L>
<L>Friends of my Guard, as yee gaue othe to be</L>
<L>True to your Soueraigne, keepe it manfully:</L>
<L>Your eyes haue witnest oft th'Ambition</L>
<L>That neuer made accesse to me in Guise</L>
<L>But Treason euer sparkled in his eyes:</L>
<L>Which if you free vs of, our safetie shall</L>
<L>You not our Subiects, but our Patrons call.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our duties binde vs, hee is now but dead.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee trust in it, and thanke ye. Baligny,</L>
<L>Goe lodge their ambush, and thou God that art</L>
<L>Fautor of Princes▪ thunder from the skies,</L>
<L>Beneath his hill of pride this Gyant Guise.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE><PB REF="36"/>Enter Tamyra with a Letter, Charlotte in mans attire.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>I see y'are Seruant, sir, to my deare sister,</L>
<L>The Lady of her lou'd Baligny.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Char.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madame I am bound to her vertuous bounties,</L>
<L>For that li<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e which I offer in her vertuous seruice,</L>
<L>To the reuenge of her renowned brother.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>She writes to mee as much, and much desires,</L>
<L>That you may be the man, whose spirit shee knowes</L>
<L>Will cut short off these long and dull delayes,</L>
<L>Hitherto to bribing the eternall Iustice:</L>
<L>Which I beleeue, since her vnmatched spirit</L>
<L>Can iudge of spirits, that haue her sulphure in them;</L>
<L>But I must tell you, that I make no doubt,</L>
<L>Her liuing brother will reuenge her dead,</L>
<L>On whom the dead impos'd the taske▪ and hee,</L>
<L>I know, will come t'effect it instantly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Char.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are but words in him; beleeue them not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>See; this is the vault, where he must enter:</L>
<L>Where now I thinke hee is.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Renel at the vault, with the Countesse being blinde.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ren.</SPEAKER>
<L>God saue you Lady.</L>
<L>What Gentleman is this, with whom you trust</L>
<L>The deadly waightie secret of this houre?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>One that your selfe will say, I well may trust.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>R<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then come vp Madame.</L>
<STAGE>He helps the Countesse vp.</STAGE>
<L>See here honour'd Lady,</L>
<L>A Countesse that in loues mishap doth equall</L>
<L>At all parts▪ your wrong'd selfe; and is the mistresse</L>
<L>Of your slaine seruants brother; in whose loue</L>
<L>For his late treachrous apprehension,</L>
<L>She wept her faire eyes from her luory browes,</L>
<L>And would haue wept her soule out, had not I</L>
<L>Promist to bring her to this mortall quarrie,</L>
<L>That by her lost eyes for her seruants loue,</L>
<L>She might coniure him from this sterne attempt,</L>
<L>In which, (by a most ominous dreame shee had)</L>
<L><PB REF="36"/>Shee knowes his death fixt, and that neuer more</L>
<L>Out of this place the Sunne shall see him liue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Char.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am prouided then to take his place,</L>
<L>And vndertaking on me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ren.</SPEAKER>
<L>You sir, why?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Char.</SPEAKER>
<L>Since I am charg'd so by my mistresse,</L>
<L>His mournfull sister.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>See her Letter sir.</L>
<STAGE>Hee reades.</STAGE>
<L>Good Madame, I rue your fate, more then mine,</L>
<L>And know not how to order these affaires,</L>
<L>They stand on such occurrents.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ren.</SPEAKER>
<L>This indeede,</L>
<L>I know to be your Lady mistresse hand,</L>
<L>And know besides, his brother will, and must</L>
<L>Indure no hand in this reuenge but his.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Vmbr. Bussy.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vmb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away, dispute no more; get vp, and see,</L>
<L>Clermont must auchthor this iust Tragedie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Coun.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who's that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ren.</SPEAKER>
<L>The spirit of Bussy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>O my seruant! let vs embrace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vmb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Forbeare. The ayre, in which</L>
<L>My figures liknesse is imprest, will blast,</L>
<L>Let my reuenge for all loues satisfie,</L>
<L>In vvhich (dame) feare not, Clermont shall not dye:</L>
<L>No word dispute more, vp, and see th'euent.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt Lady<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s.</STAGE>
<L>Make the Guard sure Renel; and then the doores</L>
<L>Command to make fast, when the Earle is in.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Ren.</STAGE>
<L>The blacke soft-footed houre is now on wing,</L>
<L>Which for my iust wreake, Ghosts shall celebrate,</L>
<L>With dances dire, and of infernall state.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Guise.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guise.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who sayes that death is naturall, vvhen natur<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Is with the onely thought of it, dismaid?</L>
<L>I haue had Lotteries set vp for my death,</L>
<L>And I haue drawne beneath my trencher one,</L>
<L>Knit in my hand-kerchiefe another lot,</L>
<L>The word being; Y'are a dead man if you enter,</L>
<L><PB REF="37"/>And these words, this imperfect bloud and flesh,</L>
<L>Shrincke at in spight of me; their solidst part</L>
<L>Melting like snow within mee, with colde fire:</L>
<L>I hate my selfe, that seeking to rule Kings,</L>
<L>I cannot curbe my slaue. Would any spirit</L>
<L>F<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ee, manly, Princely, wish to liue to be</L>
<L>Commanded by this masse of slauerie,</L>
<L>Since Reason, Iudgement, Resolution,</L>
<L>And scorne of what we feare, will yeeld to feare?</L>
<L>While this same sincke of sensualitie swels,</L>
<L>Who would liue sinking in it? and not spring</L>
<L>Vp to the Starres, and leaue this carrion here,</L>
<L>For Wolfes, and Vultures, and for Dogges to teare?</L>
<L>O Clermont D'Ambois, wert thou here to chide</L>
<L>This softnesse from my flesh, farre as my reason,</L>
<L>Farre as my resolution, not to stirre</L>
<L>One foote out of the way, for death and hell.</L>
<L>Let my <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>alse man by falshood perish here,</L>
<L>There's no way else to set my true man cleere.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Messenger.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mess.</SPEAKER>
<L>The King desires your Grace to come to Councill.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guise.</SPEAKER>
<L>I come. It cannot be: hee will not dare</L>
<L>To touch me with a treacherie so prophane.</L>
<L>Would Clermont now were here, to try how hee</L>
<L>Would lay about him, if this plot should be:</L>
<L>Here would be tossing soules into the skie.</L>
<L>Who euer knew bloud sau'd by treacherie?</L>
<L>Well, I must on, and will; what should I feare?</L>
<L>Not against two, Alcides? against two</L>
<L>And Hercules to friend, the Guise will goe.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>He takes vp the Arras, and the Guard enters vpon him: hee drawes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guise.</SPEAKER>
<L>Holde murtherers.</L>
<STAGE>They strike him downe.</STAGE>
<L>So then, this is confidence</L>
<L>In greatnes, not in goodnes: wher is the king?</L>
<STAGE>The king comes in sight with Es. Sois. &amp; others.</STAGE>
<L>Let him appeare to iustifie his deede.</L>
<L><PB REF="37"/>In spight of my betrai'd wounds; ere my soule</L>
<L>Take her flight through them, and my tongue hath strength</L>
<L>To vrge his tyrannie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hen.</SPEAKER>
<L>See sir▪ I am come</L>
<L>To iustifie it before men, and God,</L>
<L>Who knowes with what wounds in my heart for woe</L>
<L>Of your so wounded faith, I made these wounds,</L>
<L>Forc't to it by an insolence of force</L>
<L>To stirre a stone, nor is a rocke oppos'd</L>
<L>To all the billowes of the churlish sea,</L>
<L>More beate, and eaten with them, then was I</L>
<L>With your ambitious mad Idolatrie;</L>
<L>And this bloud I shed, is to saue the bloud</L>
<L>Of many thousands.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guise.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's your white pretext,</L>
<L>But you will finde one drop of bloud shed lawlesse,</L>
<L>Will be the fountaine to a purple sea:</L>
<L>The present lust, and shift made for Kings liues</L>
<L>Against the pure forme, and iust power of Law,</L>
<L>Will thriue like shifters purchases; there hangs</L>
<L>A blacke Starre in the skies, to which the Sunne</L>
<L>Giues yet no light, will raine a poyson'd shower</L>
<L>Into your entrailes, that will make you feele</L>
<L>How little safetie lies in treacherous steele.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well sir, Ile beare it; y'haue a Brother to,</L>
<L>Bursts with like threates, the skarlet Cardinall:</L>
<L>Seeke, and lay hands on him; and take this hence,</L>
<L>Their blouds, for all you, on my conscience.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guise.</SPEAKER>
<L>So sir, your full swindge take; mine, death hath curb'd.</L>
<L>Clermont, farewell: O didst thou see but this:</L>
<L>But it is better, see by this the Ice</L>
<L>Broke to thine owne bloud, which thou wilt despise,</L>
<L>When thou hear'st mine shed. Is there no friend here</L>
<L>Will beare my loue to him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aum.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will, my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guise.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thankes with my last breath: recommend <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e then</L>
<L>To the most worthy of the race of men.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Dyes. E<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Monts. and Tamyra.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who haue you let into my house?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, none.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="38"/>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis false, I sauour the rancke bloud of foes</L>
<L>In euery corner.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>That you may doe well,</L>
<L>It is the bloud you lately shed, you smell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sdeath the vault opes.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>The gulfe opens.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>What vault? hold your sword.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Clermont ascends.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, let him vse it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Treason, murther, murther.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Exclaime not; tis in vaine, and base in you,</L>
<L>Being one, to onely one.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>O bloudy strumpet!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>With what bloud charge you her? it may be mine</L>
<L>As well as yours; there shall not any else</L>
<L>Enter or touch you: I conferre no guards,</L>
<L>Nor imitate the murtherous course you tooke;</L>
<L>But single here, will haue my former challenge,</L>
<L>Now answer'd single, not a minute more</L>
<L>My brothers bloud shall stay for his reuenge,</L>
<L>If I can act it; if not, mine shall adde</L>
<L>A double conquest to you, that alone</L>
<L>Put it to fortune now, and vse no ods.</L>
<L>Storme not, nor beate your selfe thus gainst the dores,</L>
<L>Like to a sauage vermine in a trap:</L>
<L>All dores are sure made, and you cannot scape,</L>
<L>But by your valour,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, no, come and kill me<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you will die so like a beast, you shall,</L>
<L>But when the spirit of a man may saue you,</L>
<L>Doe not so shame man, and a Noble man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe not show this basenesse, that I feare thee,</L>
<L>But to preuent and shame thy victory,</L>
<L>Which of one base is base, and so Ile die.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay, hold, one thought hath harden'd me,</L>
<STAGE>He starts vp.</STAGE>
<L>And since I must afford thee victorie,</L>
<L>It shall be great and braue, if one request</L>
<L>Thou wilt admit mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Giue me leaue</L>
<L>To fetch and vse the sword thy Brother gaue mee</L>
<L>When he was brauely giuing vp his life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, Ile not fight against my brothers sword,</L>
<L>Not that I feare it, but since tis a tricke,</L>
<L><PB REF="38"/>For you to show your backe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>By all truth, no:</L>
<L>Take but my honourable othe, I will not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your honourable othe, plaine truth no place ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Where othes are honourable.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Trust not his othe.</L>
<L>Hee will lie like a Lapwing, when shee flyes</L>
<L>Farre from her sought nest, still here tis shee cryes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Out on thee damme of Diuels, I will quite</L>
<L>Disgrace thy braues conquest, die, not fight.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Lyes downe.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Out on my fortune to wed such an abiect.</L>
<L>Now is the peoples voyce, the voyce of God;</L>
<L>Hee that to wound a vvoman vants so much,</L>
<L>(As hee did mee) a man dares neuer touch.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Reuenge your wounds now madame, I resigne him</L>
<L>Vp to your full vvill, since hee will not fight.</L>
<L>First you shall torture him (as hee did you,</L>
<L>And Iustice wils) and then pay I my vow.</L>
<L>Here, take this Ponyard.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sinke Earth, open Heauen,</L>
<L>And let fall vengeance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come sir, good sir hold him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>O shame of women, whither art thou fled!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why (good my Lord) is it a greater shame</L>
<L>For her then you? come, I will be the bands</L>
<L>You vs'd to her, prophaning her faire hands.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>No sir, Ile fight now, and the terror be</L>
<L>Of all you Champions to such as shee.</L>
<L>I did but thus farre dally: now obserue,</L>
<L>O all you aking fore-heads that haue rob'd,</L>
<L>Your hands of weapons, and your hearts of valour,</L>
<L>Ioyne in mee all your rages, and rebutters,</L>
<L>And into dust ram this same race of Furies,</L>
<L>In this one relicke of the Ambois gall,</L>
<L>In his one purple soule shed, drowne it all.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Fight.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now giue me breath a while.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Receiue it freely.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>What thinke y'a this now?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is very noble.</L>
<L><PB REF="39"/>Had it be<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ne free (at least) and of your selfe,</L>
<L>And thus wee see (where valour most doth vant)</L>
<L>What tis to make a coward valiant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now I shall grace your conquest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>That you shall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you obtaine it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>True sir, tis in fortune.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you were not a D'Ambois, I would scarce</L>
<L>Change liues with you, I feele so great a change</L>
<L>In my tall spirits breath'd, I thinke, with the breath</L>
<L>A D'Ambois breathes here, and necessitie</L>
<L>(With whose point now prickt on, and so, vvhose helpe</L>
<L>My hands may challege, that doth all men conquer,</L>
<L>If shee except not you, of all men onely)</L>
<L>May change the case here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>True as you are chang'd,</L>
<L>Her power in me vrg'd, makes y'another man,</L>
<L>Then yet you euer were.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, I must on.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Lordship must by all meanes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then at all.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Fights, and D'Ambois hurts him.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Charlotte aboue.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Char.</SPEAKER>
<L>Death of my father: what a shame is this,</L>
<L>Sticke in his hands thus?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ren.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gentle sir forbeare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Coun.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is he not slaine yet?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>She gets downe.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ren.</SPEAKER>
<L>No Madame, but hurt in diuers parts of him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'haue giuen it me,</L>
<L>And yet I feele life for another vennie,</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Charlotte.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>What would you sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Char.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would performe this Combat.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Against which of vs?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Char.</SPEAKER>
<L>I care not much if twere</L>
<L>Against thy selfe: thy sister would haue sham'd,</L>
<L>To haue thy Brothers wreake with any man</L>
<L>(In single combat) sticke so in her fingers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Sister? know you her?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>I sir, shee sent him,</L>
<L>With this kinde Letter, to performe the vvreake</L>
<L><PB REF="39"/>Of my deare Seruant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now alas good sir,</L>
<L>Thinke you you could doe more?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Char.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas? I doe,</L>
<L>And wer't not, I, fresh, sound, should charge a man</L>
<L>Weary, and vvounded, I would long ere this,</L>
<L>Haue prou'd what I presume on.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'haue a minde</L>
<L>Like to my Sister, but haue patience now,</L>
<L>If next charge speede not, Ile resigne to you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray thee let him decide it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, my Lord,</L>
<L>I am the man in fate, and since so brauely</L>
<L>Your Lordship stands mee, scape but one more charge,</L>
<L>And on my life, Ile set your life at large.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Said like a D'Ambois, and if now I die,</L>
<L>Sit ioy and all good on thy victorie.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Fights, and fals downe.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Farewell, I hartily forgiue thee. Wife,</L>
<L>And thee, let penitence spend thy rest of life.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Hee giues his hand to Cler. and his Wife.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Noble and Christian.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>O it breakes my heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>And should, for all faults found in him before,</L>
<L>These words, this end, makes full amends and more.</L>
<L>Rest worthy soule, and vvith it the deare spirit</L>
<L>Of my lou'd Brother, rest in endlesse peace:</L>
<L>Soft lie thy bones Heauen be your soules abode,</L>
<L>And to your ashes be the earth no lode.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Musicke, and the Ghost of Bussy enters, leading the Ghost
of the Guise; Monsieur, Cardinall Guise, and Sha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ti∣lion,
they dance about the dead body, and Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>How strange is this? the Guise amongst these spirits,</L>
<L>And his great Brother Cardinall, both yet liuing,</L>
<L>And that the rest vvith them, vvith ioy thus celebrate</L>
<L>This our reuenge? This certainely presages</L>
<L>Some instant death both to the Guise and Cardinall.</L>
<L>That the Shattilians Ghost to should thus ioyne</L>
<L>In celebration of this iust reuenge,</L>
<L><PB REF="40"/>With Guise, that bore a chiefe stroke in his death,</L>
<L>It seemes that now he doth approue the act,</L>
<L>And these true shadowes of the Guise and Cardinall,</L>
<L>Fore-running thus their bodies, may approue</L>
<L>That all things to be done, as here wee liue,</L>
<L>Are done before all times in th'other life.</L>
<L>That Spirits should rise in these times yet are fables;</L>
<L>Though learnedst men hold that our sensiue spirits</L>
<L>A little time abide about the graues</L>
<L>Of their deceased bodies; and can take</L>
<L>In colde condenc't ayre, the same formes they had,</L>
<L>When they were shut vp in this bodies shade.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Aumall.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m.</SPEAKER>
<L>O Sir, the Guise is slaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Auert it Heauen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aum.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sent for to Councill, by the King, an ambush</L>
<L>(Lodg'd for the purpose) rusht<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>on him, and tooke</L>
<L>His Princely life; who sent (in dying then)</L>
<L>His loue to you, as to the best of men.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>The worst, and most accurst of things creeping</L>
<L>On earths sad bosome. Let me pray yee all</L>
<L>A little to forbeare, and let me vse</L>
<L>Freely mine owne minde in lamenting him.</L>
<L>Ile call yee straight againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aum.</SPEAKER>
<L>We will forbeare, and leaue you free sir.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall I liue, and hee</L>
<L>Dead, that alone gaue meanes of life to me?</L>
<L>There's no disputing with the acts of Kings,</L>
<L>Reuenge is impious on their sacred persons:</L>
<L>And could I play the worldling (no man louing</L>
<L>Longer then gaine is reapt, or grace from him)</L>
<L>I should suruiue, and shall be wondred at,</L>
<L>(Though in mine owne hands being) I end with him:</L>
<L>But Friendship is the Sement of two mindes,</L>
<L>As of one man the soule and body is,</L>
<L>Of which one cannot seuer, but the other</L>
<L>Suffers a needfull separation.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Descend Ren. &amp; Coun.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ren.</SPEAKER>
<L>I feare your seruant, Madame: let's descend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="40"/>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Since I could skill of man, I neuer liu'd</L>
<L>To please men worldly, and shall I in death,</L>
<L>Respect their pleasures, making such a iarre</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>etwixt my death and life, when death should make</L>
<L>The consort sweetest; th'end being proofe and crowne</L>
<L>To all the skill and worth wee truely owne?</L>
<L>Guise, O my Lord, how shall I cast from me</L>
<L>The bands and couerts hindring me from thee?</L>
<L>The garment or the couer of the minde,</L>
<L>The humane soule is; of the soule, the spirit</L>
<L>The proper robe is; of the spirit, the bloud;</L>
<L>And of the bloud, the body is the shrowd.</L>
<L>With that must I beginne then to vnclothe,</L>
<L>And come at th'other. Now then as a ship,</L>
<L>Touching at strange, and farre remoued shores;</L>
<L>Her men a shore goe, for their seuerall ends,</L>
<L>Fresh water, victuals, precious stones, and pearle,</L>
<L>All yet intentiue when (the master cals,</L>
<L>The Ship to put off ready) to leaue all</L>
<L>Their greediest labours, lest they there be left,</L>
<L>To the<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ues, or beasts▪ or be the Countries slaues:</L>
<L>So, now my master cals, my ship, my venture</L>
<L>All in one bottome put, all quite put off,</L>
<L>Gone vnder saile, and I left negligent,</L>
<L>To all the horrors of the vicious time,</L>
<L>The farre remou'd shores to all vertuous aimes;</L>
<L>None fauouring goodnesse; none but he respecting</L>
<L>Pietie or man-hood. Shall I here suruiue,</L>
<L>Not cast me after him into the sea,</L>
<L>Rather then here liue, readie euery houre</L>
<L>To feede theeues, beasts, and be the slaue of power?</L>
<L>I come my Lord, Clermont thy creature comes.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Hee Kils himselfe.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Aumal, Tamyra, Charlotte.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aum.</SPEAKER>
<L>What? lye and languish, Clermont? Cursed man</L>
<L>To leaue him here thus: hee hath slaine himselfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Misery on misery! O me wretched Dame</L>
<L>Of all that breath, all heauen turne all his eyes,</L>
<L><PB REF="41"/>In harty enuie, thus on one poore dame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Char.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well done my Brother: I did loue thee euer,</L>
<L>But now adore thee: losse of such a friend</L>
<L>None should suruiue, of such a Brother;</L>
<L>With my false husband liue, and both these slaine:</L>
<L>Ere I returne to him, Ile turne to earth.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Renel leading the Countesse.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ren.</SPEAKER>
<L>Horror of humane ey<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s, O Clermont D'Ambois!</L>
<L>Madame, wee staid too long, your seruant's slaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Coun.</SPEAKER>
<L>It must be so, he liu'd but in the Guise,</L>
<L>As I in him. O follow life mine eyes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hide, hide thy snakie head, to Cloisters flie,</L>
<L>In pennance pine, too easie tis to die.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cler.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is. In Cloisters then let's all suruiue.</L>
<L>Madame, since wrath nor griefe can helpe these fortunes,</L>
<L>Let vs forsake the world, in which they raigne,</L>
<L>And for their wisht amends to God complaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Count.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis fit and onely needfull: leade me on,</L>
<L>In heauens course comfort seeke, in earth is none.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Henry, Espernone, Soissone, and others.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee came indeede too late, which much I <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ue,</L>
<L>And would haue kept this Clermont as my crowne.</L>
<L>Take in the dead, and make this fatall roome</L>
<L>(The house shut vp) the famous D'Ambois Tombe.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
<PB REF="41"/>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

