<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2003-04-22</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Olivia Bottum</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page. Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Added a DIV for the first act, even though it is not explicitly labeled as the others are. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, oe's, and UNCLEARs. Corrected 182 $-groups by inserting vendor-responsible GAPs. Checked for EPIGRAPHs and ARGUMENTs. Checked CLOSERs, BYLINEs and TRAILERs. Checked for startqs, endqs, q;s, and Qs. Checked proofsheets and made corrections. DONE 2003-04-22.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A18596">
<STC T="S">5125</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99843493</BIBNO>
<VID>8232</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>THE
TRAGEDY
OF HOFFMAN
<HI>OR</HI>
A Reuenge for a Father.</P>
<P>As it hath bin diuers times acted
with great applause, at the <HI>Phenix</HI>
in <HI>Druery-lane.</HI></P>
<P><HI>LONDON,</HI>
Printed by <HI>I. N.</HI> for <HI>Hugh Perry,</HI> and are to bee
sold at his shop, at the signe of the <HI>Harrow</HI>
in <HI>Brittaines-burse.</HI> 1631.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>TO HIS MVCH
Honored Friend, Master
Richard Kiluert.</HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>Sir</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">I</SEG> Know you, and in that your worth, which I
honour more, then greatnesse in a Patron:
this Tragedy hapning into my hands, I haue now
aduentured it vnto the Presse, and wanting both
a Parent to owne it, and a Patron to protect it, am
fayne to Act the Fathers part, and haue aduentu∣red
to addresse it vnto your Worthy selfe; vnder
whose wings it flyes for a new birth: it hath passed
the Stage already with good applause, and I doubt
not, but from you it shall receiue a kinde welcome,
who haue alwaies bin a true Fauourer of Artes
and Learning; and from your selfe I haue receiued
so many noble curtesies, that I shall alwayes rest</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Yours to command
HVGH PERRY.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="play">
<PB REF="3"/>
<PB REF="3"/>
<HEAD>The Tragedy of Hoffman.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="act">
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Hoffman.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoffman.</SPEAKER>
<L><SEG REND="decorInit">H</SEG>Ence Clouds of melancholy</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>le be no longer subiect to your sismes,</L>
<L>But thou deare soule, whose nerues and artires</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n dead resoundings summon vp reuenge,</L>
<L>And thou shalt hate, be but appeas'd sweete h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>arse</L>
<L>The dead remembrance of my liuing father</L>
<STAGE>strikes ope a cur∣taine where ap∣peares a body.</STAGE>
<L>And with a hart as aire, swift as thought</L>
<L>I'le excuse iustly in such a cause</L>
<L>Where <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ruth leadeth, what coward would not fight</L>
<L>Ill acts moue some, but myne's a cause is right</L>
<STAGE>thunder and lightning.</STAGE>
<L>See the powers of heauen in apparitions</L>
<L>And fight full aspects as in<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>en<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ed</L>
<L>That <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> thus tardy am to doe an act</L>
<L>which iustice and a fathers death exites,</L>
<L>Like threatening methors antedates destruction.</L>
<STAGE>thunder</STAGE>
<L>Againe I come, I come, I come,</L>
<L>Bee silent thou <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>igies of faire virtue</L>
<L>That like a goodly syen wear't pluckt vp</L>
<L>By murderous, winds, infectious blasts and gusts</L>
<L><PB REF="4"/>I will not leaue thee, vntill like thy selfe,</L>
<L>I'ue made thy enemies, then hand in hand</L>
<L>Wee'le walke to paradise—againe more blest</L>
<L>Ile to yon promonts top, and their suruey,</L>
<L>What shipwrackt passengers the belgique sea</L>
<L>Casts from her fomy entrailes by mischance.</L>
<L>Roare sea and winds, and with celestiall fires,</L>
<L>Quicken high projects, with your highest desires.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Lorrique.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yet this is somewhat like, but brambles, you are to bu∣sie,
were I at <HI>Luningberge,</HI> and you catcht me thus, I should
goe neere to aske you at whose suit, but now I am out of sent,
And feare no <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eriants, for I thinke these woods and waters are
common wealthes that need no such subiects nay they keepe
not a Constable at sea, but a mans ouerwhelmd without
order.—Well, dry land I loue thee, though thou swarme
with millions of deuourers, yet hast thou no such swallow as
the sea.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou lyest, there liues vpon the earth more <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>easts</L>
<L>With wide deuouring throates, then can bee found</L>
<L>Of rauenous fishes in the Ocean:</L>
<L>The huge Leuiathan is but a shrimpe</L>
<L>Compar'd with our Balena on the land</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am of your mind; but the Whale has a wide mouth</L>
<L>To swallow fleeting waters, and poore fish,</L>
<L>But we haue Epicures and Cormorants,</L>
<L>Whom neyther sea, nor land can hardly serue</L>
<L>They feed them fat, while armes and honour starue,</L>
<L>Desart lookes pale as death, like those bare bones.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha—amazd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Seest thou them trembling, slaue heere were Armes?</L>
<L>That seru'd the troath lesse state of <HI>Luningberge.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lo.</SPEAKER>
<L>So doe I sir serue the dukes sonne of the state,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, ha, I laugh to see how dastard feare</L>
<L>Hastens the death doomd wretch to his distresse,</L>
<L><PB REF="4"/>Say didst thou serue the duke of <HI>Luningberge.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lo.</SPEAKER>
<L>His sonne <HI>Otho</HI> sir, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'me a poore follower of his</L>
<L>And my master is ayring of himselfe at your Cell,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is he that scapt the wracke young <HI>Luningberg?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I sir, the same sir, you are in the right sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Reuenge I kisse thee, vengeance y'are at liberty,</L>
<L>Wouldst thou hauing lost a father as I haue,</L>
<L>Whose very name dissolues my eyes to teares</L>
<L>Could duty and thy loue so different proue,</L>
<L>Not to auenge his death whose better part</L>
<L>Was thine, thou his, when he fell part of thee</L>
<L>Fell with him each drop, being part thine owne</L>
<L>And wouldst not be reveng'd;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes on the murtherer,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>On him, or anie man that is a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ied</L>
<L>Has but one <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>unce of blood, of which hees part</L>
<L>He was my father, my hart still bleeds</L>
<L>Nor can my wounds be stopt, till an incision,</L>
<L>I'ue made to bury my dead father in:</L>
<L>Therefore without protraction, sighing, or excuses</L>
<L>Sweare to be true, to ayd assist me, not to stirre</L>
<L>Or contradict me in any enterprise</L>
<L>I shall now vndertake, or heareafter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor</SPEAKER>
<L>I sweare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Were I perswaded that thou couldst shed teares,</L>
<L>As doth the Egyptian serpents neere the Nile;</L>
<L>If thou wouldst kisse and kill, imbrace and stabbe,</L>
<L>Then thou shouldst liue, for my inuictiue braine</L>
<L>Hath cast a glorious proiect of reuenge</L>
<L>Euen as thou kneel'st, wilt thou turne villaine speake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh sir when was I otherwise, from my creation nothing
else, I was made of no other stuffe, villany is my onely patri∣mony:
though I bee an irreligious slaue, yet I beare a religious
name, though I want courage, yet in talke, I'le put them all
downe, though I haue nothing in me that is good:</P>
<L>Yet i'le—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="5"/>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Forbeare thy Lord is comming ile go in</L>
<L>And royally prouide for such a Prince,</L>
<L>Say thou hast met the kindest host aliue,</L>
<L>One that adores him, with no lesse zeale</L>
<L>Then rich men gold, or true religious heauen</L>
<L>Dissemble cunningly, and thou shalt prooue</L>
<L>the minion of my thoughts, friend to my loue.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well sir ne're feare me this is an excellent fellow</L>
<L>A true vil<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aine fitter for me then better company,</L>
<L>This is Hannce <HI>Hoffmans</HI> sonne.</L>
<P>that stole downe his fathers Anotamy from the gallowes at
<HI>Leningberge,</HI> I'tis the same vpon the dead scull ther's the iron
Crowne that burnt his braines out, what will come of this, I
neyther know nor care: but here comes my lord.
<STAGE>Enter Otho.</STAGE>
How chers my most noble, my most honorable, my most
gracious; yea my most grieued prince.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Otho</SPEAKER>
<L>A fearefull storme</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>And full of horror.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Otho</SPEAKER>
<L>Trust me <HI>Lorrique</HI> besides the inlie griefe</L>
<L>That swallowes my content when I perceiue</L>
<L>How greedily the feirce vnpitying sea, and waues,</L>
<L>Deuour'd our friends another trouble greeues my vexed eyes</L>
<L>With gashtly apperitions, strange aspects</L>
<L>Which eyther I doe certainely behold</L>
<L>Or else my soule deuining some sad fate</L>
<L>Fills my maginary powers with shapes</L>
<L>Hidious and horrid.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>My lord let your hart haue no commerce with that</L>
<L>Mart of idle imaginations, rouse vp your noblenesse</L>
<L>To apprehend comfort, kindnesse ease and what otherwise</L>
<L>Entertain'd so sollitary a place as this, can the</L>
<L>Antient subiect of the state of <HI>Leningberg</HI> collect</L>
<L>Tis I take it the sonne to that Viz-admirall that</L>
<L>Turn'd a terrible pirate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Otho</SPEAKER>
<L>Let vs turne backe into the sea againe</L>
<L><PB REF="5"/>Yealding our bodies to the ruthles sound</L>
<L>That hath diuided vs and our late friends</L>
<L>Rather then see choyce <HI>Hoffman.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor,</SPEAKER>
<L>Corrage braue <HI>Otho,</HI> hee'l vse thee kindly.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Hoffman.</STAGE>
<L>Heere he comes, sweete host heere is the dukes heire of</L>
<L>Leningberge doe homage and after entertaine him and me his</L>
<L>Follower with the most conspictious pleasures</L>
<L>That lies in thy poore hability.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Before I speake to my most sacred Lord</L>
<L>I ioyne my soft lipps to the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ollid earth</L>
<L>And with an honord bennison I blesse</L>
<L>The hower, the place, the time of your arriue</L>
<L>For now my sauadge life, lead amongst beasts</L>
<L>Shalbe turn'd ciuell by your grarious helpe</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Otho</SPEAKER>
<L>I see thy true hearts loue drope downe in teares</L>
<L>And this imbrace shewes I am free from feares</L>
<L>My disturb'd blood runnes smoothly through my veines</L>
<L>And I am bold to call thee friend, bold to intreate</L>
<L>Food for by wrack I haue lost ship, friends and meat.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>You that attend my Lord enter the caue</L>
<L>Bring forth the homely Cakes theis hands prepar'd</L>
<L>While I intreat his excellence sit downe</L>
<L>Villaine bring nothing buta burning Crowne.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Otho</SPEAKER>
<L>What's that thou bidst him bring, a burning Crowne</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Still you suspect my harmelesse inocence</L>
<L>What though your father with the power state</L>
<L>And your iust vncle duke of <HI>Brusia</HI></L>
<L>After my father had in thirty fights</L>
<L>Fill'd all their treasures with somens spoyles</L>
<L>And payd poore souldiors from his treasury</L>
<L>What though for this his merrits he was nam'd</L>
<L>A prescript out law for a little debt</L>
<L>Compeld to flie into the Belgique sound</L>
<L>And liue a pirate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Otho</SPEAKER>
<L>Prithee speake no more</L>
<L><PB REF="6"/>Thou raysest new doubts in my troubled heart</L>
<L>By repetition of thy fathers wrongs</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then hee was wrong'd you graunt but not by you,</L>
<L>You vertuous gentleman</L>
<L>Sate like a iust <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>udge of the vnder-shades,</L>
<L>And with an vnchang'd Rhadamantine looke,</L>
<L>Beheld the fiesh mangled with many scars</L>
<L>Par'd from the bones of my offended father</L>
<L>And when hee was a bare anatomy,</L>
<L>You saw him chain'd vnto the common gallowes,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Otho</SPEAKER>
<L>Hoffman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay heare me patiently kind Lord</L>
<L>My innocent youth as guilty of his sinne,</L>
<L>Was in a dungeon hidden from the sunne,</L>
<L>And there I was condemn'd to endlesse night</L>
<L>Except I past my vow neuer to steale</L>
<L>My fathers fleshles bones from that base tree</L>
<L>I know nor who it was, I guesse your mother,</L>
<L>She kneeld and wept for me, (but you did not)</L>
<L>Beseeching from that vow I might be freed</L>
<L>Then did I sweare if Nations forraigne power</L>
<L>Compel'd me to take downe those naked bones</L>
<L>I neuer would release them from those chaines</L>
<L>Neuer intombe them, but immediately</L>
<L>Remoue them from that gallowes to a tree</L>
<L>I kept mine oath: looke <HI>Luningberg;</HI> tis done</L>
<L>Behold a father hang'd vp by his sonne</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Otho</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh horrible aspect murtherer stand off</L>
<L>I know thou meanst mee wronge</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord behold these pretious twines of light</L>
<L>Burnt out by day eclipst when as the sunne</L>
<L>For shame obscur'd himselfe this deed was done</L>
<L>Where none but schrich owles sung, thou receptacle</L>
<L>thou organ of the soule;</L>
<L>Rest, goe rest, and you most louely Couplets</L>
<L>Leggs and armes reside, for euer heere</L>
<L><PB REF="6"/>This is my last farewell, what doe you weepe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Otho</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh <HI>Lorrique</HI> I am betrayd, slaue touch me not</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not touch thee? yes, and thus trip downe thy pride.</L>
<L>You pla'ct my father in a Chaire of state:</L>
<L>This earth shall bee your throne, villaine come forth</L>
<STAGE>Enter Lorrique.</STAGE>
<L>And as thou mean'st to saue thy forfeit life,</L>
<L>Fixe on thy Masters head my burning Crowne,</L>
<L>While in these Cords, I in eternall bands</L>
<L>Binde fast his base and coward trembling hands.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Otho</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Lorrique,</HI> art thou turn'd villaine to my life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile turne any thing sir rather then nothing, I was taken
life promist to betray you, and I loue life so well, that I would
not loose it for a Kingdome, for a Kings Crowne, an Empire.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>On with the Crowne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Otho</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh tortor aboue measure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>My father felt this paine▪ when thou hadst pleasure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Otho</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy father dyed for piracy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh peace, had he bi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>iudge himselfe, he would haue shew'd</L>
<L>He had bin clearer then the Christall morne!</L>
<L>But wretches sentenc'd neuer finde defence,</L>
<L>How euer guiltlesse bee their innocence,</L>
<L>No more did hee, no more shalt thou, no ruth</L>
<L>Pittied his winter age, none helps thy youth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Otho</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh <HI>Lorrique</HI> tortor, I feele an Aetna burne</L>
<L>Within my braines, and all my body else</L>
<L>Is like a hill of Ice, all these Belgique seas</L>
<L>That now, surround vs cannot quench this flame</L>
<L>Death like a tyrant seazeth me vnawares,</L>
<L>My sin<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>wes shrinke like leaues parcht with the sunne</L>
<L>My blood dissolues, nerues and tendons fayle</L>
<L>Each part's disioynted, and my breath expires</L>
<L>Mountsoule to heauen, my body burnes in fire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee's gon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe let him come <HI>Lorrique</HI></L>
<L>This but the prologue to the'nsuing play.</L>
<L><PB REF="7"/>The first step to reuenge, this seane is donne</L>
<L>Father I offer thee thy inurtherers <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>onne.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nt,</STAGE>
<STAGE>Florish. Enter <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>erdinand, Rodor<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>k, Lodowick, Mathias,
Lucibet, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>erom, Stilt, attendants.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Princes of <HI>Saxony</HI> and <HI>Austria,</HI></L>
<L>Though your owne wor<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>sare of sufficient weight</L>
<L>To iustifie the honorable loue borne by <HI>Lodowick</HI> to bright <HI>Lucybell,</HI></L>
<L>Yet since your parents liue and as I heare</L>
<L>There is betweene them some dissention,</L>
<L>Blame vs not for detaining yo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> thus long</L>
<L>Till we had notice how the businesse stood</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lodo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your royall entertaine great <HI>Ferdinand,</HI></L>
<L>Exceeding expectation in our stay,</L>
<L>Bind vs to thanks, and if my brother please</L>
<L>To hold his challenge for a Turnament</L>
<L>In praise of <HI>Lucibellas</HI> excellence,</L>
<L>No doubt our father and the <HI>Austrian</HI> duke</L>
<L>Will be in person at so royall sport.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>We trust they will.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rodo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe assure your grace</L>
<L>The <HI>Austrian</HI> and the duke of <HI>Saxony</HI></L>
<L>By true report of pilgrimes at my cell</L>
<L>From eyther of there courts set hetherward</L>
<L>Some sixe dayes since.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thankes <HI>Rodorick</HI> for this newes</L>
<L>They are more welcome then the sad discourse</L>
<L>Of <HI>Leningberg</HI> our nephewes timeles wrake</L>
<L>Which addeth sorrow to the mourning g<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>iefes</L>
<L>Abound in vs for our Dutches death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ie.</SPEAKER>
<P>I truly Princes, my father has had but hard lucke since your
comming to his court, for ought I know you are bred of ill
weather, come before you are sent for, yet if my most gratious
father say you are welcome, I his more gratious sonne take you
by the hands, though I can tell you my mothers death comes
somewhat neere my heart, but I am a prince, and princes haue
<PB REF="7"/>
power more then common people to subdue their passions.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<P>We know your worthinesse is experienc't in all true
wisedome.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<P>True, I am no foole, I haue bin at <HI>Wittenberg,</HI> where
wit growes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace thou vnshapen honor, my states shame,</L>
<L>My ages co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>siue, and my blacke sinnes curse,</L>
<L>Oh hadst thou neuer bin, I had bin then,</L>
<L>A happy childlesse man, now among men,</L>
<L>I am the most vnhappie, one that knowes</L>
<L>No end of mine, and of my peoples woes.</L>
<L>I tell you Princesse, and most gracious maide;</L>
<L>I doe not weare these sable ornaments</L>
<L>For <HI>Isabel<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HI> death, though she were deare,</L>
<L>Nor are my eyelids ouerflowne with teares,</L>
<L>For <HI>Otho</HI> of <HI>Luningberg,</HI> wrackt in the Soun,</L>
<L>Though he wer<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> my hope: but heer's my care,</L>
<L>A wit<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>esse foole must needs be <HI>Prussias</HI> h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, and you were not my father,—s'nailes, and I
would not draw rather then put vp the foole, would I
might neuer winne this lady at tilt and turnament: <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s
Knights, I defie you both, for her; euen you <HI>Lodowick,</HI> that
loues her, and your brother that loues you: looke to
me, <HI>Stilt,</HI> and I haue practis'd these two dayes: s'nailes god
forgiue me to sweare, she shall not be carried away so.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<P>We are glad to heare your grace so <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>esolute.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<P>As I am a Prince, and a D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>kes heire, though I say it
my selfe, I am as full of resolution as the prowdest of you
all</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luci.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thanke Prince <HI>Lodowick</HI> he ha's bound my youth</L>
<L>To bee the conquerers prize, and if my starres</L>
<L>Allott me to be yours, I will be prowd,</L>
<L>For how so ere you seeme not fashioned</L>
<L>Like mee, and cunning Courtiers; I protest,</L>
<L>By some small loue I beare thee in mine eie,</L>
<L>Your worthy beautie, wealth and dignity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="8"/>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heart you would not vnhorse Hercules for her fa∣ther,
ile practice againe at Dantzike, you say in the Dukes
meade; ile meete thee <HI>Mathias:</HI> ther's my gloue<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
For a gauntle<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, though my father count me a foole, you shall
finde me none.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would I might neuer find thee any thing,</L>
<L>For thou indeede art nothing in <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>steeme,</L>
<L>My sad soule sinkes with sorrow at thy sight,</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Lorrique.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Health to the right gratious, generous, vertuous,
and valorous <HI>Ferdinand</HI> Duke of Prussia.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hermet dost thou not know this young mans face?</L>
<L>I'st not <HI>Lorique,</HI> that met vs at thy cell</L>
<L>With letters from our brother <HI>Luningberg?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rodo.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is that gentleman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am no l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>thou saydst thou wast my nephewes play fellow,</L>
<L>Appointed to await his vertuous person,</L>
<L>How is it then thou wert so ill aduised</L>
<L>To take the land away, and forsake thy Lord?</L>
<L>Whom I haue neuer seene, nor neuer may,</L>
<L>Though in his life my hope and comfort lay.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Be it knowne right gracious: <HI>Lorrique</HI> had neuer so
little grace, as to leaue his loued lord for weather or water,
for torture or fire, for death or for life, since I first came to
moue in a pilgrims proportion; much disguised, being so
proper a man: but onely for those sixe words; that I was
sent wholy to giue notice of his comming.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<P>But thou hast left him now sunke in the sea.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>I left the ship sunke, and his highnesse sau'd<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, for
when all hope had left Master and pilot, sailer and swabber,
I caus'd my Lord to leape into the cocke, and for feare she
should be sunke with too much company; I caper'd out▪
and cut the cable: rowse, quoth the ship against the rocks,
roomer cry I in the cocke, my Lord wept for the compa∣ny:
I laught to comfort him; last by the power of heauen,
<PB REF="8"/>
goodnesse of starrs, kindnesse of winds, mercy of the waues,
our cocke and wee were cast a shore vnder Reeshopscurre,
we clamberd vp, but hauing scap't drowning, were in dan∣ger
of killing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<P>What there betided you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor,</SPEAKER>
<P>Marry <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Lord a young villaine, sonne of a damn'd
pirate, a mayd rauisher.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<P>Be briefe, what was he?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Clois Hoffman.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh my heart! did the false rebell hurt his soueraignes
sonne?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Noe my Lord, the prince so hought and hoft him,
that he had no other helpe but to his heeles, and then I, my
good Lord, being ro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>footed, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>utstript him in running, tript
him by strength, and in fine, finely cut's throat.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<P>Where is the villaines body?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Marry euen heaued ouer the scarr, and sent a swim∣ming
toward Burtholme, his old habitation; if it bee not
intercepted by some Scale, Sharke, Sturgeon, or such like.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<P>Where is our nephew?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>He intends to stay at the same hermitage, where I
saluted your excellence, with newes of my lords excellen∣cies
intent, to visite you▪ for that his apparrell is some∣what
sea-sicke, and he wants shift.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>A charriot, and rich robes attend <HI>Lorrique.</HI></L>
<L>And his rewa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d, be thirteene hundred dollers,</L>
<L>For he hath driuen dolour from our heart.</L>
<L>Princes, and Princesse, in your kindest loue,</L>
<L>Attend our person to the hermitage,</L>
<L>where we shall meete the heire of two great States,</L>
<L>Rich <HI>Luningberg,</HI> and warlike <HI>Prussias,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Otho</HI> liuing, wee'l disinherit our fond sonne:</L>
<L>And blesse all Dantzike, by our sonne elect,</L>
<L>Hermet you haue at home, a guest of ours,</L>
<L>Your little cell, is a great princes court;</L>
<L>Had you bin there to entertaine young <HI>Otho,</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="9"/>He would haue tooke your welcome thankfully,</L>
<L>Where now he mournes, for want of company.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rodo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will goe on before my gracious Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd,</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay I am iealous of my approaching ioy,</L>
<L>And fearefull, any eye but mine, should gaine</L>
<L>The pleasure of my glad diuining soule;</L>
<L>Forward come all, in my delight take part,</L>
<L>He that's now glad, addes ioy to gladnes heart.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Clois Hoffman.</STAGE>
<L>If there liue ere a surgeon that dare say</L>
<L>He could doe better: ile play Mercury,</L>
<L>And like fond Marsias flea the Quacksaluer<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>There were a sort of filthy Mountebankes,</L>
<L>Exp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rt in nothing but in idle words,</L>
<L>Made a daies work<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, with their incision kniues</L>
<L>On my opprest poore father: silly man,</L>
<L>Thrusting there dastard fingers in his flesh,</L>
<L>That durst not while he liued, behold his face;</L>
<L>I haue fitted my anatomy</L>
<L>In a fair<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> chaine to; father this youth scorn'd</L>
<L>When he was set in an ascending throne,</L>
<L>To haue you stand by him; would he could see,</L>
<L>How the case alters, you shall hang by him,</L>
<L>And hang afore him to, for all his pride,</L>
<L>Come image of bare death, ioyne side, to side,</L>
<L>With my long iniur'd fathers naked bones;</L>
<L>He was the prologue to a Tragedy,</L>
<L>That if my destinies deny me not,</L>
<L>Shall passe those of Thyestes, Tereus,</L>
<L>Iocasta, or Duke Iasons iealous wife;</L>
<L>So shut our stage vp, there is one act done</L>
<L>Ended in <HI>Othos</HI> death; 'twas somewhat single;</L>
<L>Ile fill the other fuller, if <HI>Lorrique,</HI></L>
<L>That I haue late sworne to be murders slaue,</L>
<L>Sweares hee will protest me to be <HI>Othos,</HI></L>
<L>Whom Prussia his vncle vnknowne loues;</L>
<L><PB REF="9"/>If I be taken for him well: Oh then!</L>
<L>Sweet vengeance make me happiest of all men:</L>
<L><HI>Prussia,</HI> I come as comets against change:</L>
<L>As apparitions before mortall ends;</L>
<L>If thou accept me for thy nephewe, so;</L>
<L>Vncle, ile vncle thee of thy proud life.</L>
<L>Father farewell, ile to the hermitage,</L>
<L>Where if I be receaued for <HI>Luningberg,</HI></L>
<L>I will haue thy drie bones, sanguin'd all or'e</L>
<L>With thy foes bloud, Rhamnusia helpe thy priest,</L>
<L>My wrong thou know'st, my willingnesse thou seest.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus secundus.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Ierom and Stilt,</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come <HI>Stilt,</HI> bestirre your stumpes; you know I must
be a tilter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stilt.</SPEAKER>
<P>I my lord, I know you should be one, but I hope
you are not so madd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<P>what dost thou count it madnesse to runne a tilt.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stilt.</SPEAKER>
<P>I my Lord, for you that cannot sit a hobby, you'le
hardly manage your tilthorse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why? they say <HI>Stilt,</HI> that stone Mares are gentler, see
if thou canst get me one of them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stilt.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not afore next grasse; I could helpe you now to a
stone mule, a stone asse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, ile trie one course with thee at the halfe pike,
and then goe, come draw thy pike.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stilt.</SPEAKER>
<P>That's not your fit word; you must say, aduance
your pike, and you must be here sir, and here, you'l neuer
learne for all my teaching.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue answered you <HI>Stilt,</HI> that Princes haue no need
to bee taught, and I haue e'en determin'd with my selfe,
not to runne at tilt, least I hazard my horse and harnesse:
<PB REF="10"/>
therefore ile to the court, and onely see my new cousin,
that they sayd was drownd: and then retire to my (astle
at <HI>Helsen,</HI> and there write a new poem, that I haue taken
paines in, almost these ten yeares: It is in prayse of picke∣toothes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stilt.</SPEAKER>
<P>That will be excellent my Lord, the barbers will
buy those poems abominably.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay sirra, ile get a patent from the Duke, my father,
for the <HI>Cum Priuilegio</HI> for that poem, <HI>Ad imprimendum
solum;</HI> besides thou shalt haue a priniledge, that no man
shall sell tooth pickes without thy seale: my father saies I
am a foole, but I thinke I bestow my time to looke out for
setting a new nappe vpon his thredbare Common wealth:
Who's that knockes? who dares disturbe our honorable
meditation? harke <HI>Stilt,</HI> dost thou see no noyse?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stilt.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, but I heare a noyse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ierom.</SPEAKER>
<P>A hall then; my father and my new cousen: stand
aside, that I may set my countenance, my beard brush and
mirror, <HI>Stilt,</HI> that set my countenance right to the mirror
of Knight-hood, for your mirror of magistrates is some∣what
to sober▪ how lik'st me?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stilt.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh excellent! heers your casting bottle.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sprinkle, good <HI>Stilt,</HI> sprinkle, for my late practize
hath brought mee into strange fauour: ha mother of mee,
thou hadst almost blinded the eyes of excellence; but
<HI>omnia bene,</HI> let them approach now, and I appeare not like
a Prince, let my father casheere me, as some say hee will.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stilt.</SPEAKER>
<P>Casheere you? no, doe but manage your body, and
haue heere, and heere your congies, and then <HI>quid sequi∣tur,
Stilt</HI> knowes, and all the court shall see.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Hoboyes.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Ferdinand leading Clois Hoffman: Mathias, and L<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>∣dowick
leading Lucibella: Lorrique, with other lords atten∣ding:
comming neere the chayre of state, Ferdinand
Ascends, places Hoffman at his feete, sets a Co∣ronet
on his head, A Herald proclaimes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="10"/>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Ferdinand</HI> by the diuine grace, prince of <HI>Heidel∣berg</HI>
lord of <HI>Pomer,</HI> and Duke of <HI>Prussia,</HI> for sundry reasons
h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m mouing, the quiet state of his people especially:
which as a witl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sse and insufficient prince, disinherits <HI>Ie∣rom
Heidelberg</HI> his knowne sonne, and adopteth <HI>Otho</HI> of
<HI>Iuningberg</HI> his sisters sonne, as heire, immediately to suc∣ceed
after his death in all his prouinces. God saue Duke
<HI>Ferdinand,</HI> and <HI>Otho</HI> his heire.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Florish.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Amen, Heauen witnesse, how my heart is pleas'd,</L>
<L>With the conceit of <HI>Prussias</HI> after-peace,</L>
<L>By this election.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why? but heare you father▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away, disturbe vs not, let's in and feast,</L>
<L>For all our country in our choyce is blest.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Florish.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, but <HI>Stilt,</HI> what's now to be done <HI>Stilt?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stilt.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay that's more then I know: this matter will
trouble vs more then all your poem of picktooths, s'nailes:
you were better be vnknighted then vnprinc'd, I haue lost
all my hope of preferment, if this hold.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<P>Noe more <HI>Stilt,</HI> I haue it heere; 'tis in my head, and out
it shall not come, till red reuenge in robes of fire, and mad∣ding
mischiefe runne and raue: they say I am a foole <HI>Stilt,</HI>
but follow me; ile seeke out my notes of Machiauel, they say
hee's an odd politician.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stilt.</SPEAKER>
<P>I faith hee's so odd, that he hath driuen euen hone∣sty
from all mens hearts.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, sword come forth, and courage enter in,</L>
<L>Brest breake with griefe; yet hold to be reueng'd:</L>
<L>Follow me <HI>Stilt;</HI> widdowes vnborne shall weepe,</L>
<L>And beardlesse boyes with armour on their backes</L>
<L>Shall beare vs out, <HI>Stilt</HI> we will tread on stilts,</L>
<L>Through the purple pauement of the court,</L>
<L>Which shall bee, let me see, what shall it be?</L>
<L>No court, but euen caue of misery.</L>
<L><PB REF="11"/>Ther's an excellent speech <HI>Stilt,</HI> follow me, pursue me,
will accquire,</L>
<L>And either die, or compasse my desire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stilt.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh braue master, not a Lord: O, <HI>Stilt</HI> will stalke, and
make the earth a stage,</P>
<L>But hee will haue thee lord in spight of rage.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Rodorigo, and Austria's Duke, some followers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir since you are content, you heere shall finde,</L>
<L>A sparing supper, but a bounteous minde:</L>
<L>Bad lodging, but a heart as free, and generous,</L>
<L>As that which is fed with generous blood,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aust.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your hermitage is furnish't for a prince.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rodo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Last night this roofe couer'd the sacred heads</L>
<L>Of fiue most noble, faire, and gratious Princes,</L>
<L>Duke <HI>Ferdinand</HI> himselfe, and <HI>Otho</HI> his nephew,</L>
<L>The sonnes of <HI>Saxon,</HI> and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he <HI>Austrian</HI> Princesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aust.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh god! that girle, which fled my Court and loue,</L>
<L>Making loue colour for her heedles flight,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rodo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pardon great prince: are you the <HI>Austrian</HI> duke?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aust.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hermet I am, <HI>Saxons</HI> proud wanton sonns</L>
<L>Were entertaind like <HI>Priam's</HI> Firebrand</L>
<L>At Sparta: all our State gladly 'appear'd</L>
<L>Like chierfull <HI>Lacedemons,</HI> to receaue</L>
<L>Those Daemons that with magicke of their tongues,</L>
<L>Bewitch't my Lucibells my Helen's eares.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Knocking and calling within.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rodo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who traueleth so late? who knockes so hard?</L>
<L>Turne to the east end of the Chappell, pray;</L>
<L>We are ready to attend you.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter duke of Saxony.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sax.</SPEAKER>
<L>Which is the way to Dantzike?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rodo.</SPEAKER>
<L>There is no way to Dantzike you can finde</L>
<L>Without a guide thus late, come neere I pray,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sax.</SPEAKER>
<L>looke to our horses, by your leaue master Hermet,</L>
<L><PB REF="11"/>We are soone bidden, and will proue bold guests:</L>
<L>God saue you sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aust.</SPEAKER>
<L>That should bee <HI>Saxons</HI> tongue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sax.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeed I am the Duke of <HI>Saxony.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aust.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then art thou father to lasciuious sonnes,</L>
<L>That haue made <HI>Austrea</HI> childles.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sax.</SPEAKER>
<L>O subtill duke, thy craft appeares in framing thy ex∣cuse,</L>
<L>Thou dost accuse my yong sons innocence:</L>
<L>I sent them to get knowledge, learne the tongues,</L>
<L>Nor to be metamorphis'<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> with the view</L>
<L>Of flattering beauty, peraduenture painted.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aust.</SPEAKER>
<L>No; I defie thee <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ohn of <HI>Saxony;</HI></L>
<L>My <HI>Lucibell</HI> for beauty needs no art,</L>
<L>Nor doe I thinke the vertues of her minde</L>
<L>Euer inclind to this ign<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ble course</L>
<L>But by the charmes and forcings of thy sonnes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sax.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh would thou durst maintaine thy words prowd Duke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rodo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hope great Princes, neither of you dare</L>
<L>Commit a deede so sacrilegious: This holy cell</L>
<L>Is dedicated to the sonne of peace;</L>
<L>The foot of war neuer prophan'd this floore,</L>
<L>Nor doth wrath here with his cons<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ming voyce</L>
<L>Affright these buildings; charity with prayer,</L>
<L>Humility with abstinence combin'd,</L>
<L>Are heere the guardians of a grieued minde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aust.</SPEAKER>
<L>Father we obey thy <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> voyce;</L>
<L>Duke Iohn of <HI>Saxony,</HI> receiue my faith;</L>
<L>Ti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l our eares heare the true course thy so<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nes</L>
<L>Haue taken with my fond and mis-led child.</L>
<L>I proclaime truce, Why dost thou <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ullen stand?</L>
<L>If thou meane peace, giue me thy Princely hand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sax.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thus doe I plight thee troth, and promise peace,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aust.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, but thy eyes agree not with thy heart;</L>
<L>In vowes of combination, ther's a grace</L>
<L>That shewes the intention in the outward face,</L>
<L>Looke cherefully, or I expect no leagu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="12"/>
<SPEAKER>Sax.</SPEAKER>
<L>First giue me leaue to view a while the person,</L>
<L>Of this He<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mer, <HI>Austria</HI> note him well,</L>
<L>Is he not like your brother <HI>Rodorick?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aust.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee's like him, but I heard he lost his life</L>
<L>Long since in <HI>Persia,</HI> by the <HI>Sophies</HI> warres.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L>I heard so much my Lords, but that report</L>
<L>Was purely fain'd, spread by my erring tongue,</L>
<L>As double as my heart, when I was yonge▪</L>
<L>I am that <HI>Rodorick</HI> that aspir'd your throne;</L>
<L>That vile false brother who with rebell breath,</L>
<L>Drawne sword, and trecherous heart threatned your death▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sax.</SPEAKER>
<L>My brother I nay, then i'faith old Iohn lay by</L>
<L>Thy sorrowing thoughts, turne to thy wonted veyne,</L>
<L>And be madd Iohn of <HI>Saxony</HI> againe.</L>
<L>Mad <HI>Rodorick,</HI> art aliue? my mothers so <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nne</L>
<L>Her ioy and her last birth; oh she coniur<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d me</L>
<L>To vse thee thus, and yet I banisht thee:</L>
<L>Body of me; I was vnkinde I know,</L>
<L>But thou deseru'st it then; but let it goe:</L>
<L>Say thou wilt leaue this life thus truly idle,</L>
<L>And liue a Statesman, thou shalt share in raigne,</L>
<L>Commanding all but me thy soueraigne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thanke your Highnes; I will thinke on it:</L>
<L>But for my sinnes this sufferance is more fit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sax.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tut, title, tatle, tell not me of sinne.</L>
<L>Now <HI>Austria</HI> once againe thy Princely hand:</L>
<L>Ile looke thee in the face, and smile, and sweare,</L>
<L>If any of my sonnes haue wrong'd thy child,</L>
<L>Ile helpe thee in reuenging it my selfe;</L>
<L>But if as I beleeue they<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> meane, but honor,</L>
<L>As it appeareth by these iusts proclaim'd.</L>
<L>Then thou shalt be content to name him thine,</L>
<L>And thy faire daughter ile account as mine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aust.</SPEAKER>
<L>Agreed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sax.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ah <HI>Austria!</HI> t'was a world when you and I</L>
<L>Ran these Carreers; but now we are stiffe and drie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="12"/>
<SPEAKER>Aust.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am glad you are so pleasant my good Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sax.</SPEAKER>
<L>T'was my old mood, but I was soone turn'd sad▪</L>
<L>With ouer grieuing for this long lost lad;</L>
<L>And now the Boy is growne, as old as I,</L>
<L>His very face as full of grauity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Please your Graces enter,</L>
<L>I know the seruants that attend one me</L>
<L>By the appointment of Duke <HI>Ferdinand</HI></L>
<L>By this haue couered.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sax.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why then let's in: brother I trust, and brother</L>
<L>Hold you this hand, <HI>Rodorick</HI> hold thou the other,</L>
<L>By heauen my heart with happinesse is crow'nd,</L>
<L>In that my long lost brother now is found:</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt,</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Clois Hoffman solus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>so run on fate, my destinies are good,</L>
<L>Reuenge hath made me great by shedding blood:</L>
<L>I am suppos'd the heire of <HI>Luningberg,</HI></L>
<L>By which I am of <HI>Prussia</HI> Prince elect.</L>
<L>Good: who is wrong'd by this? Onely a foole:</L>
<L>And 'tis not fit that idiots should beare rule.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Lorrique.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lo.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord I haue as you inioyn'd, intic't <HI>Saxons</HI> elder
sonne to talke with you: and heere hee comes with his
most excellent, amorous, and admirable Lady.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha'st thou the Hermets weeds for my disguise?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>All ready, fit, fit' in the next chamber, your beard is
point-vice, not a haire amisse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff</SPEAKER>
<L>Faithfull <HI>Lorrique</HI> in thy vnfaithfulnes:</L>
<L>I kisse thy cheeke, and giue thee in that kisse</L>
<L>The mo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tie of all my earthly blisse.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good: I am halfe a Monarke: halfe a fiend</L>
<L>Blood I begun in and in blood must end</L>
<P>yet this <HI>Clois</HI> is an honest villaine, ha's conscience in his kil∣ling
of men: he kils none but his fathers enemies, and there
issue, 'tis admirable, 'tis excellent, 'tis well 'tis meritorious,
where? in heauen? no, hell.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="13"/>Enter Lodowick and Lucibella.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now friend, where is prince <HI>Otho?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sad, sir, and grieued.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luci.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why? prithee why?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas I know not why.</L>
<L>The hermet <HI>Rodorigo</HI> talkt with him</L>
<L>Somewhat of you, and somewhat of the Duke,</L>
<L>About surprizing you and murdering <HI>Lodowick:</HI></L>
<L>Or such a thing, nay sure 'twas such a thing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luci.</SPEAKER>
<L>Surprizing me and murdering <HI>Lodowicke.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>By whom? by what complot?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sure by the Duke, the Duke's an odd old lad:</L>
<L>I know, this nigh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> ther's set a double guard,</L>
<L>And ther's some tricke in that: but patience:</L>
<L>Heere comes the Hermet: holy reuerent man!</L>
<STAGE>Enter Clois Hoffman like a her<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>.</STAGE>
<L>Somewhat important, wings his aged feete</L>
<L>With speedy nimblenesse: heauen graunt that all be well▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clois.</SPEAKER>
<L>Princes in pitty of your youth, your loue,</L>
<L>Your vertues, and what not, that may moue ruth,</L>
<L>I offer you the tender of your liues,</L>
<L>Which yet you may preserue: but if you stay,</L>
<L>Death and destruction waiteth your delay.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod,</SPEAKER>
<L>Who hath conspir'd our deathes? speake reuere<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Duke of <HI>Prussia,</HI> doating on this face;</L>
<L>Worthy indeed of wonder, being so faire,</L>
<L>This night hath plotted, first to murder you;</L>
<L>The guard are set that you may not escape,</L>
<L>Within, without, and round about the court;</L>
<L>Onely one way, thorow Prince <HI>Otho</HI> his lodging</L>
<L>Is left; heere is the key, and for more proofe</L>
<L>Of my great zeale and care, on with these robes.</L>
<L><PB REF="13"/>Within are Grecian habits for your heads;</L>
<L>Nay if you loue life do not stand amaz'd,</L>
<L>But take the path toward my hermitage,</L>
<L>Yet I aduize you, that you goe not in;</L>
<L>There may be plots to, for ought I know;</L>
<L>But turne downe by the riuer, ther's a way</L>
<L>Leads to a little Chappell; in that porch</L>
<L>Stay, till I visit you with better newes;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will but call my brother, and then goe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>That were a going neuer to returne:</L>
<L>I'le send him after you, be well assur'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luci.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh god! the Duke of <HI>Prussia</HI> grown thus false,</L>
<L>such shewes of freindship, and so little faith.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come Lucibella lets embrace this meane,</L>
<L>Duke Ferdinand shall with a sorrowing heart,</L>
<L>Repent this base dishonourable plot:</L>
<L>Father, our fortunes if they sort aright,</L>
<L>shall with continuall thankfulnesse require</L>
<L>This vertuous and this charitable care:</L>
<L>Farwell: wee'l wait thee in the Chappell porch</L>
<L>Bring Prince <HI>Mathias</HI> our kind brother thither,</L>
<L>And thou shalt add good works to charity:</L>
<L>Once more farewell <HI>Lorrique;</HI> ther's for thee,</L>
<L>Commend me to thy Lord, tell him this wronge</L>
<L>Of his false vncle, sha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l meere full reuenge:</L>
<L>But doe to him our duties. Come chast, faire,</L>
<L>We must not now by <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> and turnameut</L>
<L>Maintayne thy honor: for thy champion Knight,</L>
<L>Is for'st by treason to vnwilling flight.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>so runne to mischiefe: Oh my deare Lorrique<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>When I haue summ'd vp my account of death,</L>
<L>And rob'd those fathers of there lifes and ioy,</L>
<L>That rob'd mee of my ioy, my fathers life,</L>
<L>Thus thy hand claspt in mine, wee'l walke and meditate,</L>
<L>And boast in the reuenges I haue wrought;</L>
<L><PB REF="14"/>That done; ile seat thee by m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> throne of state,</L>
<L>And make thee riuall in those gouernments,</L>
<L>That by thy secrecy thou li<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>'<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t me to;</L>
<L>Shalt be a Duke at least.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thanke your Grace, but pray resolue me,</L>
<L>what you now intend,</L>
<L>To these three Princes <HI>Lodowick,</HI> and <HI>Mathias,</HI></L>
<L>And the thrice beautious Princesse <HI>Lucibell.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<P>Death certaine: call in <HI>Mathias,</HI> if my plot proue
good, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> make one brother shed the others blood.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am nimble as your thought, deuise, i'le execute
what you command.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>A pre<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ious villaine: a good villaine too▪</L>
<L>W<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ll if he be no worse; that is doe worse,</L>
<L>And hony me in my death-stinging thoughts,</L>
<L>I will preferre him: he shall be prefer'd</L>
<L>To hanging peraduenture; why not? 'tis well</L>
<STAGE>Enter Lorriqne.</STAGE>
<L>His sufferance heere may saue his soule from hell.</L>
<L>Hee comes; what newes my faithfull seruant? wher's the Prince.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee's talking with the lady <HI>Lucibell,</HI></L>
<L>And when I said your Highnesse sent for him,</L>
<L>Hee 'gan with courtly salutations,</L>
<L>To take his leaue and to attend your grace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well god-a-mercy friend, thou got'st me grace:</L>
<L>But more of that at leasure: take this gowne;</L>
<L>My cloake, a chaire; I must turne melancholy.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Mathias.</STAGE>
<L>Second what ere I say, approoue my words,</L>
<L>That we may mooue <HI>Mathias</HI> to mad rage.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>God saue your excellence: what sad, dull, heauy?</L>
<L>Or are you now in meditation</L>
<L>Which part to take to morrow at the Tilt?</L>
<L><PB REF="14"/>The mead is ringd with tents of stranger Knights,</L>
<L>Whose rich deuices, and caparisons</L>
<L>Exceed the <HI>Persian</HI> Monark's, when he met</L>
<L>Destruction and pale death sent from the sword</L>
<L>Of <HI>Philips</HI> sonne, and his stout Macedons</L>
<L>Cheerely Prince <HI>Otho</HI> ther's such a warlike sight</L>
<L>That would stirre vp a leaden heart to fight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>For what?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>For honor and faire <HI>Luicbell.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh Prince <HI>Mathias!</HI> it is ill combin'd</L>
<L>When honor is with fickle beautie ioynd.</L>
<L>Where is your most Princely brother?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>I cannot tell I left him with his loued <HI>Lucibell.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>But shee has got another loue,</L>
<L>Dishonored all this rich assembly,</L>
<L>Left the m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>moriall of such infamy,</L>
<L>As cannot die while men haue memory.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>How? p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ay you how? what hath the princesse done?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>she with a Grecian is but new fled hence,</L>
<L>Belike some other loue of hers before:</L>
<L>Our tilt and turnament is spoild and crost.</L>
<L>The faire we should defend, her faith hath lost.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fled with a Grecian? saw you them goe Prince <HI>Otho?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, I, I saw them goe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>And would not stay them?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>My true seruant knowes,</L>
<L>How at the sight of such inconstancy</L>
<L>My gentle heart was smitt with inward griefe</L>
<L>And I sunke downe with sorrow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>s'death; what path? which way? that I may track her harlot-steps,</L>
<L>Fled now: gone now: ile goe seeke <HI>Lodowicke</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay then you add an irreligious worke,</L>
<L>To there lasciuious act; follow your selfe,</L>
<L>I and my man will beare your company</L>
<L><HI>Lorrique,</HI> as I thinke, thou nam'dst a chappell,</L>
<L>A Hermet, some such thing: I haue lost the forme.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="15"/>
<SPEAKER>Lo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I heard her say, she could not trauell far,</L>
<L>He told her, they would rest the dead of night▪</L>
<L>Neere to a chappell, by a hermitage.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where is that chappell? wher's that hermitage?</L>
<L>If you loue honor Princely <HI>Luningberg,</HI></L>
<L>Lets to that chappell: if you know the way,</L>
<L>That I may kill our shame, ere it s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e day.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile guide you to the chappell, ayd your arme▪</L>
<L>In your reuenge, against that Grecian,</L>
<L>But for the Lady spare her, she is faire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will doe what I can; oh hell of life!</L>
<L>Who, but a foole would striue to winne a wife?</L>
<L>shall we call <HI>Lodowick?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>no<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, t'would smite his soule in sunder, split his heart,</L>
<L>If he should heare of such adulterate wronge,</L>
<L>Couer the fault or punish as you please:</L>
<L>Yet I would saue her faine, for she deserue<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>pitty for beanty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nothing, noe for nothing.</L>
<L>Shee is as harlots, faire, like guilded tombs</L>
<L>Goodly without; within all rottennes:</L>
<L>shee's like a painted fire vpon a hill,</L>
<L>set to allure the frost-nipt passengers,</L>
<L>And starue them after hope: she is indeed<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>As all such strumpets are, Angell in shew,</L>
<L>Diuell in heart: Come, come if you loue me goe.</L>
<STAGE>Exit</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Follow <HI>Lorrique;</HI> we are in the right way.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>To hell I feare: tush let all feare goe by,</L>
<L>Whoo'l shun a bad way with good company.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus tertus.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Lodowick and Lucibell.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you not faint diuinest <HI>Lucibell?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="15"/>
<SPEAKER>Luci.</SPEAKER>
<L>Noe, the cleare moone strowes siluer in our path,</L>
<L>And with her moist eyes weepes a gentle dew</L>
<L>Vpon the the spotted pauement of the earth,</L>
<L>Whi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h softens euery flowre whereon I tread</L>
<L>Besides; all trauell in your company</L>
<L>Seemes but a walke made in some goodly bowre,</L>
<L>Where loues faire mother strips her paramoure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is the Chappell, and behold a banke,</L>
<L>Couer'd with sleeping flowers, that misse the Sunne:</L>
<L>Shall Wee repose vs till <HI>Mathias</HI> come?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luci.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Hermet will soone bring him, let's sit downe▪</L>
<L>Nature, or art hath taught these boughes to spred,</L>
<L>In manner of an arbour o're the banke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, they bow downe as vailes to shadow you▪</L>
<L>And the fi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sh flowers beguiled by the light</L>
<L>Of your celestiall eyes, open there leaues,</L>
<L>And when they entertaine the lord of day</L>
<L>You bring them comfort like the Sunne in May.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luci.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come▪ come, you men will flatter beyond meane:</L>
<L>Will you sit downe? and talke of the late wronge</L>
<L>Intended by the Duke of <HI>Prussia?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fairest forget it, leaue till we are cleare freed hence,</L>
<L>I will defie him, and cause all the knights</L>
<L>Assembled for our purpos'd turnament,</L>
<L>To turne there keene swords 'gainst his catiue head.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luci.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prithee no more, I feele thy blood turne hot,</L>
<L>And wrath inflames thy spirit, let it cease;</L>
<L>Forgiue this fault, conuert this war to peace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>O breath sweet touch with what a heauenly charme</L>
<L>Doe your soft fingers my wa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>-<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>houghts disarme,</L>
<L><HI>Prussia</HI> had reason to attempt my life</L>
<L>Inchanted by the magicke of these lookes,</L>
<L>That cast a luster on the blushing starrs.</L>
<L>Pardon chast Queene of beauty, make me proude</L>
<L>To rest my toild head on your tender knee,</L>
<L>My chin with sleepe is to my bosome bow'd;</L>
<L><PB REF="16"/>Faire if you please a little rest with mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luci.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, ile be Centinell; ile watch for feare</L>
<L>Of venomous wormes, or wolues, or woluish theeues:</L>
<L>My hand shall fanne your eyes, like the film'd winge</L>
<L>Of drowsie morpheus; and my voyce shall sing</L>
<L>In a low compasse for a <HI>Lucibell.</HI></L>
<L>Sleepe sweete, perhaps ile sleepe for company.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thanke you; I am drowsie, sing I pray;</L>
<L>Or sleepe: doe what you please, I am heauy, I;</L>
<L>God night to all our care: oh! I am blest</L>
<L>By this soft pillow where my head doth rest.</L>
<STAGE>Hee sleepes,</STAGE>
<L>By my troth I am sleepy too: I cannot sing,</L>
<L>My heart is troubled with some heauy thing.</L>
<L>Rest one these violets, whilst I prepare,</L>
<L>In thy soft slumber to receiue a share:</L>
<L>Blush not chast Moone to see a virgin lie</L>
<L>So neere a Prince, 'tis noe immodestie:</L>
<L>For when the thoughts are pure, noe time, noe place,</L>
<L>Hath power to worke faire chastities disgrace;</L>
<L><HI>Lodowick</HI> I claspe thee thus, so arme clip arme,</L>
<L>So sorrow fold them that wish true loue harme.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Sleepes.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Lorrique, Mathias, Clois Hoffman.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Art sure tha'st found them?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Looke, are these they?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Adulterer: stiumpet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luci.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vnhumane deede to kill both.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Both haue abu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'d our glory, both shall bleed,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luci.</SPEAKER>
<L>how now! what haue ye done? my <HI>Lodowick</HI> bleeds</L>
<L>Some sauage beast hath fixt his ruthles fange</L>
<L>In my soft body: <HI>Lodowick,</HI> I faint▪</L>
<L><PB REF="16"/>Deere wake; my <HI>Lodowick:</HI> alas what meanes</L>
<L>Your brest to be thus wet? I'st blood or sweat▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who troubles me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Brother.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who is that? <HI>Mathias.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, accursed I,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wher's the good Hermet? thanke him for his loue▪</L>
<L>Yet tell him; <HI>Ferdinand</HI> of <HI>Prussia</HI></L>
<L>Hath a long arme; some murderer of his</L>
<L>hath kild vs sleeping.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luci.</SPEAKER>
<L>Kild thee? oh no! I trust the carefull destinies deny</L>
<L>So hard a fate: 'tis I alone am kild.</L>
<L>Come <HI>Lodowick,</HI> and close vp my night-vaild eies</L>
<L>That neuer may agen behold the day.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>What meanes <HI>Mathias?</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>He offers to Kill himselfe.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold me not Prince <HI>Otho.</HI></L>
<L>I will reuenge my selfe vpon my selfe▪</L>
<L>For Parricide for damned parricide:</L>
<L>I haue kild my brother sleeping in the armes</L>
<L>Of the diuinest forme that e're held breath.</L>
<L>I haue kild loues Queene defac't with my foule hand,</L>
<L>The goodliest frame that euer nature built</L>
<L>And driuen the graces from the mansion</L>
<L>Wherein they haue continued from their birth;</L>
<L>She now being dead, shee'l dwell no more on earth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>What mooued you to it brother?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Iealous rage, suspition by Prince <HI>Otho,</HI></L>
<L>That <HI>Lucibell</HI> had fled with a base Greeke,</L>
<L>Oh me accursed! I am borne to shame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>But I am wretcheder, that from the lou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Deuoted to the house of <HI>Saxony,</HI></L>
<L>Haue thus begot this monster cruelty:</L>
<L>I lay within an arbour, whence I saw</L>
<L>The princesse, and your selfe in this disguise</L>
<L>Departing secretly my vncles court:</L>
<L><PB REF="17"/>I iudg'd you for a Greeke as you appear'd.</L>
<L>Told Prince <HI>Mathias</HI> of your secret flight;</L>
<L>And hee led on by fury followed you</L>
<L>Where thus deceased by night and your attire,</L>
<L>Hath rob'd your heart of life, his owne of ioy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Forgiue me brother, pardon fairest maide,</L>
<L>And ere the icy hand of ashie death</L>
<L>Fo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d your faire bodies in this sable vaile;</L>
<L>Discouer why you put on this disguise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>To scape the lustfull Duke of <HI>Prussia,</HI></L>
<L>Who purpos'd this night to murder me,</L>
<L>And rauish her whom death hath made his pray</L>
<L>My <HI>Lucibell,</HI> whose lights are mask't with clouds</L>
<L>That neuer will be cleard.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>My vncle, fie, who buz'd into your head</L>
<L>This damned lie?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>it's no lie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luci.</SPEAKER>
<L>Noe lie: 'tis true, 'tis true,</L>
<L>The reuerent Hermet <HI>Rodorick</HI> told it vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Hermet is a villaine damn'd in hell</L>
<L>Before the worlds creation, if he sai't</L>
<L>My Princely vncle purpos'd such a thought.</L>
<L>Looke to the Princesse, ther's life in her:</L>
<L>Cheere vp your heart Prince <HI>Lodowicke,</HI> courage man.</L>
<L>Your being of comfort may recouer her,</L>
<L>While I bring forth the Hermet and disprooue</L>
<L>This false assertion: <HI>Rodorick</HI> is a slaue</L>
<L>A vile and irreligious hypocrite,</L>
<L>No Hermet, but a diuell if he dare</L>
<L>Affirme such falshood of Duke <HI>Ferdinand.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Rodorigo, Saxony, and Austria.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rodo.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Rodorick</HI> is not as you report him sir,</L>
<L>Nor did he ere<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>belie Duke <HI>Ferdinand.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>No did? why then did you maliciously</L>
<L><PB REF="17"/>Aduise Prince <HI>Lodowick</HI> and faire <HI>Lucibell</HI></L>
<L>To flie the <HI>Prussian</HI> court this dismall night.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rodo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who I? I spake not with them,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lodo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes ye did.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sax.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where was it that he spake with you? tell vs where?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lodo.</SPEAKER>
<L>At Dantzike in the Duke of <HI>Prussias</HI> court.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sax.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who heard him besides you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Princesse <HI>Lucibell.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luci.</SPEAKER>
<L>As heauen shall helpe my fleeting soule, I did.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aust.</SPEAKER>
<L>why speakes my dukedomes hope in hollow sounds?</L>
<L>Looke vp fayre child heer's <HI>Saxony</HI> and I</L>
<L>Thy father, <HI>Lucibella</HI> looke on me;</L>
<L>I am not angry that thou fled'st away</L>
<L>But come to grace thy nuptials; prithee speake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luci.</SPEAKER>
<L>Father I thanke you: <HI>Lodowick</HI> reach me thy hand</L>
<L>How cold thou art; death now assailes our hearts,</L>
<L>Hauing triumph't ouer the outward parts;</L>
<L>Farewell a while, we die but part, to meete</L>
<L>Where ioyes are certaine, pleasures endlesse, sweet.</L>
<L>Father, this latest boone of you I craue,</L>
<L>Let him, and me, lie in one bed, and graue.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Moritur.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aust.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh me! oh miserable wretched me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Houer a little longer blessed soule,
glide not away too fast: mine now forsaks his earthly man∣sion
and on hopes gilt wings will gladly mount with thine,
where Angels sing celestiall ditties to the King of Kings.
brother adew, your rashnesse I forgiue, pardon me father,
pardon; <HI>Austria</HI> your daughter is become a bride for death:
the dismall euen before her wedding day. Hermet God
pardon thee: thy double tongue hath caus'd this errour:
but in peace farewell. Hee that lifts vs to Heauen keepe
thee from Hell.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Moritur.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh strange coniecture! what should moue this Prince</L>
<L>To charge me with such horrid cruelty?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="18"/>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile tell thee hypocrite.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sax</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay <HI>Mathias</HI> stay,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> is thy vncle <HI>Rodorigo,</HI> and besides,</L>
<L>My hon or and Duke <HI>Austria's</HI> shall bee gag'd,</L>
<L>He neuer parted from our company in his owne hermitag<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Since day declinde, and glimmering twilight vsher'd in the night.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not from his hermitage?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aust.</SPEAKER>
<L>Noe not he.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'st possible?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aust.</SPEAKER>
<L>By Heauen he did not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then there is villany, practice, and villainy</L>
<L><HI>Mathias</HI> hath bin wrong'd and drawne to kill</L>
<L>His naturall brother, with him to destroy</L>
<L>The rarest peece of natures workmanship,</L>
<L>No doubt by practize and base villany</L>
<L>The Hermet not at court? strange! wondrous!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sax.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh for my fonne, and <HI>Austria's</HI> worthy childe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aust.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou weep'st in scorne, and very teare of thine</L>
<L>Cou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rs a smile: <HI>Saxony,</HI> I defie</L>
<L>All truce, all league of loue, guard thee prowd Duke;</L>
<L>Thy sonnes haue made me childlesse; Ile haue thee</L>
<L>Con<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ort in death with my wrong'd girle and mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Helpe Prince <HI>Mathias:</HI> Hermet, oh the Heauens!</L>
<L>The <HI>Austrian</HI> Duke sinkes downe vpon the earth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aust.</SPEAKER>
<L>Proud Iohn of <HI>Saxony:</HI> ha'st thou no wound?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sax.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not any <HI>Austria;</HI> neither toucht I thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aust.</SPEAKER>
<L>Somebody toucht me home: vaine world farewell</L>
<L>Dying I fall on my dead <HI>Lucibell.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Saxo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir what are you that take on you to parte?</L>
<L>It's by your weapon that the Duke is falne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>If I thought so, i'de fall vpon the point,</L>
<L>But I am innocent of such an ill:</L>
<L>Kill my good kinsman, Duke of <HI>Austria;</HI></L>
<L>Then were Prince <HI>Otho</HI> of <HI>Luningberg</HI> set downe</L>
<L>In sad dispaires blacke booke to raue and die;</L>
<L>But I am free from such imprety.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="18"/>
<SPEAKER>Sax<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you Prince <HI>Otho</HI> of <HI>Luningberg?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rodo.</SPEAKER>
<L>He is, and heire apparent to Duke <HI>Ferdinan<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sax.</SPEAKER>
<L>May be the Moone deceaues me, and my grief<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>As well in the distinguishing of sounds,</L>
<L>As sight: I haue heard of young <HI>Luningberg,</HI></L>
<L>And seene him to at <HI>Hoffmans</HI> ouerthrow,</L>
<L>He lookt not like you, neither spake like you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Father, 'tis he: <HI>Lorrique</HI> his man attends him,</L>
<L>That fellow which is all compos'd of mirth</L>
<L>Of mirth? of death: why should I thinke of mirth</L>
<L>After so foule a murder? come lend hands</L>
<L>To giue this Princely body funerall rites,</L>
<L>That I may sacrifice this hand and heart</L>
<L>For my peace-offerings on theyr sepulchers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sax.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, boy, thou shall not leaue old Saxony</L>
<L>Childles for all this sorrow: Prince, and if <HI>Otho</HI></L>
<L>Helpe in my son with noble <HI>Austria,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Lodowick</HI> shalbe my burden: brother yours</L>
<L>The louely but the lucklesse <HI>Lucibell.</HI></L>
<L>So treade a heauy measure; now lets goe</L>
<L>To interre the dead, our hearts being dead with woe.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt carrying the dead bodie<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ther's life in <HI>Lucibell,</HI> for I feele</L>
<STAGE>Rodo. last with Lucibell.</STAGE>
<L>A breath, more odoriferous then balme</L>
<L>Thirle through the corrall pora<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s of her lipps,</L>
<L>Apparent signes of life, her pu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ses beate;</L>
<L>Oh if I could but yet recouer her,</L>
<L>T'would satisfie the State of <HI>Austria,</HI></L>
<L>That else would be disturb'd for want of heires</L>
<L>Heauen be propitious, guide my artlesse hand,</L>
<L>To preserue fainting life in this cleare forme.</L>
<L>Graunt this thou soule of all Diuinity,</L>
<L>And I will striue what euer mortall may</L>
<STAGE>Enter Hoffman and Saxony.</STAGE>
<L>To serue thee on my knees both night and day.</L>
<L>Tarry Prince <HI>Otho</HI> and see theyr bodies balm'd,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="19"/>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>I pray you thinke me not in passion dull;</L>
<L>I must withdraw, and weepe, my heart is full.</L>
<L>Oh reuerent man, thou bearst the richest fruite;</L>
<L>That euer fell in the vnripired spring,</L>
<L>Goe lay her soft, she had ill fatero fall;</L>
<L>But rich or faire or strong, death swallowes all,</L>
<L>Hol<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>! <HI>Lorrique,</HI> leaue our horse; draw neere.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Lorrique.</STAGE>
<L>Helpe me to sing a hymne vnto the fates</L>
<L>Compos'd of laughing interiections.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why my good Lord? what accidents</L>
<L>Haue chanc't, that tickle so your spleene?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh my deere selfe: thou trusty treasurer of my re∣uenge<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Kneele downe, and at my bidding kisse the earth;</L>
<L>And on her cold eare whisper this strict charge:</L>
<L>That she prouide the best of her perfumes,</L>
<L>The fat of Lambs rap't from the bleating Ewes,</L>
<L>The sweetest smelling wood she can deuise;</L>
<L>For I must offer vp a sacrifice,</L>
<L>To blest occasion that hath seconded</L>
<L>With opportune meanes my desire of wreake▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now I haue kis't the earth, let me pertake</L>
<L>In your great ioy, that seemes to exceed.</L>
<L>Are <HI>Lodowick,</HI> and the Princesse murder'd?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis done, goe, hie thee to Prince <HI>Ferdinand;</HI></L>
<L>Tell him how misaduenture and mistrust</L>
<L>Hath kild Prince <HI>Lodowick</HI> and bright <HI>Lucibell:</HI></L>
<L>By Prince <HI>Mathias</HI> hand: adde to that chaunce,</L>
<L>Another vnexpected accident:</L>
<L>Say that the Dukes of <HI>Austria</HI> and <HI>Saxony,</HI></L>
<L>Being by the Hermet <HI>Rodorick</HI> intertain'd,</L>
<L>And hearing outcries in the dead of night,</L>
<L>Came and beheld the tragick spectacle,</L>
<L>Which sight did so inrage the <HI>Austrian</HI> Duke,</L>
<L>That he, assail'd the <HI>Saxon,</HI> but fell slaine,</L>
<L><PB REF="19"/>On his <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> daughter, now defloured by death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is <HI>Austria</HI> then slaine by <HI>Saxony?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, come, hee's dead, eyther by him or me,</L>
<L>Noe matter, hee's gone: ther's more to goe.</L>
<L>Runne with the newes; away.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Stilt, and a rabble of poore souldiers: old Stilt his
father, with hi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> scarfe like a Captaine. A
s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uruy march.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stilt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Father, set you the army in qeraye, while I inuocate:</L>
<L>The Generall <HI>Foulkes: Fibs,</HI> forman, and</L>
<L>Friends all, Officers ail, helpe to marshall; Prince</L>
<L><HI>Ierom</HI> my Lord shall remunerate that, is shall be</L>
<L>Full of thankesgiuing, while nature is able to</L>
<P>Nourish, or sustayne; Father you haue order to stay the
rest, be sententious, and full of circumstance I aduise you;
and remember this, that more then mortality fights on
our side; For we haue treason and iniquity to maintayne
our quarrell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old Stilt.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hah! what say'st my sonne? treason and ini∣quity?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stilt.</SPEAKER>
<P>Reason, and equity I meant Father; ther's little
controuersity in the words: but like a Captaine couragi∣ous,
I pray goe forward, remember the place you are, in noe
more, but this; the dayes of old, no more, but that; and
the glory Father; Knighthood at least, to the vtter defa∣cing
of you and your posterity, Noe more but soe.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Stilt.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, goe thy waies: thou art able to put fire
into a Flint stone; thou hast as rheumatique a tongue to
<PB REF="20"/>
perswade as any is betweene <HI>Pole</HI> and <HI>Pomer;</HI> but thou art
euen kitt after kind, I am thy father, and was infamous
for my exprobations, to discourage a dissembly of tall
souldiers afore thou w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rt borne, and I haue made them
stand to it tooth and nayle; how say you, most valiant and
reprobate Country men: haue ye not heard I haue bin a
stinger, a tickler, a wormer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fibs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yet; noble, ancient Captaine <HI>Stilt,</HI> ye haue re∣mou'd
mens hearts I haue heard that of my father (God
rest his soule,) when yee were but one of the common all
souldiers that seru'd old <HI>Sarloys</HI> in Norway.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Stilt.</SPEAKER>
<P>I then was, and <HI>Sarloys</HI> was; a gentleman wou'd
not haue giuen his head for the washing; but hee is cut
of, as all valiant caualeroes shall; and they be no more neg∣ligent
of themselues; But to the purpose: wee are dissem∣bled
together, and falne into ba<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tayle beray in the behalfe
Prince <HI>Ierom</HI> a vertuous Prince, a wise Prince, and a most
respectlesse Prince; my son Timothies master, and the vn∣lawfull
heire of this land. Now sir the old Duke has put out
a declamation, and saies our rising is noe other then a re∣surrection,
for the Prince inspires not against his father;
but the Duke inspires against his son, vsing him most natu∣rally,
charitably, and abhominably, to put him from inter∣cession
of the crowne; wherefore as yee bee true men,
and obstinate subiects to the State vncouer your heads, and
cast vp your caps and cry a <HI>Ierom, a Ierom,</HI></P>
<P>Om, A Ierom, a Ierom, a Ierom.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Ierom, and Stilt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<P>Most noble Countrymen I cannot but cond le in
ioy, and smile in teares to see you assembled in my right,
but this is the lamentation that I poore Prince must
make, who for my fathers proclamation am like for to
<PB REF="20"/>
loose my head; except you stand to mee, for they are com∣ming
on with bowes, bills, and guns, against vs: but if
you be valiant, and stand to me lustily, allth' earth 'shall roare
but wee'l haue victory.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter with Drum, and Colours, Duke Ferdinand, Hoffman
Lorrique, Captaiue to leade the drum the souldiers march
and make a stand; All on Ieroms side cast
vp their caps and cry a Ierom.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vpon those traytors valiant gentlemen:</L>
<L>Let not that bea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> the multitude confront,</L>
<L>With garlicke-breath and their confused cries</L>
<L>The Maiesty of me their awfull Duke,</L>
<L>Strike their Typhoean body downe to fire</L>
<L>That dare 'gainst vs, their soueraigne conspire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, come, you shall haue your hands full, and you</L>
<L>Come where we haue to doe, stand to it <HI>Stilt.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stilt.</SPEAKER>
<P>stand to't? heer's the father and the son will stand,
though all the rest flie away.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O Stilt.</SPEAKER>
<P>I warrant you Prince, when the battaile comes
to ioyning, my son and I will bee inuisible, and they ouer∣come
vs, ile giue you leaue to say I haue no pith in me; vp∣on
vm true Prince vpon vm.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>An Alarum: Hoffman kneeles betweene the Armies.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stilt.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thought twou'd come to that;</L>
<L>I thought we shou'd bring</L>
<L>The false Prince on his knees.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<P>What meanes my Dukedomes hope to turne thus
base? arise, and smite thy fo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rl.</SPEAKER>
<L>I see them not my most honor'd vncle; pittie I beseech</L>
<L>These silly people, that offend as babes,</L>
<L>Not vnderstanding, how they doe <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ffend:</L>
<L>And s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ffer me chiefe agent in this wrong,</L>
<L>To plead their pardons with a peacefull tongue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="21"/>
<SPEAKER>Stilt.</SPEAKER>
<L>We scorne pardons, Peace and pitty; Wee'l</L>
<L>haue a Prince of our owne chusing, Prince <HI>Ierom.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Stilt.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, I, Prince <HI>lorom</HI> or no body; be not obstacle old
Duke, let not your owne flesh and blood bee inherited of
your Dukedome, and a stranger displac'd in his retority:
for and you doe, wee will take no comparison of you and
your army, but fall vpon you like temperance and light∣ning.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vpon your perill; gentlemen assayle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sarl.</SPEAKER>
<L>If any bosome meete the brunt of war,</L>
<L>Mine shall be first oppos'd; these honest men</L>
<L>That rise in armes for my young Cozens right</L>
<L>Shall be Protected whil'st Prince <HI>Charles</HI> can stand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why see now what a thing Maiesty is;</L>
<L><HI>Stilt</HI> and the rest of my good people; my couzen)</L>
<L><HI>Charles</HI> looking but in the face of our excellence</L>
<L>Cannot choose but take our parte.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stilt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay but trust him not my Lord; take heed of him,</L>
<L>Aware your enemies at any hand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why should you make this intercession</L>
<L>For these base abiects, whose presumptuous hearts</L>
<L>Haue drawne their rebell bodies 'gainst their head:</L>
<L>Intreat not for them, they are all but dead.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sarl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Forbeare a little worthy Countrymen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stilt.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay we deny that, weare none of your Countrymen;
you are an ar<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ant arrant Alien.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Stilt.</SPEAKER>
<P>True son uncere peregrination, and one that was not
borne within our Dukes damnation, and therefore not to
be remitted to any vpstantiall degree of office amongst vs:
that's the fine, that's the confusion of all.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sarl.</SPEAKER>
<P>But heare mee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, I▪ pray heare him; nay I charge you all vpon paine
of death that you heare my cozen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stilt.</SPEAKER>
<P>he Well wee will are him: come on, speake, what
wlil yee say?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sarl.</SPEAKER>
<L>O I beseech you saue your liues and goods,</L>
<L><PB REF="21"/>
For the Dukes squadrons arm'd with wrath and death,</L>
<L>Watch but the signall when to ceaze on you,</L>
<L>That can noe more with stand their approoued strengthes</L>
<L>Then sparrowes can contend with towring hawks:</L>
<L>Or 'gainst the Eagles ayer<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>:</L>
<L>This act of yours by gathering to a head,</L>
<L>Is treason capitall, and without grace</L>
<L>Your liues are forfeit to extreamest law.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O Stilt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mas he saies true son; but what's the remedy?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stilt.</SPEAKER>
<P>None at all father, now wee are in, wee must goe
through stitch.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sarl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, there is remedy: cast your weapons downe,</L>
<L>And arme your selues with mercy of your Prince</L>
<L>Who like a gracious shepheard ready stands</L>
<L>To take his lost sheepe home in gentle hands.</L>
<L>As for your Prince, I will for him intreat</L>
<L>That he may be restor'd againe in loue,</L>
<L>And vnto offices of dignity, as eyther Taster,</L>
<L>Sewer, Cupbearer, the place himselfe thinkes</L>
<L>Fittest for his state, and for my part when</L>
<L>That vnhappy time of Princely <HI>Ferdinands</HI></L>
<L>Sad death shall, come:—</L>
<L>Which moment:—</L>
<L>But should I as I say behold that houre,</L>
<L>Although I am elected for your Prince,</L>
<L>Yet would I not remooue this gentleman,</L>
<L>Bat rather serue him as his councellor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<P>Giue me your hand of that Cozen; well sayd, now
get a pardon for mee, and my merry men all; and then let
me be my fathers Taster, being the office belonging to his
eldest sonne; I Being the same, and then you shall see mee
behaue my selfe, not as a rebell, or reprobate, but as a most
reasonable Prince, and sufficient subiect.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stilt.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well since my Lord ha's sayd the word, bring that
of spake he to passe and ye shall haue my word too, and old
<HI>Stilt</HI> my fathers, being a man of good reproch I tell you,
<PB REF="22"/>
and condemnation in his country.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Stilt.</SPEAKER>
<P>I that I am my Lord, I haue liu'd in name and shame
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hese threescore, and seuen winters, all my neighbours can
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>are me testament, and accord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sarl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, rest yee quiet; Soueraigne on my knees</L>
<L>I beg your Highnes graunt to there request:</L>
<L>Suppose them silly, simple, and your owne;</L>
<L>To shed their blood were iust, yet rigorous,</L>
<L>The praise of Kings is to prooue gracious.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>True soule of honor, substance of my selfe,</L>
<L>Thy merit wins thee mercy, goe in peace,</L>
<L>Lay by your vniust armes, liue by your sweate,</L>
<L>And in content the bread of quiet eate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Om.</SPEAKER>
<L>Godsaue Duke <HI>Ferdinand.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exuni</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray Father, forgiue me, and my man,</L>
<L>And my mans father by our single selues;</L>
<L>For we haue bin the capitall offendors.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Stilt<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></SPEAKER>
<L>I truely my Lord, we rais'd the resurrection,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>I pardon all; giue thee my Tasters place:</L>
<L>Honor this Prince that hath thus won you grace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. S.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y-S. God saue Duke <HI>Ferdinand,</HI> and Prince <HI>Otho.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<L>I and me too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Stilt.</SPEAKER>
<P>And Prince <HI>Ierom</HI> too; well son, ile leaue thee a
Courtier still, and get mee home to my owne desolation,
where ile labour to compell away excessity: and so fareyee
well.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>This busines ouer: worthy nephew <HI>Charles,</HI></L>
<L>Let vs goe visi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> the sad <HI>Saxon</HI> Duke,</L>
<L>The mourning Hermet,</L>
<L>That through affection wrought his brothers fall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sarl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile wait your Highnes to that house of woe,</L>
<L>Where sad mischance sits in a purple chayre,</L>
<L>And vnderncath her beetle cloudy browes</L>
<L>smiles at vnlockt for mischsefes; oh there</L>
<L><PB REF="22"/>
Doth griefe vnpainted, in true shape appeare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shrill trumpets sound a flourish</L>
<L>For the cryes of war are drownd.</L>
<STAGE>Exit</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier,</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay but cozen cozen, i'st not necessary I wait</L>
<L>Vpon myne owne father? and <HI>stilt</HI> vpon me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sarl.</SPEAKER>
<L>It's most expedient, be obsequious.</L>
<L>Noe doubt his <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>xcellence will l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>e that well.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Lorrique like a French Doctor.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dieu vou guard Mounsieur.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sarl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Welcome my friend, ha'st any suit to me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away Mounsieur, if you be the grand Princ<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Legitimate of <HI>Prussia,</HI> I haue for tendre</L>
<L>To your Excellence de service of one poore</L>
<L>Gentle home of Champaigne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sarl.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am not he you looke for gentlemen,</L>
<L>My cozen is the true and lawfull Prince.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<L>I sir I am the legitimate, and am able to entertayne</L>
<L>A gentleman though I say't and he be of any quality,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sarl,</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Lorrique,</HI> now or neuer play thy part:</L>
<L>This Act is euen our Tragedies best hart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me alone for plots, and villany,</L>
<L>Onely commend me to this foole the Prince.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<L>I tell thee, I am the Prince, my cozen knowes it,</L>
<L>That's my cozen, this is <HI>stilt</HI> my man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>A vostree seruice Mounsieur most Genereux.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sarl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Noe doubt he is some cunning gentleman</L>
<L>Your Grace may doe a deede befitting you</L>
<L>To entertaine this stranger.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<L>It shall bedone cozen; ile talke with him a little</L>
<L>And follow you, goe commend me to my father</L>
<P>Tell him I am comming, and Stilt, and this stranger, bee
mindfull cozen, as you will answere to my Princely in∣diguation.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="23"/>
<SPEAKER>Sarl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well sir, I will be carefull, neuer doubt;</L>
<L>Now scarlet Mistris from thicke sable clouds</L>
<L>Thrust forth thy blood-staind hands, applaud my plot,</L>
<L>That giddy wonderers may amazed stand</L>
<L>While death smytes downe suspectles <HI>Ferdinand.</HI></L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stilt.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sweet Prince I scarce vnderstand this fellow well,
but I like his conceit in not trusting Prince <HI>otho;</HI> you must
giue him the remooue that's flat.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>I be, gar, hee be chose agen you, hee giue you good
worde so be dat, but he will haue one fisgig or dia by gar
for company on in principality be no possible.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, I apprehend thee, I haue a certaine Princely
feeling in my selfe that he loues me not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stilt.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hold yee there my Lord, I am but a poore fellow
and haue but a simple liuing left me; yet my brother were
he a very naturall brother of mine owne, should hee b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e
dopted, I would dopt him, and herrite him, i'le fit him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<P>I but how <HI>Stilt,</HI> but how?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>By gar my Lord, I will tell you fine knacks, for make
him kicke vp his heeles, and cry wee, or be gar
I be hange, and so shall I be to, and for de grand loue I beare
you, for de Lady <HI>Issabella's</HI> sake your most tres-excellent
Lady moder,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<P>Didst, thou know her French doctor? didst thou?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Silt.</SPEAKER>
<P>I as beggars doe the Ladies that are their Almesgi∣giuers.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>By gar you lye, like Iacknape, I loue de Lady.</P>
<P>With a boone coeur, and for her sake here take dissame, and
dis same, put dis in de cup, where de competitor Prince
<HI>otho</HI> shall drinke; by gar it will poyson him brauely.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stilt.</SPEAKER>
<P>That were excellent my Lord, and it could be done,
and noe body know on't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, but he alwaies drinkes in my Fathers cup.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>I so let be, let de Duke drinke a de same.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<P>What poyson my father? noe, I like not that so well.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="23"/>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>You shall drinke too, and I too and when wee bee
sicke, as we shall baue as shall haue a petit rumble in de belly; dan take a
dis same, and giue your sadra dis: but your cozin none of
it, and bygar noe body shall be dead, and kicka, and cry oh,
but <HI>Otho.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stilt.</SPEAKER>
<P>That's excellent, master;</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<P>This is the poyson then, and this is the medicine?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>I dat be true.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well Phisitian, attend in my chamber heere, till <HI>Stilt</HI>
and I returne; and if I pepper him not, say I am not wor∣thy
to be cald a Duke, but a drawlatch.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stilt.</SPEAKER>
<P>Farewellawe, and iebbit a vow; and wee speede by
thy practice wee'l crush a cup of thine owne country
wine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe speede to spoyle your selues.</L>
<L>Doctor lie there, <HI>Lorrique,</HI> like thy selfe appeare</L>
<L>So now ile post vuto the Hermitage, and smile</L>
<L>While silly fooles act treason act through my guile.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus quartus.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Ferdinand and Sarlois, open a curtaine: Kneele
Saxony, the Hermet and Mathias:
tapers burning.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sarl.</SPEAKER>
<L>See Princely vncle blacke dormitory,</L>
<L>Where <HI>Austria</HI> and Prince <HI>Lodowick</HI> are layd</L>
<L>On the cold bed of earth, where they must sleepe</L>
<L>Till earth and ayre, and sea consume by fire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Their rest be peace, their rising glorious;</L>
<L>Sad mourners, giue your partners leaue to kneele,</L>
<L>And make their offertorie on this tombe,</L>
<L>That does containe the honourablest earth</L>
<L>That euer went vpright in <HI>Germany,</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="24"/>
<SPEAKER>Sax.</SPEAKER>
<L>Welcome Duke <HI>Ferdinand,</HI> come, come, keele, kneele▪</L>
<L>Thus should each friend anothers sorrow feele.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sarl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is <HI>Lucibella</HI> in this monument?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Red.</SPEAKER>
<L>Noe, shee's recouer'd from deaths violence;</L>
<L>But through her woundes and griefe distract of sence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sarl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heauen helpe her, here she comes;</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Lucibella mad.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Kneele still, I p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ay.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh mee accurst I why liue I this blacke day▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh a sword, I pray you kill me not,</L>
<L>For I am going to the riuers side.</L>
<L>To fetch white lillies, and b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ew daffadils</L>
<L>To sticke in <HI>Lodowicks</HI> bosome, where it bled,</L>
<L>And in mine owne; my true loue is not dead,</L>
<L>Noe y'are deceiud in him, my father is:</L>
<L>Reason he should, he made me run away▪</L>
<L>And <HI>Lodowick</HI> too, and you <HI>Mathias</HI> too;</L>
<L>Alacke for woe, yet what a the remedy?</L>
<L>We must run all awaye: yet all must dye.</L>
<L>'Tis soe, I wrought it in a sampler,</L>
<L>'Twas heart in hand, and true loues knots and words,</L>
<L>All true stitch by my troth: the posie thus:</L>
<L>No flight deare loue but death, shall seuer vs;</L>
<L>Nor that did not neyther; he lies here does he not?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes louely madam, pray be patient.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Iso I am, but pray tell me true,</L>
<L>Could you be patient, or you, or you, or you,</L>
<L>To loose a father and a husband too:</L>
<L>Yee could, I cannot; open, doore here hoe!</L>
<L>Tell <HI>Lodowick, Lucibell</HI> would speake with him;</L>
<L>I haue newes from heauen for him, he must not dy,</L>
<L>I haue rob'd <HI>Prometheus</HI> of his moouing fire:</L>
<L>Open the dore, I must come in, and will,</L>
<L>Ile beate my selfe to ayre, but Ile come in.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="24"/>
<SPEAKER>Sarl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas her tender hands smiting the ston<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Beweepe their mistris rage in teares of blood.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faire Lady be of comfort, t'is in vaine</L>
<L>To inuocate the dead to life againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sax.</SPEAKER>
<L>I gentle Daughter be content, I pray▪</L>
<L>Their fate is come, and ours is not, far off.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here is a hand ouer my fate hath power▪</L>
<L>And I now sinke vnder the stroke of death,</L>
<L>But that a purer spirit fils my brest</L>
<L>And guides me from the footsteps of dispaire,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sarl.</SPEAKER>
<L>A heauenly motion full of charity,</L>
<L>Your selfe to kill you selfe were such a sinne</L>
<L>As most diuines hold deadly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>I but a knaue may kill one by a tricke,</L>
<L>Or lay a plot, or soe, or cog, or prate,</L>
<L>Make strife, make a mans father hang him,</L>
<L>Or his brother, how thinke you goodly Prince,</L>
<L>God giue you ioy of your adoption;</L>
<L>May nor trickes be vsd?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sarl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas poore Lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thats true, I am poore, and yet haue things,</L>
<L>And gold ring, and amidst the leaues greenea</L>
<L>Lord how dee, well I thanke god, why thats well,</L>
<L>And you my Lord, and you too; neuer a one weepe,</L>
<L>Must I shed all the teares? well he is gone,</L>
<L>And he dwells here ye sayd, ho i'le dwell with him,</L>
<L>Death, dastard, Diuell, robber of my life</L>
<L>Thou base adulterer, that partst man and wife</L>
<L>Come I defie thy darts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>O sweet for beare.</L>
<L>For pitties sake a while her rage restraine</L>
<L>Last she doe violence vpon herselfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>O neuer feare me, there is somewhat cri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></L>
<L>Within menoe: tels me there's knaues abroad</L>
<L><PB REF="25"/>
Bids mee be quiet, lay me downe and sleepe</L>
<L>Good night good gentlefolkes, brother your hand,</L>
<L>And yours good father, you are my father now,</L>
<L>Doe but stand here, l'fe sun a little course</L>
<L>At base, or barley-breake, or some such toye,</L>
<L>To catch the fellow, and come backe againe,</L>
<L>Nay looke thee now, let goe, or by my troth</L>
<L>Ile tell my <HI>Lodowick</HI> how yee vse his loue:</L>
<L>Soe now god-buye, now god-night indeede:</L>
<L>Lie further <HI>Lodowick▪</HI> take not all the roome,</L>
<L>Be not a churle, thy <HI>Lucibell</HI> doth come.</L>
<STAGE>Exit</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sax.</SPEAKER>
<L>Follow her brother, follow son <HI>Mathies,</HI></L>
<L>Be carefull guardians of the troubled mayd;</L>
<L>While I con<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>erre with Princely <HI>Ferdinand</HI></L>
<L>About an embassie to <HI>Aüstria,</HI></L>
<L>With true reports of there disasterous haps.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, I will be her guardian and her guide,</L>
<L>By me her sences haue bin weakned,</L>
<L>But i'le contend with charitable paine,</L>
<L>To serue her, till they be restord againe.</L>
<STAGE>Exit</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sarl.</SPEAKER>
<L>A vertuous, noble resolution.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Worthy Prince <HI>Rodorigo,</HI> when tempestuous woe</L>
<L>Abates her violent storme, I shall haue time</L>
<L>To chide you for vnkindenes, that haue liu'd</L>
<L>In solitary life with vs so long.</L>
<L>Beleue me <HI>Saxon</HI> Prince you did vs wrong:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would I might neuer liue in noe worse state;</L>
<L>For contemplation is the path to heauen.</L>
<L>My new conversing in the world is prou'd</L>
<L>Lucklesse and full of sorrow; fare-ye-well</L>
<L>My heauens, alone, all company seemes hell.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>My nephew call for winemy soule is dry</L>
<L><PB REF="25"/>
I am sad at sight of soe much misery.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter I erom and Stilt, with cup, towell, and wine.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sarl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is the Dukes taster there?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am at hand with my office.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sarl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fill for the Duke good cozen, tast it first.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue no minde to it <HI>Stilt,</HI> for all my antidote.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stilt.</SPEAKER>
<L>I warrant you Master let Prince <HI>Otho</HI> drinke next,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heere cozen, will you begin to my father?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sarl.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thanke you kindly, i'le not be so bold,</L>
<L>It is your office; fill vnto my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well god be with it, it's gon downe, and now ile
send the medicine after; Father pray drinke to my cozen
for hee is soe mannerly that hee'l not drinke before you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stilt.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray yee doe my Lord, for Prince <HI>Otho</HI> is best wor∣thy
of all this company to drinke of that cup, which and
he doe, I hope he shall nere drinke more.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer,</SPEAKER>
<P>Good for tune after all this sorrow <HI>Saxony.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sax.</SPEAKER>
<P>O worthy <HI>Ferdinand,</HI> fortune and I are parted, she
has playd the minion with mee, turn'd all her fauours in
to frownes, and in scorne rob'd mee of all my hopes, and in
one houre o're turnd mee from the top of her proud
wheele.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Build not on fortune, shee's a sickle dame</L>
<L>And those that trust vnto her spheare are fooles.</L>
<L>Fill for his Excellence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here cozen for your Excellence, pray drinke you to
the Duke of <HI>Saxony.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sarl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not I kind cozen, I list not to drinke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gods Lady, I thinke <HI>Stilt,</HI> wee are all vndone, for I
feele a iumbling worse and worse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stilt.</SPEAKER>
<P>O giue the Duke some of the medicine</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<P>What medicine talk'st thou of? what ayles my son?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<P>O lord, father, and yee meane to be a liues man take
some of this.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="26"/>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why? this is deadly poyson vnprepar'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<P>True, but it was prepar'd for you and mee by an ex∣cellent
fellow, a french Doctor?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stilt.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, he is one that had great cqre of you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>For,</SPEAKER>
<L>Villaine what was he? drinke not <HI>Saxony</HI></L>
<L>I doubt I am by treason poyson'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sarl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heauen keepe that fortune from my dread Lord.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Lorrique hastily.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Treason ye Princes, treason to the liues</L>
<L>Of <HI>Ferdinand</HI> the D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ke of <HI>Prussia</HI></L>
<L>My Princely master! <HI>Otho</HI> of <HI>Luningberg</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sarl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who should intend vs treason?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>This fond Prince.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<P>Neuer to you Father, but to my cozen <HI>Charles▪</HI>
indeede I meant to poyson him, but I haue pepperd my
selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sarl.</SPEAKER>
<P>I neuer gaue thee cause.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stilt.</SPEAKER>
<P>That's nothing to the purpose, but my Lord tooke
occasion by the councell of a French Doctor.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sarl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Physitians for the Duke, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y vncie faints.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stilt.</SPEAKER>
<P>Surgeons for the Prince, my master falls.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Call no Phisitians, for I feel't too late,</L>
<L>The subtill poyson mingled with my blood</L>
<L>'Nums all the passages, and<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> nimble death</L>
<L>Fleetes on his p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rple currents to my heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<L>Father, I am dying too, oh now I departe,</L>
<L>Be good to <HI>Stilt</HI> my man, he was accessary</L>
<L>to all this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stils.</SPEAKER>
<P>I truely: was I sir therefore I hope you'le be good
to me, I helpt to mingle the poyson as the French Doctor,
and my master charged me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<P>What's that French Doctor?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sarl.</SPEAKER>
<P>What's become of him?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stilt.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wee left him in the court in my masters cham∣ber.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="26"/>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<L>I sir woe worth him, farewell <HI>Stilt,</HI> farewell fathers</L>
<L>I aske you pardon with repentant eyes;</L>
<L>Fall stars, O <HI>Stilt,</HI> for thus thy master dyes.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>mortiur</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<P>Take hence that maytor for the foole his man.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stilt.</SPEAKER>
<P>I pray prouide for me sit;</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let him be tortur'd, then vpon a wheele</L>
<L>broke like a traytor and a murderer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stilt,</SPEAKER>
<P>O lord sir. I meant you noe hurt, but to Prince <HI>Charles</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sarl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Away, distur be vs not with idle talke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stilt.</SPEAKER>
<P>Prouide quoth a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> and you call this prouiding, pray
let mee, prouide for my selfe, alas my poore father, hee'le
creepe vppon crutches into his graue when, he heares his
proper'st <HI>Stilt</HI> is cut off by the stumpes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hence with that fellow.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stilt.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray, not soe hasty, you would scarce bee
soe forward, and you were going as I am, to the gal∣lowes.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt guard with Stilt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sarl.</SPEAKER>
<L>How cheares my royall vncle <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Likea ship that hauing long contended with</L>
<L>The waues, is at last with one proud billow</L>
<L>Smit into the ruthlesse swallow of the sea.</L>
<L>For thee alas I perceiue this plot was lay de;</L>
<L>But heauen had greater mercy-on <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hy youth,</L>
<L>And one my people, that shall finde true rest</L>
<L>Being with a Prince so wise and vertuous blest.</L>
<L>Farewell most noble Iohn of <HI>Saxony,</HI></L>
<L>Beare thy vnmatched griefe with a minde bent</L>
<L>Against the force of all temptations;</L>
<L>By my example Princely brother, see,</L>
<L>How vaine our liues and all our glories bee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sax.</SPEAKER>
<L>God for thy mercy! treason vpon treason,</L>
<L><PB REF="27"/>
How now yong <HI>Otho</HI> what art thou poyson'd too?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sarl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would God I were, but my sad starrs reserue</L>
<L>This simple building for extreamer ruine:</L>
<L>Oh that French doctor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>I that worst of hell.</L>
<L>Noe torment shall content vs in his death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sax.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay soft and faire, let him be taken first;</L>
<L>How now sad brother, are you come to see</L>
<L>This Tragicke end of worthy <HI>Ferdinand?</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Rodorigo.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L>I heard of it too soone, and come too late.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sax</SPEAKER>
<L>Well brother leaue the Duke, and waite on mee▪</L>
<L><HI>Mathias,</HI> and the heartgreiu'd <HI>Lucibell</HI></L>
<L>Shall goe with vs to <HI>Wittenberg,</HI> and shun</L>
<L>That fatall land fild with destruction.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L>But <HI>Lucibella</HI> like a chased hinde</L>
<L>Flys through the thickets, and neglects the bryers,</L>
<L>After her runs your Princely son <HI>Mathias,</HI></L>
<L>As much disturbd, though not so much distract,</L>
<L>Vowing to follow her, and if he can,</L>
<L>Defend her from dispairing actions.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sax.</SPEAKER>
<L>And we will follow them, Prince <HI>Otho</HI> adue</L>
<L>Care goes with vs, yet we leaue griefe with you,</L>
<L>Interre your vncle, punish traytours crimes,</L>
<L>Looke to your person▪ hese are dangerous times,</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Saxony and Rodorige.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sarl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lords take this body, beare it to the court,</L>
<L>And all the way sound a sad heauy march,</L>
<L>Which you may truly keepe, then peeple treade</L>
<L>A mournesfull march indeed,</L>
<L>Goe on afore, ile stay a while, and weepe</L>
<L>My tributary teares paid on the ground</L>
<L>Where my true ioy your Princemy vncle fell:</L>
<L><PB REF="27"/>
Ile follow to driue from you all distresse</L>
<L>And comfort you, though I be comfortles.</L>
<L>Art not thou plumpt with laughter my <HI>Lorrique,</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt with the body. A marck.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>All this excellent, but worthy Lord,</L>
<L>There is an accident this instant chanc'st</L>
<L>Able to ouerthrow in one poore howre</L>
<L>Aswell your hopes as these assurances.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sarl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whats that <HI>Lorrique?</HI> what can fortune doe</L>
<L>That may diuert my strai<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e of pollicy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>You know all <HI>Prussia</HI> take you for the son</L>
<L>Of beautious Martha,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sarl.</SPEAKER>
<L>I they suppose me to be <HI>Otho</HI> her son,</L>
<L>And son to that false Duke whom I will kill</L>
<L>Or curse my stars</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>His star is sunke already, death and he</L>
<L>Haue vowed an endlesse league of amity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sarl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Had I Briareus hands, i'de strine with heauen</L>
<L>For executing wrath before the houre,</L>
<L>But wishes are in vaine, hee's gone.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Flourish.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter as many as may be spar'd, with lights, and make a lan<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
kneeling while Martha the Dutchesse like a mourner
with her traine passeth through.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our son is somewhat slacke as wee conceiue</L>
<L>By this delaying, while our heart is fear'd,</L>
<L>And our eyes dim'd with expectation</L>
<L>As are the lights of such as on the beach</L>
<L>With many a longing, yet a little proofe</L>
<L>Stand wayting the returne of those they loue.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Lorrique, fals on's knees.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lord.</SPEAKER>
<L>His Excellence no doubt hath great affaires</L>
<L>But his familiar friend <HI>Lorrique</HI> is come.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="28"/>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>kneele not Lorrique, I prethee glad my harte</L>
<L>With thy tongues true report of my son Otho</L>
<L>Whome since his Princely Father is decea'st</L>
<L>I am come from opprest with griefe</L>
<L>In person to salute him for our Duke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your mother like affection, and high care,</L>
<L>His H<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>igh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es doth returne with dut<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ous thankes</L>
<L>Defiring pardon of your excellence,</L>
<L>In that he did not first salute your grace:</L>
<L>But dis<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>al accidents and bloody deeds,</L>
<L>Poysoning streasons, soe disturbe this state</L>
<L>Chiefly this gentle mind since the late death</L>
<L>Of your right princely brother <HI>Ferdinand</HI></L>
<L>That like the carefull Captaine of a band</L>
<L>He is compeld to bee the last in field;</L>
<L>Yet he protests by me, and I for him:</L>
<L>That no soft rest shall enter his grecu'd eyes</L>
<L>Till he behold your presence, more desir'd</L>
<L>Then the large Empire of the wide earth;</L>
<L>Onely he prayes that you would take your rest</L>
<L>For in your soft content his heart is blest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Spread me a Carpet on the humble earth:</L>
<L>My hand shall be the pillow to my head.</L>
<L>This stepmy bolster, and this place my bed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Highnes will take harme▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, neuer feare.</L>
<L>A heart with sorrow fild sleepes any where,</L>
<L>Will our son come to night?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam hee will.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>See our traine lodgd, and then <HI>Lorrique</HI> attend</L>
<L>For captaine of the guard; that wayt on vs,</L>
<L>Goe all away, no body stay with mee</L>
<L>Except our son, come if we chaunce to call,</L>
<L>Trouble vs not, god night vnto you all.</L>
<STAGE>All with doing duty depart, and she sits downe hauing a can∣dle
by her, and reades.</STAGE>
<L><PB REF="28"/>
Quo fugiat mortale genm? nil denique tutum est,</L>
<L>Crudelis nam morsomnia falce secat?</L>
<L>Nil durum, nil non mortis penetrabile telis,</L>
<L>Omnia vi demit, mors vio <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nesa sua.</L>
<L>Tis true, the wise, the foole, the rich, the poore</L>
<L>The fayre, and the deformed fall; their life turnes</L>
<L>Ayre: the King and Captaine are in this alike</L>
<L>None hath free hold of life, but they are still</L>
<L>When death heauens steward comes, tennents at will.</L>
<L>I lay me downe, and rest in thee my trust,</L>
<L>If I wake neuer more, till all flesh rise</L>
<L>I sleepe a happy sleepe, sin in me dyes.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Hoffman, and Lorrique.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Art sure she is a sleepe!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor,</SPEAKER>
<L>I cannot tell, be not too hasty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>She stirs not, shee is fast.</L>
<L>Sleepe sweet fayre Dutchesse, for thou sleep'st thy last:</L>
<L>Endymions loue, muffle in cloudes thy face,</L>
<L>And all ye yellow tapers of the heauen</L>
<L>Vayle your cleare brightnes in Cimerian mistmis;</L>
<L>Let not one light my blacke deed beautiste;</L>
<L>For with one stroake vertue and honour dyes.</L>
<L>And yet we must not kill her in this kind:</L>
<L>Weapons draw blood, blood shed will plainely prooue</L>
<L>The worthy Dntchesse, worthles of this death</L>
<L>Was murdered, and the guard are witnesses,</L>
<L>None enter'd but our selues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then strangle her, here is a towell fit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good: kneele and helpe, compasse her necke about,</L>
<L>Alas poore Lady thou sleep'st here secure</L>
<L>And neuer dream'st of what thou shalt endure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, good my Lord dispatch.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>What ruthlesse hinde</L>
<L>Shall I wrong nature that did ne're compose</L>
<L><PB REF="29"/>
One of her sexe so perfect? prethee stay,</L>
<L>Suppose we kill her thus about her necke,</L>
<L>Circles of purple blood will change the hue</L>
<L>Of this white porphirie and the red lines</L>
<L>Mixt with a deadly blacke, will tell the world</L>
<L>She dyed by violence, then t'will be inquir'd</L>
<L>And we held euer hatefull for the act.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then place beneath her nostrils this small box</L>
<L>Conteyning such a powder that hath power,</L>
<L>Being set on fire to suffocate each sence</L>
<L>Without the sight of wound, or shew of wrong.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's excellent, fetch fire, or doe not, stay:</L>
<L>The candle shall suffice, yet that burnes dim;</L>
<L>And drops his waxen teares as if it mourn'd</L>
<L>To be an agent in a deed so darke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you confound your selfe by dotage speake,</L>
<L>S'wounds ile confound her, and shee linger thus.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou wer't as good, and better,—note my words:</L>
<L>Run vnto the top of dreadfull scarre,</L>
<L>And thence fall headlong on the vnder rocks,</L>
<L>Or set, thy brest against a cannon fir'd,</L>
<L>When iron death flies thence on flaming wings,</L>
<L>Or with thy shoulders, <HI>Atlas</HI> like attempt,</L>
<L>To beare the ruines of a falling tower,</L>
<L>Or swim the Ocean; or run quicke to hell;</L>
<L>(as dead assure thy selfe no better place)</L>
<L>Then once looke frowning on this angells face</L>
<L>Confound her? blacke confusion be my graue</L>
<L>Whisper one such word more, thou dyest base slaue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue done, ile honor her if you command.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>She stirs, and when she wakes obserue me well,</L>
<L>Sooth vp what ere, I say, touching Prince <HI>Otho.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prince <HI>Otho,</HI> is our son come? who's there <HI>Lor∣rique?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>What shall I answere her?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whose that thou talkst with?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="29"/>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>The most indebted seruant to your Grace</L>
<L>Of any creature vnderneath the Moone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I prethee friend be briefe, what is thy name?</L>
<L>I know thee not, what businesse hast thou here?</L>
<L>Art thou a messenger come from our son?</L>
<L>If so acquaint vs with the newes thou bring'st.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<P>I saw your Highnes son, <HI>Lorrique</HI> here knowes,
the last of any liuing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Liuing? heauen helpe,</L>
<L>I trust my son h'as no commerce with death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your son noe doubt is well, in blessed state.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>My heart is smitten through thy answere,</L>
<L><HI>Lorrique,</HI> where is thy gracious Lord?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>In heauen I hope.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>True madam, he did perish in the wracke</L>
<L>When he came first by sea from <HI>Lubecke</HI> hauen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>What false impostor then hath mock't my care?</L>
<L>Abus'd my Princely brother <HI>Ferdinand?</HI></L>
<L>Gotten his Dukedome in my dead sons name?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>I grant him an impostor, therein false</L>
<L>But when your Highnes heares the circumstance,</L>
<L>I know your wisedome and meeke piety</L>
<L>Will Iudge him well deseruing in your eyes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>What can be sayd now I haue lost my son?</L>
<L>Or how can this base two-tongu'd hypocrite</L>
<L>Excuse concealing of his masters death.</L>
<L>Vnhappy <HI>Martha,</HI> in thy age vndone,</L>
<L>Robd of a husban'd, cheated of a son.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heare me with patience for that pitties sake</L>
<L>You shewed my captiue body, by the teares</L>
<L>You shed, when my poore father dragd to death</L>
<L>Indur'd all violence at theyr hands:</L>
<L>By all the mercies powrd on him and me</L>
<L>That like coole rayne somewhat allayd the heate</L>
<L>Of our sad torment, and red sufferings;</L>
<L>Here me but speake a little to repay</L>
<L><PB REF="30"/>
With gratitude the fauours I receiu'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Art thou the lucklesse son of that sad man</L>
<L>Lord of Burtholme some time admirall?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>I was his onely son, whom you set free,</L>
<L>Therefore submissiuely I kneele and craue,</L>
<L>You would with patience heare your seruant speake;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be briefe, my swolne heart is at poynt to breake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>I stood vpon the top of the high scarre,</L>
<L>Where I beheld the splitted ship let in</L>
<L>Deuouring ruine in the shape of waues,</L>
<L>Some got on Rafts, but were as soone cast off</L>
<L>As they weare seated; many strid the mast,</L>
<L>But the seas working was soe violent,</L>
<L>That nothing could preserue them from their fury,</L>
<L>They did and were intombed in the deepe.</L>
<L>Except some two the surges washt a shore</L>
<L>Prince <HI>Charles</HI> being one, who on <HI>Lorriques</HI> backe</L>
<L>Hung w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>h claspt hands, that neuer could vnfold,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why not aswell as he <HI>Lorrique</HI> doth liue,</L>
<L>Or how was he found claspt vpon his backe</L>
<L>Except he had had life to fold his hands.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, your Highnes errs in that conceite,</L>
<L>For men that dye by drowning, in their death,</L>
<L>Hold surely what they claspe, while they haue breath.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well he held mee, and sunke me too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile witnes, when I had recouerd him</L>
<L>The Princes head being split against a Rocke</L>
<L>Past all recouer, <HI>Lorrique</HI> in desperate rage,</L>
<L>Sought sundry meanes to spoyle his new-gain'd; life▪</L>
<L>Exclay minge for his master: cursing heauen,</L>
<L>For being vniust to you, though not to him,</L>
<L>For robbing you of comfort in your son</L>
<L>Oh gratious Lady sayd this grieued man</L>
<L>Could I but worke a meanes to cald me her griefe.</L>
<L>Some reasonable course to keepe blacke care</L>
<L>From her white bosome; I were happy then;</L>
<L><PB REF="30"/>
But knowing this, her heart will sinke with woe</L>
<L>And I, am rankt with miserablest men,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>I gods my witnesse, these were my laments,</L>
<L>Till <HI>Hoffman</HI> being as willing, as my selfe;</L>
<L>Did for his loue to you, that pittied him.</L>
<L>Take on him to be cald by your sons name,</L>
<L>Which now he must refuse except your Grace</L>
<L>Attept his seruice in Prince <HI>Otho's</HI> place,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>If this that you protest be true, your care</L>
<L>Was like a long reprieue, the date worne out;</L>
<L>The execution of my woe is come,</L>
<L>And I must suffer it with patience:</L>
<L>Where haue you layd the body of my son?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Within the chappell of an hermitage,</L>
<L>Some halfe a myle hence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile build mee there a Cell,</L>
<L>Made like a tombe, till death, therein ile dwell:</L>
<L>Yet for thy wrongs yong man attend my words</L>
<L>Snce neyther <HI>Ferdinand,</HI> nor <HI>Saxony,</HI></L>
<L>Haue any heires, to sway their seuerall states;</L>
<L>Ile worke what lies in <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e to make thee Duke,</L>
<L>And since thou art accepted for my son,</L>
<L>Attempting it onely to doe me good</L>
<L>I here adopt thee: myne christen thee <HI>Otho,</HI></L>
<L>Mine eyes are now the font, the water teares,</L>
<L>That doe baptize thee in thy borrowed name.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thanke your Highnes, and of iust heauen craue</L>
<L>The ground I wrong you in, may turne my graue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lights to our chamber, now our feares are past,</L>
<L>What we long doubted, is prou'd true at last.</L>
<L>Attend vs sonne.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nit Martha and Lorrique</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee'l wait vpon your Grace.</L>
<L>Son, this is somewhat, this will beare the eyes</L>
<L>Of the rude vulgar, but this serues not me;</L>
<L>Dukedomes I will haue them my sword shall win,</L>
<L><PB REF="31"/>
If any interposer crosse my will,</L>
<L>But new made mother, ther's another fire</L>
<L>Burnes in this liuer lust, and hot desire,</L>
<L>which you must quench; must? I and shall; I know</L>
<L>Women will like how euer they say noe;</L>
<L>And since my heart is knit vnto her eyes</L>
<L>If she, being sanctimonious, hate my <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uit,</L>
<L>In loue this course ile take, if she denie;</L>
<L>Force her: true, soe: <HI>si non blanditijs, vi.</HI></L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus quintus.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Saxony, Rodorique, Mathias: seuerally.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Haue you not found her yet?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sax.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not I,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then I beleeeue borne by her fits of rage</L>
<L>She ha's done violence to her bright same,</L>
<L>And falne vpon the bosome of the Balt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sax.</SPEAKER>
<L>What reason leads yee to beleeue it, son?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>I did perceiue her some halfe houre since</L>
<L>Clambring vpon the steepenes of the rocke,</L>
<L>But whether vp or downe I could not guesse</L>
<L>By reason of the distance.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Lucibella with rich clothes,</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stand aside, she comes, let her not scape vs now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sax.</SPEAKER>
<L>What has shee got apparrell? I and rich,</L>
<L>Poore soule, shee in her idle lunacy</L>
<L>Hath tooke it from some house where t'will be mist.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lets circle her about, least spying vs</L>
<L>she run away with wonted nimblenesse,</L>
<L><PB REF="31"/>
Fayrest well met.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well ouertaken sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sax.</SPEAKER>
<L>What haue ye here?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>And you too heartely.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod</SPEAKER>
<L>I am sure you know.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why that's well, I like that, that you are well
and you, and you: god buye.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sax.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, nay you must not goe, wee'l hold you now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why that's well, done, Pray come, see my house</L>
<L>I haue a fine house now, and goodly knacks</L>
<L>And gay apparrell; looke ye here, this is braue;</L>
<L>And two leane porters staru'd for lacke of meat,</L>
<L>Pray let goe minearmes, looke here they bee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Om.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh horrid sight!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, neuer start I pray; is it not like I keepe</L>
<L>A princely house, when I haue such fat porters at my gate;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sax:</SPEAKER>
<L>What should this meane? why in this wood</L>
<L>So thicke, so solitary, and remote</L>
<L>From common road of men, should these hang thus▪</L>
<L>Brother your Hermitage is not far hence,</L>
<L>When knew you any execution here?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L>I neuer knew any, and these bones are greene,</L>
<L>This lesse anatomy hath not hung long</L>
<L>The bigger, by the mosse and drynes seemes</L>
<L>Of more coutinuance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat</SPEAKER>
<L>What's on there heads?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>why golden Crownes, my porters shall bee Kings▪</L>
<L>And hide there barebones with these gay weeds.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sarx.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe remember the Admirall</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoffman,</SPEAKER>
<L>that kept the Iland of Burtholme</L>
<L>Was by the Duke of <HI>Prussia</HI> adiudg'd</L>
<L>To haue his head fear'd with a burning crowne,</L>
<L>And after made a bare Anatomy,</L>
<L>Which by his son was from the gallowes stolue;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc</SPEAKER>
<L>I, that same son of his, but where liues he</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sax.</SPEAKER>
<L>No doubt, he doth possesse some caue hard by.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="32"/>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, goe with me, ile shew you where he dwels,</L>
<L>Or some body; I know not who it is;</L>
<L>Here, looke, looke here, here is a way goes downe,</L>
<L>Downe, downe a downe, hey downe, downe.</L>
<L>I sung that song, while <HI>Lodowicke</HI> sl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pt with me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is some Caue, let's boldly enter in,</L>
<L>And learne the mistery of that sad sight,</L>
<L>Come Lady, guide vs in, yon know the way.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>True, thats the way, you cannot misse the path;</L>
<L>The way to death and black destruction</L>
<L>Is the wide way; no body is now at home,</L>
<L>Or tarry, peraduenture here comes some will tell you more.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Martha, and Lorrique:</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stand close, this is <HI>Lorrique,</HI> I doe not know the</L>
<L>Lady comes with him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sax.</SPEAKER>
<L>I ha' seene that countenance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stand close, I pray, my heart diuines,</L>
<L>Some strange and horrid act will be reueald.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay that's most true, a fellow with a red cap told me so</L>
<L>And bad me keepe these cloathes, and giue them</L>
<L>To a faire Lady in a mourning gowne;</L>
<L>Let goe my armes; I will not run away</L>
<L>I thanke you now, now you shall see mee stay,</L>
<L>By my troth I will, by my maidenhead I will.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Lorrique</HI> returne into the beaten path,</L>
<L>I ask't thee for a solitary plot,</L>
<L>And thou hast brought me to the dismal'st groue</L>
<L>That euer eye beheld, noe woodnimphes here</L>
<L>Seeke with their agill steps to outstrip the Roe,</L>
<L>Nor doth the sunsucke from the queachy plot</L>
<L>The ranknes and the venom of the Earth</L>
<L>It seemes frequentlesse for the vse of men:</L>
<L>Some basiliskes, or poysonous serpents den!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="32"/>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is indeede an vndelight full walke;</L>
<L>But if I doe not erre in my beleefe,</L>
<L>I thinke the ground, the trees, the rockes, the springs,</L>
<L>Haue since my Princely Master <HI>Charles</HI> his wracke</L>
<L>Appear'd more dismall, then they did before,</L>
<L>I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> memory of his vntimelesse fall.</L>
<L>For hereabouts, hereabouts the place,</L>
<L>Where his <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ayre body lay deform'd by death</L>
<L>Here <HI>Hoffmans</HI> son, and I enbalm'd him</L>
<L>After we had concluded to de<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>caue</L>
<L>Your sacred person, and Duke <HI>Ferdinand</HI></L>
<L>By causing <HI>Hoffman</HI> to assume his name.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sax.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is very strange.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay tary, you shall heare all the knauery anon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>And where's the Chappell that you layd him in?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'ts an old Chappell, neere the Hermitage:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>But was the Hermet at his buriall?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Noe, <HI>Hoffman</HI> and I onely dig'd the graue</L>
<L>Play'd Priest and Clarke, to keepe his buriall close?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most admirable!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sax.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, pray you peace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas! poore son, the soule of my delights;</L>
<L>Thou in thy end wert rob'd of Funerall rites,</L>
<L>None sung thy requiem, noe friend clos'd thine eyes,</L>
<L>Nor layd the hallowed earth vpon thy lips,</L>
<L>Thou wert not houseled, neither did the bells ring</L>
<L>Blessed peales, nor towle thy funerall knell,</L>
<L>Thou wo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>st to death, as those that sinke to hell;</L>
<L>Where is the apparrell that I bad him weare</L>
<L>Against the force of witches and their spells.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>We buried it with him it was his shroude,</L>
<L>The desert woods noe fitter meanes allowd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thinke he lyes.</L>
<L>Now by my troth, that gentleman smels knaue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweare one thing to me, ere we leaue this place;</L>
<L><PB REF="33"/>
Whether young <HI>Hoffman</HI> did the most he might to saue my son.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>By heauen it seemes hee did, but all was vaine</L>
<L>The flinty rockes had cut his tender scull,</L>
<L>And the rough water wash't away his braine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lyer, lyer, licke dish.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now what woman's this? what men are these?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Apoore mayden mistris, ha's a suite to you,</L>
<L>And 'tis a good suite, very good apparrell.</L>
<L>Loe, heere I come a woing my ding, ding,</L>
<L>Loe, heere we come a suing, my darling,</L>
<L>Loe, heere I come a praying, to biaea, bidea.</L>
<P>How doe you Lady, well I thanke God, will you buy
a barganei pray, i'ts fine apparrell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Run my liues blood, comfort my troubled heart,</L>
<L>That trembles at the sight of this attire:</L>
<L>Lorrique, looke on them, knowest thou not these clothes?</L>
<L>Nor the distracted bringer? prethee speake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ay me, accurst and damn'd; I know them both;</L>
<L>The bringer is the <HI>Austrian Lucibell<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, you say true, I am the very same,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>The apparrell was my Lords, your Princely son's.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is not seawet, if my son were drown'd</L>
<L>Then why thus dry is his apparrell found?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor,</SPEAKER>
<L>O me accurst, o miserable me?</L>
<L>Fall heauen, and hide my shame, gape earth, rise sea,</L>
<L>Swallow, orewhelme me, wherefore should I liue,</L>
<L>The most perfidious wretch that euer breath'd,</L>
<L>And base consenter to my deare Lords death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, looke you heere, do you see these poore staru'd
ghosts; can you tell whose they be?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas! what are they? what are you that seeme</L>
<L>In ciuill habits to hide ruthlesse hearts;</L>
<L><HI>Lorrique,</HI> what are they? what wilt thou attempt?</L>
<L><PB REF="33"/>
Helpe Gentlemen, if yee be Gentlemen,</L>
<L>And stay this fellow from dispayring ill.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>I was ordain'd vnto perdition, stay me not;</L>
<L>For when yee know the mischiefes I haue done,</L>
<L>(at least, consented to, through coward feare)</L>
<L>You would not stop me, if I skipt in quicke</L>
<L>To that blacke, bottomlesse and ruthlesse, gulph,</L>
<L>Where euerlasting sorrowes like linkt chaynes</L>
<L>Fetter the wretched in eternall night.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>what hast thou done?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Knauery I warrant you, tell truth and shame the</L>
<L>Diuell my boy, doe, and thou shalt haue a fine thing by and
by.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sax.</SPEAKER>
<L>I take your Highnes for that reuerend Dutches</L>
<L>Late wife vnto the Duke of <HI>Prussia.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar</SPEAKER>
<L>I am the wretched childlesse widdow sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Princesse heare me, and I will briefely tell</L>
<L>How you came childlesse, you brotherlesse,</L>
<L>You husbandlesse, and fatherlesse, all, all,</L>
<L>Ile tell you, hauing ended, act my fall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, forward;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be it soe, I haue deseru'd a greater cruelty,</L>
<L>To bee kept liuing when I long to dye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I charge thee setting by all circumstance,</L>
<L>Thou vtter what thou knowest: my heart is steele,</L>
<L>Nor can it suffer more then it doth feele.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then thus, Prince <HI>Charles</HI> and I escap't the wracke,</L>
<L>Came safe a shore to this accursed plot,</L>
<L>Where we met <HI>Hoffman,</HI> who vpon yon tree</L>
<L>Preseru'd his fathers bare anatomy,</L>
<L>The biggest of them two were those strong bones</L>
<L>That acted mighty deeds.</L>
<L><HI>Hoffman</HI> the son full of reuenge and hate,</L>
<L>'Gainst euery hand that wrought his fathers hurt,</L>
<L>Yet guilded ore his enuie with faire shewes,</L>
<L>And entertain'd vs with as friendly termes</L>
<L><PB REF="34"/>
As falshood could inuent; and 'tis well knowne▪</L>
<L>Bitter deceit vseth the sweetest speech.</L>
<L>At length he tooke aduantage, bound my Lord,</L>
<L>And in a chayne tyed him to yonder rocke,</L>
<L>While with a burning Crowne he feard in twaine</L>
<L>The purple Veynes, strong sinewes, arteries, uerues,</L>
<L>And euery cartilage about the head,</L>
<L>In which sad torment the mild Prince fell dead.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did <HI>Hoffman</HI> this? and thou conceal'st the deed?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pardon my feare, Dread Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>well, goe on, I am confident to heare all cruelty,</L>
<L>And am resolu'd to act some, if noe hand</L>
<L>Will else attempt the murderers and, but mine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be patient; you will finde associates:</L>
<L>For there are many murderers more behinde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>what did hee with the body of my son?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Buried the slesh, the bones are they that hang</L>
<L>Close by his fathers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let them hang a while</L>
<L>Hope of reuenge in wrath doth make mee smile.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray let him tell the rest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>This acted, <HI>Hoffman</HI> forc't me to conceale</L>
<L>The murder of my Lord, and threatned more</L>
<L>Then death by many torments, till I swore</L>
<L>To call him <HI>Otho,</HI> and say he was your son▪</L>
<L>I swore and kept my oath.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L>O Heauen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sax.</SPEAKER>
<L>O Diuell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, I pray you peace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thensent he me for you, and you he sent,</L>
<L>Or as I best remember, lead you on</L>
<L>Vnto the Chappell porch, where hee himselfe</L>
<L>Appointed them to stay, and there you know</L>
<L>What hapned in your wrath.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>To me a sleepe,</L>
<L>And to my harmelesse <HI>Lodowick</HI> in my armes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="34"/>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>On on, that deed is writ among the acts of guilt:</L>
<L>A brothers sword a brothers life blood spilt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sax.</SPEAKER>
<L>Proceed, what's next? kild he not <HI>Austria?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ler.</SPEAKER>
<L>He did.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>O villaine did he kill my Father?</L>
<L>And make my brother kill my husband too?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sax.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe forward.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>After all those hated murders</L>
<L>He taught the foolish prince in the disguise</L>
<L>Of a French Doctor to prepare a poyson,</L>
<L>Which was the death of Princely <HI>Ferdinand:</HI></L>
<L>Next plot hee purpos'd your graces death,</L>
<L>And had opposd my strength of my teares,</L>
<L>You had bin murder'd as you lay a sleepe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sax.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let's heare no more, seeke out the hated wretch,</L>
<L>And with due torture let his life be forc'd</L>
<L>From his despised body.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe I pray.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sax.</SPEAKER>
<L>All the Land will helpe,</L>
<L>And each man be a iustice in this act.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, I that neuer knewreuenges power,</L>
<L>Haue entertaind her newly in my brest:</L>
<L>Determine what's to doe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Euen what you will; would I were with my <HI>Lod<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>wick</HI> a sleepe</L>
<L>In the Elizian fieldes, where no feares dwell;</L>
<L>For earth appeares as vile to me as hell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me be Prologue to your scene of wrath,</L>
<L>And as the Romane Cateline resolu'd</L>
<L>His doubtfull followers by exhausting blood</L>
<L>From the liue body, so draw mine, cast mine</L>
<L>Vpon the troubled and offended earth;</L>
<L>Offer blood fit for an infernall sacrifice,</L>
<L>Wine is not powr'd but on celestiall offrings:</L>
<L>Therefore I aduise you</L>
<L>As you hope to thriue in your reuenge, smite me.</L>
<L><PB REF="35"/>
That haue bin pander to this iniury.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou merit'st death indeede.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay iudge him not, let me a little plead in his excuse,</L>
<L>And this one sentence serues; a manaompel'd</L>
<L>To euill acts, cannot be iustly held</L>
<L>A wilfull malefactor; the law still</L>
<L>Lookes vpon the deede, ne're on the will:</L>
<L>Besides although I grant the matter small</L>
<L>And very safe to rayse a multitude,</L>
<L>That by their power might ceaze the m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rderer,</L>
<L>Yet two especiall reasons crosse that course:</L>
<L>First: many hauing notice of our plot,</L>
<L>One babling tongue may vtter out intent,</L>
<L>And <HI>Hoffman</HI> being warn'd is surely arm'd</L>
<L>Hauing the fort and treasure in his powre,</L>
<L>And be his cause more then notorious ill,</L>
<L>He may with gold maintaine it at his will</L>
<L>Scape vs, for no doubt hee's full of sleights:</L>
<L>Besides, Reuenge should haue proportion,</L>
<L>By slye deceit he acted euery wronge,</L>
<L>And by deceit I would haue him intrapt;</L>
<L>Then the re<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>enge were fit, iust, and square,</L>
<L>And t'would more vex him that is all compos'd</L>
<L>Of craft and subtilty to be outstript</L>
<L>In his owne fashion, then a hundred deaths.</L>
<L>Therefore by my aduice pardon <HI>Lorrique</HI></L>
<L>Vpon condition, that he lay some plot</L>
<L>To intercept the other.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Om.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are agreede.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your mercy doth all bounds of hope exceed,</L>
<L>And if you will repose that trust in me,</L>
<L>By all the protestations truth can make,</L>
<L>Before the Sun haue run his mid-dayes course,</L>
<L>I will to morrow! yeeld him to your handes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sax.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shew vs the meanes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="35"/>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>The meanes is in the Dutchesse pollicy.</L>
<L>If she can smooth the murder but a while.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile turn deceit to ouerthrow his fraud.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then with faire words his flatteries e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tertayne,</L>
<L>And when he doth importune you for loue,</L>
<L>Desire him first to shew you the first place,</L>
<L>Where he beheld Prince <HI>Charles</HI> after the wracke</L>
<L>Say you haue earnestly entreated me,</L>
<L>But I haue lead you in a labyrinth</L>
<L>Of noe effect; he full of heate and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ust,</L>
<L>Glad of occasion will no doubt alone</L>
<L>Conduct you to this fatall horrid caue,</L>
<L>Thi king by force, or fayre meanes, to attaine</L>
<L>His false hearts longing, and your honors stayne;</L>
<L>But being in the height of his base pride,</L>
<L>The Duke, the Hermet, <HI>Lodowick</HI> and my selfe,</L>
<L>Will change his pleasures into wretched</L>
<L>And redeemelesle misery.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sax.</SPEAKER>
<L>The plot is good, Madam, are you agreed?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>To any thing how euer desperate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>I but by your leaue, Lady, and Lords all, what if</L>
<L>This knaue that has bin, play the knaue still,</L>
<L>And tell tales out of schoole; how then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know not what to sweare by; but noe soule</L>
<L>Longs for the sight of endlesse happinesse,</L>
<L>With more desire, then mine thirsts for his death:</L>
<L>By all the gods that shall giue ill men li<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e,</L>
<L>I am resolu'd chiefe agent in his end.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>We credit thee, ioyne hands, and ring him round,</L>
<L>Kneele, on his head lay our right hands, and sweare</L>
<L>Vengeance against <HI>Hoffman.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Om.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vengeance, vengeance, fall</L>
<L>On him, or suddaine death vpon vs all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sax</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, part, we to the caue,</L>
<L>You to the Court:</L>
<L>Iustice dig murthers graue.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="36"/>
Exit Lorrique and Martha.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, Ile come, my wits are mine agen</L>
<L>Now faith growes firme to punish faithlesse men.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Hoffman, and all the traine that attended
the Dutchesse first.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not to be found? hell which way is she gon?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lord.</SPEAKER>
<L>Her Highnes charg'd vs to call you her son,</L>
<L>The mistery we know not, but we know,</L>
<L>You are not Princely <HI>Otho</HI> of Luningberg.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Noe matter what I am; tell me the way she went</L>
<L>With that <HI>Lorrique;</HI> speake, or by heauen</L>
<L>Hell shall receiue you all.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Martha, and Lorrique.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lord.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be not in rag'd she comes,</L>
<L>And with her comes trusty <HI>Lorrique.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, I fear'd you, and my heart was sicke,</L>
<L>With doubt some ouer-desperate accident</L>
<L>Had drawne you to the melancholy pathes,</L>
<L>That lye within the verge of this rough scarre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your doubt was but an Embrio; I indeed</L>
<L>Desir'd <HI>Lorrique</HI> to bring me to the place</L>
<L>Where you beheld the shipwracke of my son;</L>
<L>And he hath led me vp and downe the wood,</L>
<L>But neuer brought me to the fatall beach,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>It were not fit you should see the sad place,</L>
<L>That still seemes dismall since the Princes death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lord.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dead? is our soueraigne Lord the Prince dead?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Inquire no more of that, I will anon</L>
<L>Resolue you of his fate, this time for beare,</L>
<L>Esteeme this gentleman your Lord and Prince.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="36"/>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee hold him soe, sith you command vs so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you goe forward, Madam?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Willingly, soe you will promise mee to walke to morrow</L>
<L>And see the Earth that gently did receiue</L>
<L>My sons wrack't body from the churlish fome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile wayt vpon your Grace, set forward there,</L>
<L>Trickes, and deuices! longings! well 'tis good:</L>
<L>Ile swim to my desires, through seas of blood.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fox you'l be taken, hunter you are falne</L>
<L>Into the pit you dig'd; I laught to see</L>
<L>How I out-strip the Prince of villany.</L>
<L><HI>Hoffman</HI> for me told such a smoothing tale,</L>
<L>That had not this strange accident befalne</L>
<L>In finding of the caue; I had bin held</L>
<L>More d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ere then euer, in the Dutchesse eyes:</L>
<L>But now shee'l hold me hard, what ere she say,</L>
<L>Yet is her word past that shee'l pardon me,</L>
<L>And I haue wealth hoor'd vp which ile beare</L>
<L>To some strange place: rich men liue any where.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Hoffman.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>What? are you gadding sir? what mooues your flight?</L>
<L>Coyne not excuses in your crouching come,</L>
<L>What cause haue you to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ie and seeke strange hoords</L>
<L>For your wealth gotten by my liberall gift?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>And my desert, my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well be it your desert;</L>
<L>But what's the cause you'l flye this country?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>As I liue, my Lord, I haue noe such intent▪</L>
<L>But with your leaue, I was debating things,</L>
<L>As if it should chaunce thus, and thus, why then</L>
<L>'Twere better be far of, but otherwise</L>
<L>My loue and life, low at your seruice lye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are a villaine damn'd as low as hell;</L>
<L>An hypocrite, a fawning hypocrite:</L>
<L><PB REF="37"/>
I know thy heart, come Spaniell vp, arise,</L>
<L>And thinke not with your antickes and your lies</L>
<L>To goe beyond mee, you haue play'd the slaue,</L>
<L>Betrayd me to the Datchesse, told her all,</L>
<L>Disappoynting all my hopes with your base tongue,</L>
<L>Ore<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>rn'd the height of my intendments,</L>
<L>For which ile hurle thee from my mountaine wracke,</L>
<L>Into the lowest Cauerne of pale death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas my Lord for beare, let me be heard.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou hast betrayd me, therefore neuer talke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>By heauen—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>O hell! why should'st thou thinke on heauen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay, and beleeue me, thinke you I am mad,</L>
<L>Soe great a foe to my owne happy chaunce,</L>
<L>When things are sorted to so good an end,</L>
<L>That all is hid, and we held in regard:</L>
<L>After such horrid, and perfidious acts,</L>
<L>Now to betray my selfe; be reasonable,</L>
<L>And thinke how shallow such an act would seeme</L>
<L>In me, chiefe agent in so many ills.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou hast a tong<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e as glib and smooth to lyes,</L>
<L>As full of false inuentions, and base fraud,</L>
<L>As prone to circumuent beleeuing soules,</L>
<L>As euer heretique or traytor vsd,</L>
<L>Whose speeches are as hony, their acts gall,</L>
<L>Their words rayse vp, but their hands ruine all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>By vertues glorious soule.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Blasphemer peace, sweare not by that thou hat'st;</L>
<L>Vertue, and thou haue no more sympathie,</L>
<L>Then day with night, Heauen with Hell.</L>
<L>Thou knowest, I know thy Villanyes excell</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why then by vil<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>any, by blood, by sleightes,</L>
<L>By all the horrours tortures can present,</L>
<L>By Hell, and by reuenges purple hand</L>
<L>The Dutchesse had no conference with me,</L>
<L><PB REF="37"/>
But onely a desire to see the place</L>
<L>That first receiu'd her son, whom she beleeues</L>
<L>The vnrelenting waues and flinty rocks,</L>
<L>Had seuer'd from sweet life after the wracke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>May I beleeue thee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Haue I fayld you yet?</L>
<L>Measure my former acts, and you shall find</L>
<L>My foule allyed to yours, wholly estrang'd</L>
<L>From all I <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uer lou'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Noe more, haue done.</L>
<L>Tha'st won me to continue thee my friend;</L>
<L>But I can tell thee somewhat troubles me,</L>
<L>Some dreadfull misaduenture my soule doubts,</L>
<L>And I conceiue it with noe common thought,</L>
<L>But a most potent apprehension;</L>
<L>For it confounds imaginary sence,</L>
<L>Sometimes inflames my blood, another while</L>
<L>'Nums all the Currents that should comfort life,</L>
<L>And I remayne as 'twere a senceles stone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, come, I know the cause, you are in loue,</L>
<L>And to be soe, is to be any thing.</L>
<L>Doe you not loue the Dutchesse?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, I doe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why there's the matter, then, be ruld by me,</L>
<L>To morrow morning she desires to see</L>
<L>The shore, that first receiu'd her sea-wrackt son,</L>
<L>And to be vnaccompained she loues;</L>
<L>Except some one or two, you and I:</L>
<L>Now when you haue her neare your dismal I caue,</L>
<L>Force her, I dot man, make no scruple do't,</L>
<L>Else you shall neuer win her to your bed:</L>
<L>Doe a mans part, please her before she goe,</L>
<L>Or if you see, that she turnes violent,</L>
<L>Shut her perpetuall prisoner in that den;</L>
<L>Make her a Philomel, proue Tereus:</L>
<L>Do't, neuer feare it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="38"/>
<SPEAKER>Hoff,</SPEAKER>
<L>Why she will be mist.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>By whom? by fooles▪ grosse, dull, thicke sighted fooles,</L>
<L>whom euery mist can blinde, I'le sway them all,</L>
<L>With exclamation that the grieued Dutchesse</L>
<L>when she beheld the sea that drownd her son,</L>
<L>S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ood for a while like weeping <HI>Niobe,</HI></L>
<L>As if she had bin stone: and when we striu'd</L>
<L>With mi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>de perswasions to make lesse her woe</L>
<L>She madd<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r then the wife of <HI>Athamas</HI></L>
<L>Leap't suddenly into the troubled sea,</L>
<L>Whose surges greedy of soe rich a prey,</L>
<L>Swallowed her vp, while we in vaine exclaym'd</L>
<L>'Gainst Heauen and hell, 'gainst fortune and her fate,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh my good vi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>laine! how I hug thy plots,</L>
<L>This shall be done, shee's mine: run swi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t slow houres,</L>
<L>Make a short night hasten on day apace,</L>
<L>Rough armes waxe soft soft beauty to embrace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why soe, now your feare will q<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ickly end,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou wilt not talke of this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will I be hang'd?</L>
<L>Nee're take me for a blab, you'l finde me none.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue a nother secret, but—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come what ist? come, this brest is yours,</L>
<L>My heart's your treasury.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou must be secret, 'tis a thing of weight
concernes thee neere.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Were it as neere as life, come, pray speake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hearke in thine eare, I would not haue the ayre</L>
<L>Be priuy to this purpose, wilt thou sweare?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>What? to bee secret? if the least iot I tell</L>
<L>Let all my hopes sinke suddenly to hell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou hast thy wish, downe villaine, keepe this close.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor,</SPEAKER>
<L>Vnthankefull murtherer, is this my meede?</L>
<L>Oh slaue, tha'st kild thy heart in wounding mine,</L>
<L>This is my day, to morrow shall be thine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe foole; now thou art dead, I neede not feare.</L>
<L><PB REF="38"/>
Yet as thou wert my seruant iust and true,</L>
<L>Ile hide thee in the ditch: giue dogs there due,</L>
<L>He that will proue a mercenary slaue</L>
<L>To murder, seldome findes soe good a graue,</L>
<L>Hee's gone, I can now spare him, <HI>Lorrique</HI> farewell;</L>
<L>Commend me to our friends thou meet'st in hell:</L>
<L>Next plot for <HI>Mathias</HI> and old <HI>Saxony,</HI></L>
<L>There ends shall finish our blacke tragedy.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Saxony, and Mathias.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sax.</SPEAKER>
<L>How little care had we to let her 'scape,</L>
<L>Especially on this so needfull time,</L>
<L>When we are vowed to wayt vpon reuenge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Noe doubt our vncles care will keepe her safe,</L>
<L>Nor is she in her fits so violent</L>
<L>As she was wont, looke where my</L>
<L>Vncle comes, sustayning with one hand</L>
<L>A dying man, and one the other side,</L>
<L>Fayre <HI>Lucibell</HI> supports the fainting body.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Rodorique, and Lucibell leading Lorrique.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Looke you here, you maruai'ld why I went,</L>
<L>Why this man drew me vnto him, can you helpe</L>
<L>Him now. <HI>Hoffman</HI> has hought him too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Saz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Brother who ist you bring thus ashe pale;</L>
<L>I'st not <HI>Lorrique;</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am, and 'tis in vayne to striue for longer hope.</L>
<L>I cannot, onely be prouident; I greatly feare</L>
<L>The murdrous traytor out of meere suspect</L>
<L>Will plot some stra<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>agem against the life</L>
<L>Of the chast Dutchesse, help her what you can,</L>
<L>Against the violence of that wicked man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod</SPEAKER>
<L>Hast thou not told him, what we doe intend?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="39"/>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Noe, as heauen help mee in my wretched end,</L>
<L>Be confident of that, now I must fall</L>
<L>Neuer agen to rise, you know his wrongs:</L>
<L>Be carefull Princes to reuenge them all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc,</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, farewell fellow, thou art now paid home</L>
<L>For all thy counce<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ling in knauery,</L>
<L>Good Lord! what very fooles are very knaues!</L>
<L>There cunning bodies often want due graues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sax.</SPEAKER>
<L>Son, daughter, brother, follow my aduice,</L>
<L>Let vs noe longer keepe this hatefull plot,</L>
<L>Least we be circumuented.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L>True, 'tis to put on open armes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis now too late, we are beset</L>
<L>With souldiers, we must fight, and since it must be;</L>
<L>Let's to't valiantly.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Dutchesse: Lord, with souldiers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lord.</SPEAKER>
<L>Princes prepare not to resist your foes,</L>
<L>Wee are as firme as life vnto your blood.</L>
<L>The Dutchesse <HI>Martha</HI> greetes old <HI>Saxony,</HI></L>
<L>Prince <HI>Mathias, Rodorick,</HI> and fayre <HI>Lucibell:</HI></L>
<L>To me she hath discouer'd the damnd plots</L>
<L>Of that perfidious <HI>Hoffman,</HI> and hath sent</L>
<L>These armed souldiers, to attend on you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sax.</SPEAKER>
<L>We thanke her Highnes, but we thinke in vaine</L>
<L>Both you and we attend; <HI>Lorrique</HI> lyes slaine</L>
<L>By <HI>Hoffmans</HI> slye suspition; best be ioyn'd</L>
<L>To appr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hend him publiquely.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lord.</SPEAKER>
<L>There is no need, our Dutchesse hath apparrel'd</L>
<L>Her speech in a greene liuery,</L>
<L>She salutes him faire, but her heart</L>
<L>Like his actions, is attir'd</L>
<L>In red, and blew, and sable ornaments.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sax.</SPEAKER>
<L>But 'tell vs where they are?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lord,</SPEAKER>
<L>At hand she comes, with him alone her plot is,</L>
<L><PB REF="39"/>She comes in happy time for all your good.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat</SPEAKER>
<L>Cease words, vse deedes</L>
<L>Reuenge drawes nigh.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sax.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come set his body like a scarcrow,</L>
<L>This bush shro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d you, this you,</L>
<L>Stand close true souldiers, for reuenge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>I: doe, doe, doe, I pray you heartely doe,
stand close.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Hoffman and Dutchesse.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>I wonder much why you aske me for <HI>Lorrique,</HI></L>
<L>What is Lorrique to you, or what to me?</L>
<L>I tell you he is damn'd, enquire no more,</L>
<L>His name <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s hatefuller then death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heauen! what alterations these!</L>
<L>Can I beleeue you loue mee as you swore,</L>
<L>When you are so inconstant to your friend?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>He is noe friend of mine whom you affect,</L>
<L>Pardon me Madam, such a fury raignes</L>
<L>Ouer my boyling blood, that I enuy</L>
<L>Any one on whom you cast anamorous eye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>What growne so louing? marry heauen defend,</L>
<L>Wee shall deceiue you if you dote on vs,</L>
<L>Fot I haue sworne to lead a widdowes life,</L>
<L>And neuer more to be tearm'd married wife.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, but you must.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Must? vse not force, I pray.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yeild to my loue, and then with meekest word<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>And the most humble actions, ile intreat</L>
<L>Your sacred beauty; deny me? ile turne fire,</L>
<L>More wild then wrath, come then agree,</L>
<L>If not to marry, yet in vnseene sports</L>
<L>To quench these Lawlesse heates that burne in me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>What my adopted son become my louer?</L>
<L>And make a want on minion of his mother?</L>
<L>Now fie vpon you fie y'are too obsceane</L>
<L><PB REF="40"/>
If like your words, your thoughts appeare vncleane.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>By heauen I doe not ieast, goe to, belieue me,</L>
<L>'Tis well you laugh; smile on, I like this:</L>
<L>Say, will you yeild?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>At the first? fie noe.</L>
<L>That were an abiect course, but let vs walke</L>
<L>Into some couert, there are pretty caues,</L>
<L>Lucky to louers suites, for Virgil sings;</L>
<L>That Dido being driuen by a sharpe storme</L>
<L>Into a Lybian caue, was there intic'd</L>
<L>By siluer-tongu'd Aeneas to affect;</L>
<L>And should you serue me soe, I were vndone,</L>
<L>Disgrac'd in <HI>Germany</HI> by euery Boore,</L>
<L>Who in their rymes woud iest at <HI>Marthas</HI> name</L>
<L>Calling her mynion to her cozen son.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fayrer then Dido, or loues amorous Queene;</L>
<L>I know a caue, where in the bright dayes eyes</L>
<L>Look't neuer but a skance through a small creeke,</L>
<L>Or little cranny of the fretted scarre;</L>
<L>There I haue sometimes liu'd, there are fit seates,</L>
<L>To sit and chat, and coll, and kiffe, and steale</L>
<L>Loues hidd<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n pleasures, come, are you disposd</L>
<L>To venter entrance? if yo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> be, assay,</L>
<L>'Tis death to quicke desire, vse no delay.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vertue and modesty bids me say noe,</L>
<L>Yet trust me <HI>Hoffman</HI> tha'rt so sweet a man,</L>
<L>And so belou'd of me, that I must goe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am crown'd the King of pleasure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hatefull slaue, thou goest to meete destruction
in the caue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>S'death who stands here?</L>
<L>What's that? <HI>Lorriques</HI> pale ghost?</L>
<L>I am amaz'd: nay slaue stand of:</L>
<L>Thy weapons sure, the prize is ours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come forth deere friends, murder is in our powers</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sax.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yeild thee, base son of shame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="40"/>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now whats here? am I betrayd?</L>
<L>By dotage, by the falshood of a face?</L>
<L>Oh wretched foole falne by a womans hand</L>
<L>From high reuenges spheare, the blisse of soules.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sax.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cut out the murtherers tongue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>What doe you meane?</L>
<L>Whom haue I murder'd; wherefore bind yee me;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are Iustices to punish thy bare bones,</L>
<L>Looke with thy blood-shed eyes on these bare bones,</L>
<L>And tell me that which dead Lorrique confest</L>
<L>Who ist thou villained that least? who wast?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why Otho thy sons, and that's my fathers by him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>O mercil<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sse and cruell murtherer</L>
<L>To leaue me childl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>And mee husbandlesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Me brotherlesse. oh smooth tongu'd hypocrite</L>
<L>How thou didst draw me to my brothers death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sax.</SPEAKER>
<L>Talke noe more to him, he seekes dignity,</L>
<L>Reason he should receaue his desperate hire,</L>
<L>And weare his crowne made flaming hot with fire:</L>
<L>Bring forth the burning crowne there.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter a Lord with the Crowne</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff,</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe old dog, thou helpst to worry my dead Father</L>
<L>And must thou kill me too? 'tis well, 'tis fit,</L>
<L>I that had sworne vnto my fathers soule</L>
<L>To be reueng'd on <HI>Austria, Saxony,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Prussia, Luningberg,</HI> and all there heires:</L>
<L>Had prosper'd in the downefall of some fiue;</L>
<L>Had onely three to offer to the fiends,</L>
<L>And then must fall in loue; oh wretched eyes</L>
<L>That haue betray'd my heart; bee you accurst;</L>
<L>And as the melting drops run from my brows,</L>
<L>Soe fall they on the strings that guide your heart</L>
<L>Whereby their oylye heat may cracke them first,</L>
<L>I soe, boyle on thou foolish idle braine,</L>
<L>For giuing entertainement to loues thoughts.</L>
<L><PB REF="41"/>
A man resolu'd in blood, bound by a vow</L>
<L>For noe lesse vengeance, then his fathers death,</L>
<L>Yet become amorous of his foes wife!</L>
<L>Oh sin against all conceit! worthy this shame</L>
<L>And all the tortures that the world can name.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Call vpon heauen, base wretch, thinke on thy soule.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>In charity and prayer</L>
<L>To no purpose without charity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sax.</SPEAKER>
<L>We pardon thee, and pray for thy soules health.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Soe doe not I for yours, nor pardon you;</L>
<L>You kild my father, my most warlike father,</L>
<L>Thus as you deale by me, you did by him;</L>
<L>But I deserue it that haue slackt reuenge</L>
<L>Through fickle beauty, and a womans fraud;</L>
<L>But Hell the hope of all dispayring men,</L>
<L>That wring the poore, and eate the people vp,</L>
<L>As greedy beasts the haruest of their spring:</L>
<L>That Hell, where cowards haue their seats prepar'd▪</L>
<L>And barbarous asses, such as haue rob'd souldrers of</L>
<L>Reward, and punish true desert with scorned death.</L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
<PB REF="41"/>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

