<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2005-10-24</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Elspeth Healey</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Checked for TYPE="book". Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, etc.). Checked for signatures. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, and UNCLEARs. Corrected ** $s of **. Converted __ $s to GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc". Checked spacing of foreign GAPs. Checked for EPIGRAPHs and ARGUMENTs. Checked for startqs, endqs, oes, q;s, and Qs. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Checked for CLOSERs, TRAILERs, and BYLINEs. Sample: ** minutes. Proofing: ** minutes. Tag review and corrections: ** minutes. DONE.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A19877">
<STC T="S">6303</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99844957</BIBNO>
<VID>9816</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT>
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>THE IVST ITALIAN.</P>
<P>Lately presented in the priuate house at Blacke Friers </P>
<P> By his Maiesties Seruants.</P>
<P>LONDON, ¶Printed by <HI>Thomas Harper</HI> for <HI>Iohn Waterson,</HI> and are to be sold at the signe of the Crowne, in Paules Churchyard. 1630.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>TO THE RIGHT Honourable, The Earle of <HI>DORSET,</HI> &amp;c.</HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>My Lord,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">T</SEG>HE vnciuill ignorance of the People, had depriu'd this hum∣ble worke of life; but that your Lordships approbation, stept in, to succour it. Those many that came with resolution to dispraise (knowing your Lordships iudgement, to be powerfull, aboue their malice) were eyther corre∣cted to an vnderstanding, or modesty: And this large benefit, hath betray'd your Lordship to a De∣dication. I am bold to beleeue, fancies of this com∣posure, haue beene nobly entertayn'd, by the most knowing Princes of the World: The ignorance,
<PB REF="3"/>
that begets the change in this our age, it may become your Lordships example, to correct, mee to lament; if so tame a passion, can possesse a Poet, and one, ex∣alted with a hope to be receiu'd</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Your Lordships humble Seruant, <HI>WILLIAM D'AVENANT.</HI></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="encomium">
<PB REF="3" MS="y"/>
<HEAD>To my Friend M. D'AVENANT, on his legitimate Poeme.</HEAD>
<L>EVen so the silly <HI>Midas</HI> iudg'd of old</L>
<L>Twixt <HI>Pan</HI> and great <HI>Apollo.</HI> As this bold</L>
<L>Herd, of his race, that th'untun'd Pipe admire,</L>
<L>And heare thy straynes, as the dull Asse the Lyre.</L>
<L>What wonder then, if thou the lawfull Son</L>
<L>Of <HI>Phaebus,</HI> taste what was to him begun.</L>
<L>Hence, giddy fooles; run to the noyse they make</L>
<L>At <HI>Paris</HI>-garden; or your selues betake</L>
<L>To the new Motion, the fine Puppet playes,</L>
<L>And there adore. Commend the learned layes</L>
<L>That make a din about the streets, or els</L>
<L>Extoll the Iewes-trumpe, or the morris bells.</L>
<L>These, your great heads may manage. Only let</L>
<L>The wiser few, (whose blessed eares haue met</L>
<L>The harmony that all the Muses make,</L>
<L>And from those heauenly sounds assurance take,</L>
<L>That thou sing'st the same tunes) admitted be</L>
<L>To thy Seraphyck musicke, and set free</L>
<L>To entertayne their soules in that high quire,</L>
<L>Which, not weake fooles, but such as know, admire.</L>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Will. Hopkins.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="encomium">
<PB REF="4"/>
<HEAD>To my worthy Friend, M. D'AVENANT, Vpon his Excellent Play, <HI>The Iust Italian.</HI></HEAD>
<L>ILe not misspend in prayse, the narrow roome</L>
<L>I borrow in this leafe; the Garlands bloome</L>
<L>From thine owne seedes, that crowne each glorious page</L>
<L>Of thy triumphant worke; the sullen Age</L>
<L>Requires a Satyre. What starre guides the soule</L>
<L>Of these our froward times, that dare controule,</L>
<L>Yet dare not learne to iudge? When didst thou flie</L>
<L>From hence, cleare, candid Ingenuity?</L>
<L>I haue beheld, when pearchd on the smooth brow</L>
<L>Of a fayre modest troope, thou didst allow</L>
<L>Applause to slighter workes; but then the weake</L>
<L>Spectator, gaue the knowing leaue to speake.</L>
<L>Now noyse preuayles, and he is taxd for drowth</L>
<L>Of wit, that with the crie, spends not his mouth.</L>
<L>Yet aske him, reason why he did not like;</L>
<L>Him, why he did; their ignorance will strike</L>
<L>Thy soule with scorne, and Pity: marke the places</L>
<L>Prouoke their smiles, frownes, or distorted faces,</L>
<L>When, they admire, nod, shake the head: they'le be</L>
<L>A scene of myrth, a double Comedie.</L>
<L>But thy strong fancies (raptures of the brayne,</L>
<L>Drest in Poetique flames) they entertayne</L>
<L>As a bold, impious reach; for they'l still slight</L>
<L>All that exceeds Red Bull, and Cockepit flight.</L>
<L><PB REF="4"/>These are the men in crowded heapes that throng</L>
<L>To that adulterate stage, where not a tong</L>
<L>Of th'untun'd Kennell, can a line repeat</L>
<L>Of serious sense: but like lips, meet like meat;</L>
<L>Whilst the true brood of Actors, that alone</L>
<L>Keepe naturall vnstrayn'd Action in her throne</L>
<L>Behold their Benches bare, though they rehearse</L>
<L>The tearser <HI>Beaumonts</HI> or great <HI>Iohnsons</HI> verse.</L>
<L>Repine not Thou then, since this churlish fate</L>
<L>Rules not the stage alone; perhaps the State</L>
<L>Hath felt this rancour, where men great and good,</L>
<L>Haue by the Rabble beeene misunderstood.</L>
<L>So was thy Play; whose cleere, yet lofty strayne,</L>
<L>Wisemen, that gouerne Fate, shall entertayne.</L>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Tho. Carew.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dramatis personae">
<PB REF="5"/>
<HEAD>The Persons presented.</HEAD>
<LIST>
<ITEM><HI>Altamont</HI> The iust Italian.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Florello</HI> A cast soldier his brother.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Meru<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lle</HI> Friend to <HI>Altamont.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Sciolto</HI> A yong Florentine.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Rossa Molard</HI> Companions to <HI>Florello:</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Niente</HI> Vsher to <HI>Altamonts</HI> wife.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Dandol<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> A Count of <HI>Milaine.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Stoccata Punto</HI> His Champions.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Alteza</HI> Wife to <HI>Altamont.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Charintha</HI> Her sister.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Sc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>perta</HI> Sister vnto <HI>Altamont.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Besognia</HI> Woman to <HI>Alteza:</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Mute<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, &amp;c.</HI> </ITEM>
</LIST>
<P><HI>The Scene</HI> Florence.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="play">
<PB REF="5"/>
<HEAD>THE IVST ITALIAN.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Act the first.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scene the first.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Meruolle, Altamont.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meruolle.</SPEAKER>
<L><SEG REND="decorInit">T</SEG>His puzles my beliefe: the sickly Moone</L>
<L>Hath not yet twice expir'd her vsuall <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></L>
<L>Since you did mingle Soules, and can <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></L>
<L>That she so soone recoyles from grac<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Harmonious quiet of your bed?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Deare</L>
<L><HI>Meruolle</HI> she is lost: As well may I</L>
<L>Collect the scatter'd windes into a bagge,</L>
<L>Or from the watry surface scrape the gilt</L>
<L>Reflections of the Sunne, as bring her heart</L>
<L>Within the quiet list of wiues that will</L>
<L>Obay and loue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meruolle.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can the Duke (her Vnkle)</L>
<L>Giue an encouragement to her reuolt,</L>
<L>Maintaine the females Charter 'gainst the male?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Him, and his supreame title she still <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></L>
<L>To iustifie the glory of her birth,</L>
<L>And then recites the Vilages and wealth,</L>
<L>She brought to me for dowre, in parallell</L>
<L>With what I formerly possess'd, she doth</L>
<L><PB REF="6"/>Affront my memorie with stories of</L>
<L>My leane and niggard fate, and vrging then</L>
<L>Her vast supplies, doeth challenge leaue to call</L>
<L>Her pride and rigour iust.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meruolle.</SPEAKER>
<L>This griefe is of</L>
<L>Sad quality!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>The heart hangs heauie on</L>
<L>The strings, when it alone containes the cause</L>
<L>And knowledge of its weight: for troubled windes</L>
<L>In their dispersion loose their strength; so griefes,</L>
<L>Whilst th'are reueal'd, diminish from themselues.</L>
<L>But the calamities, that doe perplex</L>
<L>The Nuptiall bed, are of a propertie</L>
<L>Recluse, and must be hidden euen from friends:</L>
<L>For on such secrets Fame doeth feede with fierce,</L>
<L>And meagre appetite▪ and as swift Fame</L>
<L>Doeth trauaile with them, they increase. So much</L>
<L>Comerce I haue with humane Arts, that I</L>
<L>Can steepe my Gall in my owne teares; and make</L>
<L>That salt which she intended bitter; Shew</L>
<L>Her crime to spring, not from poyson'd mallice,</L>
<L>But from the feminine mistakes of wit:</L>
<L>For moderne Courts now preach, wit doeth reside</L>
<L>In Ladies subtle riots, and their pride.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Florello, Rossa, Molard: in souldierly meane habits.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meruolle.</SPEAKER>
<L>Behold your brother (sir) whose safe returne,</L>
<L>This morne I mention'd to your eare—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy growth</L>
<L>Hath so orereach'd my sight, that I'm estrang'd</L>
<L>To my best blood: and but, thy figure in</L>
<L>My heart I weare (by which my memory's</L>
<L>Enform'd) I should not know I had thee heere—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>I reckon this the chiefe delight I ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e</L>
<L>Receiu'd on Earth. And (sir) your loue is of</L>
<L>Such sou'raigne qualitie, a little soone</L>
<L><PB REF="6"/>Will ouercharge my sense. Giue but a part</L>
<L>To me, the rest conferre vpon my friends—</L>
<L>Who, though in witherd habits, doe deserue,</L>
<L>Societie with Kings: for neuer yet,</L>
<L>Did bolder Souldiers listne to the Drumme.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gentlemen, ye shall enrich my knowledge—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rossa:</SPEAKER>
<L>Noble Signior, vnprofitable loue</L>
<L>Is all our wealth—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Molard.</SPEAKER>
<L>But wee'le contriue our selues</L>
<L>For your best vse.—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'ue sayd, consider them</L>
<L>Within; their weedes are ouergrowne and cheape.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Brother (how ere wise fate may answere it)</L>
<L>Me thinks, these your owne robes are not o'th right</L>
<L>Tyrian dy; nor hath the rich weight of your</L>
<L>Tall Plume the Estridge rob'd of both her winges.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>Euen thus (sir) poore, and with small victory</L>
<L>Am I return'd from our cast Troopes. Our pay</L>
<L>Rests in Areres, and Pisa's lost: But you</L>
<L>(I heare) haue fond a Iewell, that containes</L>
<L>All price and lustre; and you doe weare it</L>
<L>In your bosome: (a noble wife) whose birth</L>
<L>And beautie, are alike vnuallu'd as</L>
<L>Her dowre. This I encounterd on</L>
<L>The Lips of Fame; and I made haste to share</L>
<L>In your successe, and put your bounty to</L>
<L>The test.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Florello, I haue lost my sleepe.</L>
<L>Things differ much from the sinceritie</L>
<L>Of their first growth: Alteza hath forgot</L>
<L>Th'allegiance of a wife, she doth practise</L>
<L>How with her riot to impouerish States,</L>
<L>And by her loftie pride, to iustifie</L>
<L>The immortalitie of flesh: This Theame</L>
<L>Is sad; but I will giue you cause t'expect</L>
<L>The vtmost strength and power of my reliefe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<P>You teach my feeble wants a confidence.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="7"/>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you a while obscure your selfe (for feare</L>
<L>Your pouertie increase her scorne) you shall</L>
<L>Performe a rationall request. Our young</L>
<L>Faire Sister, is conceald for the same cause.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your mention doth anticipate my loue.</L>
<L>Is our faire Sister well?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee doth enioy</L>
<L>Rare beautie, and much health.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meruolle.</SPEAKER>
<P>I heare your wife.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alta.</SPEAKER>
<P>You and your friends, moue backe, and be not seene.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Alteza, Charintha, Niente.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>Trie Signior <HI>Allidore, Antonio's</HI> sonne:</L>
<L>Vtruuio, or the rich Pirracco.</L>
<L>Gritalin, or old Contarini of</L>
<L>Placentia—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Niente.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, your husband hath</L>
<L>Protested 'gainst your credit, euen to these.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alte.</SPEAKER>
<P>Slaue, goe force an answere more delightfull.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Niente.</SPEAKER>
<P>I obay you Madam.
<STAGE>exit.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is't come to this?</L>
<L>I'le be a crooked Spinster first, and with</L>
<L>My spittle and my flaxe procure my bread.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>What is the cause my Princesse thus delight<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>In frownes? Anger sits on her brow like age.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hence, I see thee, and my eyes shrinke into</L>
<L>My skull: the Rauen's not so ominous and blacke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet vrge the cause (my Loue) why your</L>
<L>Defiance is so violent and lowd?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alte.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Millainois shew'd me to day for sale,</L>
<L>Bright and spacious Iewels; but in the darke,</L>
<L>Your pusill malice hath betrai'd my faith,</L>
<L>With Merchants. You haue now my credit wrought</L>
<L>So low, and cheape; I cannot stand deposd</L>
<L>For th'triuiall loane of fortie thousand crownes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="7"/>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would suruay a list of all your wants,</L>
<L>That I may so haue power to hasten the</L>
<L>Redresse: Doe you dislike your properties</L>
<L>Of house, your Vestments, or seruice of your</L>
<L>Table; Giue but a name vnto thy wish?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<P>I would haue my Orchard—pau'd with Aggats.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, and your garden walls raisd high, t'hedge in</L>
<L>Paraquetos, and th'rhetoricall Dawe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altera.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou hast a rude heart, and a blisterd tongue!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charintha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, the first day of your coniunction Sir,</L>
<L>I little thought you would haue vsd her thus.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meruolle.</SPEAKER>
<P>Charintha's become her Sisters Pupill.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I perceiue a masculine itch beneath</L>
<L>Her left eye; she longs to taste man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come Loue,</L>
<L>Be gentle as thy bridall smiles: for by</L>
<L>Thy selfe I sweare, my speech did purpose nought▪</L>
<L>To tempt thy spleene. Lend me thy melting hand!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alte.</SPEAKER>
<L>There— 'tis to reach backe the heart I gaue ye—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>You spirits that secure the propertie</L>
<L>Of humane loue, be still officiall heere!</L>
<L>Why should we not for euer thus remaine,</L>
<L>Incorporate, and conioyn'd. Tis sympathie,</L>
<L>And loue, that giues the world continuance</L>
<L>And life. Each species Loue preserues. Tis loue</L>
<L>That makes th'eternall Wisedome thus forbeare</L>
<L>The silly crimes of dull humanitie:</L>
<L>And suffers vs, like each delighted flie,</L>
<L>To play the triuiall wantons in his eye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>You preach of loue, but your obedience would</L>
<L>More pleasure me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>This argues thy reuolt!</L>
<L>And is a stratagem against nature.</L>
<L>Thou wouldst vsurpe the Charter of the male,</L>
<L>Tis my confession, that thy dowre was vaste</L>
<L>And opulent, and such as may support</L>
<L>Thy titles, and thy birth, with all the pride</L>
<L><PB REF="8"/>And cunning of magnificence. Let my</L>
<L>Sincere phrase instruct thy heart. Reassume</L>
<L>The blushes of thy youth; with timerous</L>
<L>Modestie behaue thy gesture and thy tongue,</L>
<L>And then, thou shalt stand vp exemplary</L>
<L>To all triumphant Courts: the enuie of</L>
<L>The Easterne Queenes: th'Astrologers mistake,</L>
<L>Who shall direct their Opticks vnto thee,</L>
<L>As to a new and vnknowne Starre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza</SPEAKER>
<L>Sister!—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>The small Musitions of the aire (whom Queene<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>With mimicke falconrie doe pearch vpon</L>
<L>Their fists) shall be thy food. Thy maides shall eate</L>
<L>Young Pelicanes, and Squirils hearts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<P>Exc'lent!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy beuiridge shall be propheticke, and</L>
<L>Diuine; for thou shalt drinke that sou'raigne dew,</L>
<L>That hangs vpon the frighted Lillies cheeke,</L>
<L>And brew'd with Syrens teares, such as they shed</L>
<L>In reall obsequies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>O bounteous Sir!—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>The soft entraile o'th Persian worme, th'Ermines</L>
<L>Palefur, shall cloth thy limmes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<P>More precious still!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Those gums and spices which the Arabian bird,</L>
<L>Collects to make her tragicke piles, shall be</L>
<L>Thy winter fewell▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<P>Prettie Sir, proceed!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alta.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou shalt haue Marmasets, and Dwarfs, the male</L>
<L>And female too, to procreate in thy house;</L>
<L>That thy delights may euer be renew'd.</L>
<L>Thy Iewels shall increase, as if the lou'd</L>
<L>Indies were thy Quarrie. Th'Almightie Sunne</L>
<L>Shall rise, and see a nobler day breake from</L>
<L>Thy Cabinet, then yet the illustrious East</L>
<L>Ere knew.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<P>But how will you performe these hopes?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="8"/>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>The miracle, and power, doe both consist,</L>
<L>In my large wealth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<P>Death on my Tribe! Your wealth?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, my sweet Loue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your wealth?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>This iteration</L>
<L>Scarce will delight, if it be negatiue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<P>Canst thou persist in such accursed schisme?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did you not then intend, when you endow'd</L>
<L>Me with your wealth, that I should call it mine?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>By heauen not I. I forfeited the loue</L>
<L>O'th'great Duke (my Vnkle) to marry thee;</L>
<L>That wert a thing shrunke from thy fate, and lost</L>
<L>Vnto the lippes and eyes of men; but yet</L>
<L>In most assured hope, that thou wouldst prooue,</L>
<L>An humble and obedient husband.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Th'art more impudent, then the Basiliske,</L>
<L>Who stares i'th blessed face of man, vntill</L>
<L>He kill him with his eyes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heare Altamont!</L>
<L>For I will giue solemnitie vnto</L>
<L>A vow, that shall for euermore, diuide</L>
<L>Thee from my bed—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meruolle.</SPEAKER>
<L>Deare Madam hold! Each sence</L>
<L>Of mine doth blush, that can perceiue, your wild,</L>
<L>Rebellious wrath. Hath not the Church nam'd him</L>
<L>Your husband, and your Lord?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>M'opinions of</L>
<L>The Church, I'le tell to'th Conclaue, not to you—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is this the helpe, Diuinitie gaue man?</L>
<L>Snuffe the Moone, she burnes dimme. The Spheares are now</L>
<L>Ill tun'd, and aged nature backward reeles.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy anger's vaine. Heere I doe banish thee</L>
<L>My bed: And we will neuer more embrace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<P>Rebellious fiend.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>I now diuide my house:</L>
<L>This side is mine, with the dimensions that</L>
<L><PB REF="9"/>Dependance haue on this square frame: for heere</L>
<L>My familie and I will rule. That side</L>
<L>You, and your meagre ragged traine possesse.</L>
<L>Thou mayst hencefoorth my neighbour, but no more</L>
<L>My husband be. <HI>Charintha,</HI> come away—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must pursue, lest she her anger make</L>
<L>Too lowd, so we inuite the publike scorne.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Alteza, Charintha: Altamont.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meruolle.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is not thy brothers wife a pure tame henne?</L>
<L>How dost thou like her noyse?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>Were she but mine,</L>
<L>I'ld teach her keepe a noyse too after death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meruolle.</SPEAKER>
<P>How so?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'ld strippe her skinne o're her eares and</L>
<L>Make a drumme on't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rossa.</SPEAKER>
<P>She was borne in a storme!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Molard.</SPEAKER>
<P>And begot sure with the Boeswayns whistle.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Meruolle,</HI> you haue nam'd <HI>Charintha,</HI></L>
<L>As a precious Virgine, of nature most</L>
<L>Remisse, a quiet tongue, and such a heart,</L>
<L>As might become an able sacrifice,</L>
<L>T'expiate the whole world?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meruolle.</SPEAKER>
<L>This I esteem'd</L>
<L>My iustice on her merits, but it seemes</L>
<L>Her Sisters documents ore rule her now.</L>
<L>Her dowry is of ample rate, and may</L>
<L>Deserue the chiefe of our Italian youth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<P>What's <HI>Dandalo,</HI> that sues to her for loue?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meruolle.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Dandalo,</HI> the Count of Millaine? A thing</L>
<L>Co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>posd of spicery and starch! Nature</L>
<L>Contriu'd him in her sleepe. If's ignorance</L>
<L>Might answere for his sinnes; he would accompt</L>
<L>Amongst his wealth, the land he has in Heauen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<P>I heard you say, she neuer saw him yet.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meruolle.</SPEAKER>
<L>Neuer Sir: He wooes her by his letters.</L>
<L>She desiring a personall suruay</L>
<L>Ere prosecution of the sute, he sent</L>
<L><PB REF="9" MS="y"/>Her word, he'ld make's addresse by stealth; but we</L>
<L>Expect him not ere'th'birth of the next Moon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will his ariuall be so long delay'd?—</L>
<L>Brother! — How thriues your patience ore your wife?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alta.</SPEAKER>
<L>Some Philosophicke hope remaines: the storme</L>
<L>Can't last, because 'tis still more violent.</L>
<L>Sh'ath tane Caroch for the Pallace, and meanes</L>
<L>Straite to disgrace me to the Duke</L>
<L>By her complaints.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meruolle.</SPEAKER>
<P>Her vaines oreflow with Gall!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Florello,</HI> I desire thou'lt not appeare</L>
<L>Before her eye, vntill thy habit's chang'd.</L>
<L>My present power summes but a thousand crownes,</L>
<L>Which I haue brought, and prostrate to thy vse—</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Giues him a Bagge.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir it is fit your blessings were encreasd;</L>
<L>And that your wife had read your worth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Art betrayes my hopes, or I haue found</L>
<L>A remedy to cure her pride: your helpe</L>
<L><HI>Meruolle,</HI> I must craue, and with swift speed:</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Altamont, Meruolle.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Rossa, Molard,</HI> (friends to my Soule and Braine)</L>
<L>Aduance your subtle Eyes! The sou'raigne mine</L>
<L>Behold, that makes the solemne Patriarke dance,</L>
<L>And the anointed King to skippe, as doth</L>
<L>His limber Dwarfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rossa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yellow as foot of Kite!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Molard</SPEAKER>
<P>Shall we be tender natur'd, and diuide?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is the portion will procure vs all</L>
<L>High dignitie and place. <HI>Rossa,</HI> you must</L>
<L>Find cause to number these— Goe, ransome out</L>
<L>Our captiue weedes, and the rich habit I</L>
<L>From <HI>Pisa</HI> brought: whilst you <HI>(Mollard)</HI> with the</L>
<L>Assistance of these few—procure vs fit</L>
<L>Materials to adorne, and put in bright</L>
<L>Aspect our Corps. Enquire for Pearles: Stones of</L>
<L>The cunningst soyle, we'le like them, and disburse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="10" MS="y"/>
<SPEAKER>Rossa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is there some aged vessell now asleepe</L>
<L>In the Docke, that will pay for her calking?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Molard.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Florello,</HI> must we stop the publike leakes?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ere long we shall be great, be able to</L>
<L>Aduance with smiles, and with our frownes destroy.</L>
<L>You <HI>Rossa,</HI> I'le create a Magistrate.</L>
<L>Goe practise the austeere Cough. Pale dilinquents</L>
<L>Thou shalt learne to ieere, and to sleepe ore men</L>
<L>Condemn'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rossa.</SPEAKER>
<P>The calling (Sir) I doe vouchsafe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou (my <HI>Molard</HI>) shalt rule in Villages,</L>
<L>Grow popular, and mistake the Lawes. Thou shalt</L>
<L>Delight i'th Kallender: the Rubricke dayes</L>
<L>Thou shalt obserue, and then destroy thy beefe.</L>
<L>Whilst thy dull earthie Tennants feede vntill</L>
<L>They smell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Molard.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Launcepresado then shall sop</L>
<L>His Crust in Cyder and in wine!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rossa▪</SPEAKER>
<L>And my</L>
<L>Dread Corporall shall sinne no more for Leekes,</L>
<L>His Girdle and his socks he shall vnpawne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>The solitarie Hostesse shall no more</L>
<L>Boyle the Carion meate that she must trust,</L>
<L>In her owne teares; Nor with a Requiem bring</L>
<L>The seruice vp, as if it were the Haunch</L>
<L>Of her dead Husband.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rossa.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am intire flame!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Geographicke Captaine shall no more</L>
<L>Studie the Towne Mappe, that's darke walkes may be</L>
<L>Contriu'd through slender Allies and through Lanes,</L>
<L>To scape his hungrie Creditors abroade.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rossa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy Prouince is Chaldea, thy Father</L>
<L>Was a Rabby!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Molard.</SPEAKER>
<P>And thy Aunt a Sybill!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>These are the victories of wit: by wit</L>
<L>We must atchieue our hopes; which to refine</L>
<L>And purifie, with paces doubled let's</L>
<L><PB REF="10" MS="y"/>Descend a Marble vault, there taste the rich</L>
<L>Legitimate blood of the mighty Grape.</L>
<L>Tis precious as the milke of Queenes; such as</L>
<L>Would teach dull Saturne laugh. It magnifies</L>
<L>The heart, and makes the agill spirits dance,</L>
<L>It drownds all thoughts adulterate and sad;</L>
<L>Inspires the Prophet, makes the Poet glad.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt omnes.</STAGE>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Act the second.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scene the first.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter Altamont, Meruolle, S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>operta.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>I Haue receiu'd a mandate from the Duke,</L>
<L>That will (I feare) increase her insolence.</L>
<L>Like an old Tyrant he bestowes his threats;</L>
<L>As if his anger did obay his will,</L>
<L>Not iustice, nor the Lawes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meruolle.</SPEAKER>
<L>Does your wife know</L>
<L>This preparation you haue made to cure</L>
<L>Her haughtinesse?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>All is discouerd to</L>
<L>Her eare: the newes hath taught her boyle her heart</L>
<L>In her owne blood. She now weepes vineger;</L>
<L>Boasts of reuenge, as if the Thunder were</L>
<L>Her owne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meruolle.</SPEAKER>
<L>T'were fit your pretty Agent heere,</L>
<L>Receiu'd instructions how to shape her garbe</L>
<L>And port, iust as th'imployment doth require.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Her knowledge is already satisfi'd.</L>
<L><HI>Alteza's</HI> threats shall onely mooue her scorne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scoperta.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will performe my best in your behalfe▪</L>
<L>But I doe feare I am not valiant Sir.
<STAGE>Enter Niente.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, you! that call your sinnes your duty, that</L>
<L><PB REF="11"/>Obay your Ladies riots out o'zeale!—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Niente.</SPEAKER>
<L>Signior!—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Her honours spittle you preserue</L>
<L>As a Restoratiue for your salt itch</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Niente.</SPEAKER>
<L>I beseech ye—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>You thrid in Bracelets too,</L>
<L>The Pearles that drop from her authenticke nose.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Niente.</SPEAKER>
<P>What meane you Sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>To cleaue you from the scalpe</L>
<L>Vnto the twist: to make nine skittles of</L>
<L>Your bo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es, and winde your heratstrings 'bout my thumbe—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Niente.</SPEAKER>
<L>O mercy Sir! So rotten are my Limmes</L>
<L>That when you stretch your Cheekes and blow on me,</L>
<L>I strait am scatter'd into sand—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Coward!</L>
<L>Creepe strait into my Houreglasse then, and there</L>
<L>Eternally distinguish fatall time—
<STAGE>Enter Alteza.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza..</SPEAKER>
<P>What slaue disturbs the quiet of my Eare?</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Niente steps behinde her.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Niente.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nere looke Sir! I serue my Lady; and I</L>
<L>Doe scorne to yeeld—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>D'ye bristle Porcupine?—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Niente.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take heed!— I haue the mallady of France—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay <HI>Altamont!</HI> withdraw thy violence!</L>
<L>If thou disorderst but a haire, that doth</L>
<L>Belong to th'Eyebrow of my meanest Groome,</L>
<L>I will proclaime my superioritie</L>
<L>And rule i'th'Streets.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hell cannot misse thee long!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>Insult beneath thy owne low Roofe! This part</L>
<L>O'th'House doth call me soueraigne</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>She spies Scoperta, and comes neere her.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<P>Retire!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is that the Peece you haue so magnifi'd,</L>
<L>She you boast of for your pastime Royall?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>She clips the grey and shiuer'd wings of Time</L>
<L>to make him slow; that our imbraces like</L>
<L><PB REF="11" MS="y"/>Succeeding minutes then, may adde vnto</L>
<L>Their length. Let me ingender on thy lips—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scoperta.</SPEAKER>
<L>So our progeny may still be kisses—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>A meeke and gentle heate, whilst thus we bill</L>
<L>We imitate the sober lust of Doues—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scopertae.</SPEAKER>
<L>That kisse (Sir) was so powerfull and moist,</L>
<L>That you haue robd my Lips of all their wealth!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take backe thy wealth againe! —</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are ye so hot? —</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy Lips are thin and lanke (<HI>Alteza</HI>) as</L>
<L>The Lids that close thine Eyes. Hers gently swell</L>
<L>Like Easterne fruit, and are more soft then is</L>
<L>The fleecy Aire that clothes the Infant Morne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray a word! Is there in this Pagentry</L>
<L>Ought like to truth? Discouer your intent!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le make my anger equall vnto thine,</L>
<L>And my reuenge aboue them both. This bright</L>
<L>Auspicious Maid shall gouerne in my bed.</L>
<L>She is my Concubine: the Off spring of</L>
<L>Her wombe shall triumph heere, maugre thy sight:</L>
<L>Whilst enuie does consume thy flesh vntill</L>
<L>Thy bodie lighter grow then thy loose mind.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<P>How well my Starres behaue their influence?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Meruolle,</HI> goe! my Mistresse guide vnto</L>
<L>Those lodgings that oreuiew the Garden mount.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scoperta.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you retard your presence whilst the Sunne</L>
<L>(In's race) fill vp one Howre, you'le find before</L>
<L>Your next reuiew, that griefe hath made me old,</L>
<L>And I shall looke more like a Matron then</L>
<L>A Bride; so much your absence mortifies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art to euerie sense I haue, a Spell.</L>
<L>Conduct her strait <HI>(Meruolle)</HI> to some Throne!</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Meruolle, Scoperta.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then are the vowes, the Ecclesiasticke rites</L>
<L>With which the zealous Priest oblig'd vs to</L>
<L>Peculiar heate, to abstinence from change,</L>
<L>And various loue, quite cancell'd by your lust?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="12"/>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<P>Accuse thy pride!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou art a periur'd man!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe, thou art as light as feathers, or the Aire,</L>
<L>were but an Attome indiuiduall plac'd</L>
<L>With thee in ballance euen, t'would hoise thee vp</L>
<L>To th'Cloudes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy breath is fulsome as that steame</L>
<L>Which Toades when they ingender vaporate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Alteza,</HI> bath in penitentiall teares</L>
<L>Thy leprous heart, or when the Elements</L>
<L>Are mix'd and the sad day ariues, that doomes</L>
<L>The world vnto eternitie of ioy,</L>
<L>Or paine, thou shalt (like to a glimmering Lampe)</L>
<L>Be hung vpon the sootie walles of Hell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>I smile at thee, and thy thinne Arts; like to</L>
<L>Some homelie Village Leuite, thou doest preach</L>
<L>Of terrours strange, to keepe dull faith in awe:</L>
<L>I pray stay; I am not angrie Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<P>No?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>I practisd all this while how t'indanger</L>
<L>your spleene (Sir) not my owne▪ which if my powers</L>
<L>Prooue iust, I shall, performe ere long.</L>
<L><HI>Niente,</HI> send the partie in—
<STAGE>Exit Niente.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<P>More wrath!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<P>A slow deuice (Sir) but o'my owne Braine.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Sciolto.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who art thou?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>A keene Guest, inuited heere—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<P>To what?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scioeto.</SPEAKER>
<P>To taste—your wiues Gammons.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<P>Bold slaue! be in thy speech more euident.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am come to get your children for you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>D'ye want a cleerer paraphrase? He is</L>
<L>My seruant Sir, my stallion if I please.</L>
<L>A Courtly implement, and much in vse</L>
<L><PB REF="12"/>Among Ladies of my growth and Title.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alta.</SPEAKER>
<L>O my cold Blood! My patience will be wrought</L>
<L>So low, that I shall learne t'mike a Heifer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>Since I'me so aptly furnish'd with delight,</L>
<L>Your Concubine may fearelesse walke about</L>
<L>The house, and share the wholesome Sunne in peace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy tongue I doe neglect: but you (sir) shall</L>
<L>Ere long complaine of your mortality:</L>
<L>The minutes you must waste on Earth are few.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>This I consider Sir, and therefore make</L>
<L>Such haste to mingle with your wife; that the</L>
<L>Kinde world may haue some issue from my Loynes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alta.</SPEAKER>
<L>If this prooue true, let Babes pisse out my Eyes—</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>He drawes his sword, Sciolto his, Alteza her stilleto.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold <HI>Altamont,</HI> or else I wound thy heart—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you aduance one inch beyond that rush</L>
<L>I'le amble through the Streets, and blow your Dirge</L>
<L>With the great Horne that growes vpon your Brow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>If there be Gall in Heauen, the gen'rall Bagge</L>
<L>Is opned, and it falls in Showres!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>S'light Sir;</L>
<L>I come t'ease the labour of your Body;</L>
<L>And you want courtship to returne me thanks.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hang him Ingrate!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>But what hereafter I</L>
<L>Performe, shall be for your good Ladies sake,</L>
<L>And not for yours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray (sir) let's interchange</L>
<L>A little breath: withall (if you consent)</L>
<L>We'le put our Swords to a more quiet vse—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now Sir, you powre sweet Cassia in my Broath.</L>
<L>My Blood affects to skirmish more</L>
<L>With Ladies then with men. What would you speake?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>My true opinion sir concerning you.</L>
<L>I know you doe but countrfeit this lust,</L>
<L>This lawlesse heate. You purpose not t'abuse</L>
<L>the Charter of my Bed,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="13" MS="y"/>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who told ye so?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>I read it in your noble feature and</L>
<L>Your lookes. You haue Religion in your shape.</L>
<L>And can it be, you should so soone commit a crime</L>
<L>So much vnwholsome to the Angels sight?</L>
<L>Let me now make a forfeiture of Eyes,</L>
<L>If euer I beheld a man that's more oblig'd</L>
<L>To Nature for his Limmes: A carnall frame</L>
<L>So full of equall strength I neuer saw.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Sciol<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>The better shap'd I am (Sir) the more cause</L>
<L>You'le find, to loue the Issue I shall get</L>
<L>Vpon your wife.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe not belie thy owne</L>
<L>True merits and comport! Th'adulterate fire</L>
<L>Did nere inflame thy sober heart, I know</L>
<L>Thou scornst to do't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not I beleeue it Sir!</L>
<L>Sir I will doe't. Is your Lady fruitfull?</L>
<L>I would be loath t'loose my labour on her?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pestilence! and blood!</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>He drawes, and they as before.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fling a danger from</L>
<L>Thy arme, I'le summon strait (with Trumpet and</L>
<L>with Drumme) the world to heare thy infamie—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>O fie! You an Italian Sir, and thus</L>
<L>Behaue the knowledge of disgrace with lowd</L>
<L>And popular dislike?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay it becomes</L>
<L>You finelie, does it not?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>You thinke because</L>
<L>Y'are curs'd, we'le allow you short Hornes: I'le graft</L>
<L>Vpon your head a paire so tall, they shall</L>
<L>Goe neere to pricke the verie Planet (Sir)</L>
<L>Thet rul'd at your natiuitie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<P>He sleepes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Signior, goe! take downe a Cushion, and pray▪</L>
<L>You cannot choose but know the frailty of</L>
<L><PB REF="13" MS="y"/>The times: the surfeits of the wombe, and how</L>
<L>Great Ladies doe relieue their Appetites.</L>
<L>Your owne confession of my parts commends</L>
<L>Your wife in her sage choice. There be that sinne</L>
<L>With feeble vshers and the witherd Dwarfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<P>He wants a iudgement to consider this.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>I merit better looks Sir, that must thrash</L>
<L>All night for ye, and without wages Sir!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dead as a monument! Let vs leaue him!—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Had he the Deuill for's Physitian chose,</L>
<L>He could nere haue come by the like Cordiall.—</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Sciolto, Alteza.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alta.</SPEAKER>
<L>You swelling mountains (that oreuiew the Earth)</L>
<L>Fall now, make me eternally vnseene!</L>
<L>Philosophie contract thy meeke sage brow:</L>
<L>Let Patience be no more thy Saint. As soone</L>
<L>Giue med'cines to the dead, teach statues how</L>
<L>To walke, and angry windes to sleepe i'th North.</L>
<L>As soone bid emptie Lions play with Kids;</L>
<L>And to the shaggie Scythian say, Goe weepe</L>
<L>As Virgines doe, when they their Loues interre:</L>
<L>The blind and shuffled Elements that first</L>
<L>In Chaos stroue, were not so opposite</L>
<L>As this Religious frost vnto my heate.</L>
<L>Patience, thou art more fond then teeming wiues,</L>
<L>Tamer then sseepe! Diuinitie which calls</L>
<L>Our anger sinne, and courage pride, hath sent</L>
<L>This sillie Cherubine on Earth, Patience,</L>
<L>(The Cowards sword) which onlie doth disarme</L>
<L>Dull sleepe, that neither can nor would doe harme.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Sciolto, Alteza, Niente.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Florence knowes me well: I'm call'd <HI>Sciolto,</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>I needs must sing my vshers praise: he made</L>
<L>A most discreete election of a man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your mercie and your kindnesse (Lady) thus</L>
<L><PB REF="14" MS="y"/>Aduance my shape; your pleasure was I should</L>
<L>despise your husbands frownes, and I behau'd</L>
<L>My selfe with terrour masculine: but now</L>
<L>We are peculiar and reseru'd, I know</L>
<L>Humilitie, a soft and quiet garbe;</L>
<L>A distance that shall well become the state</L>
<L>So eminent and rich a beauty claimes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, that we doe expect, and then you shall</L>
<L>Ore take our noble Sense, with newer loue.</L>
<L>Our husband is a trifle, such as can</L>
<L>No way disturbe your peace or safetie heere.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, store me with armes and weapons to</L>
<L>Resist his personall assault, and I</L>
<L>Shall need no more protection then my selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>Actiue and bold! <HI>Niente</HI> thou hast made</L>
<L>A choice out-parallels the world.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Niente.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam,</L>
<L>See his horse vaines: th'are large as Conduit pipes;</L>
<L>His Sinnews are like Cables.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Las! not mine!</L>
<L>Tis true, that if I like my Opposite,</L>
<L>I haue a tricke te giue an easie fall,</L>
<L>And stand to't stifly too when I ha'done—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Niente.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will assure your Ladiship, the Bawdes</L>
<L>Giue him good report.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doe they <HI>Niente</HI>?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nienie.</SPEAKER>
<P>He's great with Ladies of all ages, all Degrees.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<P>Excuse me Sir, th'are great by me!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<P>As how Sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<P>Madam—They are all wi'child!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<P>How Signior? Is your appetite so strong?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Blame the humorous Planets that orerule</L>
<L>The blood. Ere yet this present Month expires;</L>
<L>(Let's see—I,!) Some three and forty Ladies</L>
<L>(Or there about) will quicken with male Twinnes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<P>All of your begetting?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="14" MS="y"/>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>So wise Fame sings.</L>
<L>I will make bold to gather my first fruits—
<STAGE>Goes to kisse her.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay my pregnant Signior! Our loue is not</L>
<L>Yet ripe: there is a larger distance too</L>
<L>Belongs vnto our Lips.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<P>How deare Lady?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am too proud to haue my fauours soone</L>
<L>and easilie conferr'd. Such smiles are cheape.</L>
<L>I meane to procreate by prescription Sir,</L>
<L>Make my lust as physicall as my meales.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Death, I'm Sutor vnto <HI>Gallens</HI> widdow!</L>
<L>Madam, I know it not becomes the high</L>
<L>Demeanure of your birth to dance (iust like</L>
<L>A Kid) to th'musicke of each wind that blowes.</L>
<L>Ere you admit of dalliance I should vse</L>
<L>Some industry of Tongue, and flexure of</L>
<L>the pliant Ioints, to court and wooe consent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>And can your rudenesse couet then where your</L>
<L>Safe wit and knowledge warnes your abstinence?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Only a little t'recreate the Chine—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>Keepe backe, if you'le continue life. When I</L>
<L>Am pleasd to be delighted Sir, I can</L>
<L>command the function of your Limmes.</L>
<L><STAGE>Charintha within.</STAGE>
Madam!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sister, I come. Throw him to his chamber—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hast no good booke, whose comfortable vse</L>
<L>may fill th'expence of time?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<P>What would you read?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Any o'th Moderns. <HI>Rablays</HI> i'th praise of</L>
<L>Midwiues. <HI>Aretine</HI> on copulation.</L>
<L>Or th'Odes of <HI>Theophile</HI> vnto his whore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Vsher in my closet can appoint</L>
<L>Your choice of these.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thinke on the frailtie of</L>
<L>The flesh; and be not long vnmercifull—</L>
<L><STAGE>Charintha within.</STAGE>
Sister! Madam!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<P>Away; I come, I come.
<STAGE>Exeunt Niente, Sciolto:</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="15" MS="y"/><HI>Enter Charintha, Besognia.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charintha.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Millaine Count (my Sutor) is ariu'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>Signior <HI>Dandolo</HI>! Why 'tis yet a month</L>
<L>Ere he should meet your expectation heere.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Besognia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis he Madam, and such a he as must</L>
<L>Be onely likened to himselfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charintha.</SPEAKER>
<L>More rich,</L>
<L>And gaudie then the East. So lib'rall too,</L>
<L>That you would thinke he Natures Steward were.</L>
<L>He giues amongst m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> slaues, as if vnto</L>
<L>Embassadours he did cast Donatiues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>Milke him (my <HI>Charintha</HI>) oft I haue preach'd</L>
<L>Vnto thine Eare a sou'raigntie ore man.</L>
<L>Take all he giues, it's princely fashion now.</L>
<L>Could but thy acceptation begger him,</L>
<L>Thy little wit were euer magnifi'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charintha.</SPEAKER>
<L>You know I am o'th'wits, I haue bin sworne</L>
<L>To begger Sutors, and ieere my husband.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Florello in rich habit. Rossa, Molard, shifted like his seruants.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<P>Which is the Ladie that I come to wooe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charintha.</SPEAKER>
<L>My name's <HI>Charintha</HI>—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>Present me thy Lips!</L>
<L>I say aduance —</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are not vnderstood—</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>He kisses Charintha, then giues her a Iewell.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charintha.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, I scarcely owne desert enough</L>
<L>T'intice this Iewell from your Cabinet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florel.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Stone, a Stone! the thing growes, I'ue enow—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>So free? I am <HI>Charintha's</HI> Sister Sir—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>It may be so. A fine house, fine Towne too!</L>
<L>Were Florence mine, I would not giue it for</L>
<L>The best winter Seate my father left me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis Sir, th'ambition of my loue, that you</L>
<L>Would know me for <HI>Charintha's</HI> Sister!—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="15" MS="y"/>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<P>I shall. <HI>Rossa,</HI> remember it!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rossa.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<P>I must know her for <HI>Charintha's</HI> Sister.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charintha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is there no tricke in ceremonie Sir,</L>
<L>To giue your memorie a better hint?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>Kisse none but thee! A deuice i'th'blood! but</L>
<L>Princes haue one toy or other still, t'make</L>
<L>Their descent knowne. — There, a Diamond that,</L>
<L>And that a Ruby.—
<STAGE>Giues to Alteza.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<P>What meanes your Lordship?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>Th'are none of mine. I haue enow, weare'em—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Lordship binds my great acknowledgement.</L>
<L>I'th leasure of a winke, he'le giue away</L>
<L>An Empire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Besognia.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'm <HI>Charintha's</HI> woman Sir—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who can helpe it? Mistresse, wilt thou not bid</L>
<L>My seruants welcome? Th'are rich Choughs, th'aue store</L>
<L>Of Villages, and plough'd Earth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charintha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Their iudgement is</L>
<L>So kind (Sir) as to know they may command</L>
<L>The house.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rossa, Molard.</SPEAKER>
<P>We thanke your Ladiship.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is my Parasite, and this my Pimpe.</L>
<L>I'ue a Foole, a Dwarfe too at home. I made</L>
<L>My iaunt too early by a month, or else</L>
<L>My Traine had beene enlarg'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>Th'are rarely fix'd,</L>
<L>If they import as much as you denominate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>I keepe my parasite to cure the dull</L>
<L>Melancholy of State. He does admire</L>
<L>My wit and Beard. He sayes I cannot sinne.</L>
<L>Princes would still be sad out for such worrmes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<P>But how (Sir) does your Pimpe adhere to vse?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>He is as pertinent to Lords as lust.</L>
<L>My Foole I keepe to laugh at me. My Dwarfe</L>
<L>Is for my wife. I doe intend she shall</L>
<L>Affect the Court, and then she'le quickly learne.</L>
<L><PB REF="16"/>To make the Toy vsefull.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charintha.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, be pleasd</L>
<L>To walke, and vse th'aduantage of the Aire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'ue Instruments distinct, that take a charge</L>
<L>O'th seuerall quarters of my Frame, My Dwarfe</L>
<L>Doth dresse me vp vnto the knees, and when</L>
<L>His stature leaues his reach, young Virgines then</L>
<L>(Th'issue of decay'd Barons) do beginne</L>
<L>And gouerne to the Nauell. Whilst vpwards</L>
<L>Barbars, Painters, and Parasites are vs'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charin.</SPEAKER>
<L>But will your Lordship walke and see the spring?</L>
<L>We haue a Garden where it euer dwels.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<P>And shall we be delighted and entranc'd?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charintha.</SPEAKER>
<L>We'le sacrifice the vtmost of our wealth</L>
<L>And loue, t'expresse your welcome Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wilt'I faith.</L>
<L>There's a Saphyre Chaine: Tie thy Monkie in't—</L>
<L>Take it; for by this hand I am in haste</L>
<L>And cannot offer twice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Besognia.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you should chance</L>
<L>(My honourd Lord) to drop those trifles heere,</L>
<L>I would be mannerly, and reach'em vp.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will giue thee a Bushell of Seed-Pearle</L>
<L>To imbroider thy Petticoate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charintha.</SPEAKER>
<L>This way—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rossa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Lordship hath forgot to leaue notice for</L>
<L>Those Princes in diguise that shall by chance</L>
<L>Demand ye at the gate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who does he meane?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>A leash of Germane Dukes that walke in Rugge.</L>
<L>I should consult with'em'bout subuersion</L>
<L>Of a State or two; but I'm not yet at</L>
<L>Leasure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord, they shall be answerd so.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rossa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your hypocrisie wants a little Art.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Molard.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your bounty will impouerish vs too soone.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ye both doe lie, I weaue my cunning close.</L>
<L><PB REF="16"/>Fortune, redeeme the credit of thy Eyes.</L>
<L>Thou wilt (if thou art partiall now and kind)</L>
<L>But winke on me, though to the world th'art blind.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt omnes.</STAGE>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Act the third.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scene the first.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Altamont, Meruolle. Sciolto at the other doore.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>THis is the truth, therefore consider now</L>
<L>my Fate. Hah! <HI>Sciolto!</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meruolle.</SPEAKER>
<P>What makes he there.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis <HI>Sciolto,</HI> the brute Adulterer,</L>
<L>He whom I lately mention'd in my speech.</L>
<L>A slaue more salt then is the Balticke ware,</L>
<L>More hot then hell, a Satyre or a Goate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>And shall be still so (Sir) vnlesse your wife</L>
<L>Dismisse her pride, and vouchsafe to coole me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alta.</SPEAKER>
<L>Deuils and death, I'm murderd through the Eare—</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>He drawes, Sciolto puls foorth a case of Pistols,</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take discipline awhile, Know if there be</L>
<L>A boisterous motion vsd, I haue for each</L>
<L>Of you a round Synamon Plumme, and they</L>
<L>Shall enter your nice stomacks the wrong way—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Though thou wert hardy as the Lions race;</L>
<L>And arm'd with all th'Artillery on Earth,</L>
<L>I durst assault thee as I am; but so</L>
<L>I cannot satisfie Reuenge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meruolle.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Sciolto,</HI> now my memory begins</L>
<L>To know you better: for your riots bold</L>
<L>And lowd demeanure in this City hath</L>
<L>Beene long obseru'd. I wonder much y'imploy</L>
<L>Your precious minutes in a course so vile.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>What, as to copulate and increase kind?</L>
<L><PB REF="17" MS="y"/>It has beene a vocation euer since</L>
<L>The Sunne spi'd man thus crawling on the Earth—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meruolle.</SPEAKER>
<L>But what excuse canst thou in honour vrge,</L>
<L>for wearing such aduantagious defence,</L>
<L>Against his iust and single violence?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seiolto.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue an odde humor, not to be kill'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>O <HI>Alteza,</HI> had but my name beene hid</L>
<L>Beneath some fold in the voluminous</L>
<L>Darke booke of Fate, I might haue miss'd of my</L>
<L>Creation then, so I should nere haue seene</L>
<L>Thy face.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>My curses (Sir) haue cause t'assault</L>
<L>Her more then yours: for she has staru'd me heere</L>
<L>With want of naturall delight. My free</L>
<L>Large growth and tincture of my haire denote,</L>
<L>My constitution cannot suffer me,</L>
<L>To weare a surplesse, or proceed Eunuch.</L>
<L>Though I should bath and swimme in Iulips Sir,</L>
<L>I'ue still vnrulie heate about my Chine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Salamander that doth feede and cloth</L>
<L>It selfe with flame, was thy Progenitor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Haue I not equall reason to complaine?</L>
<L>In three Houres not so much as a drie kisse.</L>
<L>Th'old amorous Deacon that imbrac'd his Cow</L>
<L>Was not so destitute.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meruolle.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fine calumny!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Negro might be vsefull now, although</L>
<L>Sh'ad but one eye, and that fix'd on her heele.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le strew vpon thy food the teeth of Snakes,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Signior, presume no more vpon a fond</L>
<L>Easie nature. I haue beene abstinent</L>
<L>Too long. Haste, and with pliant steps present</L>
<L>Your wife; Ot else I'le assure ye you shall seeke</L>
<L>Some other man to Cuckold ye for me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meruolle.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Sciolto,</HI> this is barbarous!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le shoot</L>
<L>Thy heart with needles, small as splinters of</L>
<L><PB REF="17" MS="y"/>A haire that thou mayst die, and yet not know</L>
<L>That thou art kild.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thanke ye (Signior) but</L>
<L>We Florentines doe sleepe like Leuorites,</L>
<L>With our Eyes open: how ere, I could vouchsafe</L>
<L>To shoot you now, and preuent your kindnesse.—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meruolle.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Sciolto,</HI> hold. If eyther charge doe misse,</L>
<L>He that suruiues, shall grinde thy marble heart,</L>
<L>Betweene his teeth—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>I meant not to giue fire.</L>
<L>There is a tricke of grauity i'th state</L>
<L>Cald Law. Besides, you dead, the children which</L>
<L>I chance to get vpon your bucksome wife,</L>
<L>I should goe neere to keepe at my owne charge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Africa</HI> breedes no monster like to thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le to my chamber now, and fortifie</L>
<L>There, I remaine (during the pleasure of</L>
<L>Your wife) your Tenant (Signior) in fee tayle. —
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is a cunning, and promiscuous slaue.</L>
<L>This story of <HI>Alteza's</HI> abstinence,</L>
<L>He doth but counterfet, to gull my sight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meruolle.</SPEAKER>
<L>Had the Diuell himselfe crep't into flesh,</L>
<L>And vndertooke this seruice to your wife,</L>
<L>She had possessd, the weaker Instrument.</L>
<L>He hath in 's Veynes, a most intemperat blood</L>
<L>His valour's so renown'd, that all the smooth,</L>
<L>The curl'd, and silken Nobles of the Towne,</L>
<L>Doe homage to his Sword; and by such Actes</L>
<L>As these, he glorifies his truant youth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy fayth was iealous, I seduc'd thy eare</L>
<L>To share vntruths: but now, thou knowst too much.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meruolle.</SPEAKER>
<L>T'was my suspect of Fame, and dispersement</L>
<L>Of your deepe wrong, that manacled till now,</L>
<L>Your hands. My temp'rate Lectures cease. Obey</L>
<L>Reuenge, and I will follow it, vntill</L>
<L>My wealth, and life, are forfeyted to Law.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alta.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hah! wilt thou? O my quickened heart (entomb'd</L>
<L><PB REF="18" MS="y"/>Before within my breast) wilt thou? This, this</L>
<L>Then is the direfull night, wherein I'le giue</L>
<L>A strict and cruell iustice to Reuenge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meruolle.</SPEAKER>
<L>This then is the night, wherein my bold loue</L>
<L>Shall merit me th'eternall name of friend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come sweare, sweare now (on this victorious sword)</L>
<L>Thou wilt obey th'iniunctions of my wrath,</L>
<L>And yet in personall act, not mooue, but when</L>
<L>My will appoints a mixture of thy strength.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meruolle.</SPEAKER>
<L>My choice Religion, &amp; the honors of my blood,</L>
<L>I heere doe pawne to ratifie the vow —</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Meruolle kisses the Hilts.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now worke my iniurd spirits, till you make</L>
<L>Dull sorrow rise in nimble flame. Anger,</L>
<L>Is blood, pow'rd, and perplex'd into a froth,</L>
<L>But Mallice is, the wisedome of our wrath.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ent. Florello, Charintha, Alteza, Rossa, Molard.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charintha.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your Lordships letters were of a prompt stile!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>This orient Roape is yours, and you must wear't;</L>
<L>I sickne els, and grow a villager</L>
<L>In Elizium!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charintha.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your bounty choakes my thankes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take it. Afflict me Fame, if ere I knew</L>
<L>His parallell; he woes at Neroe's rate.
<STAGE>Enter Besognia.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Besognia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, ther's a new <HI>Dand<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lo,</HI> a new</L>
<L>Count, lighted at the Gate, and craues entrance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's rare i'faith; haue I a shadow walkes</L>
<L>Without leaue o'the Sunne?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<P>A conspiracie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did not <HI>Meruolle</HI> say, t'would be a month,</L>
<L>Ere he ariu'd?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rossa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Be bold and meet your chance<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stand firme, and stiffely on your sinewes then,</L>
<L>Auouch me still, for the true <HI>Dandolo.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="18"/>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Charintha,</HI> 'tis some stratagem; but if</L>
<L>He Iewells bring, and in a hand as large,</L>
<L>And open as yon'easy snypes, thou hast</L>
<L>Ill lucke if thou constraine him not to losse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charintha·</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le smile no longer then these rich sparkles</L>
<L>Shine in my Eies.
<STAGE>Enter Dandolo.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dandolo.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Lady that is nam'd</L>
<L><HI>Charintha</HI> heere, must be reueald; for Il'd</L>
<L>Exallt her Lippes, and make'em knowne to mine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo:</SPEAKER>
<L>S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>light, this is the great <HI>Cham.</HI> Hearke ye, Signior—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charintha.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord, I pray afford him leave to speake.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dan.</SPEAKER>
<P>What, is that sawcy Groome? Does he sell Egges?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le shew ye my Trade; A poore sword-man, I—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir you destroy the quiett of my Howse:</L>
<L>He shall haue safety heere, and leaue to speake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charintha.</SPEAKER>
<P>I'm call'd <HI>Charintha</HI> Sir; proceed to speech.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dandolo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le first doe speciall grace vnto your Lip—</L>
<L>My Penne hath woo'd you oft; but now by stealth</L>
<L>Thus single I'm arui'd, a Moone before</L>
<L>The time I did prefix.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charintha.</SPEAKER>
<P>I sir, the cause.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dandolo.</SPEAKER>
<L>T'was Winter when I specifi'd the date</L>
<L>Of my aproach, and then my blood was cold;</L>
<L>But now the spring is come, Things would couple.</L>
<L>These (Lady) are very serculare Pearle—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>I sir, and in such Toyes, she much delights:</L>
<L>Allthough her modesty be loath, to make</L>
<L>Her fancys knowne. Would you had brought some few</L>
<L>To mach'em.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dandolo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doe you affect'em Lady?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charintha.</SPEAKER>
<P>I reioyce in all the workes of Nature!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dandolo.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am instructed then.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<P>As how, deare Sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dandolo.</SPEAKER>
<P>That I did ill, to leaue my Pearles behind.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sister this Hulke, is neither rigg'd, nor fraught,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charintha.</SPEAKER>
<P>I'le haue no more of him, he is too costiue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir a word. Me thinks you looke, like raw Porke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="19"/>
<SPEAKER>Dandolo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Has not this house the priuiledge of peace?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ladyes, this Impostor steales my Titles,</L>
<L>And my name, I aske leaue, to punish him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wee'le not protect his crimes, vse your iustice.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Florello drawes his Stiletto.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vnlesse you are an Estridge, Sir, and can</L>
<L>Digest steele, coole your lungs, and calmely wayt</L>
<L>Th'inquiry I shall vrge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dandolo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hence, and be dead!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Molard,</HI> reueale how long thou hast bin Pimpe,</L>
<L>To the family of the <HI>Dandolos?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Molard.</SPEAKER>
<L>About some thirty yeeres (Sir.) I'ue procur'd</L>
<L>Both time and place, for your good Fathers game,</L>
<L>Ere since he was capable of woman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rossa.</SPEAKER>
<P>He vsd the Trade (Sir) in his infancy.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Molard.</SPEAKER>
<L>I scare could walke, when I began't: the first</L>
<L>I brought him was my Nurse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>Canst point, at ought</L>
<L>He did some two and twenty yeeres agoe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Molard.</SPEAKER>
<L>Distinctly Sir. I know that Gentleman,</L>
<L>He was got, on a Tripewife of <HI>Lucca.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<P>O th'action of my fathers loynes!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<P>My lord?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'm an old <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ew at Genealogies.</L>
<L>This fellowes descent I know now, and where</L>
<L>He tooke 's creation too. By chance thus haue</L>
<L>I met forty of my Fathers Bastards.</L>
<L>Th'are poore, and put me oft to charge. Brother,</L>
<L>Welcome.— <HI>Rossa,</HI> giue him a <HI>Quardecus.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dandolo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Bid Kings winde silke, and Princes measure oats.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your trayne of Parasite, Pimpe, Foole and Dwarfe,</L>
<L>Speake you at first, to be the true yong Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet th'other has some markes, that doe belong</L>
<L>Vnto a Count, o'th last edition too:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dandolo.</SPEAKER>
<P>D'you thinke y'are the Count?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<P>I doe, thinke it, Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dandolo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thought's free.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="19"/>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>He should be a Venetian,</L>
<L>By'th' wit, and policy of his courage.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Beauties, were you<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> hands cleane, they should be kil<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<P>Bold illegitimate.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dandolo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, —you shall know,</L>
<L>No man ere got me, but my owne Father.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Besognia</HI> speake in my behalfe; I'le giue</L>
<L>Thee a Pearle then, big as a Pompeon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Besognia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Which, when your Lordship does, Ile returne ye</L>
<L>A pointed Diamond, big as a Steeple.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'on thrifty counterfet, has much perplex'd</L>
<L>Your seruants wit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charintha.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord. Lets in, and ieere.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>Slow method fooles obey. To th' stars aduance</L>
<L>His head, who thus resists the power of Chance.
<STAGE>Ex. omnes.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Scoperta, Sciolto.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scoperta.</SPEAKER>
<L>Like to my Genius he doth mooue about</L>
<L>The house. Our soules are surely neere ally'd—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cals he her, his concubine? By this hand</L>
<L>There's not a Prince in all the East, has such</L>
<L>Another. This <HI>Altamont</HI> still gripes'em</L>
<L>In the flanke; he knowes to chuse his cattell.</L>
<L>Be thou pleas'd, O yong and wholesome Lady!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scoperta.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Garden (Signior) doth containe more walks,</L>
<L>As pensatiue in shade as this. I doe</L>
<L>Beseech you, change your path, and leaue me heere.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>The fumes of spicery? you must not now —</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Holds her in his Armes.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Altamont, Meruolle, from aboue.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meruolle.</SPEAKER>
<L>My vowes haue promis'd you the ample truth</L>
<L>Of my intelligence. Behold, whom there,</L>
<L><HI>Sciolto</HI> keepes in amorous whisper.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="20"/>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hah, <HI>Scoperta</HI>! Libid'nous Girle, what makes</L>
<L>She with that Horse?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meruolle.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shall I disturbe their speech?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, let'em Knit and generate; my words</L>
<L>Shall neuer penetrate her Eare vntill</L>
<L>I am reueng'd for what my Eyes haue seene.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meruolle.</SPEAKER>
<P>There is a generall tainture in the Sex.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>She is proscrib'd, I'ue fil'd her in the List</L>
<L>With those that taste to Night a bitter fate.</L>
<L>Away, away. This obiect ruines all</L>
<L>My faculties.
<STAGE>Exeunt from aboue.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>I sigh my first salute</L>
<L>Was so intempratly perform'd. But O!</L>
<L>The iustice of my Starres! My loue is now</L>
<L>Reueng'd vpon my lust. With pure chaste flame</L>
<L>I Court the Mistresse vnto <HI>Altamont</HI>;</L>
<L>One heere reseru'd for sinfull vse. Stay, stay!—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scoperta.</SPEAKER>
<L>If I am seene, my life is forfeited—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hast thou not heard my vowes, whose violence</L>
<L>And number well might satisfie suspect</L>
<L>in wayward Kings.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scoperta.</SPEAKER>
<L>How dare I traficke thus</L>
<L>For loue with thee: when thy accompts with Heauen</L>
<L>Are yet not cleer'd that lust betrai'd thee to?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>With what aduice of modesty canst thou</L>
<L>Accuse my blood; when in this Mansion th'art</L>
<L>Contain'd for the like sinne?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scoperta.</SPEAKER>
<L>Were I well knowne</L>
<L>Vnto the qualitie of thy new loue,</L>
<L>I would reueale my selfe, and take from thy</L>
<L>Beliefe the false opinion of my guilt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>If ere I practise impious heate agen,</L>
<L>Some long armd Fiend that in the Center dwels</L>
<L>Reach at my foot, and pull me into flames.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scoperta.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beare witnesse Immortalitie and Truth</L>
<L>That I'm officiall heere but by pretence,</L>
<L>My Vaines are cold and chaste as Northerne snow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="20"/>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thy name, and then my doubts I will forsake?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scoperta.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Scoperta</HI> is my name. I Sister am</L>
<L>To <HI>Altamont</HI>; not Mistresse of his lust.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>O dire affinity! my loue is now</L>
<L>Alli'd vnto my hate. Yet <HI>Altamont</HI></L>
<L>Nere merited my wrath. It is the wit</L>
<L>The policie of sinne, to hate those men</L>
<L>We haue abusd. When first I spi'd the grace</L>
<L>And lusture of thy shape; me thought I lou'd,</L>
<L>And my sicke heart enform'd me loue was good:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scoperta.</SPEAKER>
<L>And you when I beheld, I said to Heauen,</L>
<L>O make but his immortall part like to</L>
<L>The Garment Nature clothes it in, and h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lle</L>
<L>Remaine a Type, from whom shall be deriu'd</L>
<L>The Prophets, and the Kings that rule the Earth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Her beauties so increase; that they do make</L>
<L>My comprehension poore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scoperta.</SPEAKER>
<L>I should haue vs'd</L>
<L>More leasure and nice Art, when I did giue</L>
<L>My loue away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>O stay, vntill my vowes</L>
<L>Affoord a larger warrant of my faith—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scoperta:</SPEAKER>
<L>Our new society must not be seene.</L>
<L>But if thy loue be free from carnall Arts,</L>
<L>(Such as the curled Youth of Italy</L>
<L>Doe vse) make me thy sudden stealth▪ Early,</L>
<L>(Ere the succeeding Sunne ariue i'th'East)</L>
<L>Appeare beneath my Casements view, and I</L>
<L>Will follow thee along the spacious World.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe noble Maid, wert thou diuided from</L>
<L>My reach, by Sheets of Elementall fire,</L>
<L>By streames of recking blood, by purple mists</L>
<L>(Which Cannons in their acclamation breath)</L>
<L>Or winds (when met to blow each other from</L>
<L>The Earth) yet I would pull thee to my Heart.</L>
<L>False lust, I take of thee eternall leaue—</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="21"/><HI>Ent. Niente, Alteza.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>Conuey those odors thither, and disperse</L>
<L>The costly smoke, about the roome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Niente.</SPEAKER>
<P>I shall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>Place soft and easie finger'd Lutes, behind</L>
<L>The Arras; voyces feminine and yong.</L>
<L>And spread the Cowch, with the greene Persian Quilt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Niente.</SPEAKER>
<P>All is prepard.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<P>For what are these designd?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>I feele a slothfull grudging in my veynes,</L>
<L>And therefore meane to solace with a male.</L>
<L>Brush thy Beard, and follow me. —</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now am I</L>
<L>As rascally a sinner, as euer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why comst thou not?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<P>O Loue! A little grace.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is not thy blood well? Kisse me <HI>Sciolto.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shall we be wrap't in curlings intricate?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>We'le haue our artificiall heates, and with our own</L>
<L>Panting coole vs to new, and yonger strength.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>And shall we 'tweene two shady Poplars hang</L>
<L>I'th Indian-Net, whose slippery closures may</L>
<L>Entangle vs so fast, we n'ere shall be</L>
<L>Vntied agen▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<P>We'le grow as in one skin.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, much! Not an inch.—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<P>I want thy meaning.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>And shall my action more. It mightinesse</L>
<L>And state, taught me to fast from flesh; and now,</L>
<L>I am well pleas'd to make't perpetuall Lent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<P>I like this well. My Male is witty growne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe, kneele to your husband, and beg from him</L>
<L>Lawfull recreation: My selfe intend</L>
<L>To purchase a few Beades, and turne Vot'ry.</L>
<L>She'le nere moue hence, 'till I'ue inrag'd her spleene.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<P>What motiue (Sir) perswades ye, vse me thus?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="21"/>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why—ye are not handsome.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<P>Trimme prodigie!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Question your Glasse! Your Face was caru'd—out of</L>
<L>A Blew Cabidge; and 'tis contracted now</L>
<L>To one, oblique Wrinkle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<P>Villaine, thou ly'st.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy aged skull in stead of haire</L>
<L>Oregrowne with Mosse, and lookes as if t'had binne,</L>
<L>A Thousand yeares entoomb'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<P>Adders, and snakes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy sollitary Teeth, in distance stand</L>
<L>Like the decayed Arches of a Bridge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<P>Better, th'adst binne vnborne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wilt not yet goe?</L>
<L>Thy Fingers are all crook'd, like the Tallans</L>
<L>Of a Griffon. Thou walkst on Cloven-feete.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hoa! <HI>Niente.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy Bones are pil'd acrosse▪</L>
<L>Much like the Stickes on a Coniurers fire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alte.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are my Groomes dead? what hoa! I'le impound ye.—</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Sciolto pulls out a Case of Pistolls.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>It must not be. For with these two (of which</L>
<L>I meane to rob your armorie) there shall</L>
<L>Be passage forc'd broad enough for a Teeme</L>
<L>Of Southerne Elephants. Farwell Oister! —
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alte.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where are my Groomes, my slaues? iniurious wolfe.</L>
<L>Barke at my precious feature, and thus strew</L>
<L>My beautie ore, with infamie and dust?</L>
<L>Strike my greene youth, with Epethites of age?</L>
<L>My <HI>Altamont</HI> nere vs'd me thus. He oft</L>
<L>Compar'd me to the Starres, m'Eies t' Easterne light,</L>
<L>When day smiles at her birth. O! I could curse</L>
<L>The giddie iudgement of my blood; that thus</L>
<L>Seduc'd me to forsake that Saint, and mix</L>
<L>My knowledge with this Deuill. He's fled too,</L>
<L>Vntouch'd by my reuenge. <HI>Niente,</HI> hoa!
<STAGE>Enter Altamont.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alta.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis <HI>Alteza,</HI> I know her sinfull voice,—
<STAGE>(<HI>She kneeles.</HI>)</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="22"/>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>O Sir, if anguish, or distresse, can make,</L>
<L>An humble heart, behold your Lady now;</L>
<L>That shortens thus, her stature, at your feete.—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<P>What may this forc'd humillitie portend?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Sciolto</HI> (cruell as the windes in March)</L>
<L>Hath strooke, my womanhood, with tyranie,</L>
<L>And scorne. Can Fate present so large a test,</L>
<L>Of your true loue, (both to your selfe, and me)</L>
<L>As that you minister reuenge vpon</L>
<L>His Life. Goe, and salute his recreant Heart</L>
<L>With your bright Steele, and then obedience claime</L>
<L>Repleate with fonde Idolatrie, and loue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Fiends are surelie maried too; for there's</L>
<L>Noe torment like a Wife! false <HI>Alteza.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>So ill I merit charitie: that all</L>
<L>My passions argue cunning and pretence.</L>
<L>This is a wise hypocrisie, to hide</L>
<L>Thy lust, or snare me in some guilt, whereby</L>
<L>The Duke may claime my life, and thou receiue</L>
<L>More quiet space, t'inioy <HI>Sciolto's</HI> limmes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>Those angrie spirits that reside below,</L>
<L>In flaming Ouens, are not more cruell in</L>
<L>Their enuie, then am I in hate to him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>So soone, dost steepe him in thy gall, whom thou</L>
<L>Hast washt'i'th warme distilments of thy heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>If ere I knew him, with more guilt, then what</L>
<L>My wishes and my thoughts containd; let wrath</L>
<L>Then make me her experiment, to trie</L>
<L>How much of paine, mortalitie can heare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy periur'd attestations cease; for though</L>
<L>The howres are few, since first you did conferre,</L>
<L>Yet you had both the pregnant thrift, to make</L>
<L>The time aduantagious to sinne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>Expresse,</L>
<L>Some mercie in your faith, and heare me speake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Keepe thy deniall 'tweene thy blisterd lippes.</L>
<L>I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> vtterd' thou art dead.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="22"/>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<P>Loue is no more.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alta.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dost weepe? I sooner thought t'haue seene the Flin<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Supple as Spunge; th'obdurate Diamond melt</L>
<L>At the Glow-wormes pale eie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>How hath the pride</L>
<L>Of Courts misse-led my youth, that you should thinke</L>
<L>I'ue lost, all tender complements of grace?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alta.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou wert a Virgin sweet, so precious in</L>
<L>Thy frame, that with the cordage of thy haire</L>
<L>Thou mightst haue fetterd Kings. Thy voice has marr'd</L>
<L>The beauties of the night. When thou didst sing</L>
<L>The quiet stars, would fall asleepe and winke.</L>
<L>Thou art all discord now: thy glorie's darke;</L>
<L>Thy thinne, and Rosiall blood, i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> turn'd to Inke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue outliu'd the helpe of penitence,</L>
<L>And benefit of hope.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oft haue I sai'd</L>
<L>Let's leaue the false, the buisie world and sleepe</L>
<L>Beneath our vines; Nature (not cunning) then,</L>
<L>Augments our wealth; the dew of heauen is cheape,</L>
<L>Nor need we pay for'th Sunnes warme light, If kinde</L>
<L>Diuinitie allow t'each humane soule</L>
<L>A starre; our issue w'ele increase, vntill</L>
<L>The bright and numerous throng be all imploi'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>But I am sterill as a wildernesse,</L>
<L>My name, is sickenesse to your memorie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Witnesse you silent powers, the crime is not</L>
<L>Deriu'd from me. T'explaine my innocence,</L>
<L>Know, she that heere I housd, t'affront thy pride,</L>
<L>Was my chaste sister, not my Concubine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then you are loiall still, t'oth Mariage vow.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>But; she treds the slimie path. <HI>Scoperta,</HI></L>
<L>Is now thy R<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uall in <HI>Sciolto's</HI> lust.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>All springs from the ambition of my guilt. —</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Although thy penitence be rash, it doth</L>
<L>Become thee well, and thou hast qui<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e dissolu'd</L>
<L>The stonie corners of my heart. This night</L>
<L><PB REF="23"/>I purposd thee a cruell death, but now</L>
<L>Rise, and continue mortall still—I'le lay</L>
<L>My mercy on thy Lip, and for it take</L>
<L>My last farewell—. I'le neuer see thee more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is a mercy that confounds the will</L>
<L>And strength of all my gratitude. O sad</L>
<L>Decree. You haue diuorc'd me from your Eyes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alta.</SPEAKER>
<L>Two neighboring Lillies whom rude winds disperse</L>
<L>'Mongst restlesse dust, may sooner meet vpon</L>
<L>Their stalkes agen, and kisse each other in</L>
<L>A second growth, then we our loues renew.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take heede (Sir) how you prophecy! For my</L>
<L>Humilitie with moist contrition ioyn'd,</L>
<L>May hope to wash my leprous staines away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>O no! my iealousie is growne so sicke, that my</L>
<L>Suspect enformes me, it will nere be cur'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>I creepe thus to my Toombe, indebted for</L>
<L>Your loue, till all the drowsie world shall rise</L>
<L>To generall Accompts; and then my want</L>
<L>Of earlier gratitude will make my Debt</L>
<L>A sinne—
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>O triuiall propertie of life!</L>
<L>Some doe attend the mighty warre, and make</L>
<L>Diuinitie their yoake; till for the sport</L>
<L>Of Kings th'augment the number of the dead.</L>
<L>Some walke in slipprie paths of Court, and feede</L>
<L>On silent smiles; the grauitie of mirth.</L>
<L>Some trauaile in the search of humane Arts,</L>
<L>But knowledge is reseru'd: She sits so high</L>
<L>In Cloudes, we cannot reach her with our Eye:</L>
<L>Or if with patient steps we to her climbe,</L>
<L>Death sayes we cannot reach her with our time.</L>
<L>For witherd age ariues, when numbring on</L>
<L>Our griefs not yeeres; the tedious space of life</L>
<L>We straite accuse. For life is like the spanne</L>
<L>Forc'd from a gowtie hand; which, as it gaines</L>
<L>Extent, and actiue length, the more it paines.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="23"/>
<HEAD>Act the fourth.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scene the first.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Dandolo, Besognia, Stoccata, Punto.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dandolo.</SPEAKER>
<L>MY iourney was by stealth, else I had brought</L>
<L>With these, Legions of Dukes to speake my birth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Besognia.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lady'gins t'enquire (Sir) after sleepe,</L>
<L>For it growes late.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dandolo.</SPEAKER>
<L>My corporall method</L>
<L>I will disorder, ere I'le misse her view.</L>
<L>This British Groate is thine; traficke for Pinnes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Besognia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Make the Deuill your Factor; Ther's a Stocke</L>
<L>To set vp with.
<STAGE>Flings it agen. Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dandolo.</SPEAKER>
<P>No bribes? I am belou'd.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Florello, Rossa, Molard.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>Brother, I wish you would auoid my haunts.</L>
<L>Tis not for my credit, nor yet for our</L>
<L>Dead fathers, thus to make your person knowne,</L>
<L>Being y'are illegitimate begot,</L>
<L>By the motion of the euill Spirit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></SPEAKER>
<P>Goe, let that fellow die.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, let him Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Punt<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Were we his heires, w'had cause to hasten his Decease.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>D'ye walke like <HI>Neptune</HI> in a maske,</L>
<L>Attended on by two o'th calme Windes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dandolo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Th'are Nobles of a supreame race. This is</L>
<L><HI>Stocccata</HI> call'd, and that <HI>Punto.</HI> They both</L>
<L>Are come to warrant my creation good</L>
<L>Vpon the Gauntlet of a Giant or a Whale.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Maintaine your birth—Were you my fathers Bawdes?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="24"/>
<SPEAKER>Stoccata.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas, you are young (Sir) you know not vs!</L>
<L>We cannot swell and rant like things that would</L>
<L>Be rather heard then felt: but we can thrust</L>
<L>Our Whineards home, with ioy and quiet too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Punto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweet heart; you are not read i'th'rudiments</L>
<L>Of wrath. You shall perceiue some that are lowd</L>
<L>And actiue with their Lungs; Courage in them</L>
<L>You may suspect: but when you see a coole</L>
<L>And silent anger like to ours, then keepe</L>
<L>Your wandring hands at home. Soft Sir, beware!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stoccata.</SPEAKER>
<P>Stay, woo't thou kill him <HI>(Punto)</HI> or shall I?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Punto.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'ue buisnesse now of a more serious garbe.</L>
<L>Dispatch him thy selfe. Earlie to morrow</L>
<L>I'le doe as much for thee on the two Zwits.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>D'ye make no more o'th'Infants o'the Earth?—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stoccata.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fie Sir. Draw your weapon in a Ladies</L>
<L>Chamber? You still displaie a courage ill</L>
<L>Brought vp, most vainlie nurturd (Sir) beleeue't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Punto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Forbid it Heauen; but you should haue free space</L>
<L>T'imploy your best strength in your defence.</L>
<L>But Sir, 'tis sober patience makes vs safe.</L>
<L>If now on eithers Haunch you did conferre</L>
<L>A kicke; our secret wisedome would direct</L>
<L>Vs how to beare it for the time, and in</L>
<L>Our owne aduantage too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is't possible?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stoccata.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heare Sir th'aduice of an old shot. I'ue hit</L>
<L>The marke more then once in my time, and tam'd</L>
<L>Many a mad Boy too. If either of's</L>
<L>Vouchsafe to greete ye with a hand or foot,</L>
<L>Take it, and be thankfull: le<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t by returne</L>
<L>Of wrath, worse doe ensue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not I beleeue't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Punto.</SPEAKER>
<L>He's young, <HI>Stoccata,</HI> carue him gentlie vp! —</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>They take me for a Capon. What Weapons</L>
<L>Fight ye with, Demiculuering or Drake?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stoccata.</SPEAKER>
<L>Steele of <HI>Toledo</HI> is all we manage—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="24"/>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>What then remaines but <HI>Rossa</HI> and <HI>Molard,</HI></L>
<L>Assault you two, I, my bastard Brother—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rossa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come Sir,—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Molard.</SPEAKER>
<L>We'le ierke you with our iron Rods—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stoc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Keepe your sword warme, it 'longs to the scabbard—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Punto.</SPEAKER>
<L>O Sir, your vallor still imports some want</L>
<L>Of a discreet and temperate breeding.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dandolo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tumultuous fights the vestments marre.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Charintha, Besognia.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charintha.</SPEAKER>
<L>His bountie nere will giue me cause t'aduance</L>
<L>My wit: he growes much troublesome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dandolo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lady! behold two Worthies here; Dragons</L>
<L>In fight. They come to preach my birth.</L>
<L>Th'are knowne to Fame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fame blew'em from her Breech!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dandolo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I say th'are Potentates; and they doe awe—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Chrysome Babe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Punto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Signior, you still forget</L>
<L>The quiet and the courteous wayes of spleene.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will trie your polliticke patience Sir —
<STAGE>kicks em.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Punto.</SPEAKER>
<L>You see we still are calme —</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stoccata.</SPEAKER>
<L>He has but thinne</L>
<L>Philosophie that cannot suffer this —</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charintha.</SPEAKER>
<P>You marmalet Count deserues as much too.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dandolo.</SPEAKER>
<P>I doe oppugne the motion with my scorne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<P>D'ye scorne (Sir) to be kick'd?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dandolo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pardon me Sir!</L>
<L>I say't alowd; The prowdest wight on Earth</L>
<L>Shall not kicke me, excepting your deare selfe.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Nienie.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Niente.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue priuacies (Madam) for your Eare! —</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>You, and your fierce Champions strait remoue;</L>
<L>Craule hence, and be not visible agen:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Punto.</SPEAKER>
<P>Enhaunce our pay, we'le kill him in the da<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dandolo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Agreed, Six Duck<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ts you shall number more.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Dandolo, Stoccata Punto.</STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="25" MS="y"/>
<SPEAKER>Niente.</SPEAKER>
<L>The neighbours say, fortie Seriants waite his</L>
<L>Departure hence, who giue him a new name.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charintha.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hah! What doe they call him?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Niente.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Florello,</HI> and</L>
<L>Report him brother vnto <HI>Altamont.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charintha.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Eies are infom'd, Two Faces more alli'd</L>
<L>In all deuotes of view I haue not seene.</L>
<L>The younger brother vnto <HI>Altamont</HI>;</L>
<L>Fantasticke too as Winds, and sillier then</L>
<L>A silenc'd Priest. Fate had much preferd me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Besogniae.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, it must be he. I'ue tane a strict</L>
<L>Suruay of's Nose; 'tis so like <HI>Altamonts.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charintha.</SPEAKER>
<L>He is alreadie so exhaust, that his</L>
<L>Wise bountie can no more be Argument</L>
<L>For wit: And now to haue this plea for his</L>
<L>Dismission is aboue my ioy. Signior!—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweet Loue, I haue beene bold to giue away</L>
<L>One or two of thy Farmes to these my Foll'wers,</L>
<L>They are kinde wretches both, and loue thee well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charintha.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeed?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes saith, They bid me rather then</L>
<L>Thou shouldst thus pine for loue to marrie thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charintha.</SPEAKER>
<P>Stand off! More distant yet.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wouldst view my Limmes?—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charintha.</SPEAKER>
<L>When you doe make your Christianitie</L>
<L>More knowne, you must be call'd <HI>Florello</HI>▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hah!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charintha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fortie blew Fiends wait to arrest you in</L>
<L>Your passage home.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<P>Madam, I am traduc'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charintha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Could your abusiue Arts make choice of none</L>
<L>But me? Be sure this visit is your last.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must not, dare not, leaue ye, till I'ue cleerd</L>
<L>The errours in this callumnie—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charintha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Returne,</L>
<L>Or you affront my power, and I shall thinke</L>
<L>Your loue, is, as your person, counterfeit.</L>
<L><PB REF="25"/>The strength of all my Charitie affoords</L>
<L>You but this Key, which in my Orchard Gate</L>
<L>You may imploy, and free you from th'Arrest.</L>
<L><HI>Besognia,</HI> I'le to bed. —</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Niente, Charintha, Besognia.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Florello, Rossa, Molard looke ghostly awhile at one another.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>A sober truth.</L>
<L>Summes I ow'd when I imbark'd for <HI>Pisa.</HI> —</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rossa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now shall I, like a melancholie worme,</L>
<L>Feede on raw Rootes.—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Molard.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sing Canticles of woe!</L>
<L>I must e'en goe tagge points in a Garret. —</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>This Key, with rescue o'th'young Rapiers of</L>
<L>The Law will bring vs home.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rossa.</SPEAKER>
<P>No moneis Sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith we must all disrobe, our Vestments old</L>
<L>Stitch on agen, and morgage these to raise</L>
<L>A Summe that may assist my librrtie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Molard.</SPEAKER>
<L>Creepe in our Rags of Tinder, in our thinne</L>
<L>And dustie webs agen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rossa.</SPEAKER>
<L>I feele a heard</L>
<L>Of small cattell graze on my left shoulder. —</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florellll.</SPEAKER>
<L>O my forward bountie! There's but sicke hope</L>
<L>My Iewels will returne; since custome shewes;</L>
<L>What Ladies thus from ther dull Sutors get</L>
<L>They doe preserue as Tribute to their wit.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt omnes.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Scoperta, and her Woman vnder a Canopy.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Woman.</SPEAKER>
<P>The longer moitie of the Night's vnspent.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scoperta.</SPEAKER>
<L>Since time grew old, he slowly findes his steps</L>
<L>I'th darke: by day he swifter moues. Get thee</L>
<L>To bed; The Casements of thine Eies are shut;</L>
<L><PB REF="26"/>Impris<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ning their deare Light.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Woman.</SPEAKER>
<P>Madam, good night.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scoperta.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come my <HI>Sciolto,</HI> and confirme the vertue of</L>
<L>Thy faith; or I disperse my Soule in Sighs,</L>
<L>And make this Chaire my easie monument.
<STAGE>Roads.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Altamont, Meruolle.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meruolle.</SPEAKER>
<L>All are departed that to <HI>Charintha</HI></L>
<L>Made visit: Your Seruants haue begunne</L>
<L>Their sleepe, and Guards are plac'd vpon the Gates.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are my bold Instruments in ambush laid,</L>
<L>And scatter'd for the best aduantage of</L>
<L>Their conceal'd action, and their view?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meruolle.</SPEAKER>
<P>They are.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<P>Expect me then beneath the Garden Mount.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Meruolle.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Altamont steales to Scoperta, and shews her his Armes besmeard with blood.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scoperta.</SPEAKER>
<P>You swelling Cloudes choake my afflicted sight▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Starres like scatterd embers fall. The Teares</L>
<L>Of men doe meete in Seas, and Seas orewhelme</L>
<L>The Earth. Th'amazed Heards howle to the Sunne</L>
<L>For helpe; whose Beames sucke moisture vp, till he</L>
<L>Hath made the flood his draught; but vomits all</L>
<L>In Showres agen; such as <HI>Deucalion</HI> saw!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scoperta.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nature (it seemes) is frighted from her health.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Behold my Corall hands, they seeme to blush</L>
<L>With guilt of humane sacrifice. Me thinkes</L>
<L>I looke like to a <HI>Memphian</HI> Priest, that had</L>
<L>Dissection made of <HI>Hecatombs</HI> t'appease</L>
<L>Their false Diuinitie. <HI>Alteza's</HI> dead.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scoperta.</SPEAKER>
<L>I want pretence to sooth my faith: Els I</L>
<L>Would hope your hands depriued her not of breath?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alta.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fathers that feed on Sonnes, and Sonnes that drinke</L>
<L>Their mothers blood, reach not that cruelty</L>
<L><PB REF="26"/>Which her sterne guilt did throw into my Breast.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scop.</SPEAKER>
<L>May some kinde Saint, weepe o're your Soule vntill</L>
<L>With holy dew, he wash this sinne away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou doest mis-spend thy vestall charitie.</L>
<L>I'th sollitary age of Night I come,</L>
<L>To finde those Angells that haue businesse now</L>
<L>On Earth, in Synod heere with thee: hoping</L>
<L>I shall receiue reward for my iust Act.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scoperta.</SPEAKER>
<L>The howers that gaue her opportunitie</L>
<L>To erre, were knowne so few; that my beliefe</L>
<L>Concludes her guiltlesse of the actuall sinne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Before the hindmost part of her vex'd Soule</L>
<L>Forsooke her thrilling Lipps, she did confesse,</L>
<L><HI>Sciolto</HI> had perform'd all circumstance</L>
<L>That doth ingender Man. <HI>Sciolto</HI> too,</L>
<L>Confirm'd her attestation as a truth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scoperta.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be deafe (sweete heauen) to this. Did <HI>Sciolto</HI></L>
<L>Iterate her foule speech?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>He did, which I,</L>
<L>Ore hear'd, and forc'd a passage to his Heart.</L>
<L>From its warme Throane, I snatch'd the aking Lumpe,</L>
<L>And threw it straight vnto a hungry Fiend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scoperta.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is he dead too? The Genius of the world</L>
<L>Is sicke, all Formes must cease.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<P>Dost weepe for him?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scoperta.</SPEAKER>
<L>O Sir, should I restraine the flux, my Eies</L>
<L>Would drop from their loose Stringes instead of Teares.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<P>This obsequie, doth make Compassion sinne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scoperta.</SPEAKER>
<L>O <HI>Sciolto.</HI> Art thou so early fled,</L>
<L>To tast eternitie, and vnknowne fate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stint thy hoarce Dirge, pernicious Whore. I had</L>
<L>Some hope, the interuiew that you inioy'd</L>
<L>Might be enforc'd by his vnruly strength:</L>
<L>But now, I finde it was with thy consent</L>
<L>Procur'd. Y'haue struggled in each others lust.</L>
<L>All now is euident as light.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scoperta.</SPEAKER>
<L>I bring</L>
<L><PB REF="27"/>My innocence, to'th'cleere suruay of Heauen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Though dull, to Men of harsh, strict discipline,</L>
<L>Yet know, I haue some cunning in my rage.</L>
<L>I came to fright this secret from thy Heart:</L>
<L>M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Hands I did not bath in humane blood,</L>
<L><HI>Alteza,</HI> and <HI>Sciolto</HI> are aliue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sco.</SPEAKER>
<L>This ioy will make my Heart dance in my Breast.—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alta.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sinke into th'Earth, where sorrow dwells. Ere yon—</L>
<L>Dimme Morne shall adde one Howre vnto her Age,</L>
<L><HI>Scioltos</HI> Sowle shall take a doubtfull flight:</L>
<L>It only stai'd to mingle company</L>
<L>With thine. My anger was so iust, I Would</L>
<L>Not prosecute thy life; vntill my doubts</L>
<L>Were cleer'd. Goe, goe, and number o're thy Beades.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scoperta</SPEAKER>
<L>Is there in all your vaines, no drop (vnmix'd</L>
<L>With Gaule) that from our Mother is deriu'd,</L>
<L>And so may tempt compassion from your Breast?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Alteza</HI> mournes, as if t'expiate</L>
<L>A Nation with her griefe. Hadst thou reueald</L>
<L>Such penitence, it might haue softned my</L>
<L>Decree. But thou art sowre and sterne of Soule.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scoperta.</SPEAKER>
<P>No mercie, for our Noble Mothers sake?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Mother when she lay, a cold paterne for</L>
<L>The figure on her Toombe, spent her last breath</L>
<L>In praise of thee. Quoth she; For my sake vse</L>
<L>Thy Sister well: th'acqaintance that she hath</L>
<L>In Heauen is great. I'th blossome of her growth</L>
<L>She shall ore'come the Eies of men, and in</L>
<L>Her Age, she shall haue skill in Prophecie.</L>
<L>But O false lore! Our Mother kind, (whom I</L>
<L>A <HI>Sybill</HI> held) thou now hast proou'd a Witch.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scoperta.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am too weake to force from your beliefe</L>
<L>Mistakes so strong.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe pray, the Howres are swift:</L>
<L>I'ue purposd thee a pris'ner heere till my</L>
<L>Returne. — This is a sicklie Rhume▪ and not</L>
<L>Compunction in my Eyes. —</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="27"/>
<SPEAKER>Scoperta.</SPEAKER>
<L>The last of all</L>
<L>My merits shall be calld obedience to</L>
<L>Your will: If you doe owe a kindnesse to</L>
<L>Your selfe; thinke on Religion and the Lawes.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nature doe thou direct my spleene. The Lawes</L>
<L>Are sinfullie contriu'd. Iustice should weigh</L>
<L>The present crime, not future inforence</L>
<L>On Deedes. But now they cheapen blood: 'tis spilt</L>
<L>To punish the example, not the guilt.</L>
<L>Religion too, on our Italian Earth,</L>
<L>Growes like the Cedar big and high; but yeelds</L>
<L>No fruit. The abiect race of men she doth</L>
<L>Confound with hope, and bids them not obay,</L>
<L>T'augment humilitie, but her owne sway.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Meruolle, Sciolto, and three Mutes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meruolle.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your strength does but intangle ye the more.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le not be trus'd (Sir) like a Pullet thus—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meruolle.</SPEAKER>
<L>Leaue nothing that can minister defence.</L>
<L>Disarme him of his Pinnes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pare my nailes too.—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meruolle.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall be angerd strait, till you bestow</L>
<L>The time to bite'm off. Soone as we spi'd</L>
<L>You scaling ore the Orchard wall; we guess'd</L>
<L>The hopes of your visit. There haue beene snares</L>
<L>Lai'd for your feete, ere since you left the House. —</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Meruolle, Mutes, hauing rifled him of his Pistols and his sword.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>There is some danger in this chance, my dull</L>
<L>Heart beates with slow, and ominous leasure. —</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Scoperta from her windore.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scoperta.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pale Planet shine! It must be he. My Eares</L>
<L>Perswade me they oretooke his voice. Sir, Sir! —</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="28"/>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hah! <HI>Scoperta?</HI> A cruell destinie</L>
<L>Ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> murdred all our ioy. endeuouring an</L>
<L>Add <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> for stealth of thee, I was surpris'd,</L>
<L>Disa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>md; euen heere 'ith presence of my Starres.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scoperta.</SPEAKER>
<L>There's not a Starre in all the Firmament</L>
<L>Belongs to vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>O none! Or if there be,</L>
<L>Thei<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> influence is so weake that at</L>
<L>This distance Babes may blow'em out. Sure ou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Creation we haue tooke vnknowne to Fate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scoperta.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our loue was of too nimble growth vnlesse</L>
<L>Philosophie giue hope, that after death</L>
<L>We may conuerse; this is the last of all</L>
<L>Our interuiewes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>That fatall Prophecie</L>
<L>Will shake my Soule from out my flesh; and like</L>
<L>Some tame Hermit I shall vnwounded die.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scoperta.</SPEAKER>
<L>The word that's heard abreuiates our discourse</L>
<L>And li<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e: the Sand that limits both is falne</L>
<L>Into the reach of number now: and I</L>
<L>Haue spent with thee the hasty time prefix'd</L>
<L>For a deuout imployment of my Beades.</L>
<L>The murderers are within.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Grimme wild horrour!</L>
<L>Hast thou no weapons there that I may vse</L>
<L>T'anihilate their vigor and their shape?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scoperta.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vnto thy Lips I'ld throw a kisse; but with</L>
<L>The strings of my poore solitary Lute</L>
<L>They'<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e bound my hands! —</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto</SPEAKER>
<L>O my hot rage! I could</L>
<L>Spit fire till I enkindle yonder Groue,</L>
<L>Raising a flame that might perplex the Earth,</L>
<L>And make'em thinke Heauen had dropp'd a Planet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scoperta.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I could weepe vntill I quench'd that <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ame,</L>
<L>And drew suspition that a second Flood</L>
<L>Was come to drowne mortallitie agen!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>This sudden eleuation of the Soule▪</L>
<L><PB REF="28"/>Presageth death: as if it practis'd how</L>
<L>To rise, and climbe ere she begins her flight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scoperta.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whence is that noise?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le be as calme as are <HI>Arabian</HI> winds.</L>
<L><HI>Scoperta,</HI> stay; Vnheard we will conuerse. —</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sco.</SPEAKER>
<L>They come, they come, deare loue, for euermore farewell▪</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>The Mutes snatch her from the Window.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>O for the Giant race, to helpe me heaue</L>
<L>Those Mountaines vp; that I might burie this</L>
<L>Proud Structure and my selfe! Yon burlie Oake</L>
<L>(Whose Roots reach hell) I'le manage till I pownd</L>
<L>And batter all the Marble into Flowre.—</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Altamont, Meruolle.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>You haue oreheard, what will your knowledge grieue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Her Soule is ill prepar'd▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meruolle.</SPEAKER>
<L>I gaue command</L>
<L>They should awhile delay her death, lest want</L>
<L>Of leasure might destroy her penitence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Remaine within the summons of my call:</L>
<L>And leaue me heere. I charge thee by thy Vow,</L>
<L>And our friendships deare vse, that thou depart.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Meruolle.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<P>Speake what thou art?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Some call me <HI>Altamont.</HI></L>
<L>I'ue seene thee walke armd like a Magazin▪</L>
<L>With small Artillerie entrench'd: but thou</L>
<L>Art fitly now prepar'd for sufferance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not thy tame sacrifice, but victorie</L>
<L>I'le be. For naked as I am I will</L>
<L>Resist my death; and since vnfurnish'd to</L>
<L>Reuenge, yet I shall trouble thy best strength.—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Sciolto,</HI> though, thou merit trechery▪</L>
<L>And opposition that, by darkest stealth,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" EXTENT="2+ words" DISP="〈◊◊…〉"/> of thy luxurious soule,</L>
<L><PB REF="29"/>Yet I will giue thee faire and equall Game.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<P>False tyranie!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay. This I will performe▪</L>
<L>And 'tis to know the rigour of thy might,</L>
<L>What wondrous flame and spirits doe possesse</L>
<L>Thy spacious Breast.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<P>There's relish of intent!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'ld learne the prouidence and iustice of</L>
<L>My Fate; trie if they'll let me fall before</L>
<L>Th'incounter of thy beastiall strength; thou that</L>
<L>Augments't thy sinnes t'orecome the memorie</L>
<L>Of Heauen: in sillie hope, th'accompts may be</L>
<L>Vnwillinglie surua<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'d, because th'are long.</L>
<L>Receiue thy Sword. —</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<P>Miracle of bountie!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>If whilst we struggle in the pride of hope</L>
<L>Thou canst so weaken my defence, that I</L>
<L>Become disarm'd; thy libertie is gain'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>With solemne penitence I could accuse</L>
<L>My crimes 'gainst thee: but griefe's akinne to feare.</L>
<L>This great demeanu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e of thy spleene diuides</L>
<L>Th'intent of Gratitude. I know not which</L>
<L>T'affoord thee most, my enuie, or my loue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alta.</SPEAKER>
<L>The moone hath now put on her brightest Robe;</L>
<L>My anger too, doth carrie fire enough</L>
<L>To light vs to the charge▪ Guard well thy Heart. —</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<P>A little respite giue,— Must we needs <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ight?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>You then would cousen me of my reuenge? —</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yet stay! — Know I doe loue thy Sister well.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alta.</SPEAKER>
<L>Marke (sweet Heauen) with what exalted triumph</L>
<L>He boasts the fowle remembrance of his sinne.—</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Thrusts at him.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stiffe as a columne! —</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Th'Arcadian wrastler told</L>
<L>Young <HI>Theseus</HI> so; but he did yeeld as if</L>
<L>His sinnewes had binne made of silke. So fierce?—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le worke thy strength so low, that Virgins shall</L>
<L><PB REF="29" MS="y"/>Haue power to shakle thee with spinners Thrids—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thus I will bore thy flesh, till thou become</L>
<L>Transparant as a Sieve—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>This closure hath</L>
<L>Intangled vs, let's make another charge?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Euen thus diuided Billowes part, that they</L>
<L>May meete in greater foame—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wilt thou not bleede?</L>
<L>Not yet?—I skirmish with vnbodied Aire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy guillt betrai's thy hand vnto mistakes,</L>
<L>And thus my iniurd Spirits greete thy life—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<P>That Wound gapes like to a yawning Giant.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont</SPEAKER>
<L>So hot is thy lasciuious blood, that as</L>
<L>I sprinkle it, it scaldes my hands—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>I reele</L>
<L>Before thy breast, and stumble at a Wart—</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Falls.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alta.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thy Sword's my Captiue now. <HI>Meruolle,</HI> hoa!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Sciol<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> haue some courage yet, le<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t in my Teeth,</L>
<L>If thou art kinde, come neerer with my Throate—</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Meruolle, Mutes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>O the Celestiall powers are iust. See there,</L>
<L>He bleeds like to a Spring, that borders on</L>
<L>The Rubicke Sea, whilst I remaine vntuch'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meruolle.</SPEAKER>
<P>Has he not lost the benefit of breath?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alta.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stop all his wounds, and giue him time to spend</L>
<L>The rest of's moisture in repentant Teares—</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>They binde him with scarfes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<P>My wounds clos'd vp, what meanes this courtesy?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>That thou might'st leasure haue to pray. Be sure</L>
<L><STAGE>(<HI>Meruolle.</HI>)</STAGE>
when's deuotions haue ariu'd</L>
<L>Vnto a powerfull length; you strangle him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<P>Can thy young honour stoope to such low flight?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="30"/>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vnto resistance equall, I exposd</L>
<L>My strength, to try thy courage and my fate.</L>
<L>This was my iusti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e to my selfe: <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ustice</L>
<L>I'le giue to thee: Thy crimes doe merit death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>O sooth my last ambition then▪ be thou</L>
<L>My Executioner.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art disarm'd,</L>
<L>Thy blooming honors now are wither'd on</L>
<L>Thy Crest. I should depriue my Anger of</L>
<L>Her fame, to be thy actiue opposite.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto▪</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Scoperta,</HI> stay. My Soule shall houer straite</L>
<L>With thine. Stay for me in the Milky-path.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let <HI>Italy</HI> avowch the iust demeane</L>
<L>Of my reuenge. Dull <HI>Brittaines</HI> know no wrath.</L>
<L>Th'vnskillfull youth, that equall Duell giue</L>
<L>To him that first incensd the blood; but tempt</L>
<L>The curtesie of Fate, such take delight</L>
<L>To stroke abuse, pay Iniuries, with right.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meruolle.</SPEAKER>
<L>This way (Sir) leades vnto your Graue. You shall</L>
<L>Haue space, to gaine some friendship with the Saints —</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Meruolle, Sciolto, Mutes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>A sudden frost congeales my Heart; I shrinke</L>
<L>Like crooked Age; I am vnwieldy on</L>
<L>My ioynts, as if my vaines were empty growne.—</L>
<STAGE>Opens his Dublet.</STAGE>
<L>Wounded. His point has stollne into my Breast.</L>
<L>Oh helpe. I'ue yet some vse for life. Th'nice search,</L>
<L>I made to know Heaun's secret iustice is</L>
<L>Aueng'd. (Bold Earth!) I weepe into the Sea,</L>
<L>And sigh t'augment the windes. Repentance is</L>
<L>An immateriall Salue, it cures th'vnsound</L>
<L>Diseased Soule, but not the Bodies wound.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Reeles off, Exit.</STAGE>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="30"/>
<HEAD>Act the fift.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scene the first.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Niente, Alteza in her Night Gowne.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Guard vpon my Gates, and haue they there</L>
<L>Binne plac'd ere since the first ariuall of</L>
<L>The Night?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Niente.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Meruolle</HI> keepes the Keyes, ho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>le let</L>
<L>No seruant be awake about the house.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Sunne begins to bath i'th'Mornings Teares▪</L>
<L>Hast thou <HI>Lucio</HI> call'd, and bid <HI>Pytho</HI> mix</L>
<L>With him in a sad Song?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Niente.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue Madam.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more (<HI>Niente</HI>) shalt thou seruice doe</L>
<L>For me: last night I told thee I had lost</L>
<L>My vanitie: that courtly Lady serue</L>
<L>Who findes it first. But least thy wants augment</L>
<L>Thy Sinnes, my charitie affoords thee this—</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Flings him a Purse.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Niente.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well I'm resolu'd to mend, or become worse.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<LG>
<PB REF="31"/>
<HEAD>A Song betweene two Boyes.</HEAD>
<LG N="1">
<HEAD>1</HEAD>
<L>THis <HI>Lady,</HI> ripe, and calme, and fresh,</L>
<L>As <HI>Easterne</HI> Summers are;</L>
<L>Must now forsake both <HI>Time,</HI> and <HI>Flesh,</HI></L>
<L>T'adde Light to some small <HI>Starre.</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG N="2">
<HEAD>2</HEAD>
<L>Whilst yet aliue, each <HI>Starre</HI> decay'd▪</L>
<L>Shee may relieue with Light:</L>
<L>But Death leads Beauty to a shade</L>
<L>More cold more darke, then <HI>Night.</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG N="1">
<HEAD>1</HEAD>
<L>The sawcy faith of man doth blind</L>
<L>His pride, 'till it conduce</L>
<L>To Destine all his abiect kind</L>
<L>For some Eternall vse.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="2">
<HEAD>2</HEAD>
<L>But aske not Bodies (doom'd to die)</L>
<L>To what abode they goe;</L>
<L>Since <HI>Knowledge</HI> is, but <HI>sorrowes Spy,</HI></L>
<L>It is not safe to know.</L>
</LG>
</LG>
<STAGE>Enter Meruolle.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meruolle.</SPEAKER>
<L>Howle, howle, vntill you wake the inhabitants</L>
<L>Of Graues! till you disquiet all the Spheares;</L>
<L>And put harmonious Nature out of tune,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>What meanes this fatall summon, that doth make</L>
<L>Amazement cold, as is <HI>Iberian</HI> Ice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Great <HI>Altamont</HI> (your Lord) who still was prompt</L>
<L>To curbe th'incitements of your wrath; threw wise</L>
<L><PB REF="31"/>Aduantage from his reach, and struggled with</L>
<L>The bold <HI>Sciolto,</HI> in an equall warre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>Downe holy flame. When Hope doth sicken so,</L>
<L>I would not haue the power to prophecy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meruolle.</SPEAKER>
<L>The surly Lyon, and the testy Bore,</L>
<L>Did nere maintaine, resistance with like fierce</L>
<L>And ruinous returne of strength: for from</L>
<L>Their Eyes such Lightning flew, that Villagers</L>
<L>(Whose early labours till'd the Earth) did thinke</L>
<L>Rash <HI>Phaeton</HI> did scourge the fiery Teeme</L>
<L>Agen. <HI>Sciolto</HI> chipp'd▪ gagged with wounds;</L>
<L>Did bleede away his strength. This his false Sword</L>
<L>Your Husband bade me prostrate at your feet—</L>
<L>And 'tis the last memoriall of his loue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ambiguous History! He conquerour,</L>
<L>Yet this the last memoriall of his loue!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wise Heauen did mocke your <HI>Altamont</HI>: for whilst</L>
<L>Ore ioy'd with victory, he spies in's Breast</L>
<L>A large deepe wound, and thence his Soule tooke flight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>O my poore Lord! how soone hast thou begunne</L>
<L>Thy immortalitie. The hasty Sparke</L>
<L>So vp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ard mounts, and then no more is seene.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meruolle.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'th'last remainder of his dying speech,</L>
<L>He briefly told his Testament; which doth</L>
<L>Containe imployments sad, and such as you</L>
<L>Must actuate strait. To please his Ghost, shew now</L>
<L>A little loyaltie and loue, Rise, and</L>
<L>Be conducted by my slow steps. I will</L>
<L>Enforme your knowledge all that he enioyn'd</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>Th'obedience which I <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>canted to his life,</L>
<L>Vnto his memory I'le strictly pay.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meruolle.</SPEAKER>
<L>You haue a losse that doth out-speake complai<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>▪</L>
<L>If sweete and pliant discipline of Courts,</L>
<L>If feats of mighty Warre, or sober A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ts</L>
<L>Aduance th'esteeme of humane quali<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ie;</L>
<L>'Tis fit your <HI>Altamont</HI> we striue to raise,</L>
<L>Aboue the charitie or skill of praise▪</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="32"/><HI>Enter Florello, Rossa, Molard, in their old habits, Dandolo, Stoccata, Punto, bound.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who did assist your passage to this walke?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rossa.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Meruolle</HI> Sir, with whom we vs'd your name.</L>
<L>Doe you obserue the Count, and his two leane</L>
<L>Ianizaries?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<P>What in captiuity?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rossa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Certaine stratagems (Sir) haue binne leuel'd</L>
<L>'Gainst the Prerogatiue of your li<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e ro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>all.</L>
<L><HI>Molard.</HI> Ere since the h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pe of day▪ they wai<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ed your</L>
<L>Descent from the Cloyster Bridge: but doubting</L>
<L>Their owne courage, and meeting vs disguis'd,</L>
<L>Thus in our originall weedes; they would</L>
<L>Haue brib'd vs for two Pistolets t'assist</L>
<L>The prosecution of your death. Our Grace</L>
<L>And strength bound them to their good behauiour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>They walke like Caterpillers on a Leafe. —</L>
<STAGE>Takes Dandolo aside.</STAGE>
<L>Yeeld me the cause why you contriu'd my death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dandolo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good faith (Sir) for no harme.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Flor<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>llo.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Giue me a Knife!—</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>They search Dandolo.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rossa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here is one belong'd to <HI>Hans van Geulicke.</HI></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Florello cuts Dandolos bonds, and gives him the Knife.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take your selfe solemnly aside and cut</L>
<L>Your Throat! do't strait, and neatly too, y'had best.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dandolo</SPEAKER>
<P>The motion I d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>slike, 'tis dangerous.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>Haue you three throats, can you reuiue as oft</L>
<L>As you are kill'd, to take new punishment,</L>
<L>That thus you mutinie 'gainst kind reason?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dandolo.</SPEAKER>
<L>These thousand yeeres 't has b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n obseru'd, th'eldest</L>
<L>Brothers of her house (Sir) could nere endure</L>
<L>To cut their Throates.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis fit (deare Count) that you</L>
<L>Must die; I'm els vniust vnto my selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="32"/>
<SPEAKER>Dandolo.</SPEAKER>
<L>With sapi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nt Arts, we will proiect to saue</L>
<L>Th'reputation of your i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>stice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<P>As how?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dandolo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will promulgate I am dead, and both,</L>
<L>My Champions heere shall sw<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>r't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stoccata.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wele venture one</L>
<L>Commandement to saue another sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>This cannot satisfy. How ere (Sir Count)</L>
<L>If you will patiently accept your death.</L>
<L>I'le furnish ye with Guides, for your last iaunt.</L>
<L>You <HI>Punto,</HI> and <HI>Stoccata</HI> too! No more</L>
<L>Of your phylosophie. Fix Brow, to Brow,</L>
<L>Knock out, each others Braines, and shew your Lord</L>
<L>The way, vnto th'Elizian-Field. Doe it</L>
<L>At first encounter too; For I'm in haste—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stoccata.</SPEAKER>
<L>Slight Sir, I nere was in Elizium, I.</L>
<L>Nor should I finde the way thither, though Signior</L>
<L>Argos, lent me Nintie Nine of his Eies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then <HI>Punto</HI> shall be conduct to ye both.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Punto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good Signior, any curtesie but this</L>
<L>You may command. You still doe most presume</L>
<L>Vpon the calmest, and th'easie Nature.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rossa.</SPEAKER>
<L>They all are forfeittures to th'Law. If you'le</L>
<L>Bestow'em but as prisners vnto us,</L>
<L>They shall suffer, or giue vs large ransome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>How? a ransome? Th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>se Two are poorer then</L>
<L>Carthusian-Monkes: leane as a Romish Lent.</L>
<L>Slaues, who pretend sicknesse, that they may lie</L>
<L>In Hospitalls to steale the Sheets. Achornes</L>
<L>They eate, such as Westphalia-Hoggs doe scorne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rossa.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Count (Sir) will vntie his Strings for'em.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dandolo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ransome, I'le giue: for I doe hate to die.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>The ransome must</L>
<L>Be small. Shuffle'em together: and pack</L>
<L>'Em hence. I will not heare a sillable</L>
<L>Of thankes. <HI>Rossa,</HI> see'em hors'd for Millaine.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt all but Florello.</STAGE>
<STAGE><PB REF="33"/><HI>Enter Charintha to him.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charintha.</SPEAKER>
<L>O dismall change! does your victo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ous Sword</L>
<L>Hang now on aged Belt of Bandeleere?</L>
<L>Is your high Plume moulted to a sprigge, small,</L>
<L>As if 'twere made o'th wing of a Beetle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who can resist the frownes of destiny?</L>
<L>My suffrance giues my merits their reward.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charintha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your speech was wont to be in a more high</L>
<L>Exalted Key: lowd as a Gulph! Your heart</L>
<L>Was full of ligges, and your feet did wander</L>
<L>Euen like Autumns dust.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>Affect so much</L>
<L>Humilitie as may imploy your thoughts</L>
<L>With more compassion on my ru'nou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> fall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charintha.</SPEAKER>
<P>I threw on you perpetuall banishment.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'm come to manifest the sinne of my</L>
<L>Disguise▪ though it proceeded more from hope</L>
<L>T'inioy your person then your wealth. Witnesse</L>
<L>Each nimble Register of humane Thoughts!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charintha.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Has got a sweet and powerfull way in speech.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is my reall <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hape, in which I doe</L>
<L>Appeare, a thinne and witherd Souldier borne,</L>
<L>I'th'later age of warre: When glorie's sicke,</L>
<L>And honour triuiall as the spleene of Babes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charintha.</SPEAKER>
<P>He was not wont to vse this Dialect.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>Grant now (thou beautious wealth of <HI>Italy</HI>)</L>
<L>An expiation for my crimes; For know,</L>
<L>I would be cleane when I shall dedicate</L>
<L>My future vowes to th'absent Altar of</L>
<L>Thy Heart: lest I doe loose the vse of my</L>
<L>Idolatry; and make repentance sinne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charintha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe all harmonious gifts reside within</L>
<L>Such course and humble weedes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>Destroy me not</L>
<L>With scorne: I know you Ladies most delight</L>
<L>I'th'fraile surface of the body, in name,</L>
<L><PB REF="33"/>And guilded pompe, which was the fatall cause</L>
<L>I practis'd them on you:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charintha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y' endeere the worst</L>
<L>Of fashion vnto vs, by making it</L>
<L>A custome in your selues. If men did not</L>
<L>Prouide such follies for our sight, we knew</L>
<L>Not where to finde their vse, for they digest</L>
<L>Them first, then they become our nourishment.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vaine men. We alter our creation so</L>
<L>With female shapes, that Heauen scarce knowes its stam<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>And Nature (that distinction still commands</L>
<L>T'each Sex) forgets the worke of her owne hands.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charintha.</SPEAKER>
<L>I nere beheld a feature masculine</L>
<L>Till now: had you but thus appeard vnto</L>
<L>My first suruay, I might haue lou'd in haste,</L>
<L>And yet excus'd the rashnesse of my eies.</L>
<L>I ginne to feele some danger in my stay.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ere you depart, a small memoriall from</L>
<L>Your hands, I craue, to weare vpon my crest,</L>
<L>That it may tempt kinde fate to looke on me,</L>
<L>When I in glorious battell striue; and</L>
<L>I will absent my selfe for euermore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charintha.</SPEAKER>
<L>I nothing keepe for such sad vse, as to</L>
<L>Depriue me of so sweet a miracle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>Grant my request, or I'le pursue your steps</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charintha.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you continue still to beg, I feare</L>
<L>My bounty will prooue rash: and I shall giue</L>
<L>So much of loue, as you can ne're repay. —</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>O my auspicious starres! Should I not now</L>
<L>Make vse of your good influence, I were</L>
<L>Vnworthy of your care. —
<STAGE>Enter Meruolle.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meruolle.</SPEAKER>
<L>The choice you make</L>
<L>Can nere deserue your chaste and lawfull fire</L>
<L>She is <HI>Florello</HI> of a heart and straine</L>
<L>Too insolent for nuptiall happinesse:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou hast bin cald my friend. But if thy spleene</L>
<L>Continue a dislike of her, I'le blow thee from</L>
<L><PB REF="34"/>My memory, and with my chiefest strength</L>
<L>I'le punish thy missetake —</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meruolle.</SPEAKER>
<L>A des'late griefe</L>
<L>Will more become thy breast then this proud rage.</L>
<L>Thy brother's dead, and his decease caus'd by</L>
<L>Her sisters pride.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charintha.</SPEAKER>
<P>My sisters husband dead.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>Into my <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ares thou hast a horror powr'd</L>
<L>That hath already stiffened euerie haire</L>
<L>On my amazed skull into a Reed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charintha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wilt thou neglect to cherish the swift growth</L>
<L>Of our new loues?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meruolle.</SPEAKER>
<L>Like to her sister she</L>
<L>But counterfeits a passionate esteeme,</L>
<L>That thy fond Nature she might tempt beneath</L>
<L>Her rule. If <HI>Altamont</HI> be deare vnto</L>
<L>Thy thought, leaue her, and straight attend his Hearse,</L>
<L>That in the Chappell waits thy obsequie.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charintha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Th' inspir'd Needle's not more true vnto</L>
<L>The North, the Sunne to his diurnall race,</L>
<L>Nor Riuers to the Maine; then I to thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sorrow and loue, my senses doe diuide.</L>
<L>If I remayne with thee, then only loue</L>
<L>I serue, if with sad fleps, I tread the way</L>
<L>Vnto my Brothers Herse, I both obey.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou dost requite the skornes which I did throw</L>
<L>On thy first loue. My destiny must needs</L>
<L>Be tragicke now: since the contracted scope</L>
<L>Of all my ioy, rests in diseased hope.
<STAGE>Exit▪</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Meruolle, Alteza.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meruolle.</SPEAKER>
<L>Behold the Throne, your Lord commanded me</L>
<L>Prepare: and heere you must be pleas'd to sit. —</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can this aduancement ought refer to your</L>
<L>Delight, or to my Lords last Testament?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meruolle.</SPEAKER>
<L>Iustice hath laid her sword within your reach:</L>
<L><PB REF="34"/>And you haue power to sh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ath it so; that where</L>
<L>You execute, you may a murder doe,</L>
<L>Or sacrifice. Bring the delinquents in.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Sciolto, Scoperta, at seuerall dores, each led in, bound and hoodwinkd, by two Mutes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Sciolto</HI> and <HI>Scoperta</HI> still aliue?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy spirit <HI>Altamont</HI> ascended with</L>
<L>The loue of all my chiefest orizons.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meruolle.</SPEAKER>
<L>These two were by your husbands iealousie▪</L>
<L>And hate, ordaind for death: but ere that we</L>
<L>Could actuate his will; his noble breast</L>
<L>Receiu'd a wound, that bad him strait prouide</L>
<L>For 's owne eternity. The last of all</L>
<L>His speech, referd them both vnto your power.</L>
<L>You may appoint them liue or die: and I'm</L>
<L>Oblig'd by vow, to see perform'd what you</L>
<L>Command.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<P>O dire, sinister accident!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meruolle.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Iewels, and your wealth, I haue pack'd vp,</L>
<L>To ease our flight, when we haue finish'd</L>
<L>This vsurpation of the Lawes. Let them</L>
<L>Inioy their eyes; that they may know their Iudge.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>The Mutes vnmuffle'em.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scoperta.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hah, <HI>Sciolto</HI>!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Scoperta,</HI> O my Girle!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meruolle.</SPEAKER>
<P>Keepe them diuided from each others reach▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thought thy beauties had beene darke and cold,</L>
<L>And th'adst (ere this) begun an easie sleepe</L>
<L>Within thy silent Graue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scoperta.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I suppos'd thee fled</L>
<L>A Harbenger to Heauen: with purpose to</L>
<L>Bespeake my Billet neere to thine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Since this sad night, did blind the drowsi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> world,</L>
<L>They thus haue manacled my strength. They'ue watch'd</L>
<L>My hardy violence so tame, that now</L>
<L><PB REF="35"/>Each featherd Forrester roosts in my Beard.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scoperta.</SPEAKER>
<L>We cannot (Sir) be mortall long; therefore</L>
<L>Receiue a hope our sufferance will cease.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meruolle.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Sciolto,</HI> now requite the leysure I</L>
<L>Haue giuen thy penitence, by rendring straight</L>
<L>Vnto the world, how farre thou didst corrupt</L>
<L>These Ladies with thy guilt. For know, I still</L>
<L>Perswaded <HI>Altamont</HI> thy lust inioi'd</L>
<L>No more, then what concern'd wishes or hope.</L>
<L>And I was vsher'd to'th beliefe of this,</L>
<L>By knowledge of those secret spies which he</L>
<L>Imploy'd to watch your personall remooues,</L>
<L>About the House: whose labours euer miss'd</L>
<L>Of finding that successe he prophecy'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe confesse m'imagination once</L>
<L>Did sinne against them both: but if it ere</L>
<L>Extended vnto act; let me lose Heauen▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meruolle.</SPEAKER>
<L>If <HI>Altamont</HI> were now aliue, he would</L>
<L>Permit this vtterance cleere his fayth. Madam,</L>
<L>You heare that he <HI>Scoperta</HI> vindicates</L>
<L>By oath; though his owne crime doth carry an</L>
<L>Import more euident, and blacke; but yet</L>
<L>When you behold his feature, and his youth,</L>
<L>Your mercy may conceiue t'were pity that</L>
<L>He should so soone depart from time and flesh.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, you haue skill to know my womanhood</L>
<L>Is weake as ignorance, or sleepe. Why should</L>
<L>You seat me heere, thus to dispose of Law:</L>
<L>That ne're knew any iustice, but reuenge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meruolle.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your sentence I am bound to execute.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>Haue I not heard you say, my Husband did</L>
<L>Ordaine them both for death? T'would ill become</L>
<L>The duty of my knowledge t'alter his</L>
<L>Decree.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meruolle.</SPEAKER>
<L>Keepe your intent, I will vsurpe</L>
<L>The office of your tongue. Mutes, strangle them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>If in thy functions, gentle Nature claime</L>
<L><PB REF="35"/>An interest, let vs imbrace, and vse</L>
<L>Solemnity, before we doe forsake</L>
<L>Each others view.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meruolle.</SPEAKER>
<L>I grant what you</L>
<L>Request: make your performance short; whilst I</L>
<L>Reueale m'opinions (Lady) to your eare.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Sciolto, and Scoperta kneele to each other.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>O <HI>Scoperta!</HI> this is the last of all</L>
<L>Our busie dreames; what we possesse is but</L>
<L>Imaginary now: Thy shadow I,</L>
<L>Embrace, not thee: for like to it, thou'lt flie</L>
<L>From my enioyment, and no more be seene!—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scoperta.</SPEAKER>
<L>So much of various fate, so soone expres'd</L>
<L>Two louers yet nere knew; since simpathy</L>
<L>First dwelt on Earth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ere long we must be cold,</L>
<L>Cold, cold my Loue, and wrapp'd in stubborne sheets</L>
<L>Of lead: hows'd in a deepe, a gloomy vault;</L>
<L>Where no society will mix with vs,</L>
<L>But what shall quicken from our tainted limmes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scoperta.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whilst still ther's noise, and busines in the world;</L>
<L>Whilst still the warres grow loud, and battels ioyne;</L>
<L>Whilst Kings their Queenes salute in Iuory beds.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>But O! how many Ages may succeed</L>
<L>In Heauens darke Kalender; ere we agen</L>
<L>Materiall be, and meet in our warme flesh?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sco.</SPEAKER>
<L>And whether that our soules, when they're prefer'd</L>
<L>To taste eternity will euer thinke</L>
<L>Vpon the bargaines of our humane loue,</L>
<L>Is vnto me a desolate suspence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Phylosophie doth seeme to laugh vpon</L>
<L>Our hopes, and wise Diuinity belies</L>
<L>Our knowledge, with our Fayth: iealous Nature,</L>
<L>Hath lock'd, her secrets in a Cabinet,</L>
<L><PB REF="36"/>Which Time nere saw: and he that in it prys</L>
<L>Vnto Religion forfeites his bold Eies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scoperta.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our Reason frights our Sences to distrust.</L>
<L>My Lipps doe beage from thine a Legacie—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>O sad acomp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. How is my bounty now</L>
<L>Exhaust: This is the last I ere shall giue—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meruolle.</SPEAKER>
<L>Blind them agen and stay their deaths awhile.</L>
<L>Madam, your knowledge is allready taught</L>
<L><HI>Scoperta's</HI> innocence. <HI>Sciolto</HI>'s deed</L>
<L>Stands nere your punishment; but distant far</L>
<L>From remedy. Marke, his goodly feature.</L>
<L>With what magnificence he's built? Besides</L>
<L>This Morne▪ his Vnkle too (the wealthiest of</L>
<L>Our Senators) is dead, and has bine pleasd</L>
<L>T'intitle him his Heire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza</SPEAKER>
<P>Should I not chide?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meruolle.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thinke how you lou'd him once. He will (to saue</L>
<L>His life) d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>scard <HI>Scoperta</HI>'s interest,</L>
<L>And marry you: a hapinesse compleate</L>
<L>For both</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hah?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Slaues. Stretch now your Cordage out,</L>
<L>Pull till my Eies do<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> starte like Bulletts from my Skull,</L>
<L>Murdering where they flie—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold. hold. — Did my</L>
<L>dead Lord bid you performe, what I decree?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meruolle.</SPEAKER>
<P>He did: and I asured it with my Vowes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heare then without resistan<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> of my breath,</L>
<L><HI>Sciolto</HI> is condemn'd by Law; as knowne</L>
<L>The fatall Instrument that did depriue</L>
<L>My Lord, of precious life; so he must die.</L>
<L>T'were fit my care affected mercie in</L>
<L><HI>Scoperta</HI>'s dome; she's Sister to my Lord:</L>
<L>But her sweete innocence doth make her safe.</L>
<L>She must remaine among the liuing still;</L>
<L>And in her rome, I doe condemne my selfe.</L>
<L>For my sterne pride, was the originall cause</L>
<L><PB REF="36" MS="y"/>Of this blacke Tragedy. Kind <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></L>
<L>Esteeme your Vowes, see my edic<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>▪</L>
<L>And giue me pri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>iledge first to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></L>
<L>its wrath—
<STAGE><HI>She des<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>ds.</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meruolle.</SPEAKER>
<L>This carries wonder in't</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scoperta.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le not resigne these bonds of Death, vnlesse</L>
<L><HI>Sciolto</HI> share in the compassion too—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>Giue me your pardon (gentle Mayd). I haue</L>
<L>Depriu'd you of a Brother that deseru'd</L>
<L>More Pyramids, then all th'Egiptian Kings.</L>
<L>Instead of him, receaue my pray'rs, my wealth.</L>
<L>When o're his Hersse you raise a Monument,</L>
<L>And fix my Marble-Figure neere to his,</L>
<L>Create me weeping.— I shall goe, with so</L>
<L>Much sorow, to my Graue, that being dead,</L>
<L>My Ashes will haue power to penetrate</L>
<L>The Stones. Release this pious Lady and</L>
<L>Performe your execution vpon me—</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>One o'th' Mutes pulls of his Ʋizard &amp; discouer<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> himselfe to be Altamont.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away you dreadfull Ministers of death.</L>
<L>The Lawrell Sprigge, the Mirtle nicely wreath'd</L>
<L>In Coronets, my Loue deserues; for she</L>
<L>Is growne too good for Earth. —</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>My <HI>Altamont.</HI> —
<STAGE>She sinkes.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Meruolle vnmussles, and vnbindes Sciolto, and Scoperta, who straight embrace each other.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>This deceipt brings wonder, great as our ioy.</L>
<L>They that diuide vs now, must vse the strength</L>
<L>Of swelling floods, and helpe of Thunder too —</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Put all thy beauties on agen, and smile</L>
<L>At the returne of our long absent loue:</L>
<L>My wound is clos'd, and will hau<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> instant cure —</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="37"/>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Earth groan'd at my fall, so heauie are</L>
<L>My sinnes, so much they did increase my weight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rise gently like a flame, from incense sprung.</L>
<L><HI>Meruolle,</HI> to appease my iealousie</L>
<L>Ordain'd me this disguises that I might heare</L>
<L>How in your s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ntence you behau'd your loue</L>
<L>To me: Hadst thou continu'd false, I had</L>
<L>Increas'd the anger of thy fate: but now</L>
<L>Thou art indeer'd vnto my heart agen. —</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, I haue hope my future loyaltie</L>
<L>Will manifest, your mercie well bestow'd.—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Scoperta,</HI> thou'lt excuse the cariage of</L>
<L>My doubts, I look'd on thee with th'eies of loue,</L>
<L>And loue is still too strict in her suruay. —</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scoperta.</SPEAKER>
<L>My memorie wou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d sinne, should it record</L>
<L>Ought that might nourish my dislike of you:</L>
<L>You made me taste of sorrow, not of wrath.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis I, that haue most <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eedfull vse of your</L>
<L>Kind charitie: forget my errors past,</L>
<L>And to oblige my future gratitude</L>
<L>Giue Hymen leaue to know your sister for</L>
<L>My wife. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y Vnkles death hath lent me power</L>
<L>Still to maintaine her in such qualitie</L>
<L>As shall become my deere respects to you,</L>
<L>The greatnesse of her virtue, and her blood.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take her, and be as tender of her health,</L>
<L>As Heauen hath o're thy wounds; which in their cure</L>
<L>Expresse much miracle. — My io<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'s so swell</L>
<L>My breast, that I doe finde there's danger in</L>
<L>Delight. How bless'd <HI>Meruolle</HI> are thy Arts?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meruolle.</SPEAKER>
<P>Some Angels care assisted the successe.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Charintha, Besognia.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charintha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not <HI>Altamont's</HI> returne to life, nor yet</L>
<L><HI>Sciolto's</HI> and <HI>Scoperta's</HI> glad repriue</L>
<L>Nor all the ioyes in reconcilement of</L>
<L><PB REF="37"/>Your loues express'd, can my cold sences please:</L>
<L><HI>Florello</HI> is vnkinde. —</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Besognia.</SPEAKER>
<L>The little God</L>
<L>Hath lately prick'd her with his baudy shaft.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tell me <HI>Charintha,</HI> is thy loue sincere:</L>
<L>Such as i'th simple youth of Nature is</L>
<L>Exchang'd by louers with a harmelesse plight?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charintha.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is sincere, as holy Hermits vowes,</L>
<L>And true, as their confession at their death<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meruolle.</SPEAKER>
<P>Appeare <HI>Florello,</HI> and receiue thy doome.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Florello.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>It was <HI>Meruolle's</HI> care thus to assure</L>
<L>Thy Mistresse reall loue, and constancie</L>
<L>Ere thou shouldst giue too much of thine away.</L>
<L>But now receiue her from <HI>Alteza's</HI> hand. —</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alteza.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Charintha,</HI> thy election is so safe</L>
<L>Thou neuer wilt repent the iudgement of</L>
<L>Thy sight. He cannot be so neere alli'd</L>
<L>Vnto the blood of <HI>Altamont,</HI> but he</L>
<L>Must needs participate in virtue too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charintha.</SPEAKER>
<L>We will embrace each other vntill Age,</L>
<L>Depriue our courteous sinewes of extent. —</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>The gentle Turtle shall direct vs how</L>
<L>T'augment our loues; the Eagle to renew</L>
<L>Our youth, and we will striue to imitate</L>
<L>The crooked Vine in our increase. —</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ioy, ioy!</L>
<L>The firmament is now vnmask'd, and each</L>
<L>Of vs, hath found his starre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florello.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lou'd Sister,</L>
<L>I haue orchear'd the story of your griefs,</L>
<L>And from this noble Signior, I must begge</L>
<L>A faith indeer'd, the name of Brother too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sciolto.</SPEAKER>
<P>You shall be precious to my eies as day.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="38"/><HI>Enter Rossa, Molard, fantastickly cloth'd in Dandolo's habit.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Molard.</SPEAKER>
<L>The great <HI>Dandolo</HI> and his Giant whelpes</L>
<L>Are mounted on a Mule.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rossa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Naked they ride</L>
<L>As scoutes of <HI>Tartary</HI> they're victual'd with</L>
<L>A single egge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altamont.</SPEAKER>
<P>What are these, walking Drummes?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Th'are such your knowledge shall affect: they must</L>
<L>Inioy what I atchieue. Dull men, o'war,</L>
<L>The Trophie of my victorie behold,</L>
<L>She's mine: bow, and doe homage to her lippe. —</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Still thou dost mourn (<HI>Alteza</HI>) like a Doue.
<STAGE>Soft musick▪</STAGE></L>
<L>Hearke, hearke how the Roman-Organ seemes</L>
<L>T'inuoke the Thracian Lire; the Cymbals of</L>
<L><HI>Iudea,</HI> call <HI>Castilian</HI>-Cornets foorth,</L>
<L>And <HI>German</HI>-Viols wake the <HI>Tuscan</HI> Lute▪</L>
<L>The sacred noise attend, that whilst wee heare,</L>
<L>Our soules may dance into each others eare.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt omnes.</STAGE>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
<PB REF="38"/>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

