<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2003-02-13</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Olivia Bottum</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Checked for TYPE="book". Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, etc.). Checked for signatures. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, and UNCLEARs. Corrected 79 $-groups by inserting appropriate letters or GAPs. Checked for EPIGRAPHs and ARGUMENTs. Checked for startqs, endqs, oes, q;s, and Qs. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Checked for CLOSERs, TRAILERs, and BYLINEs. DONE 2003-02-13.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A20077">
<STC T="S">6518</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99840986</BIBNO>
<VID>5536</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>THE PLEASANT COMOEDIE OF Patient Grissill.</P>
<P>As it hath beene sundrie times lately plaid by the right honorable the Earle of Not∣tingham (Lord high Admirall) his seruants.</P>
<P>LONDON. Imprinted for Henry Rocket, and are to be solde at the long Shop vnder S. Mildreds Church in the Poultry. 1603.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>The pleasant Commoedye of Patient Grissil.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter the Marquesse, Pauia, Mario, Lepido, and hunts∣men: all like Hunters. A noyse of hornes within.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marquesse.</SPEAKER>
<L>LOoke you so strang my hearts, to sée our limbes</L>
<L>Thus suited in a Hunters liuery?</L>
<L>Oh tis a louely habite, when gréene youth</L>
<L>Like to the flowry blossome of the spring,</L>
<L>Conformes his outward habite to his minde,</L>
<L>Looke how yon one-ey'd wagoner of heauen,</L>
<L>Hath by his horses fiery winged hoofes,</L>
<L>Burst ope the melancholy Iayle of Night,</L>
<L>And with his gilt beames cunning <HI>Alchimy,</HI></L>
<L>Turn'd al these cloudes to gold, who (with the winds)</L>
<L>Upon their misty shoulders bring in day:</L>
<L>Then sally not this morning with foule lookes,</L>
<L>But teach your Iocond spirits to ply the Chase,</L>
<L>For hunting is a sport for Emperors.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pau.</SPEAKER>
<L>We know it is, and therefore doe not throw</L>
<L>On these your pastimes, a contracted brow,</L>
<L>How swift youths Bias runs to catch dēlights,</L>
<L>To me is not unknowne: no brother <HI>Gualther,</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="3"/>When you were woo'd by vs to choose a wife,</L>
<L>This day you vowed to wed: but now I see,</L>
<L>Your promises turne all to mockerie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lepi.</SPEAKER>
<L>This day your self appointed to give answere</L>
<L>To all those neighbour-Princes, who in loue</L>
<L>Offer their Daughters, Sisters and Allies,</L>
<L>In marriage to your hand: yet for all this</L>
<L>The houre being come that calles you to your choyce</L>
<L>You stand prepard for sport and start aside:</L>
<L>To hunt poore déere when you should séeke a Bride.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay come <HI>Mario</HI> your opinion too,</L>
<L>H'ad néede of ten men's wit that goes to woe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>First satisfie these Princes, who expect</L>
<L>Your gracious answere to their embassies,</L>
<L>Then may you freelie reuell: now you flie</L>
<L>Both from your owne vowes, &amp; their amitie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>How much your iudgmens erre: who gets a wife</L>
<L>Must like a huntsman beate vntrodden pathes,</L>
<L>To gaine the flying presence of his loue.</L>
<L>Looke how the yelping beagles spend their mouthes</L>
<L>So Louers doe their sighes: and as the deare,</L>
<L>Out-strips the actiue hound, &amp; oft turnes backe</L>
<L>To note the angrie visage of her foe,</L>
<L>Who greedy to possesse so sweet a pray,</L>
<L>Neuer giues ouer till he ceaze on her,</L>
<L>So fares it with coy dames, who great with scorne</L>
<L>Shew the care-pined hearts, that sue to them</L>
<L>Yet on that feined slight, (Loue conquering them)</L>
<L>They cast an eye of longing backe againe,</L>
<L>As who would say, be not dismaid with frownes,</L>
<L>For though our tongues speake no: our hearts sound</L>
<L>Or if not so, before theile misse their louers,</L>
<L>Their swéet breathes shal perfume the Amorous ayre yea,</L>
<L>And braue them still to run in beauties Chase:</L>
<L>Then can you blame me to be hunter like,</L>
<L>When I must get a wife: but be content,</L>
<L><PB REF="3"/>So yo'ule ingage your faith by othe to vs,</L>
<L>Your willes shall answere mine, my liking yours,</L>
<L>And that no wrinckle on your cheekes shall ride.</L>
<L>This day the Marquesse vowes to choose a bride.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Euen by my honor,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Brother be aduis'd,</L>
<L>The importunitie of you and these,</L>
<L>Thrusts my free thoughts into the yoake of loue,</L>
<L>To grone vnder the loade of marriage,</L>
<L>Since then you throwe this burthen on my youth</L>
<L>Sweare to me whome soeuer my fancie choose,</L>
<L>Of what discent, beautie or birth she be,</L>
<L>Her you shall like and loue as you loue me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now by my birth I sweare, wed whome you please,</L>
<L>And Ile imbrace her with a brothers arme.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lepi.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Mario</HI> and my selfe to your faire choice,</L>
<L>Shall yeeld all dueties and true reuerence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your protestations please me Iollilie,</L>
<L>Lets ring a hunters peale, and in the eares</L>
<L>Of our swift forrest, Cittizens proclaime,</L>
<L>Defiance to their lightnes: our sports done,</L>
<L>The Uenson that we kill shall feast our bride,</L>
<L>If she proue bad, ile cast all blame on you,</L>
<L>But if sweet peace succeede this amorous strife,</L>
<L>Ile say my wit was best to choose a wife.
<STAGE>Exeunt,</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>As they goe in, hornes sound &amp; hollowing within: that done, Enter Ianicolo, Grissil, and Babulo, with two baskets begun to be wrought.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bab.</SPEAKER>
<P>Olde Master heeres a morning able to make vs worke tooth and naile (marrie then we must haue victualls) the Sun hath plaid boe péep in the element anie time these two houres, as I doe some mornings whē you cal: what <HI>Babulo</HI> say you: héere Master say I and then this eye opens, yet don is the mouse, lis still:
<PB REF="4"/>
what <HI>Babulo</HI> sayes <HI>Grissil,</HI> anone say I, and then this eye lookes vp, yet downe I snug againe: what <HI>Babu∣lo</HI> say you againe, and then I start vp, and sée the Sunne, and then snéeze, and then shake mine eares, and then rise, and then get my breakfast, and then fal to worke, and then wash my hands, and by this time I am ready: héer's your basket, and <HI>Grissil</HI> I heer's yours.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ian.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fetch thine own <HI>Babulo</HI> lets ply our busines.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bab.</SPEAKER>
<P>God send me good lucke Master.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gri.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why <HI>Babulo,</HI> what's the matter?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bab.</SPEAKER>
<P>God forgiue mee, I thinke I shall not eate a pecke of salt: I shall not liue long sure, I should be a rich man by right, for they neuer doe good déedes, but when they sée they must dye, and I haue now a mon∣strous stomacke to worke, because I thinke I shall not liue long.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ian.</SPEAKER>
<P>Goe foole, cease this vaine talke and fall to worke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bab.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile hamper some body if I dye, because I am a basket maker.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ian.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come <HI>Grissill,</HI> worke swéet girle, héere the warme Sunne will shine on vs,</P>
<L>And when his fires begin,</L>
<L>Wée'll coole our sweating browes in yonder shade.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Father, me thinkes it doth not fit a maide,</L>
<L>By sitting thus in view, to draw mens eyes</L>
<L>To stare vpon her: might it please your age,</L>
<L>I could be more content to worke within.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ian.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indéed my childe, mens eyes do now adaies,</L>
<L>Quickly take fire at the least sparke of beauty,</L>
<L>And if those flames be quencht by chast disdaine,</L>
<L>Then their inuenom'd tongues (alacke) doe strike,</L>
<L>To wound her fame whose beauty they did like.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gri.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will auoide their darts and worke within.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ian.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou needst not, in a painted coate goes sin,</L>
<L><PB REF="4"/>And loues those that loue pride; none lookes on thee,</L>
<L>Then keepe me companie: how much vnlike</L>
<L>Are thy desires to manie of thy sex?</L>
<L>How manie wantons in <HI>Saliuia,</HI></L>
<L>Frowne like the sullen night, when their faire faces</L>
<L>Are hid within doores: but got once abroad,</L>
<L>Like the proud Sun they spred their staring beames,</L>
<L>They shine out to be seene, their loose eyes tell,</L>
<L>That in their bosomes wantonnes doe dwell:</L>
<L>Thou canst not doe so <HI>Grissill,</HI> for thy Sun,</L>
<L>Is but a Starre, thy Starre, a sparke of fire,</L>
<L>Which hath no power t'inflame doting desire:</L>
<L>Thy silkes are thrid-bare russets: all thy portion</L>
<L>Is but an honest name: that gon thou art dead,</L>
<L>Though dead thou liu'st, that being unblemished.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gris.</SPEAKER>
<L>If to die free from shame be nere to die,</L>
<L>Then Ile be crownd with immortallitie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ian.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray God thou maist: yet childe my iealous soule</L>
<L>Trembles through feares, so often as mine eyes</L>
<L>Sees our Duke court thée: and when to thine eares</L>
<L>He tunes sweet loue-songs: oh beware my <HI>Grissill</HI></L>
<L>He can prepare his way with gifts of golde,</L>
<L>Upon his breath, winged Promotion flies</L>
<L>Oh my deare Girle trust not his sorceries,</L>
<L>Did he not séeke the shipwracke of thy fame?</L>
<L>Whie should he send his tailors to take measure</L>
<L>Of <HI>Grissils</HI> bodie: but as one should say,</L>
<L>If thou wilt be the Marquesse concubine,</L>
<L>Thou shalt weare rich attires: but they that thinke,</L>
<L>With costly garments, sins blacke face to hide,</L>
<L>Weare naked brauerie and ragged pride.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good father doe not shake your age with feares</L>
<L>Although the Marquesse sometimes visit vs,</L>
<L>Yet all his words and deedes are like his birth,</L>
<L>Steept in true honor: but admit they were not,</L>
<L>Before my soule looke black with speckled sinne,</L>
<L><PB REF="5"/>My hands shal make me pale deathes underling,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ian.</SPEAKER>
<L>The musick of those words sweetē mine eares</L>
<L>Come girle lets faster worke: time apace weares.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Babulo with his worke.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gris.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come <HI>Babulo</HI> why hast thou staid so long?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay why are you so short, Masters heeres mo∣nie I tooke (since I went) for a cradle: this yeare I thinke be leape yeare, for woniē doe nothing but buy cradles, by my troth I thinke the world is at an end, for as soone as we be borne we marrie: as soone as we marrie we get children, (by hooke or by crooke gotten they are) children must haue cradles, and as soone as they are in them, they hop out of thē, for I haue séene little girls that yesterday had scarce a hand to make them ready, the next day had worne wedding rings on their fingers, so that if the world doe not ende, we shall not liue one by another: basket making as all o∣ther trades runs to decay, and shortly we shall not be worth a butten, for non in this cutting age sowe true stitches, but taylers and shoomakers, &amp; yet now and then they tread their shooes a wrie too.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let not thy tongue goe so: sit downe to worke</L>
<L>And that our labour may not seeme to long,</L>
<L>Weele cunningly beguile it with a song.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe master for thats honest cousonage.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>The Song.</STAGE>
<LG>
<L><HI>Song</HI> Art thou poore yet hast thou golden Slumbers:</L>
<L>Oh sweet content!</L>
<L>Art thou rich yet is thy minde perplexed?</L>
<L>Oh punnishment.</L>
<L>Dost thou laugh to see how fooles are vexed?</L>
<L>To ad to golden numbers, golden numbers.</L>
<L>O sweet content, of sweet &amp;c.</L>
<L><PB REF="5"/><HI>Foote</HI> Worke apace, apace, apace, apace▪</L>
<L>Honest labour beares a louely face,</L>
<L>Then hey noney, noney: hey noney, noney.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Canst drinke the waters of the Crisped spring,</L>
<L>O sweet content!</L>
<L>Swim'st thou in wealth, yet sinck'st in thine owne teares,</L>
<L>O punnishment.</L>
<L>Then hee that patiently wants, burden beares,</L>
<L>No burden beares, but is a King, a King,</L>
<L>O sweet content, &amp;c.</L>
<L><HI>Foot.</HI> Worke apace, apace, &amp;c.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Enter Laureo.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<P>Weep master, yonder comes your Sonne</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ian.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Laureo</HI> my Sonne? oh heauen let thy rich hand</L>
<L>Poure plentious shewers of blessing on his head.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Treble the number fall vppon your age,</P>
<P>Sister?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gri.</SPEAKER>
<P>Deare brother <HI>Laureo</HI> welcome home.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<P>Master <HI>Laureo</HI>) (aniculaes sonne) welcome home, how doe the nine muses, Pride, couetousnes, enuie, sloth, wrath, gluttonie and letcherie? you that are Schollers read how they doe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Muses: these (foole) are the seauen deadly sins.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<P>Are they: Mas me thinkes its better seruing thē, then your nine muses, for they are starke beggers.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ian.</SPEAKER>
<P>Often I haue wisht to sée you heere,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<P>It grieues me that you see me heere so soone.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ian.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why <HI>Laureo</HI> dost thou grieue to see thy father,</L>
<L>Or dost thou scorne me for my pouertie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<P>He needes not, for he lookes like poore Iohn him∣selfe, eight to a necke of Mutten, is not that your com∣mons, &amp; a Cue of breade?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Father I grieue my young yeares to your age,</L>
<L>Should adde more sorrowe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="6"/>
<SPEAKER>Ian.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why sonne whats the matter?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>That which to thinke on makes me desperate.</L>
<L>I that haue chargd my friends, and from my father</L>
<L>Puld more then he could spare, I that haue liud,</L>
<L>These nine yeares at the Uniuersity,</L>
<L>Must now for this worlds deuill: this angell of golde,</L>
<L>Haue all those daies and nights to beggerie solde,</L>
<L>Through want of money, what I want I misse,</L>
<L>Who is more scorn'd then a poore: scholler is?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bab.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes three things: Age, wisdome, &amp; basket ma∣kers</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gri.</SPEAKER>
<P>Brothers whatmeanes these words?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, I am mad.</L>
<L>To thinke how much a Scholler vndergoes,</L>
<L>And in th'ende reapes naught but pennurie.</L>
<L>Father I am inforced to leaue my booke,</L>
<L>Because the studie of my booke doth leaue me,</L>
<L>In the leane armes of lancke necessitie.</L>
<L>Hauing no shelter (ah me) but to flie</L>
<L>Into the sanctuarie of your aged armes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bab.</SPEAKER>
<P>A trade, a trade, follow basket-makeing, leaue bookes and turne block head.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ian.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace foole, welcome my sonne, thogh I am poore</L>
<L>My loue shall not be so: goe daughter <HI>Grissill,</HI></L>
<L>Fetch water from the spring to séeth our fish,</L>
<L>Which yesterday I caught: the cheare is meane,</L>
<L>But be content, when I haue solde these Baskets,</L>
<L>The monie shall be spent to bid thee welcome:</L>
<L><HI>Grissill</HI> make hast, run and kindle fire.
<STAGE>Exit Grissill.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<P>Goe <HI>Grissill</HI> Ile make fire, and scoure the kettle, its a hard world when schollers ease fish vpon flesh daies</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ist not a shame for me that am a man,
<STAGE>Exit. Ba.</STAGE></L>
<L>Nay more, a scholler to endure such neede,</L>
<L>That I must pray on him, whome I should feede?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ian.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay grieue not Sonne, better haue felt worse woe</L>
<L>Come sit by me while I worke to get bread,</L>
<L>And <HI>Grissill</HI> spin vs yearne to cloath our backs.</L>
<L><PB REF="6"/>Thou shalt reade doctrine to vs for the soule,</L>
<L>Then what shall we there want, nothing my sonne</L>
<L>For when we cease from worke euen in that while,</L>
<L>My song shall charme griefes eares and care beguile.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Grissill running with a Pitcher.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gris</SPEAKER>
<L>Father as I was runaing to fetch water,</L>
<L>I saw the <HI>Marquesse</HI> with a gallant traine</L>
<L>Come riding towards vs, O see where they come.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Marquesse, Pauia, Mario, Lepido, two Ladies and some other attendants.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>See where my <HI>Grissill,</HI> and her father is,</L>
<L>Me thinkes for beautie shining through those weedes,</L>
<L>Seemes like a bright starre in the sullen night.</L>
<L>How louely pouertie dwels on her backe,</L>
<L>Did but the proud world note her as I doe,</L>
<L>She would cast off rich robes, forsweare rich state,</L>
<L>To cloth them in such poore abiliments,</L>
<L>Father good fortune euer blesse thine age.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ian.</SPEAKER>
<P>All happines attend my gracious Lorde.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<P>And what wish you faire Maide?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gris.</SPEAKER>
<L>That your high thoughts.</L>
<L>To your contentment may be satisfied.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar,</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou wouldst wish soe, knewst thou for what I come</L>
<L>Brother of <HI>Pauia</HI> beholde this virgin,</L>
<L><HI>Mario Lepido</HI> is she not faire?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Brother I haue not seene so meane a creature,</L>
<L>So full of beautie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Were but <HI>Grissils</HI> birth,</L>
<L>As worthie as her forme, she might be held</L>
<L>A fit companion for the greatest state.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh blindnes, so that men may beautie finde,</L>
<L>They nere respect the beauties of the minde,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="7"/>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Father <HI>ani<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="indecipherable" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ola</HI> whats hee that speakes</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ian.</SPEAKER>
<P>A poore despised scholler and my Sonne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is no time to holde dispute with schollers</L>
<L>Tell me in faith olde man what dost thou thinke,</L>
<L>Because the <HI>Marquesse</HI> visits thee so oft?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ian.</SPEAKER>
<L>The will of Princes subiects must not serch,</L>
<L>Let it suffice, your grace is welcome hither.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>And ile requite that welcome if I liue,</L>
<L><HI>Grissill</HI> suppose a man should loue you dearely,</L>
<L>As I know some that doe, would you agree</L>
<L>To quittance true affection with the like.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gri.</SPEAKER>
<P>None is so fond to fancie pouertie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I say there is: come Lords stand by my side,</L>
<L>Nay brother you are sped and haue a wife,</L>
<L>Then giue vs leaue that are all Batchelers,</L>
<L>Now <HI>Grissil,</HI> eye vs well and giue your verdicte,</L>
<L>Which of vs three you holde the proprest man,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gri.</SPEAKER>
<P>I have no skill to iudge proportions.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay then you iest, women haue eagles eyes,</L>
<L>To prie euen to the heart, and why not you?</L>
<L>Come, we stand fairely, freely speake your minde,</L>
<L>For by my birth, he whome thy choice shall blesse,</L>
<L>Shall be thy husband.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>What intends your graft?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lepi.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord I haue vowed to leade a single life,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>A single life? this cunning cannot serue,</L>
<L>Doe not I know you loue her I haue heard?</L>
<L>Your passions spent for her your sighes for her,</L>
<L><HI>Mario</HI> to the wonder of her beautie,</L>
<L>Compiled a Sonnet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I my Lord write sonnets?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>You did intreate me to intreate her father,</L>
<L>That you might haue his daughter to his wife.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lep.</SPEAKER>
<L>To anie one I willingly resigne,</L>
<L>All interest in her, which doth looke like mine,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lorde I sweare she nere shall be my bride,</L>
<L><PB REF="7"/>I hope sheele sweare so too being thus denide,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Both of you turn'd <HI>Apostataes</HI> in loue,</L>
<L>Nay then Ile play the cryer: once, twice, thrice,</L>
<L>Speake or shee's gone els: no since twill not be,</L>
<L>Since you are not for her, yet shee's for me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pau.</SPEAKER>
<P>What meane you Brother?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith no more but this:</L>
<L>By loues most wondrous Metamorphosis,</L>
<L>To turne this Maide into your Brothers wife,</L>
<L>Nay sweet heart looke not strange I doe not iest,</L>
<L>But to thine eares mine Amorous thoughts impart,</L>
<L><HI>Gualter</HI> protests he loues thée with his heart,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>The admiration of such happines,</L>
<L>Makes me astonisht.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh my gracious Lord,</L>
<L>Humble not your high state to my lowe birth,</L>
<L>Whome not worthy to be held your slaue,</L>
<L>Much lesse your wife.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Grissill</HI> that shall suffice,</L>
<L>I count thee worthie: olde <HI>Ianicola,</HI></L>
<L>Art thou content that I shall be thy Sonne?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ian.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am vnworthy of so great a good.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tush tush talk not of worth, in honest tearmes</L>
<L>Tell me if I shall haue her? for by heauen</L>
<L>Unlesse your free consent alowe my choice,</L>
<L>To win ten kingdomes Ile not call her mine.</L>
<L>Whats thy Sonnes name?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ian.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Laureo</HI> My gracious Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile haue both your consents: I tell ye Lords,</L>
<L>I haue wooed the virgin long, oh manie an houre,</L>
<L>Haue I bin glad to steale from all your eyes,</L>
<L>To come disguis'd to her: I sweare to you,</L>
<L>Beautie first made me loue, and vertue woe,</L>
<L>I lou'd her lowlynes, but when I tride</L>
<L>What vertues were intempled in her brest,</L>
<L>My chast hart swore that she should be my bride</L>
<L><PB REF="8"/>Say Father, must I be forsworne or noe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ian.</SPEAKER>
<P>What to my Lord séemes best to me séemes so</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Laureo</HI> whats your opinion?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thus my Lorde.</L>
<L>If equall thoughts durst both your states conferre,</L>
<L>Her's is to lowe, and you to high for her,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<P>What saies faire <HI>Grissill</HI> now?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gris.</SPEAKER>
<L>This doth she say,</L>
<L>As her olde Father yeeldes to your dread will,</L>
<L>So she her fathers pleasure must fulfill.</L>
<L>If olde <HI>Ianicola</HI> make <HI>Grissill</HI> yours,</L>
<L><HI>Grissill</HI> must not deny, yet had she rather,</L>
<L>Be the poore Daughter still of her poore Father.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile gild that pouertie and make it shine,</L>
<L>With beames of dignitie: this base attire,</L>
<L>These Ladies shal teare of, and decke thy beautie</L>
<L>In robes of honour, that the world may say,</L>
<L>Uertue and beautie was my bride to day.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>This meane choice, will distaine your noblenes</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more <HI>Mario</HI> then it doth disgrace</L>
<L>The Sunne to shine on me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lep.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shee's poore and base.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shee's rich: for vertue beautifies her face.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pau.</SPEAKER>
<L>What will y<SUP>e</SUP> world say when the trump of fame</L>
<L>Shall sound your high birth with a beggers name?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>The world still lookes a squint, &amp; I deride</L>
<L>His purblind iudgement; <HI>Grissill</HI> is my Bride,</L>
<L><HI>Ianicola,</HI> and <HI>Laureo</HI>: father, brother,</L>
<L>You and your Son grac'd with our royal fauour,</L>
<L>Shall liue to outweare time in happines.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Babulo.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<P>Master I haue made a good fire: sirha <HI>Grissill,</HI> the fishe</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ian.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fall on thy knees thou foole: sée heeres our duke</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue not offended him, therefore Ile not ducke
<PB REF="8"/>
and he were ten Dukes.</P>
<LG>
<L>Ile kneele to none but God and my Prince.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<P>This is thy Prince, be silent <HI>Babulo,</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bab.</SPEAKER>
<P>Silence is a vertue, marie tis a dumbe vertue: I love vertue that speakes, and has a long tongue like a belweather, to leade other vertues after: if he be a Prince, I hope hee is not Prince ouer my tongue, snailes, where∣fore come all these: Master heeres not fish enough for vs, Sirha <HI>Grissill</HI> the fire burnes out.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tell me my loue what pleasant fellow is this?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gris.</SPEAKER>
<P>My aged Fathers seruant my gracious Lorde.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bab.</SPEAKER>
<P>How, my loue: master a worde to y<SUP>e</SUP> wise, <HI>scillicet</HI> me my love.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whats his name,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bab.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Babulo</HI> Sir is my name▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why dost thou tremble so? we are al thy friends</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bab.</SPEAKER>
<P>Its hard sir for this motley Ierkin, to find friend∣ship with this fine doublet.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Ianicola</HI> bring him to Court with thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bab.</SPEAKER>
<P>You may be asham'd to lay such knauish burden vppon olde ages shoulders: but I see they are stooping a little, all crie downe with him: He shall not bring me sir, ile carrie my selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<P>I pray thee doe, Ile haue thee liue at court,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue a better trade sir, basketmaking,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Grissill</HI> I like thy mans simplicitie,</L>
<L>Still shall he be thy seruant <HI>Babulo,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Grissill</HI> thy mistresse, now shall be my wife</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bab</SPEAKER>
<P>I thinke sir I am a fitter husband for her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why shouldst thou think, I wil make her rich</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bab.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thats al one sir, beggers are fit for beggers, gētle∣folkes for gētlefolkes: I am afraid y<SUP>t</SUP> this wōder of y<SUP>e</SUP> rich leuing y<SUP>e</SUP> poor, wil last but mine daies: old M bid this mer∣rie gentlemā home to dinner, you shal haue a good dish of fish sir: &amp; thank him for his good wil to your daughter <HI>Gris.</HI> for ile be hāgd if he do not (as many rich cogging marchāts) now adaies doe when they haue got what they would,
<PB REF="9"/>
giue her the belles, let her flye.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gri.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh beare my Lord with his intemperate tongue</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Grissill</HI> I take delight to beare him talke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bab.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, I, y'eare best take mee vp for your foule: are not you he, that came speaking so? to <HI>Grissill</HI> héere, doe you remember how I knockt you once for offering to haue a licke at her lips.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe remember it and for thy paines,</L>
<L>A golden recompence ile giue to thée.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bab.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why doe, and ile knock you as often as you list.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Grissill</HI> this merrie fellow shall be mine,</L>
<L>But we forget our selues, the daie growes olde.</L>
<L>Come Lords cheare vp your lookes &amp; with faire smiles,</L>
<L>Grace our intended nuptials: time may come,</L>
<L>When all commaunding loue your hearts subdue,</L>
<L>The <HI>Marquesse</HI> may performe as much for you.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Farneze, Vrcenze, and Rice meeting them running.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Far.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Rice</HI> how now man? whether art y<SUP>u</SUP> gallopping?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ric.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith euen to finde a full maunger: my téeth wa∣ter till I be mounching, I haue bin at the Cutlers, to bid him bring away Sir <HI>Owens</HI> rapier, and I am ambling home thus fast, for feare I am driuen to fast.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrc.</SPEAKER>
<P>But Sirha <HI>Rice,</HI> when's the day? will not thy master Sir <HI>Owen</HI> and <HI>Signior Emulo</HI> fight?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ric.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, for <HI>Signior Emulo</HI> has warn'd my Master to the court of Conscience, and theres an order set downe, that the coward shall pay my Master good words weeke∣lie, till the debt of his choller be runne out.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Far.</SPEAKER>
<P>Excellent, but did not <HI>Emulo</HI> write a challenge to Sir <HI>Owen.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rice.</SPEAKER>
<P>No he sent a terrible one, but hee gaue a sexton of a Chuch a groate to write it, and hee set his marke to
<PB REF="9"/>
it, for the gull can neither write nor reade.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ric.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha ha, not write and reade? why I haue séene him pul out a bundle of sonnets writen, &amp; read them to Ladies.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Far.</SPEAKER>
<P>He got thē by heart <HI>Vrcenze,</HI> &amp; so deceiu'd the poor soules: as a gallant whome I know, cozens others: for my briske spāgled babie wil come into a Stationers shop, call for a stoole and a cushion, and then asking for some greeke Poet, to him he falles, and there he grumbles God knowes what, but Ile be sworne he knowes not so much as one Character of the tongue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ric.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why then its greeke to him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Far.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha, ha, <HI>Emulo</HI> not write and read?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ric.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not a letter and you would hang him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then heele neuer be saued by his book.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ric.</SPEAKER>
<P>No nor by his good workes, for heele doe none. Signiors both, I commend you to the skies, I commit you to God, adew.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Far.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay sweet <HI>Rice</HI> a little more,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ric.</SPEAKER>
<P>A little more will make me a great deale lesse, house keeping you know is out of fashion: vnlesse I ride post, I kisse the post: in a worde ile tell you all, challenge was sent, answered no fight, no kill, all friends, all fooles,<HI>Emulo</HI> coward, Sir <HI>Owen</HI> braue man, farewell, dinner, hungrie: little cheare, great great stomacke, meate meat, meate, mouth, mouth, mouth, adue, adue, adue.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha, ha, adue <HI>Rice,</HI> Sir <HI>Owen</HI> belike kéepes a leane Kitchin.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Far.</SPEAKER>
<P>What els man, thats one of the miserable vowes he makes when hee's dubd: yet he doth but as manie of his brother knights doe, keepe an ordinarie table for him and his long coate follower.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrc.</SPEAKER>
<P>That long coate makes the master a little king, for whersoeuer his piece of a follower comes hopping after him, hees sure of a double guarde.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Far.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile set some of the Pages vpon thy skirts for this</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrc.</SPEAKER>
<P>I shall feele them no more then so many fleas,
<PB REF="10"/>
therefore I care not: but <HI>Farneze</HI> youle prooue a most ac∣complisht coxecombe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Far.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh olde touch lad, this yonker is right <HI>Trinidado</HI> pure leafe <HI>Tobacco,</HI> for indeed hee's nothing purffe, réeke, and would be tried (not by God and his countrie) but by fire, the verie soule of his substance and needes would conuert into smoke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hee's Steele to the backe you see, for he writes Challenges.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Far.</SPEAKER>
<P>True, and Iron to the head, oh theres a rich lea∣den minerall amongst his braines, if his skull were well digd, Sirha <HI>Vrcence,</HI> this is one of those changeable Silke gallants, who in a verie scuruie prid, scorne alschol∣lers, and reade no bookes but a looking glasse, and speake no language but sweet Lady, and sweet <HI>Signior</HI> and chew between their téeth terrible words, as though they would coniure, as complement and Proiects, and Fastidious, &amp; Caprichious, and Misprizian, and the Sintheresis, of the soule, and such like raise veluet tearmes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrc.</SPEAKER>
<P>What be the accontremēts now of these gallāts?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Far.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeed thats one of their fustiā outlādish phrases to, marrie sir their accontremēts, are al y<SUP>e</SUP> fātasticke fashi∣ons, y<SUP>t</SUP> can be taken vp, either vpō trust or at second hand.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whats their quallities?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Far.</SPEAKER>
<P>None good, these are the best: to make good fa∣ces: to take Tobacco well, to spit well, to laugh like a wayting Genllewoman, to lie well, to blush for nothing, to looke big vpon little fellowes, to scoffe with a grace, though they hane a verie filthie grace in scoffing, and for a neede to ride prettie and well.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrc.</SPEAKER>
<P>They cannot choose but ride well, because euerie good wit rides them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Far.</SPEAKER>
<P>Héere's the difference, that they ride vpon horses, and when they are ridden they are spur'd for asses, so they can crie wighee and hollow kicking iade, they care not if they haue no more learning then a Iade.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="10"/><HI>Enter Emuloes Sir Owen talking, Rice after them eating secretly.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrc.</SPEAKER>
<P>No more of these Iadith tricks: heere comes the hobbie horse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Far.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh he would daunce a morrice rarely if hee were hung with belles.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrc.</SPEAKER>
<P>He would iangle vilanously.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Far.</SPEAKER>
<P>Peace lets incounter them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S. O.</SPEAKER>
<P>By Cod Sir <HI>Emuloes,</HI> sir <HI>Owen</HI> is clad out a crie becaus is friends with her, for Sir <HI>Owen</HI> sweare, did her not sweare <HI>Rice</HI>?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ric.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes forsooth. <HI>Spit out his meate.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S. Ow.</SPEAKER>
<P>By Cod is sweare terrible to knog her pade, and fling her spingle legs at plum trees, when her come to fall to her tagger and fencing trigs, yes faith and to breag her shins did her not <HI>Rice</HI>?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ric.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes by my troth Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S. Ow.</SPEAKER>
<P>By Cods vdge me is all true, and to giue her a great teale of blouddie nose, because Sir <HI>Emuloes</HI> you shallenge the prittish Knight, <HI>Rice</HI> you knowe <HI>Sir Owen</HI> shentleman first, and secondly knight, what apoxale you <HI>Rice,</HI> is shoke now?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ric.</SPEAKER>
<P>No sir I haue my fiue sences and am as wel as any man.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S. O.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well here is hand, now is mighty friends.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Emu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir <HI>Owen</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Far.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now the gallimaufrie of language comes in.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Emu.</SPEAKER>
<P>I protest to you, the magnitude of my condole∣ment, hath bin eleuated the higher to sée you and my selfe, two gentlemen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S. Ow.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay tis well knowne <HI>Sir Owen</HI> is good shen∣tleman, is not <HI>Rice</HI>?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ric.</SPEAKER>
<P>He that shall deny it Sir ile make him eate his words.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Emu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good friend I am not in the Negatiue, bee not so Caprichious, you misprize me, my collocution tēdeth to S. <HI>Owens</HI> dignifiing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fra.</SPEAKER>
<P>Lets step in, God saue you <HI>Singnior Emulo.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well encountred S. <HI>Owen.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S.O.</SPEAKER>
<P>Owe, how do you S. <HI>Em.</HI> is frends out a cry now
<PB REF="11"/>
but <HI>Emuloes</HI> take heede, you match no more loue trigs to widdow <HI>Gwenthyans,</HI> by Cod vrdge me, that doe so must knoge her, see you nowe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Emu</SPEAKER>
<P>Not so tempestious sweet knight: though to my disconsolation, I will obliuionize my loue to the welch widdowe, and doe heere proclaime my delinquishment, but sweet <HI>Signior</HI> be not to <HI>Diogenicall</HI> to me,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir O.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha ha is knowe not what <HI>genicalls</HI> meane, but Sir <HI>Owen</HI> will <HI>genicall</HI> her, and her fag her <HI>genicalling Gwenthyan.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Far.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay faith weele haue you sound friends indeede, otherwise you know, <HI>Signior Emulo,</HI> if you should beare all the wrongs, you would be our <HI>Athlassed.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Emu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Most true.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir O.</SPEAKER>
<P>By god is out a crie friends, but harg <HI>Farneze, Vrcenze</HI> twag a great teale to <HI>Emuloes: Ow.</HI> is great teale of frends: ha ha is tell sine admirable shest, by Cod <HI>Emu∣loes,</HI> for feare S. <HI>Owen,</HI> knog her shines, is tell, Sir <HI>Owen</HI> by tozen shentlemen her pooets is put about with lathes, ha, ha, serge her serge her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fa.</SPEAKER>
<P>No more tell <HI>Vrcenze</HI> of it: why should you two fall out for the loue of a woman, considering what store we haue of them? Sir <HI>Emulo</HI> I gratulate your peace, your company you know is precious to vs, and weele bee merrie, and ride abroad: before god now I talke of riding, Sir <HI>Owen</HI> me thinkes has an excellent boote.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrc.</SPEAKER>
<P>His leg graces the boote.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S. Ow.</SPEAKER>
<P>By God is fine leg and fine poote to: but <HI>Emu∣las</HI> leg is petter, and finer, and shenglier skin to weare.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Emu.</SPEAKER>
<P>I bought them of a pennurious Cordwainer, &amp; they are the most incongruent that ere I ware.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S. Own.</SPEAKER>
<P>Congruent? sploud what leather is congru∣ent, spanish leather?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Emu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha ha, well Gentlemen I haue other proiects becken for me, I must disgresse from this bias, and leaue you: accept I beseeeh you of this vulgar and domestick
<PB REF="11"/>
complement.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Whilst they are saluting, Sir Owen gets to Emuloes leg and puls downe his Boote.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir. O.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray <HI>Emuloes</HI> let her see her congruenee leather ha ha, owe what a pox is heere: ha, ha, is mag a wall to her shins, for keeb her warme?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whats heer lathes? where's the lime &amp; hair <HI>Emulo,</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ric.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh rare, is this to saue his shins?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S. Ow.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha, ha, <HI>Rice</HI> goe call <HI>Gwenthyan,</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ric.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will master <HI>dahoma, Gewnthyan dahoma</HI>?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S. Ow.</SPEAKER>
<P>A pogs on her goe sedge her and call her within</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ric.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am gone sir.
<STAGE>Exit Rice.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay sir <HI>Owen</HI> what meane you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S. Ow.</SPEAKER>
<P>By Cod is meane ta let <HI>Gwenthyan</HI> see what bobie foole loue her, apogs on you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Emu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir <HI>Owen</HI> and Signiors both, doe not expatiate my obloquie, my loue shall bee so fast conglutinated to you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S. Ow.</SPEAKER>
<P>Cods plud, you call her gluttons, <HI>Gwenthyan,</HI> so ho <HI>Gwenthyan</HI>?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Emu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile not disgest this pill, <HI>Signiors</HI> adieu.</L>
<L>You are <HI>Fastidious</HI> and I banish you.
<STAGE>Exit Emulo.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Gwenthyan.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gods so, heere comes the widdow, but in faith Sir <HI>Owen</HI> say nothing of this.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S Ow.</SPEAKER>
<P>No goe to thē, by Cod Sir <HI>Owen</HI> beare as praue minde as Emprour.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gwe.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who calles <HI>Gwenthyan</HI> so great teale of time?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sweet widdow euen your countrieman heere.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S. Ow.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Belly the ruddo whee: wrage witho, Mandag¦eny Mou du ac whellock en wea awh.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gwe.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Sir Owen gramarrye whee: Gwenthyan Mandage
<PB REF="12"/>
eny, ac wellock en Thawen en ryn mogh.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Far</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Mundage Thlawen,</HI> oh my good widdow gabble that we may vnderstand you, and haue at you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S. Ow.</SPEAKER>
<P>Haue at her: nay by Cod is no haue at her to, Is tawge tn her prittish tongue, for tis fine delicates tongue, I can tell her. welshe tongue is finer as greeke tongue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Far</SPEAKER>
<P>A bakte Neates tongue is finer then both.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S. Ow,</SPEAKER>
<P>But what saies <HI>Gwenthyans</HI> now? will haue Sir <HI>Owen,</HI> Sir <HI>Owen</HI> is knowne for a wiselie man, as any since <HI>Adam</HI> aud <HI>Eues</HI> time, and that is by Gods vdge me a great teale agoe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrc.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thinke <HI>Salomon</HI> was wiser then Sir <HI>Owen.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S. Ow.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Salomons</HI> had prettie wit: but what say you to King <HI>Tauie</HI>: King <HI>Tauie</HI> is well knowne was as good musitions, as the pest fidler in aul <HI>Italie,</HI> and King <HI>Tauie</HI> was Sir <HI>Owens</HI> countrieman, yes truely a prettish shen∣tlemen porne, and did twinckle, twinckle, twinckle, out a crie vpon welsh-harpe, and tis knowne <HI>Tauie</HI> loue Mis∣tris <HI>Persabe,</HI> as Sir <HI>Owen</HI> loues <HI>Gwenthyan</HI>: will her haue Sir <HI>Owen</HI> now?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Far</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith widdow take him, Sir <HI>owen</HI> is a tall man I can tell you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S. ow.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tall man, as God vnde mee, her thinke the prittish shentelman, is faliant as <HI>Mars</HI> that is the fine knaues, the poets say the God of pribles &amp; prables, I hope widdowe you see little more in Sir <HI>owen</HI> then in Sir <HI>Emuloes,</HI> say shal her? haue her now, tis faliant, as can desire, I warrant her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gw.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir <HI>owen,</HI> Sir <HI>owen,</HI> tis not for faliant, <HI>Gwen∣thyan</HI> care so much, but for honest and fertuous, and lo∣uing and pundall to leade her haue her will.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S. owe.</SPEAKER>
<P>God vdge mee, tage her away▪ to her hus∣band, and is led her haue her will owd a crie, yet by God is pridle her well enoughe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gw.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well S. <HI>owen, Gwenthyan</HI> is going to her cozen
<PB REF="12"/>
<HI>Gualther</HI> the Duke, for you knowe is her neere cozen by marriage, by tother husband that pring her from <HI>Wales.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ow.</SPEAKER>
<P>By Cod <HI>Wales</HI> is better countrie then <HI>Italies,</HI> a great teale so better.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gw.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now if her cozen <HI>Gwalther</HI> say <HI>Gwenthyan</HI> tage ths pritish knight, shall loue her diggon: but must haue her good will: marg your thad Sir <HI>owen.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ow.</SPEAKER>
<P>Owe whats else: Sir <HI>owen</HI> marg yt ferrewel, yet shall tage her downe quiglie inough, come widdowe will wag to the coward, now to her cozen, and bid her co∣zen tell her minde of Str <HI>owen.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gw.</SPEAKER>
<P>Youle man <HI>Gwenthyan</HI> Sir <HI>owen</HI>?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ow.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes by Cod and prauely to, come Shentlemans you'le tag paines to goe with her?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Far.</SPEAKER>
<P>Weele follow you presently Sir <HI>owen.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S. ow.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come widdow: <HI>Vn lod dis Glane Gwēthyā mondu</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gw.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Gramercie wheeh, Am a Mock honnoh.</HI>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Far.</SPEAKER>
<P>So this wil be rare: Sirrah <HI>Vrcenze,</HI> at the mar∣riage night of these two, insteede of Io <HI>Hymen,</HI> we shall heere hey ho <HI>Hiemen,</HI> their loue will bee like a great fire made of bay leaues, that yeeldes nothing but cracking noise, noise.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrc.</SPEAKER>
<P>If she misse his crowne tis no matter for crack∣king,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Far.</SPEAKER>
<P>So she soader it againe, it will passe currant.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Onophrio and Iulia walking ouer the Stage.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Peace heere comes our faire mistris.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Far.</SPEAKER>
<P>Lets haue a fling at her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrc.</SPEAKER>
<P>So you may, but the hardnes is to hit her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ono.</SPEAKER>
<P>Farewel <HI>Farneze</HI> you attēd wel vpō your mistris,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, nay, their wages shall be of the same colour that their seruice is of.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Far.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith mistris would you had trauelled a litile soo∣ner this way, you should haue seene a rare comedy ac∣ted by <HI>Emulo.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="13"/>
<SPEAKER>Vrc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Euerie courteous mouth will be a stage for that, rather tell her of the welch tragedie that's towards.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<P>What Tragedie?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Far.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir <HI>Owen</HI> shall marrie your couzen <HI>Gwenthyan,</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ist possible: oh they two will beget braue warri∣ours: for if she scolde heele fight, and if he quarrell sheele take vp the bucklers: shee's fire and hee's brimstone, must not there be hot doeings then thinke you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>On.</SPEAKER>
<P>Theyle prooue Turtles, for their hearts being so like, they cannot choose but bee louing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<P>Turtles: Turkie-cocks, for Gods louelets intreate the Duke my brother, tomake a lawe, that wheresoe∣uer Sir <HI>Owen</HI> and his Ladie dwell, the next neighbour may alwaies be Constable, least the peace bee broken, for theyl'e doe nothing but cryearme, arme, arme.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Far.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thinke sir <HI>Owen</HI> would die rather then loose her loue</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<P>So thinke not I.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>On.</SPEAKER>
<P>I should for <HI>Iulia,</HI> if I were <HI>Iulies</HI> husband.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<P>Therefore <HI>Iulia</HI> shal not be <HI>Onophries</HI> wife, for Ile have none die for me.</P>
<LG>
<L>I like not that coloure.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Far.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes for your love you would <HI>Iulia.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<P>No nor yet for my hate <HI>Farneze.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Would you not haue men loue you swéet mistris?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<P>No not I, fye vpon it sweet seruant.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>On.</SPEAKER>
<P>Would you wish men to hate you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes rather then loue me, of al saints I loue not to serue mistris <HI>Venus.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Far.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then I prceiue you meane to leade apes in hell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<P>That spitefull prouerbe was proclaim'd against them that are marryed vpon earth, for to be married is to liue in a kinde of hell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Far.</SPEAKER>
<P>I as they doe at barlibreake.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your wife is your ape, and that heauie burthen wedlocke, your Iacke an Apes clog, therefore ile not be tyed too't: Master <HI>Farneze,</HI> sweet virginitie is that
<PB REF="13"/>
inuisible God-head that turns into Angells, that makes vs saints on earth and starres in heauen: heere Uirgins seeme goodly, but there glorious: In heauen is no wooing yet all there are louely: in heauen are no weddings yet al ther are louers.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>On.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let vs sweet Madame turne earth into heauen, by being all louers heere to.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<P>So we doe to an earthly heauen we turne it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>On.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay but deare <HI>Iulia,</HI> tel vs why so much you hate, to enter into the lists of this same combat Martimonie?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<P>You may well call that a combat, for indéede mar∣riage is nothing else, but a battaile of loue, a friendly figh∣ting, a kinde of fauourable terrible warre: but you erre <HI>Onophrio</HI> in thinking I hate it I deale by marriage as some <HI>Indians</HI> doe the Sunne, adore it, and reuerence it, but dare not stare on it, for feare I be starke blinde: you three are batchellers, and being sicke of this maiden∣head, count al thinges bitter, which the phisicke of a sing∣le life minnisters vnto you: you imagine if you could mak the armes of faire Ladies the spheres of your hearts, good hearts, then you were in heaven: oh but Batchilers take heede, you are no sooner in that heauen, but you straite slip into hell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Far.</SPEAKER>
<P>As long as I haue a beautifull Ladie to torment me, I care not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nor I the sweetnes of her lookes shall make me rellish any punnishment.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>On.</SPEAKER>
<P>Except the punnishment of the horne <HI>Vrcenze,</HI> put that in.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay hee were best put that by: Lord, Lord, see what vnthrifts this loue makes vs? if he once but get into ourmouthes, hee labours to turne our tongues to clap∣pers, and to ring all in, at <HI>Cupids</HI> Church when we were better to bite off our tōgues, so we may thrust him out, <HI>Cupid</HI> is sworne enemie to time, &amp; he that looseth time I can tell you looseth afriend.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="14"/>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<P>I a bald friend.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Therefore my good seruants if, you weare my li∣uerie, cast of this loose vpper coate of loue: bee ashamde to waite vppon a boy, a wag, a blinde boy, a wanton: My brother the Duke wants our companies, tis Idle∣nes and loue, makes you captaines to this solitarines, fol∣lowe me &amp; loue not, &amp; ile teach you how to find libertie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<P>We obey to follow you, but not to loue you, no re∣nounce that obedience.
<STAGE>Exeunt</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter the Marquesse and Furio.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Furio.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fur.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lorde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy faith I oft have tride, thy faith I credits</L>
<L>For I haue found it sollid as the rocke:</L>
<L>No babbling eccho sits vpon thy lips,</L>
<L>For silence euen in speach, doth seale them vp,</L>
<L>Wilt thou be trustie <HI>Furio</HI> to thy Lorde?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fur.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is enough, those words I will,</L>
<L>Yeelds sweeter musicke then the gilded sounds,</L>
<L>Which chatting parrats long toung'd sicophants,</L>
<L>Send from the organs of their siren voice,</L>
<L><HI>Grissill</HI> my wife thou seest beare in her wombe,</L>
<L>The ioy of marriage: <HI>Furio</HI> I protest,</L>
<L>My loue to her is as the heate to fire,</L>
<L>Her loue to mée as beautie to the Sunne,</L>
<L>(Inseperable adiuncts) in one word,</L>
<L>So dearely loue I <HI>Grissill,</HI> that my life</L>
<L>Shall end, when she doth ende to be my wife.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis well done.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet is my bosome burnt vp with desires,</L>
<L>To trie my <HI>Grissils</HI> patience, Ile put on</L>
<L>A wrinckled forehead, and turne both mine eyes,</L>
<L>Into two balles of fire, and claspe my hand</L>
<L><PB REF="14"/>Like to a mace of Iron, to threaten death.</L>
<L>But <HI>Furio</HI> when that hand lifts up to strike,</L>
<L>It shall flie open to embrace my loue,</L>
<L>Yet <HI>Grissill</HI> must not knowe this: all my words,</L>
<L>Shall smack of wormewood, all my deeds of gall,</L>
<L>My tongue shall iarre, my hart be musicall,</L>
<L>Yet <HI>Grissill</HI> must not knowe this?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Grissill.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not for me,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Furio</HI> My triall is thy secrecie,</L>
<L>Yonder she comes: on goes this maske of frownes,</L>
<L>Tell her I am angrie: men men trie your wiues,</L>
<L>Loue that abides sharpe tempests, sweetely thriues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fur.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lorde is angry.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Angry? the heauēs foresēd: with whō? for what?</L>
<L>Is it with mee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gris.</SPEAKER>
<L>May I presume,</L>
<L>To touch the vaine of that sad discontent,</L>
<L>Which swels vpon my deare Lords angrie browe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away away,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh chide me not away,</L>
<L>Your handmaid <HI>Grissill</HI> with vnuexed thoughts,</L>
<L>And with an vnrepining soule, will beare</L>
<L>The burden of all sorrowes, of all woe,</L>
<L>Before the smallest griefe should wound you so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am not beholding to your loue for this,</L>
<L>Woman I loue thee not, thine eyes to mine</L>
<L>Are eyes of Basiliskes, they murder me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Suffer me to part hence, Ile teare them out,</L>
<L>Because they worke such treason to my loue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Talke not of loue I hate thee more thē poyson</L>
<L>That stickes vpon the aires infected winges,</L>
<L>Exhald vp by the hot breath of the Sunne,</L>
<L><PB REF="15"/>Tis for thy sake that speckled infamie,</L>
<L>Sits like a screech-owle on my honoured brest,</L>
<L>To make my subiects stare and mocke at mee,</L>
<L>They sweare theyle neuer bend their awfull knees,</L>
<L>To the base issue of the begger wombe,</L>
<L>Tis for thy sake they curse me, raile at me,</L>
<L>Thinkst thou then I can loue thee (oh my soule)</L>
<L>Why didst thou builde this mountaine of my shame,</L>
<L>Why lye my ioyes buried in <HI>Grissills</HI> name?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gri.</SPEAKER>
<L>My gracious Lorde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Call not me gracious Lorde,</L>
<L>See woman heere hangs vp thine auncestrie,</L>
<L>The monuments of thy nobillitie,</L>
<L>This is thy russet gentrie, coate, and crest</L>
<L>Thy earthen honors I will neuer hide,</L>
<L>Because this bridle shall pull in thy pride.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Poore <HI>Grissill</HI> is not proud of these attires,</L>
<L>They are to me but as you liuerie,</L>
<L>And from your humble seruant when you please,</L>
<L>You may take all this outside, which indéede</L>
<L>Is none of <HI>Grissills,</HI> her best wealth is neede,</L>
<L>Ile cast this gaynesse of, and be content</L>
<L>To weare this russet brauerie of my owne,</L>
<L>For thats more warme then this, I shall looke olde,</L>
<L>No sooner in course freeze then cloth of golde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Spite of my soule sheele triumph ouer mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your gloue my Lord,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cast downe my gloue againe,</L>
<L>Stoope you for it, for I will haue you stoope,</L>
<L>And kneele euen to the meanest groome I keepe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis but my duetie if youle haue me stoope,</L>
<L>Euen to your meanest groome my Lord ile stoope.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Furio</HI> how slouenly thou goest attir'd?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why so my lorde?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq</SPEAKER>
<L>Looke heere thy shooes are both vntide,</L>
<L><HI>Grissill</HI> kneele you and tye them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="15"/>
<SPEAKER>Fur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pardon me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Quickely I charge you,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Friend you doe me wrong,</L>
<L>To let me holde my Lord in wrath so long,</L>
<L>Stand still Ile kneele and tye them: what I doe</L>
<L><HI>Furio</HI> tis done to him and not to you.
<STAGE>Tye them.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh strange oh admirall patience,</L>
<L>I feare when <HI>Grissills</HI> bones sleepe in her graue,</L>
<L>The world a second <HI>Grissill</HI> nere will haue,</L>
<L>Now get you in.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gris.</SPEAKER>
<L>I goe my gracious Lord.
<STAGE>Exit</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Didst thou not here her sigh, did not one frown</L>
<L>Contract her beautious forehead.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fur.</SPEAKER>
<L>I saw none</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did not one drop fal downe frō sorrowes eies,</L>
<L>To blame my heart for these her iniuries?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith not a drop, I feare sheele frowne on mee,</L>
<L>For doeing mee seruice?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Furio</HI> that ile trie,</L>
<L>My voice may yet ore-take her: <HI>Grissill, Grissill?</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Grissill.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fur.</SPEAKER>
<L>She comes at first call.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did my Lorde call?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Woman I cald thee not,</L>
<L>I said this slaue was like to <HI>Grissill, Grissill,</HI></L>
<L>And must you therefore come to torture mee?</L>
<L>Nay stay here's a companion fit for you,</L>
<L>Thou vexest me, so doth this villaine to,</L>
<L>But ere the Sun to his highest throne ascend,</L>
<L>My indignation in his death shall end.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh pardone him my Lord, for mercies wings</L>
<L>Beares round about the world the fame of Kings,</L>
<L>Temper your wrath I beg it on my knee,</L>
<L><PB REF="16"/>Forgiue his fault though youle not pardon mée,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thanke her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thankes Madame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue not true power,</L>
<L>To wound thée with deniall, oh my <HI>Grissill,</HI></L>
<L>How dearely should I loue thee,</L>
<L>Yea die to doe thee good, but that my subiects</L>
<L>Upbraid me with thy birth, and call it base.</L>
<L>And grieue to sée thy Father and thy Brother</L>
<L>Heau'de vp to dignities.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh cast them downe,</L>
<L>And send poore <HI>Grissill</HI> poorely home againe,</L>
<L>High Cedars fall, when lowe shrubs safe remaine.
<STAGE>Exit</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter at the same doore Mario and Lepido.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mari.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fetch me a cup of wine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shees a saint sure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh <HI>Furio</HI> now ile boast that I haue found,</L>
<L>An Angell vpon earth: she shalbe cround</L>
<L>The empresse of all women. <HI>Lepido?</HI></L>
<L><HI>Mario</HI>? what was she that passed by you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Both.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your vertuous wife.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Call her not vertuous,</L>
<L>For I abhorre her, did not her swolne eyes</L>
<L>Looke red with hate or scorne? did she not curse</L>
<L>My name or <HI>Furioes</HI> name?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mari.</SPEAKER>
<L>No my deare Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>For he and I raild at her, spit at her,</L>
<L>Ile burst her heart with sorrow, for I grieue</L>
<L>To see you grieue that I haue wrong'd my state,</L>
<L>By louing one whose basenes now I hate.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Grissill with wine.</STAGE>
<L>Come faster if you can forbeare <HI>Mario,</HI></L>
<L>Tis but her office: what she does to mée,</L>
<L>She Shall performe to any of you three,
<STAGE>Ile drinke</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="16"/>
<SPEAKER>Lep.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am glad to see her pride thus trampeled downe</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now serue <HI>Mario,</HI> then serue <HI>Lepido</HI>:</L>
<L>And as you bowe to me, so bend to them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile not deni't to win a diademe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mari.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your wisdome I commend that haue y<SUP>e</SUP> power</L>
<L>To raise or throw downe as you smile or lower.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your patience I commend that can abide,</L>
<L>To heare a flatterer speake yet neuer chide.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hence, hence dare you controule thē whome I grace</L>
<L>Come not within my sight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gris.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will obey,</L>
<L>And if you please, nere more beholde the day.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Furio?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fur.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lorde,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Watch her where she goes,</L>
<L>And marke how in her lookes this tryeall shewes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fur.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Mario, Lepido,</HI> I loath this <HI>Grissill,</HI></L>
<L>As sicke men loath the bitterest potion</L>
<L>Which the Phisitions hand holdes out to them,</L>
<L>For Gods sake frowne vpon her when she smiles,</L>
<L>For Gods sake smile for ioy to see her frowne,</L>
<L>For Gods sake scorne her, call her beggers brat,</L>
<L>Torment her with your lookes, your words your déedes,</L>
<L>My heart sha'l leape for ioy, that her heart bleedes,</L>
<L>Wilt thou doe this <HI>Mario</HI>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mari.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you say.</L>
<L><HI>Mario,</HI> doe this I must in it obey.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know you must, so <HI>Lepido</HI> must you</L>
<L>Tis well; but counsell me whats best to doe,</L>
<L>How shall I please my subiects? doe but speake,</L>
<L>Ile doe it though <HI>Grissills</HI> heart in sunder breake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lepi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your subiects doe repine at nothing more,</L>
<L>Then to beholde <HI>Ianicola</HI> her Father,</L>
<L>And her base brother lifted vp so high.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mari.</SPEAKER>
<L>To banish them from Court were pollicie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="17"/>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh rare, oh profound wisedome, deare <HI>Marie,</HI></L>
<L>It foorthwith shall be done, they shall not stay,</L>
<L>Though I may win by them a Kingdomes sway,
<STAGE>Exit</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lep.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Mario</HI> laugh at this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why so I doe.</L>
<L>Hedlong I had rather fall to miserie.</L>
<L>Then see a begger rais'd to dignitie.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Babulo singing with a boy after him.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bab.</SPEAKER>
<P>Boy how sits my rapier: <HI>la sol la sol. &amp;c.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>It hangs as euen as a chandlers beame.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bab.</SPEAKER>
<P>Some of them deserue to hang vpon a beame for that euennes, boy learne to give euery man his due, giue the hangman his due, for hee's a necessary member.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thats true, for he cuts of manie wicked mēbers.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bab.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hees an excellent barber, he shaues most cleanly But page how dost thou like the Court?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>Prettilie and so,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bab.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith so doe I pretlie and so: I am wearie of being a Courtiour Boy.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>That you cannot bee Master, for you are but a Courtiers man.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bab.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou saist true &amp; thou art the Courtiers mans boy, so thou art a courtier in <HI>decimo sexro</HI> in the least volume, or a courtier at the third hand, or a courtier by re∣uersion, or a courtier three descents remoued, or a courti∣er in minoritie or an vnder Courtier or a courtier in <HI>posse,</HI> and I thie Master in <HI>esse</HI>:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>A posse an esse non este argumentum</HI> Master,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bab.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou hast to much wit to be so little, but imita∣tion, imitation, is his good Lord and Master.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Ianicola Laureo and Furio.</STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="17"/>
<SPEAKER>Ian.</SPEAKER>
<P>Banisht from Count, oh what haue wee mis∣done?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<P>What haue wee done, wee must bee thus dis∣graced?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fu.</SPEAKER>
<P>I know not, but you are best packe, tis my Lords will, and thats law, I must vncase you: your best course is to fall to your owne trades.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sirra, what art thou a Broker?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fu.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, how then, I am a Gentleman.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba,</SPEAKER>
<P>Th'art a Iewe, th'art a Pagan: howe darst thou leaue them without a cloke for the raine, whē his daugh∣ter, and his sister, and my Mistris is the Kings wife?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Goe looke, sirra soole, my condition is to ship you too.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bab.</SPEAKER>
<P>There's a ship of fooles ready to hoyst sayle, they stay but for a good winde and your company: ha ha ha, I wonder (if all fooles were banisht) where thou wouldst take shipping.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ian.</SPEAKER>
<P>Peace <HI>Babulo,</HI> we are banisht from the Court.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bab.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am glad, it shall case me of a charge héere, as long as we haue good cloathes on one backes, tis no mat∣ter for our honesty, wée'll liue any where, and kéep Court in any corner.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Grissill.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ian.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh my déere <HI>Grissill.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gri.</SPEAKER>
<L>You from me are banisht,</L>
<L>But ere you leaue the Court, oh leaue I pray</L>
<L>Your griefe in <HI>Grissils</HI> bosome, let my chéekes</L>
<L>Be watred with woes teares, for héere and héere,</L>
<L>And in the error of these wandring eyes,</L>
<L>Began your discontent: had not I been,</L>
<L>By nature painted thus: this had not been,</L>
<L>To leaue the Court and care be patient,</L>
<L>In your olde cottage you shall finde content.</L>
<L>Mourne not because these silkes are tane away,</L>
<L><PB REF="18"/>You'll seeme more rich in a course gowne of gray,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you be parking? when?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Friend whats thy name?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fur.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Furio</HI> my name is, what of that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bab.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is thy name <HI>Furie</HI>? thou art halfe hang'd, for thou hast an ill name.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thy lookes are like thy name, thy name &amp; lookes Approoue thy nature to be violent.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Brother forbeare, hee's seruant to my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<L>To him, M. spare him not an inch.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Princes are neuer pleas'd with subiects sinnes,</L>
<L>But pitie those whom they are sworne to smite,</L>
<L>And grieue as tender mothers when they beate,</L>
<L>With kinde correction their vnquiet babes-</L>
<L>So should their Officers compassionate,</L>
<L>The misery of any wretches state.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fur.</SPEAKER>
<P>I must obey my Master, though indéed My heart (that seemes hard) at their wrongs doth bleed. Pray get you gone, I say little, but you knowe my minde.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bab.</SPEAKER>
<P>Little said is soone amended, thou say'st but lit∣tle, and that little will be mended soone indeed, thats ne∣uer, and so the Prouerbe stands in his full strength, pow∣er and vertue.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Marquesse, Mario and Lepido, and attendantes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fur.</SPEAKER>
<L>They will not goe my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will they not goe?</L>
<L>Away with them, expell them from our Court,</L>
<L>Base wretches, is it wrong to aske mine owne?</L>
<L>Thinke you that my affection to my wife,</L>
<L>Is greater then my loue to publicke weale?</L>
<L>Doe not my people murmure euerie houre,</L>
<L>That I haue rais'd you vp to dignities?</L>
<L><PB REF="18"/>Doe not lewde Minstrels in their ribalde runes,</L>
<L>Scofe at her birth, and descant on her dower?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ian.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas my Lord, you knew her state before.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>I did, and from the bounty of my heart,</L>
<L>I rob'd my wardrop of all precious robes,</L>
<L>That she might shine in beautie like the Sunne,</L>
<L>And in exchange, I hung this russet gowne,</L>
<L>And this poore pitcher for a monument,</L>
<L>Amongst my costliest Iemmes: sée heere they hang,</L>
<L><HI>Grissill</HI> looke héere, this gowne is vnlike to this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gris.</SPEAKER>
<L>My gratious Lord, I know full well it is.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Grissill</HI> was as pretty a <HI>Grissill</HI> in the one as in the other.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>you haue forgot these rags, this water pot.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gris.</SPEAKER>
<L>With reuerenre of your Highnes I haue not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nor I, many a good messe of water grewell has that yeelded vs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, you are proude of these your rich attyres.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Neuer did pride keep pace with my desires.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wel, get you on, part brieflie with your father.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ian.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our parting shall be short, daughter farewell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our parting shall be short, sister farewell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our parting shall be short, <HI>Grissill</HI> farewell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ian.</SPEAKER>
<L>Remember thou didst liue when thou wert poor,</L>
<L>And now thou dost but liue, come sonne no more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>See them without the Pallace <HI>Furio.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good, yet tis bad.
<STAGE>Exeunt with Furio.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shall <HI>Furio</HI> see them out of the Pallace? doe you turne vs out of doores? you turne vs out of doores then?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hence with that foole, <HI>Mario</HI> driue him hence,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<P>He shall not neede, I am no Oxe nor Asse, I can goe without driuing, for al his turning, I am glad of one thing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lep.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whats that <HI>Babulo</HI>?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="19"/>
<SPEAKER>Bab.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mary that hee shall neuer hit vs ith téeth with turning vs, for tis not a good turne, follower I must ca∣shere you: I must giue ouer houskeeping, tis the fashion, farewell boy.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>Marie farewell and be hang'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am glad thou tak'st thy death so patiently, fare∣well my Lord, adue my Lady, great was the wisedome of that Taylor, that stitcht me in Motley, for hée's a foole that leaues basket making to turne Courtier: I sée my destiny dogs me: at first I was a foole (for I was borne an Innocent) then I was a traueller, and then a Basket-maker, and then a Courtier, and now I most turne bas∣ket-maker and foole againe, the one I am sworne to, but the foole I bestowe vpon the world, for <HI>Stultorum plena sunt ominia</HI> adue, adue.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Farewell simplicity, part of my shame farewell, Now Lady what say you of their exile?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gri.</SPEAKER>
<L>What euer you thinke good, Ile not terme vile,</L>
<L>By this rich burthen in my worthles wombe,</L>
<L>Your hand-maide is so subiect to your will,</L>
<L>That nothing which you doe, to her seemes ill.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am glad you are so patient, get you in,
<STAGE>Exit Gr.</STAGE></L>
<L>Thy like will neuer be, neuer hath bin.</L>
<L><HI>Mario, Lepido</HI>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mario Lepi.</SPEAKER>
<L>My gratious Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>The hand of pouerty held downe your states,</L>
<L>As it did <HI>Grissils,</HI> and as her I rays'd,</L>
<L>To shine in greatnes sphere, so did mine eye,</L>
<L>Through gilt beames of your births, therfore me thinkes</L>
<L>Your soule should simpathize, and you should know,</L>
<L>Wht passions in my <HI>Grissils</HI> bosome flowe,</L>
<L>Faith tell me your opinions of my wife?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lep.</SPEAKER>
<L>She is as vertuous and as patient,</L>
<L>As innocente, as patience it selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mari.</SPEAKER>
<L>She merits much of loue, little of hate,</L>
<L>Onely in birth she is vnfortuuate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="19"/>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, I, the memory of that mirth doth kill me,</L>
<L>She is with childe you see, her trauaile past,</L>
<L>I am determined she shall leaue the Court,</L>
<L>And liue againe with olde <HI>Ianicola.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Both.</SPEAKER>
<L>Therein you shew true wisedome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe I indeed?</L>
<L>Deare friends it shall be done, Ile haue you two</L>
<L>Rumour that presently, to the wide eares</L>
<L>Of that newes-louing-beast the multitude,</L>
<L>Goe tell them for their sakes this shall be done.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mari.</SPEAKER>
<L>With wings we flye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lep.</SPEAKER>
<L>Swifter then time we run.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Begone then: oh these times, these impious times,</L>
<L>How swift is mischiefe? with what nimble feete</L>
<L>Doth enuy gallop to doe iniury?</L>
<L>They both confesse my <HI>Grissils</HI> innocence,</L>
<L>They both admire her wondrous patience,</L>
<L>Yet in their malice and to flatter me,</L>
<L>Head-long they run to this impiety.</L>
<L>Oh whats this world, but a confused throng</L>
<L>Of fooles and mad men, crowding in a thrust</L>
<L>To shoulder out the wise, trip downe the iust.</L>
<L>But I will try by selfe experience,</L>
<L>And shun the vulgar sentence of the base,</L>
<L>If I finde <HI>Grissill</HI> strong in patience,</L>
<L>These flatterers shall be wounded with disgrace,</L>
<L>And whilst verse liues, the fame shall neuer dye,</L>
<L>Of <HI>Grissils</HI> patience, and her constancy.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Vrcenze and Onophrio at seuerall doores, and Farnezie in the mid'st.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Far.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Onophrio</HI> and <HI>Vrcenze</HI> early met, euery man take his stand, for there comes a most rich purchase of mirth: <HI>Emulo</HI> with his hand in a faire scarfe, and <HI>Iulia</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="20"/>
<SPEAKER>Far.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hee'll strip himselfe out of his shirt anone, for Gods sake step in.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Emu.</SPEAKER>
<P>My opinion is I shall neuer recuperate the le∣gittimate office of this member my arme.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>All</HI> 3.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Signior Emulo.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Emu</SPEAKER>
<P>Sweet and accomplisht <HI>Signiors.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Far.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha ha, Madame you had a pitiful hand with this foole, but see he is recouered.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iu.</SPEAKER>
<P>But seruant where is your other hand?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ono.</SPEAKER>
<P>See sweet mistris one is my prisoner.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrc.</SPEAKER>
<P>The other I haue tane vp with the fine finger.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<P>Looke in his scarfe <HI>Farneze</HI> for an other, hee has a third hand, and tis pitifully wounded hee tels me, pitiful∣ly, pitifully.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Far.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wounded, oh palpable, come a demonstration of it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ono.</SPEAKER>
<P>Giue him your larded cloake <HI>Signior</HI> to stop his mouth, for he will vndoe you with lyes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come <HI>Signior,</HI> one fine lye now to apparrell all these former, in some light sarcenet robe of truth: none, none, in this mint?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fye seruant, is your accomplisht Courtship no∣thing but lyes:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ono.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fye <HI>Signior,</HI> no musicke in your mouth, but bat∣tles, yet a meere milke-sop.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fye <HI>Emulo,</HI> nothing but wardrop, yet heare all your trunckes of suites?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Far.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fye <HI>Signior,</HI> a scarse about your necke, yet will not hang your selfe to heare all this?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<P>Seruant I discharge you my seruice, Ile enter∣taine no braggarts.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ono.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Signior,</HI> we discharge yoy the Court, wee'l haue no gulles in our company.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Far.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Abram</HI> we casheere you our company, wee must haue no minnions at Court.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Emu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh patience bee thou my fortification: <HI>Italy</HI>
<PB REF="20"/>
thou spurnest me for vttering that nutriment, which I suckt from thée.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fa.</SPEAKER>
<P>How <HI>Italy?</HI> away you ideot: <HI>Italy</HI> infects you not, but your owne diseased spirits: <HI>Italy?</HI> out you froth, you scumme, because your soule is mud, and that you haue breathed in <HI>Italy,</HI> you'll say <HI>Italy</HI> haue defyled you: away you bore, thou wilt wallow in mire in the sweetest coun∣trie in the world.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Emu.</SPEAKER>
<L>I cannot conceipt this rawnes: <HI>Italy</HI> farewell, <HI>Italians</HI> adue.</L>
<L>A vertuous soule abhorres to dwell with you.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha ha ha:
<STAGE>Laugh.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Marquesse and Sir Owen.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Peace seruants, here comes the Duke my brother.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Loe cousen heere they be: are yee heere Gen∣tlemen?</L>
<L>And <HI>Iulia</HI> you too? then Ile call your eyes,</L>
<L>To testifie, that to Sir <HI>Meredith,</HI></L>
<L>I doe deliuer heere foure sealed bondes:</L>
<L>Coze haue a care to them, it much behooues you,</L>
<L>For Gentlemen, within this parchment lyes,</L>
<L>Fiue thousand Duckets payable to him,</L>
<L>Iust foureteene daies before next Penticoast,</L>
<L>Coze it concernes you, therefore keep them safe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Owen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fugh, her warrant her shall log them vb from Sunne and Moone, and seauen starres too I hobe, but harg you cozen <HI>Marquesse.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq</SPEAKER>
<P>Now, whats the matter?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ow.</SPEAKER>
<P>A pore on it tis scalde matter, well, well pray cozen <HI>Marquesse,</HI> vse her Latie <HI>Grissill</HI> a good teale better, for as God vdge me, you hurd Sir <HI>Owen</HI> out a cry by maging her sad and powd so, see you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hurt you? what harme or good reape you thereby?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="21"/>
<SPEAKER>Owen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Harme, yes by Gods lid, a poggie teale of harme, for loog you cozen, and cozen <HI>Iulia,</HI> &amp; Shentlemen awl, (for awl is to know her wifes case) you know her tag to wife the widdow <HI>Gwenthyan.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<P>True cozen &amp; shée's a vertuous gentlewoman.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>On.</SPEAKER>
<P>One of the patientest Ladies in the world.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shée's wondrous beautifull &amp; wondrous kinde.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Far.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shée's the quietest woman that ere I knew, for good heart, shée'll put vp any thing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<P>Cozen I am proude that you are sped so well.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ow.</SPEAKER>
<P>Are you? by God so are not I, ile tel you what co∣zen <HI>Marquesse,</HI> you awl know her wel, you know her face is liddle faire &amp; smug, but her has a tung goes Iingle ian∣gle, Iingle iangle, petter and worse then pelles when her house is a fire: patient? ha ha sir <HI>Owen</HI> shall tag her héeles and run to Wales, and her play the tiuell so out a cry ter∣rible a pogs on her la.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why cozen what are her quallities that you so commend her?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ow.</SPEAKER>
<P>Commend her? no by God not I, ha ha: is know her quallities petter &amp; petter, fore I commend her: but <HI>Gwenthian</HI> is worse and worse out a cry, owe out a cry worse, out of awl cry, shée's feard to be made fool as <HI>Gris∣sill</HI> is, &amp; as God vdge me, her mag fine pobbie foole of Sir <HI>Owen,</HI> her shide &amp; shide, &amp; prawle &amp; scoulde, by God and scradge terrible somtime, owe &amp; haid her wil doe what her can, ha ha ha, and sir <HI>Owen</HI> were hansome pachcler agen, pray cozen <HI>Marquesse</HI> tag some order in <HI>Grissill,</HI> or fedge sir <HI>Owen</HI> to mag <HI>Gwenthians</HI> quiet and tame her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>To tame her? that Ile teach you presently,</L>
<L>You had no sooner spake the word of Taming,</L>
<L>But mine eye met a speedy remedie,</L>
<L>Sée cozen heere's a plot where Osiers grow,</L>
<L>The ground belongs to olde <HI>Ianicula</HI></L>
<L>(My <HI>Grissils</HI> father) come Sir <HI>Meredith,</HI></L>
<L>Take out your knife cut three and so will I,</L>
<L><PB REF="21"/>So, keep yours cozen let them be safe laide vp,</L>
<L>These thrée (thus wound together) Ile preserue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ow.</SPEAKER>
<P>What shal her doe now with these? peate and knog her <HI>Gwenthian.</HI>
<STAGE>Enter Mario.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shal not take such counsaile from my lips,</L>
<L>How now <HI>Mario?</HI> what newes brings thee hither in such quicke haste?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mari.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your wife (my gratious Lord)</L>
<L>Is now deliuered of two beautious twins,</L>
<L>A sonne and daughter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take that for thy paines,</L>
<L>Not for the ioy that I conceiue thereby,</L>
<L>For <HI>Grissill</HI> is not gratious in the eye</L>
<L>Of those that loue me, therefore I must hate</L>
<L>Those that doe make my life vnfortunate.</L>
<L>And thats my children: must I not <HI>Mario?</HI></L>
<L>Thou bowest thy knee, well, well I know thy minde,</L>
<L>Uertue in villaines can no succour finde,</L>
<L>A sonne and daughter? I by them will prooue,</L>
<L>My <HI>Grissils</HI> patience better, and her loue:</L>
<L>Come <HI>Iulia,</HI> come <HI>Onophrio,</HI> coze farewell,</L>
<L>Reserue those wandes, these three Ile beare away,</L>
<L>When I require them backe, then will I shew</L>
<L>How easily a man may tame a shrew.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ow.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha ha ha, tame a shrew, owe tis out a cry terri∣ble hard, and more worse then tame a mad pull, but whad meane her cozen to mag her cut her wands? ha ha, God vdge me tis fine knag, I sée her knauery now, tis to pang <HI>Gwenthyans</HI> podie and she mag a noise &amp; prabble: Is not so? by Gods lid so, &amp; <HI>Gwenthian,</HI> sir <HI>Owen</HI> will knog you before her abide such horrible doe.
<STAGE>Enter Gwenthian and Rice.</STAGE>
Gods lid here her comes. <HI>Terdawgh Gwenthian Terdawgh.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gwe.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Terdawgh whee,</HI> Sir <HI>Owen Terdawgh whee.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>owen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Owe, looge heere, fine wandes <HI>Gwenthyan,</HI> is not?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="22"/>
<SPEAKER>Gwe.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Rees</HI> tag them and preag them in peeces.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ric.</SPEAKER>
<P>What say you forsooth?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gwe.</SPEAKER>
<P>What say you forsooth? you saucie knaue, must her tell her once, and twice, and thrice, and foure times, what to doe? preag these wands.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ow.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Rees</HI> is petter preake <HI>Rees</HI> his pate: heere <HI>Rees</HI> carry her home.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ri.</SPEAKER>
<P>Would I were at gallowes, so I were not heere:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gwen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doe and her tare, doe and her tare, see you now, what shall her doe with wands? peate <HI>Gwenthyan?</HI> podie and mag <HI>Gwenthyan</HI> put her finger in me hole: ha, by God by God, is scradge her eies out that judge her, that tawg to her, that loog on her, marg you that Sir <HI>Owen?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>owen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, her marg her, <HI>Rees</HI> pray marg her Ladie?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ri.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not I sir shee'll set her markes on me then.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gwen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is prade? is prade? goe too <HI>Rees,</HI> Ile <HI>Rees</HI> her, you tawg you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Owen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray <HI>Gwenthien</HI> bee patient, as her cozen <HI>Grissill</HI> is.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gwe.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Grissill</HI> owe? owe? <HI>Grissill</HI>? no, no, no, no. her shall not mag <HI>Gwenthian</HI> such ninny pobbie foole as <HI>Grissill,</HI> I say preage her wandes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>owen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Cods plude is pought her to peate dust out of her cloag and parrels.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gwe.</SPEAKER>
<P>Peate her cloag and parrels? fie, fie, fie, tis lye Sir <HI>Owen</HI> tis lye.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ri.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your worship may stab her, she giues you the lye.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ow.</SPEAKER>
<P>Peace <HI>Rees,</HI> goe to, I pought them indeede to mag her horse run and goe a mightie teale of pace, pray let <HI>Rees</HI> tag her in good <HI>Gwenthian?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gwen.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Rees</HI> beare in her wandes because Sir <HI>Owen</HI> beg so gently.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>owen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Goe <HI>Rees,</HI> goe locke them vp in a pox or shest, goe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ri.</SPEAKER>
<P>You shal not need to bid me goe, for Ile run.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="22"/>
<SPEAKER>Owen.</SPEAKER>
<P>I pought them for her horse indeede, for heere was her cozen <HI>Marquesse</HI> and prought her pondes and scriblings heere for her money: <HI>Gwenthyan</HI> pray keepe her pondes and keep her wisely: Sirra <HI>Gwenthyan</HI> is tell her praue newes, <HI>Grissill</HI> is prought to bed of liddle shentleman and shentlewoman: (is glad out a cry speag her faire) yes truely <HI>Grissill</HI> is prought a bed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gwen.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Grissils</HI> no podie but <HI>Grissils</HI>? what care I for <HI>Grissill</HI>: I say if Sir <HI>Owen</HI> loue <HI>Gwenthyan,</HI> shal not loue <HI>Grissill</HI> nor <HI>Marquesse</HI> so, see you now?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ow.</SPEAKER>
<P>God vdge me, not loue her cozen? is shealous? owe is fine trig, not loue her cozen? God vdge me her wil, and hang her selfe, see you now?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gwe.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hang her selfe, owe, owe, owe, <HI>Gwenthyans</HI> to∣ther husband is scawrne to say hang her selfe: hang her selfe? owe owe, owe owe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ow.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gods plude, what cannot get by prawles, is get by owe, owe owe, is terrible Ladie, pray be peace, and cry no more owe, owe, owe, <HI>Tawsone Gwenthyans,</HI> God vdge me is very furie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gwen.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>O mon lago, mon due,</HI> hang <HI>Gwenthyans?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ow.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Adologo whee Gwenthyan bethogh, en Tho∣nigh, en moyen due.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gw.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Ne vetho en Thonigh, cna wathe gethla Tee,</HI> hang <HI>Gwenthyans?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Owen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir <HI>Owen</HI> shall say no more hang her selfe, be out a cry still and her shall pye her new card to ride in, &amp; two new fine horses, and more plew coates and padges ta follow her heeles, see you now?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gwen.</SPEAKER>
<P>But will her say no more hang her selfe?</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Rice.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ow.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh no more, as God vdge mee no more, pray leaue, owe, owe, owe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ri.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Tannekin</HI> the Fide hath brought your Rebato, it comes to three pound.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ow.</SPEAKER>
<P>What a pestilence is this for <HI>Gwenthyan?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="23"/>
<SPEAKER>Gwe.</SPEAKER>
<P>For her neg, is cald repatoes, <HI>Gwenthian</HI> weare it heere, ist not praue?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>owen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Praue? yes is praue, tis repatoes I warrant her: I patoes money out a crie, yes tis praue, <HI>Rees</HI> the preece? <HI>Rees</HI> the preece?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ri.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Froe sir saies fiue pound.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>owen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha ha ha, pound, <HI>Gwenthyan</HI> pray doe not pye it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gwen.</SPEAKER>
<P>By God vdge me her shall pye it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>owen.</SPEAKER>
<P>God vdge me her shall not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gwen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shall not? <HI>Rees</HI> tag her away, I say her shall and weare it pye and pye.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>owen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then mag a pobbie foole of Sir <HI>Owen</HI> indeed: Gods plude shall? I say shal not: fiue pound for puble, for patoes: here there, so tag it now, weare it now powte her neg, shall pridle sir <HI>Owen</HI> ha?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ri.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh rare sir <HI>Owen,</HI> ah pretious Kninght, oh rare Sir <HI>Owen.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gwe.</SPEAKER>
<P>Out you raskals, you prade and prade, ile prade your neaces.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ri.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh rare Madame, oh pretious Madame, O God, O God, O God, O.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gwe.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is domineere now, you teare her ruffes and re∣patoes, you preake her ponds? Ile teare as good pondes, and petter too, and petter too.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ow.</SPEAKER>
<P>Owe <HI>Gwenthyan,</HI> Cods plude is fiue thousand duckets, hold hold hold, a pogs on her pride, what has her done?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gw.</SPEAKER>
<P>Goe loog, is now paide for her repatoes, ile haue her willes &amp; desires, ile teadge her pridle her Lady: <HI>Catho crogge, Ne vetho, en Thlonigh gna wathee Gnathlatee.</HI>
<STAGE>Exit</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>owen.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>A breath vawer or no Tee</HI>: pridle her, sir <HI>owen</HI> is pridled I warrant: widdows (were petter Gods plude marry whoore) were petter be hang'd and quarter, then marry widowes as God vdge me: Sir <HI>owen</HI> fall on her knees, &amp; pray God to tag her to her mercy, or else put pet∣ter minde in her Lady: awl prittish Shentlemans tag
<PB REF="23"/>
heede how her marry fixen widowe.</P>
<L>Sir <HI>owen ap Meredith</HI> can rightly tell,</L>
<L>A shrewes sharpe tongue is terrible as hell.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Marquesse and Furio with an infant in his armes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did she not see thee when thou took'st it vp?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fur.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, she was fast a sleepe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Giue me this blessed burthen, pretty foole</L>
<L>With what an amiable looke it sleepes,</L>
<L>And in that slumber how it sweetly smiles,</L>
<L>And in that smile how my heart leapes for ioy:</L>
<L><HI>Furio</HI> Ile turne this circle to a cradle,</L>
<L>To rocke my deare babe: A great <HI>Romaine</HI> Lord,</L>
<L>Taught his young Sonne to ride a Hodby-horse.</L>
<L>Then why should I thinke scorne to dandle mine:</L>
<L><HI>Furio</HI> beholde it well, to whom ist like?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fur.</SPEAKER>
<L>You, there's your nose and blacke eye-browes.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Mario.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou dost but flatter me, heere comes <HI>Mario,</HI></L>
<L>I know <HI>Mario</HI> will not flatter me,</L>
<L><HI>Mario,</HI> thy opinion, view this childe,</L>
<L>Doth not his lips, his nose, his fore-head,</L>
<L>And euery other part resemble mine?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mari.</SPEAKER>
<L>So like my Lord, that the nice difference,</L>
<L>Would stay the iudgement of the curioust eye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>And yet me thinkes I am not halfe so browne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mari.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeed your cheekes beare a more liuely colour</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Furio,</HI> play thou the nurse, handle it softly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fur.</SPEAKER>
<L>One were better get a dossen then nurse one.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Mario</HI> step to <HI>Grissill</HI> shee's a sleepe,</L>
<L>Her white hand is the piller to those cares,</L>
<L>Which I vngently lodg'e within her head,</L>
<L>Steale thou the other childe and bring it hither,</L>
<L>If <HI>Grissill</HI> be awake and striue with thee,</L>
<L><PB REF="24"/>Bring it perforce, nor let her know what hand,</L>
<L>Hath rob'd her of this other, haste <HI>Mario.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mari.</SPEAKER>
<L>I flie my gratious Lord.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Run flatterie, because I did blaspheme and cal it browne,</L>
<L>This Parrasite cride (like an Eccho) browne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fur.</SPEAKER>
<L>The childe is faire my Lord, you were nere so faire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know tis faire, I know tis wondrous faire,</L>
<L>Deare prettie infant let me with a kisse,</L>
<L>Take that dishonor off, which the foule breath</L>
<L>Of a prophane slaue, laide vpon thy cheekes;</L>
<L>Had but I said my boy's a Blackamoore,</L>
<L>He would haue damn'd himselfe and so haue swore.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Grissill and Mario with a childe.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Giue me mine infant, where's my other babe?</L>
<L>You cannot plaie the nurse, your horred eyes</L>
<L>Will fright my little ones and make them crie,</L>
<L>Your tongue's too ruffe to chime a lullabie:</L>
<L>Tis not the pleasure of my Lord I know,</L>
<L>To loade me with such wrong.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mari.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, I vnloade you.
<STAGE>Scoffingly.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Giue her her childe <HI>Mario</HI> and yet staie,</L>
<L><HI>Furio</HI> holde thou them both, <HI>Grissill</HI> forbeare,</L>
<L>You are but nurse to them they are not thine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gri.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know my gratious Lord they are not mine,</L>
<L>I am but their poore nurse I must confesse,</L>
<L>Alas let not a nurse be pittilesse.</L>
<L>To see the colde ayre make them looke thus bleake,</L>
<L>Makes me shed teares because they cannot speake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>If they could speake, what thinke you they would say?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gri.</SPEAKER>
<L>That I in all things will your wil obay.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Obay it then in silence: shall not I</L>
<L><PB REF="24"/>Bestowe what is myne owne, as likes me best?</L>
<L>Deliuer me these brats: come presse me downe,</L>
<L>With weightie infamie: heere is aloade</L>
<L>Of shame, of speckled shame: O God how heauie</L>
<L>An armefull of dishonour is? heeres two,</L>
<L><HI>Grissill</HI> for this ile thanke none els but you,</L>
<L>Which way so ere I turne I meete a face,</L>
<L>That makes my cheekes blush at mine owne disgrace.</L>
<L>This way or this way, neuer shall mine eye</L>
<L>Looke thus, or thus: but (oh me) presentlie,</L>
<L>(Take them for Gods sake <HI>Furio</HI>) presentlie</L>
<L>I shall spend childish teares: true teares indéed,</L>
<L>That thus I wrong my babes and make her bleede,</L>
<L>Goe <HI>Grissill</HI> get you in.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gri.</SPEAKER>
<L>I goe my Lorde.</L>
<L>Farewell sweet sweet deare babes, so you were free,</L>
<L>Would all the worlds cares might be throwne on me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, ha, why this is pleasing harmonie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fu.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord they'le wrawle, what shall I doe with them?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tell her thou must prouide a nurse for them</L>
<L>Comes she not backe <HI>Mario</HI>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mari.</SPEAKER>
<L>No my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tush, tush, it cannot be but sheele returne,</L>
<L>I know her bosome beares no marble heart,</L>
<L>I knowe, a tender Mother cannot part,</L>
<L>With such a patient soule, from such sweet soules,</L>
<L>She stands and watches sure, and sure the weepes,</L>
<L>To see my seeming flintie breast, <HI>Mario</HI></L>
<L>Withdraw with me: <HI>Furio</HI> stay thou heere still,</L>
<L>If she returne, seeme childish, and denie</L>
<L>To let her kisse or touch them.
<STAGE>Exeunt</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fur.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith not I: I haue not such a heart, and shee aske to touch them. Ile deny it because ile obey my Lord, yet she shall kisse and touch them to, because Ile please my Ladie: alas, alas, prettie fooles I loue you well but I would you had a better Nurse.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="25"/><HI>Enter Grissill stealingly.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gris.</SPEAKER>
<L>A better Nurse: seek'st thou a better Nurse?</L>
<L>A better Nurse then whome?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then you, away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gris.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am their Mother I must not away,</L>
<L>Looke, looke, good <HI>Furio</HI> looke they smile on mée,</L>
<L>I know poore hearts they feare to smile on thee,</L>
<L>I prithée let me haue them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Touch them not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gri.</SPEAKER>
<L>I prie thee let me touch them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fu.</SPEAKER>
<L>No: Hands off.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gri.</SPEAKER>
<L>I prie thee gentle <HI>Furio</HI> let me kisse them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fu,</SPEAKER>
<L>Not one kisse for a Kings crowne:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Must I not kisse my babes: must I not touch them?</L>
<L>Alas what sin so vile hath <HI>Grissil</HI> done</L>
<L>That thus she should be vex'd? not kisse my infants?</L>
<L>Who taught thee to be cruell gentle churle,</L>
<L>What must thou doe with them?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Get them a nurse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gris.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Nurse alacke, what Nurse? where must shee dwell</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fu.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must not tell you: till I know my selfe,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gri.</SPEAKER>
<L>For Gods sake who must Nurse them doe but name her,</L>
<L>And I will sweare those firie eyes doe smile,</L>
<L>And I will sweare that which none els will sweare,</L>
<L>That thy grim browes, doe mercies liuerie weare,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Choose you.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Marquesse, standing aside.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh God, oh God, might <HI>Grissill</HI> haue her choice</L>
<L>My babes should not be scard with thy diuils voice.</L>
<L>Thou get a Nurse for them? they can abide,</L>
<L>To taste no milke but mine, come, come Ile chide,</L>
<L>In faith you cruell man, Ile chide indéede,</L>
<L>If I growe angrie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do do I care not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>To chide &amp; curse thy Lord thou hast more néed</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="25"/>
<SPEAKER>Gris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wilt thou not tell me who shall be their Nurse?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fu.</SPEAKER>
<L>No.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wilt thou not let me kisse them?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fu</SPEAKER>
<L>No I say.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gris.</SPEAKER>
<L>I prithee let my teares, let my bow'd knees,</L>
<L>Bend thy obdurate hart, see héer's a fountaine,</L>
<L>Which heauen into this Alablaster bowels,</L>
<L>Instil'd to nourish them: man theyle crie,</L>
<L>And blame thee that this ronnes so lauishly,</L>
<L>Heres milke for both my babes two brests for two.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Poore babes I wéep to sée what wrong I doe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gris.</SPEAKER>
<L>I pray thee let them suck I am most méete,</L>
<L>To play their Nurse: theyle smile and say tis swéet,</L>
<L>Which streames frō hence, if thou dost beare them hēce,</L>
<L>My angrie breasts will swell, and as mine eyes</L>
<L>Lets fall salt drops, with these white Necter teares,</L>
<L>They will be mixt: this sweet will then be brine,</L>
<L>Theyle crie Ile chide and say the sinne is thine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mine armes ake mightily.</L>
<L>And my heart akes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>And so doth mine: sweet sounds this discord makes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heere Madame take one, I am weary of both, touch it and kisse it to, its a sweet childe, I would I were rid of my miserie, for I shall drowne my heart, with my teares that fall inward.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh this is gentlie done this is my boy.</L>
<L>My first borne care: thy feete that neuere felt ground,</L>
<L>Haue traueld longest in this land of woe,</L>
<L>This worlds wildernes, and hast most neede,</L>
<L>Of my most comfort: oh I thanke thee <HI>Furio,</HI></L>
<L>I know I should transforme thee with my teares,</L>
<L>And melt thy adamantiue heart like waxe,</L>
<L>What wrong shall these haue to be tane from mée,</L>
<L>Mildely intreate their Nurse to touch them mildely,</L>
<L>For my soule tels me, that my honoured Lord,</L>
<L><PB REF="26"/>Does but to trie poore <HI>Grissils</HI> constancie,</L>
<L>Hees full of mercie iustice, full of loue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>My cheekes doe glow with shame to heere her speake,</L>
<L>Should I not weepe for ioy my heart would breake,</L>
<L>And yet a little more Ile stretch my tryall.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Mario and Lepido.</STAGE>
<L>Mario, Lepido?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Both</SPEAKER>
<L>My gracious Lord?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall be witnesse of this open wrong,</L>
<L>I gaue strait charge, she should not touch these brats,</L>
<L>Yet has she tempted with lasciuious teares,</L>
<L>The heart of <HI>Furio,</HI> see she dandles them,</L>
<L>Take that childe from her: stay, stay, ile commend,</L>
<L>That pittie in thee which Ile reprepend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dare you thus contradict our strait commaund</L>
<L>But heeres a trustie groome, out hipocrite,</L>
<L>I shall doe Iustice wrong to let thée breath,</L>
<L>For disobaying me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gris.</SPEAKER>
<L>My gracious Lord,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tempt me not Syren, since you are so louing,</L>
<L>Hold you take both your children, get you gon,</L>
<L>Derobe her of these rich abiliments,</L>
<L>Take downe her hat, her pitcher and her gowne,</L>
<L>And as she came to me in beggerie,</L>
<L>So driue her to her fathers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mari.</SPEAKER>
<L>My deare Lorde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Uex me not good <HI>Mario</HI> if you woe me,</L>
<L>(Or if you shed one teare) to pittie her,</L>
<L>Or if by any drift you succour her,</L>
<L>You loose my fauour euerlastingly,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Both.</SPEAKER>
<L>We must obey since there's no remedye,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>You must be villaines theres no remedie,</L>
<L><HI>Mario, Lepido,</HI> you two shall helpe,</L>
<L>To beare her children home.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="26"/>
<SPEAKER>Gri.</SPEAKER>
<L>It shall not néede I can beare more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou bearest too much indeed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, come sweet lambes wee'll laugh and liue content</L>
<L>Though from the Court we liue in banishment,</L>
<L>These rich attyres are for your mother fit,</L>
<L>But not your nurse, therefore Ile off with it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq</SPEAKER>
<L>Away with her I say.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away, away?</L>
<L>Nothing but that colde comfort wee'll obay,</L>
<L>Heauen smile vpon my Lord with gratious eye,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Driue her hence <HI>Lepido.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lep.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good Madame hence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thus tyranny oppresseth innocence,</L>
<L>Thy lookes seeme heauy, but thy heart is light,</L>
<L>For villaines laugh when wrong oppresseth right.
<STAGE>Run to him</STAGE></L>
<L>Must we then be driuen hence: Oh see my Lord,</L>
<L>Sweet prettie fooles they both smil'd at that word.</L>
<L>They smile as who should say indeede indeede,</L>
<L>Your tongue cryes hence, but your heart's not agree'd,</L>
<L>Can you thus part from them? in truth I know,</L>
<L>Your true loue cannot let these infants goe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee'll tryumph ouer me doe what I can.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Turnes from her.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mari.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good Madame hence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh send one gratious smile</L>
<L>Before we leaue this place: turne not away,</L>
<L>Doe but looke backe, let vs but once more see</L>
<L>Those eyes, whose beames shall breath new soules in three,</L>
<L>It is enough now weele depart in ioy,</L>
<L>Nay be not you so cruell, should you two</L>
<L>Be thus driuen hence, trust me Ide pitty you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Disrobe her presently.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Both.</SPEAKER>
<L>It shall be done.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grissi.</SPEAKER>
<L>To worke some good deede thus you would not runne.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh <HI>Grissill</HI> in large Carracters of golde,</L>
<L><PB REF="27"/>Thy vertuous sacred fame shall be enroulde,</L>
<L>Tell me thy iudgement <HI>Furio</HI> of my wife?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fur.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thinke my Lord shee's a true woman, for shee loues her children, a rare wife, for shee loues you, (I be∣leeue you'll hardly finde her match) and I thinke shee's more then a woman, because shee conqueres all wrongs by patience.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet once more will I trye her, presently</L>
<L>Ile haue thée goe to olde <HI>Ianicolaes,</HI></L>
<L>And take her children from her, breed some doubt,</L>
<L>(By speeches) in her, that her eyes shall neuer</L>
<L>Beholde them more: beare them to <HI>Pauia,</HI></L>
<L>Commend vs to our brother, say from vs,</L>
<L>That we desire him with all kinde respect,</L>
<L>To nurse the infants, and withall conceale,</L>
<L>Their parentage from any mortall eare,</L>
<L>I charge thee on thy life reueale not this,</L>
<L>I charge thee on thy life, be like thy name,</L>
<L>(When thou comst to her) rough and furious.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fur.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, I will: It's far from <HI>Saluce</HI> to <HI>Pauia,</HI> the children will cry, I haue no teates you know, twere good you thought vpon it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>There's golde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fu.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's good.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prouide them nurses.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fu.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's better, I will and I can.
<STAGE>Exit Furio.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away, though I dare trust thy secrecy,</L>
<L>Yet will I follow thee in some disguise,</L>
<L>And try thy faith, and <HI>Grissils</HI> constancy:</L>
<L>If thou abide vnblemisht, then I sweare,</L>
<L>A haue found two wonders that are sildome rise,</L>
<L>A trusty seruant, and a patient wife.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Ianicola and Laureo, with burdens of Osiers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Father how fare you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ian.</SPEAKER>
<L>Uery well my sonne,</L>
<L><PB REF="27"/>This labour is a comfort to my age,</L>
<L>The <HI>Marquesse</HI> hath to me been mercifull,</L>
<L>In sending me from Courtly delicates,</L>
<L>To taste the quiet of this country life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Call him not mercifull, his tyranny</L>
<L>Exceedes the most inhumaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ian.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace my sonne,</L>
<L>I thought by learning thou hadst been made wise,</L>
<L>But I perceiue it puffeth vp thy soule,</L>
<L>Thou takst a pleasure to be counted iust,</L>
<L>And kicke against the faults of mighty men:</L>
<L>Oh tis in vaine, the earth may euen as well</L>
<L>Challenge the potter to be partiall,</L>
<L>For forming it to sundry offices:</L>
<L>Alas the errour of ambitious fooles,</L>
<L>How fraile are all their thoughts, how faint, how weake?</L>
<L>Those that doe striue to iustle with the great,</L>
<L>Are certaine to be bruz'd, or soone to breake.</L>
<L>Come, come mell with our Osiers, heere let's rest,</L>
<L>This is olde homely home, &amp; that's still best.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Babulo with a bundle of Osiers in one arme and a childe in another, Grissill after him with another childe.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bab.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hush, hush, hush, hush, and I daunce mine own childe and I dance mine owne childe, &amp;c: ha ha, whoop olde Master, so ho ho, looke heere, and I dance mine own childe, &amp;c: heere's sixteene pence a weeke, and sixteene pence a weeke, eight groates, sope and candle, I met her in Osier groue, crying hush, hush, hush, hush: I thought it had been some begger woman, because of her pitcher, for you know they beare such houshold stuffe, to put drinke and porrage together, and I dance mine, &amp;c.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh father now forsweare all patience,</L>
<L><HI>Grissill</HI> comes home to you in poore array,</L>
<L><HI>Grissill</HI> is made a drudge, a cast-away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ian.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Grissill</HI> is welcome home to pouerty,</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="28"/><HI>The Song.</HI></STAGE>
<LG>
<L>GOlden slumbers kisse your eyes,</L>
<L>Smiles awake you when you rise:</L>
<L>Sleepe pretty wantons doe not cry,</L>
<L>And I will sing a lullabie,</L>
<L>Rocke them rocke them lullabie.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Care is heauy therefore sleepe you,</L>
<L>You are care and care must keep you:</L>
<L>Sleepe pretty wantons doe not cry,</L>
<L>And I will sing a lullabie,</L>
<L>Rocke them rocke them lullabie.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Enter Furio and Marquesse aloofe disguised with baskets.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fur.</SPEAKER>
<P>Leaue singing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<P>We may choose, Grandsire sol fa once more, we'll alla mire him, and he we waile in woe, and who can hin∣der vs?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fur.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sirra Scholler read there, it's a commission for mee to take away these children.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay then y'are welcome, there's foure groates, and heere's foure more.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gri.</SPEAKER>
<L>To take away my children gentle <HI>Furio,</HI></L>
<L>Why must my babes beare this vngentle doome?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe looke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>O misery, O most accursed time,</L>
<L>When to be foes to guilt is helde a crime,</L>
<L>Sister this fiend must beare your infants hence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good <HI>Grissil</HI> beare al wrongs w<SUP>t</SUP> patience.
<STAGE>Weepes</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good father let true patience cure all woe,</L>
<L>You bid me be content, oh be you so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Father why doe you weepe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ian.</SPEAKER>
<L>What can I doe,</L>
<L>Though her he punish, he might pitty you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let's fret and curse the <HI>Marquesse</HI> cruelly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="28"/>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<P>I by my troth that's a good way, we may well do it, now we are out of his hearing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Must I then be diuorc'd? and loose this treasure,</L>
<L>I must and am content, since tis his pleasure,</L>
<L>I prie thee tell we whither they must goe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fu.</SPEAKER>
<L>No.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Art thou commaunded to conceale the place?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fur.</SPEAKER>
<L>I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then will not I inquire, thou dost but iest</L>
<L>I know thou must not rob me, tis to try</L>
<L>If I loue them: no, no, heere I read,</L>
<L>That which strikes blinde mine eyes, makes my heart bleede,</L>
<L>Farewell, farewell, deare soules, adue adue,</L>
<L>Your father sendes and I must part from you,</L>
<L>I must oh God I must, must is for Kings,</L>
<L>And loe obedience for loe vnderlings.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>He shall not hale them thus, keep them perforce,</L>
<L>This slaue lookes on them with a murdring eye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, he shal not haue them, knocke out his braines, and saue the little hop a my thombes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe if you dare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now my hearts, what's the matter?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fu.</SPEAKER>
<L>What car'st thou.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is poore <HI>Grissil,</HI> wife vnto our Duke,</L>
<L>And these her children, thus he sendes her home,</L>
<L>And thus he sends a serpent to deuour,</L>
<L>Their pretious liues he brings commission,</L>
<L>To hale them hence, but whyther none can tell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Forbeare, forbeare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take them from him perforce,</L>
<L>Are these his children?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<L>So she saies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Two sweet Duckes, and is this his wife?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, he has lyne with her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>A pretty soule, sirra thou wilt be hang'd for this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hang thy selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="29"/>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beate him, but first take these two from his armes,</L>
<L>I am a basket maker, and I sweare</L>
<L>Ile dye before he beare away the babes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh rare, cry prentises and clubs, the corporation cannot be ( ) sirra set downe thy baskets and to't pell mell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Would I were rid of my office?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gri.</SPEAKER>
<P>What will you doe, driue this rashe fellowe hence?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<P>The <HI>Marquesse</HI> is a tyrant and does worng.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gri▪</SPEAKER>
<P>I would not for the world that hee should heare thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>I would not for ten worlds but heare my <HI>Grissil.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gri.</SPEAKER>
<L>A tyrant, no he's mercy euen her selfe,</L>
<L>Iustice in triumph rides in his two eyes,</L>
<L>Take héede how thou prophanest high deityes:</L>
<L>Goe <HI>Furio,</HI> get thee gone: good father helpe me</L>
<L>To guard my deare Lords seruant from this place,</L>
<L>I know hée'll doe my pretty babes no harme,</L>
<L>For see <HI>Furio</HI> lookes gently: oh get thee gone,</L>
<L>Pitty sits on thy cheekes, but God can tell,</L>
<L>My heart saies my tongue lyes, farewell farewell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<P>Stay sirra take thy purse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fur.</SPEAKER>
<P>I let none fall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<P>Halfe part.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ia.</SPEAKER>
<P>A purse of golde <HI>Furio</HI> is falne from thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Its none of mine, sirra basket-maker, if my armes were not full, thou should haue thy handes full: farewel <HI>Grissill,</HI> if thou neuer see thy children more, curse mee, if thou dost see them againe, thanke God, adue.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<P>Farewell and be hang'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gri.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will thanke God for all, why should I grieue,</L>
<L>To loose my children? no no, I ought rather</L>
<L>Reioyce, because they are borne to their Father.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ia.</SPEAKER>
<P>Daughter, heere's nothing in this purse but golde.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<P>So much the better, Master we'll quickely turne
<PB REF="29"/>
it into siluer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ia.</SPEAKER>
<L>This purse that fellow did let fall, run run,</L>
<L>Carry it him againe, run <HI>Babulo,</HI></L>
<L>Away with it, tis laide to doe vs wrong.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Try all their golden baites, stay neuer run,</L>
<L>They can doe no more wrong then they haue done.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ia.</SPEAKER>
<L>What ayles my <HI>Grissill</HI>? comfort my childe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile fetch <HI>Rosa solis.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Poore soule her griefe burnes inward, yet her tung</L>
<L>Is loath to giue it freedome: I doe wrong,</L>
<L>Oh <HI>Grissill</HI> I doe wrong thee and, lament,</L>
<L>That for my sake thou feel'st this languishment.</L>
<L>I came to try a seruant and a wife,</L>
<L>Both haue I prooued true, that purse of golde I brought,</L>
<L>And let if fall of purpose to relieue her,</L>
<L>Well may I giue her golde that so much grieue her,</L>
<L>As I came in by stealth, so Ile away,</L>
<L>Ioy has a tongue, but knowes not what to say.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gri.</SPEAKER>
<L>So father I am well, I am well indeed,</L>
<L>I should doe wondrous ill, should I repine,</L>
<L>At my babes losse for they are none of mine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ia.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am glad thou tak'st this wound so patiently.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whoope whether is my brother basket-maker gone: ha let me see, I smell a rat, sneakt hence and neuer take leaue, eyther hee's a craftie knaue, or else hee dogs <HI>Furio</HI> to byte him, for when a quarrell enters into a trade it serues seauen yeares before it be free.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let him be whome he will, he seem'd our friend,</L>
<L><HI>Grissill</HI> lay vp this golde tis <HI>Furioes</HI> sure,</L>
<L>Or it may be thy Lord did giue it him,</L>
<L>To let it fall for thee, but keep it safe,</L>
<L>If he disdaine to loue thee as a wife,</L>
<L>His golde shall not buy foode to nourish thee,</L>
<L><HI>Grissill</HI> come in, time swiftly runs away,</L>
<L>The greatest sorrow hath an ending day.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="30"/><HI>Enter Gwenthyan and Rice, she meanely, he like a Cooke.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gwen.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Rees,</HI> lay her table, and set out her fittailes, and preades, and wines, and ale, and peare, and salt for her guesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ri.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes forsooth my Lady but what shal I do with all yonder beggers?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gwe.</SPEAKER>
<P>Send out the peggers into her Lady, goe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ri.</SPEAKER>
<P>How? the beggers in, wee shall haue a louzie feast Madame.
<STAGE>Exit Rees.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gwen.</SPEAKER>
<P>You rascals prate no more, but fetch them in: shall pridle Sir <HI>Owen</HI> a good teale well enough, is war∣rant her. Sir <HI>Owen</HI> is gone to bid her cozen <HI>Marquesse</HI> and a meiny to dyne at her house, but <HI>Gwenthyan</HI> shall kiue her dinner I warrant her, for peggers shall haue all her meate.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Rees with a company of beggers: a Table is set with meate.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ri.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come my hearts, troope, troope, euery man follow his leader, heere's my Lady.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<P>God blesse your Ladiship, God blesse your Ladi∣ship.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gwen.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thang you my good peggers, <HI>Rees</HI> pring stooles, sid awl downe, <HI>Rees</HI> pring more meate.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ri.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heere Madame, Ile set it on, tak't off who will.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let vs alone for that, my Lady shall we scram∣ble or eate mannerly?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gwen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Peggers I hobe haue no manners, but first heare me pray you now, and then fall to out a crie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Peace heare my Lady, Iacke-mumble-crust steale no penny loaues.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gwen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Peggers, awl you know Sir <HI>Owen</HI>?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<P>Passing well, passing well, God blesse his wor∣ship.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="30"/>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Beg.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Madame, we know him as well as a begger knowes his dish.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gwe.</SPEAKER>
<P>Awl these fittels is made for Cozen <HI>Marquesse</HI>: Sir <HI>Owen</HI> is gone to fedge him, but Sir <HI>owen</HI> has anger her Ladie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Beg.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>More shame for him, hee's not a Knight, but a knitter of caps for it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gwe.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir <HI>Owen</HI> has anger her Lady, and therfore her Lady is anger Sir <HI>Owen</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Beg.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Make him a cuckolde Madame, and vpon that I drinke to you: helter skelter here roagues, top and top gallant, pell mell, huftie tuftie, hem, God saue the Duke, and a fig for the hangman.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gwen.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Rees</HI> fedge wine and peares enough, and fall to pegger, and eate awl her shéere, and tomineere, see you now, pray doe.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>A drunken feast, they quarrel and grow drunke, and pocket vp the meate, the dealing of Cannes like a set a Mawe. Exit Rees.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gwe.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay I pray peggers be quiet, tag your meates, you haue trinkes enough I see, and get you home nowe good peggers.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Beg.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Come your roagues, lets goe tag and rag, cut and long taile, I am victualed for a month, God bo'y Madame, pray God Sir <HI>owen</HI> and you may fall out eue∣ry day: Is there any harme in this now? hey tri-lill, giue the dog a loafe, fill the tother pot you whoore &amp; God saue the Duke.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gwe.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thang you good peggers, ha ha, this is fine spord, by God is haue peggers eate her fittales all day long.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Sir Owen and Rees.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ow.</SPEAKER>
<P>Where is the sheere <HI>Rees</HI>? Cods plude where?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ri.</SPEAKER>
<P>I beseech you sir be patient, I tell you the beggers haue it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Owen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wad a pogs is doe with peggers? wad is peg∣gers
<PB REF="31"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="31"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="missing" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="32"/>
<SPEAKER>Fa.</SPEAKER>
<P>How my Lady <HI>Gwenthian?</HI> ha ha ha.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Marquesse, Iulio, Onophria, Vrcenze, Mario.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>You see Sir <HI>Owen</HI> we are soone inuited,</L>
<L>Where is your wife the Lady <HI>Gwenthian?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Owen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is come pie and pie, Cod vdge me <HI>Gwenthian</HI> pray put on your prauerie and fine knags, and shame not Sir <HI>Owen,</HI> yes truely <HI>Gwenthian</HI> is come out pie and pie, <HI>Man gras worthe whee</HI> cozen <HI>Marguesse, Man gras worthe whee</HI> cozen <HI>Iolia</HI> is welcome awl.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fa</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha ha welcome, come come Madame appeare in your likenes, or rather in the likenes of another, my Lord y'are best send backe to your owne Cookes, if you meane to set your teeth a worke to day.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why <HI>Farneze</HI> what's the matter?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay there's no matter in it, the fire's quencht, the victuals giuen to beggers, Sir <HI>Owens</HI> kitchin lookes like the first <HI>Chaos,</HI> or like a Brokers stall, full of odde endes: or like the end of some terrible battle, for vpon euery dres∣ser lyes legges and feathers, and heads of poore Capons and wilde foule that haue bin drawne and quartred, and now mourne that their carkasses are carried away: his are not rewmaticke, for there's no spitting heere lye fish in a pittifull pickle, there standes the coffins of pyes, wherein the dead bodies of birdes should haue been buri∣ed, but their ghostes haue forsaken their graues &amp; walkt abroad: the best sport is to see the scullians, some laugh∣ing, some crying, &amp; whilst they wipe their eies they blacke their faces, the Cookes curse her Lady, and some pray for our Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir <HI>Owen Meredith</HI> is all this true?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ow.</SPEAKER>
<P>True, et is true I warrant her pogs on her too true.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ono.</SPEAKER>
<P>You tolde his Grace you had tam'd your wife.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Owen.</SPEAKER>
<P>By Cod is tell her a lye then, her wise has pri∣dled
<PB REF="32"/>
&amp; tam'd her indeed: cozen <HI>Marquesse</HI> pecause <HI>Grissill</HI> is made foole and turne away, <HI>Gwenthian</HI> mag foole of sir <HI>owen</HI>: is good? ha, is good?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gwen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis lye cozen <HI>Marguesse,</HI> is terrible lye: <HI>raw∣sone en Ennoh Twewle,</HI> tis lye, tis lye, sit <HI>Owen</HI> teare her repatoes and ruffes, and pridle her Latie, &amp; bid her hang her selfe, but is pridled I warrant her, is not Sir <HI>Owen</HI>?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>owe.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Adologg whee bethogh en Thlonigh, en Moyen due, Gwenthian.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gwe.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Ne vetho en Thlonigh, Gna watha gethla Tee.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrc.</SPEAKER>
<P>What sayes she sir <HI>Owen?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Owe.</SPEAKER>
<P>I pray &amp; pray her for Cods loue be quiet, splude her say her will not be quiet, do what Sir <HI>owen</HI> can: <HI>mon due Gwenthian, Me knocke the pen, en vmbleth, pobe des, and pobe nose.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gwe.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Gwenogh olcha vessagh whee, en herawgh, ee.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Stand betweene them <HI>Farneze.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Far.</SPEAKER>
<P>You shall bob no nose heere.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gwe.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>En herawgh Ee? Me grauat the Legatee, athlan ith pendee▪ adroh ornymee on dictar, en hecar Ee.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ono.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doth she threaten you Sir <HI>Owen</HI>? binde her to the peace.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>owe.</SPEAKER>
<P>By Cod is threaten her indeed, her saies shee'll scradge out Sir <HI>owens</HI> eyes, and her frowne vpon her, a pogs on her nailes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh my deare <HI>Grissill,</HI> how much different</L>
<L>Art thou to this curst spirit heere, I say</L>
<L>My <HI>Grissils</HI> vertues shine Sir <HI>Meredith.</HI></L>
<L>And Cozen <HI>Gwenthian</HI> come Ile haue you friends,</L>
<L>This dinner shall be sau'd, and all shall say,</L>
<L>Tis done, because tis <HI>Gwenthians</HI> fasting day.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gwe.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Gwenthian</HI> scawrnes to be fciendes, her Ladie will be Master Sir <HI>owen.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ow.</SPEAKER>
<P>By Cod ile see her Latie hang'd first: cozen <HI>Mar∣quesse</HI> &amp; cozens awl, pray tag time &amp; stay heere, <HI>Rees</HI> shall
<PB REF="33"/>
dresse more fittels, and shall dine her in spite of her La∣die: Cod splude <HI>Rees Rees.</HI>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gwe.</SPEAKER>
<P>Will you? Is try that pie and pie: <HI>Stethe whee lawer,</HI> Cozen <HI>Marguesse Stethe whee lawer</HI> Shentlemen, <HI>Gwenthian</HI> is not pridled so soone.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile see the peace kept sure, doe what he can, I doubt his wife will prooue the better man.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Signior Mario</HI> you say nothing, how like you this enterlude?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mari.</SPEAKER>
<P>So well Madame, that I rather with to play the begger, then a Kinges part in it in Sir <HI>Owens</HI> ap∣parrell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why this it is to be married, thus you see those that goe to wooe, goe to woe, oh for a Drum to summon all my louers, my suiters, my seruants together.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fa.</SPEAKER>
<P>I appeare sweet mistresse without summons.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ono.</SPEAKER>
<P>So does <HI>Onophrio.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrc.</SPEAKER>
<P>So does <HI>Vrcenze.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Signior Emulo</HI> I see will not bee seene without calling.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Far.</SPEAKER>
<P>No faith Madame, he's blowne vp, no calling can serue him, hee has tane another manner of calling vpon him, and I hope repents the folly of his youth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iu.</SPEAKER>
<P>If he follow that vocation well, he'll prooue weal∣thy in wit.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrc.</SPEAKER>
<P>He had need for his head is very poore.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Far.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well mistris wee appeare without drumming, what's your parley (and yet not so) your eyes are the drums that summons vs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrc.</SPEAKER>
<P>And your beauty the colours we fight vnder.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ono.</SPEAKER>
<P>And the touch of your soft hand, armes vs at al pointes with deuotion to serue you, desire to obey you, and vowes to loue you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay then in faith make me all souldier, mine eies a drum, my beautie your colours, and my hand your ar∣mour: what becomes of the rest?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="33"/>
<SPEAKER>Far.</SPEAKER>
<P>It becomes vs to rest, before we come to the rest, yet for a neede we could turne you into an armourie: as for example, your lips (let me see) no point of war for your lips? can I put them to no vse but kissing? oh yes, if you change them to shoote out vnkinde language to vs that stand at your mercie, they are two culuerins to de∣stroy vs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<P>That ile trie: my tongue shall giue fire to my words presently.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh be more mercifull faire Iulia.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not I, would you haue mee pittie you and pun∣nish my selfe? would you wish me to loue? when loue is so full of hate? how vnlouely is loue? how bitter? how ful of blemishes, my Lord and brother insults our <HI>Grissill,</HI> that makes me glad, <HI>Gwenthyan</HI> curbs Sir <HI>Owen,</HI> that makes you glad, Sir <HI>Owen</HI> is maistred by his Mistris that makes you mad, poore <HI>Grissil</HI> is martred by her Lord that makes you merrie, for I alwaies wish that a womā may neuer meete better bargaines, when sheele thrust her sweet libertie into the hands of a man: fye vpon you, you're nothing but woormewood, and oake, and glasse: you haue bitter tongues, hard hearts, and brittle faith.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ono.</SPEAKER>
<P>Condemne vs not till you trye our loues.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sweet seruant speake not in this language of loue, <HI>Gwenthyans</HI> peeuishnes and <HI>Grissils</HI> patience, make me heere to defie that Ape <HI>Cupid,</HI> if you loue stand vpon his lawes, I charge you leaue it, I charge you neither to sigh for loue nor speake of loue, nor frowne for hate: if you sigh ile mocke you, if you speake ile stop mine eares, if you frowne ile bend my fist.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Far.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then youle turne warriour in deede.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<P>Had I not neede encountring with such ene∣mies? but say will you obay and followe mee or disobay, and Ile flie you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="34"/>
<SPEAKER>Ono.</SPEAKER>
<P>I obay since it is your pleasure.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrc.</SPEAKER>
<P>I obay though I taste no pleasure in it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Farn.</SPEAKER>
<P>I obay to, but so God helpe me mistris I shall shew you a faire paire of heeles and crie a new Mistris a new, if any pittifull creature will haue me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<P>Better lost then found if you be so wauering.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Marquesse Lepido, Sir owen, Gwenthyan braue, and Furio.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Furio</HI> hie thee to olde <HI>Ianicolaes,</HI></L>
<L>Charge him, his daughter <HI>Grissil,</HI> and his Sonne</L>
<L>To come to Court, to doe such office,</L>
<L>Of duetie to our marriage, as shall like</L>
<L>Our state to lay vpon them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh my Lord,</L>
<L>Uex not poore <HI>Grissill</HI> more, alas her heart,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tut tut, ile haue my will and tame her pride,</L>
<L>Ile make her be a seruant to my bride,</L>
<L><HI>Iulia</HI> Ile bridle her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<P>You doe her wrong.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sister correct that errour, come Sir <HI>owen,</HI></L>
<L>Is not this better musicke then your brawles?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ow.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes as Cod vdg me is: how cozen <HI>Iulia,</HI> is out a crie friends now, <HI>Gwenthyan</HI> is laugh &amp; be ferie patience now Sir <HI>Owen</HI> kisse her Ladie, a great teale now: see els?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Far.</SPEAKER>
<P>I but Sir <HI>owen,</HI> the kissing her Lady is no mirth to vs, if wee kisse the poste.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>owe.</SPEAKER>
<P>Owe her cozen <HI>Marquesse</HI> has terrible mightie newes for tell her, or els is made readie a great banquit at home for awl, pray come home, is awll ready for her, her Ladie say not boepeepe now: but first heare her cozen <HI>Marquesse</HI> newes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Iulia</HI> and Gentlemen these are the newes,</L>
<L>Brought on the wings of hast and happines,</L>
<L>By trustie <HI>Lepido</HI> our endeared brother,</L>
<L>Is hard at hand who in his companie,</L>
<L>Brings my faire second choice a worthie bride,</L>
<L><PB REF="34"/>Attended by the States of <HI>Pauia,</HI></L>
<L>Shees daughter to the Duke of <HI>Brandenburgh,</HI></L>
<L>Now shall no subiects enuious soule repine,</L>
<L>And call her base whome now I will make mine,</L>
<L>None shall vpbraid me now, (as they haue done)</L>
<L>That I will slay a daughter and a Sonne,</L>
<L><HI>Grissils</HI>▪ two babes are dead, and kild by scorne,</L>
<L>But that faire issue that shall now be borne</L>
<L>Shall make a satisfaction of all wrongs.</L>
<L>Come gentlemen we will goe meete this traine,</L>
<L>Let euerie one put on a smiling browe,</L>
<L>Sir <HI>Owen</HI> I will haue your company,</L>
<L>And your's faire cozen: well remembred to,</L>
<L>Bring your three wands Sir <HI>Owen</HI> to the Court,</L>
<L>Though <HI>Gwenthyan</HI> looke with a smoother eye,</L>
<L>Ile teach you how to win the soueraigntie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ow.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is glad of that, ha, ha, ha, tag heed of wands</P>
<P>Lady,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gwen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tag heede of nailes knight,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>We play the vnthrifts in consuming time,</L>
<L>Though your curst wife make some afraid to woe</L>
<L>Yet Ile woe once more and be married to.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ow.</SPEAKER>
<P>Cod vdge me Sir <HI>Owen</HI> would hang before her marrie once more, if I were another Patcheler: marie owe.
<STAGE>Exeunt omnes.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Laureo reading and Babulo with him.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bab.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come I haue left my worke to see what mattēs you mumble to your selfe, faith <HI>Laureo</HI> I would you could leaue this lattin, and fal to make baskets, you think tis enough if at dinner you tell vs a tale of Pigmes, and then mounch vp our virtuals, but that fits not vs: or the historie of the well <HI>Helicon,</HI> &amp; then drinke vp our beare we cannot liue vpon it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<P>A Scholler doth disdaine to spend his spirits, Vpon such base imploiments as hand labours.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="35"/>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good <HI>Furio</HI> vanish, we haue no appetite, tell your Master, Clownes are not for the Court, wee'll keepe Court our selues, for what doe Courtiers but wee doe the like: you eate good cheere, and wee eate good bread and cheese: you drinke wine, and we strong beare: at night you are as hungry slaues as you were at noone, why so are wee: you goe to bed, you can but sleepe, why and so doe wee: in the morning you rise about eleuen of the clocke, why there we are your betters, for wee are going before you: you weare silkes, and wee sheepe∣skinnes, innocence caries it away in the world to come, and therefore vanish good <HI>Furio,</HI> torment vs not good my sweet <HI>Furio.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fur.</SPEAKER>
<P>Asse Ile haue you snaffled,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<P>It may be so, but then <HI>Furio</HI> Ile kicke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Will you goe, or shall I force you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gri.</SPEAKER>
<L>You neede not, for Ile run to serue my Lord,</L>
<L>Or if I wanted legs, vpon my knees</L>
<L>Ile creepe to Court so I may see him pleas'd,</L>
<L>Then courage Father.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ian.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well said patience,</L>
<L>Thy vertues arme mine age with confidence,</L>
<L>Come son, bond-men must serue, shall we away?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, I, but this shall prooue a fatall day.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gri.</SPEAKER>
<P>Brother, for my sake doe not wrong your selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shall I in silence bury all our wrongs?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes when your words cannot get remedy,</L>
<L>Learne of me <HI>Laureo</HI> I that share most woe,</L>
<L>Am the least moou'd, father leane on mine arme,</L>
<L>Brother leade you the way, whilst wretched I</L>
<L>Upholde olde age, and cast downe miserie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Away.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba,</SPEAKER>
<P>Old M. you have fisht faire &amp; catcht a frog.
<STAGE>Exeunt</STAGE></P>
<STAGE>Enter Marquesse, Pauia Lepido, Onophrio, Vrcenzi, Farnezi, and Mario.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lords as you loue our State, affect our loues,</L>
<L><PB REF="35"/>Like of your owne content, respect your liues,</L>
<L>Urge vs no further, <HI>Gwalter</HI> is resolu'd,</L>
<L>To marry the halfe heyre of <HI>Brandenburgh,</HI></L>
<L>My brother <HI>Pau<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="indecipherable" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></HI> with no small expence,</L>
<L>Hath brought the Princesse out of <HI>Germany.</HI></L>
<L>Together with Prince <HI>Gwalter</HI> her young brother,</L>
<L>Now they are come, learne of the rising Sunne,</L>
<L>Scatter the clowdy mistes of discontent,</L>
<L>As he disperceth vapours with his beames.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Brother, there is no eye but brightly shines,</L>
<L>Gladnes voth lodge in your Nobles lookes,</L>
<L>Nor haue they any cause to cloude their browes.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Sir Owen, Gwenthian, and Rees with wandes:</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Far</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh heere comes Sir <HI>Owen,</HI> and my Lady pati∣ence, coome there.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>owen.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Tardaugh</HI> Cozen <HI>Marquesse</HI> &amp; Lawrdes awl.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Welcome good cozen <HI>Gwenthian,</HI> wil you please Goe in, and lend your prefence to my bride?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gwe.</SPEAKER>
<P>Cozen, tis her intentions so to do, but I sweare and I were <HI>Grissill</HI>▪ I would pull her eyes out, &amp; she were as many <HI>Sharmaines</HI> daughter is there becowes in <HI>Cam∣bria</HI> and that is aboue twenty score and a lidle more, you know Sir <HI>Owen</HI>?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ow.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes truely aboue a dozen more is warrant her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Grissill</HI> is patient Madame, be you pleas'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gwen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, and she bee so baselies minded tis well, but I know whad I know Sir <HI>Owen</HI> heere thinkes to make <HI>Gwenthians</HI> so patience, sir <HI>owen</HI> tis awl in vaines, well I goe to her Brides.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ow.</SPEAKER>
<P>You prade and you taug <HI>Gwenthians,</HI> but I made you put on parrels for awl your taug and prade: <HI>Rees,</HI> where's <HI>Rees</HI> spring the wandes heere <HI>Rees.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ri.</SPEAKER>
<P>They are héere sir, in the twinckling of an eye.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>owe.</SPEAKER>
<P>Cozen, when her weddings are done and at lea∣sures, I will learne your medicines to tame shrewes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="36"/>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<P>You shall anon good Cozen <HI>Meredith.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ow.</SPEAKER>
<P>Stand by <HI>Rees,</HI> walke in the halles among the Seruingmans, kéepe her wandes till I call, heare you now?</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Inter Furio.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ri.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes Sir.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Furio</HI> are <HI>Grissill</HI> and the other come?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fur.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, they are come.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<P>Are they imployed according to our charge?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fu.</SPEAKER>
<P>They are.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<P>How does her brother take it?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ill.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<P>How her Father?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<P>How her selfe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Better.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Furio,</HI> goe call out <HI>Grissill</HI> from the Bride.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fu.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will.
<STAGE>Exit Furio.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Farn.</SPEAKER>
<P>It's pitty that fellow was not made a Soldier, hee should haue but a word and a blow at his hands.</P>
<STAGE>Enter lanicola and Babulo carrying coales, Laureo with wood, Grissill with wood.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<P>Master goe you but vnder the Cole-staffe, <HI>Babu∣lo</HI> can beare all, staffe basket and all.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ian.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is the <HI>Marquesse</HI> pleasure I must drudge,</L>
<L>Loade me I pray thee, I am borne to beare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>But Ile no longer beare a logger head,</L>
<L>Thus Ile cast downe his fewell in dispight,</L>
<L>So, though my heart be sad, my shoulder's light.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas what doe you brother, see you not</L>
<L>Our dread Lord yonder▪ come performe his will,</L>
<L>Oh in a subiect this is too too ill.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>What mean'st thou fellow to cast downe thy loade?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have cast downe my burthen not my loade,</L>
<L>The loade of your grosse wrongs lyes héere like leade.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<P>What fellow is this?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="36"/>
<SPEAKER>Gris.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your handmaid <HI>Grissils</HI> brother,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<P>Take him away into the Posters lodge,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lodge me in dungeons, I will still exclaime,</L>
<L>On <HI>Gwalters</HI> cursed acts and hated name.
<STAGE>Exit. with Marq.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Grissill</HI> Take you his load and beare it in.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh tiger minded monstrous <HI>Marquesse,</HI> make thy Ladie a collier?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whats that that villiane prates so?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bab.</SPEAKER>
<P>God blesse the noble <HI>Marquesse,</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sirha take you his coales, <HI>Grissill</HI> depart,</L>
<L>Returne but beare that first,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gris.</SPEAKER>
<P>With all my heart.
<STAGE>Exeunt. Gris. and Ba. grinning at him.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<P>Stay you <HI>Ianicola,</HI> I haue heard you sing,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ian</SPEAKER>
<P>I could haue sung when I was free from care.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<P>What grief can in your aged bosome lie?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ian.</SPEAKER>
<P>Griefe that I am vngratious in your eye,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then would he not desire your company▪</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Grissill.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Ianicola</HI> here is a bridall song,</L>
<L>Play you the Larke to greete my blessed sunne,</L>
<L><HI>Grissill</HI> are you return'd? play you the morning,</L>
<L>To leade forth <HI>Gratiana</HI> my bright bride</L>
<L>Goe in and waite on her <HI>Ianicola.</HI></L>
<L>Sing <HI>Hymeneus</HI> himmes, Musicke I say.
<STAGE>Exit. Grissill.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ow.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Tawsone Tawsone</HI> Cozens aul, and here harmonies and sol faes.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>The Song.</STAGE>
<L>Song. Beautie arise, shew foorth thy glorious shining,</L>
<L>Thine eyes feed Loue, for them he standeth pyning,</L>
<L>Honour and youth attend to doe their duetie,</L>
<L>To thee (their onely soueraigne) Beautie.</L>
<L>Beautie arize, whilst we thy seruants sing,</L>
<L>Ioue to Hymen wedlocke iocund King.</L>
<L>Ioto Hymen lo lo sing.</L>
<L>of wedlock, loue, and youth is Hymen King.</L>
<L><PB REF="37"/>Beauty arise, beauty arise, thy glorious lightes display▪</L>
<L>Whilst we sing so, glad to see this day,</L>
<L>Io Io Io Hymen Io Io sing,</L>
<L>Of wedlocke, loue, and youth is Hymen King.</L>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Art thou as glad in soule as in thy song?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ian.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who can be glad when he indureth wrong?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ow.</SPEAKER>
<P>As Cod vdge me <HI>Ian Niclas</HI> is honest man, hee does not flatter and sembles, but tell his intentions: owe more melodies, owe heere come her new pride.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Musicke sounds, enter Grissill alone, after her the Marquesse Sonne and daughter, Iulia, Gwenthian and other Ladies, and Mario and Furio.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Salute my beautious loue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<L>All ioy betide to <HI>Gratiana</HI> our deare <HI>Marquesse</HI> Bride.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bring me a crowne of gold to crowne my loue,</L>
<L>A wreath of willow for dispised <HI>Grissill.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gri.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Grissill</HI> is not despised in your eye,</L>
<L>Sithence you name her name so gently.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ow.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Gwenthians</HI> there's wiues, there's patient wiues</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gwe</SPEAKER>
<L>Fuh fuh is fooles, <HI>Tawsone</HI> is arrant pobie fooles.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Grissill</HI> place you this crowne vpon her head,</L>
<L>Put these imbrodered slippers on her feete.</L>
<L>Tis well, deliuer me your wedding ring,</L>
<L>Circle-her finger with it, now stand by,</L>
<L>Art thou content with all?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gris.</SPEAKER>
<P>Content with all.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Bride is Crown'd, now tell me all of you,</L>
<L>Which of you euer saw my loue before?</L>
<L>What is her name, her birth, place, or estate,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lep.</SPEAKER>
<P>Till now I neuer behelde her beautie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ono.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nor I.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Trust me nor I.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Far.</SPEAKER>
<L>By my troth nor I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mari.</SPEAKER>
<L>We heare that she was borne in <HI>Germany,</HI></L>
<L>And halfe heyre to the Duke of <HI>Brandenburgh.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="37"/>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<P>You all heare this, and all thinke this?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<L>We doe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq</SPEAKER>
<L>Then <HI>Fu.</HI> stand thou foorth, Lords in his brest</L>
<L>A loyall seruants true soule doth rest,</L>
<L><HI>Furio</HI> shall be apparrelled in a robe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fur.</SPEAKER>
<P>I shall not become it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Some that are great put robes on Parasites,</L>
<L><HI>Mario, Lepido</HI> come you two hither,</L>
<L>Are not you richly clad? haue I done so?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Both.</SPEAKER>
<P>What meanes your grace by this?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gracelesse, haue done,</P>
<L>Truth, sildome dwels in a still talking tongue,</L>
<L><HI>Furio</HI> bring <HI>Laureo</HI> from the Porters lodge,</L>
<L>Take in <HI>Ianicola,</HI> and cloath them both</L>
<L>In rich abiliments, they shall awhile</L>
<L>Be flattered with false fortunes wanton smiles.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fortune can do no more then she hath done,</L>
<L>They that are markt to woe, to woe must run.
<STAGE>Exit Futio &amp; Ianicola.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<P>How doe you like my Bride?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gri.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thinke her blest.</L>
<L>To haue the loue of such a noble Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<P>You flatter me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grissi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeed I speake the truth,</L>
<L>Onely I prostrately beseech your grace,</L>
<L>That you consider of her tender yeares,</L>
<L>Which as a flower in spring may soone be nipt,</L>
<L>With the least frost of colde aduersity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq</SPEAKER>
<L>Why are not you then nipt? you stil seeme fresh</L>
<L>As if aduersities colde Izie hand,</L>
<L>Had neuer laide his fingers on your heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gri.</SPEAKER>
<L>It neuer toucht my heart, aduersity</L>
<L>Dwels still with them that dwels with misery,</L>
<L>But milde content hath eas'd me of that yoake,</L>
<L>Patience hath borne the bruize and I the stroke.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Furio, Ianicola, and Laureo, striuing about attyre.</STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="38"/>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Giue him his silkes they shal not touch my back</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>What strife is there, what aileth <HI>Laureo</HI>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will not weare proud trappings like a beast,</L>
<L>Yet hourelie feele the scornfull riders spurre,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cloth olde <HI>Ianicola</HI> in rich attire,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ian.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe, load me, for to beare is my desire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe ye repine, nay then ile vex you more,</L>
<L><HI>Grissill</HI> I will receiue this second wife</L>
<L>From none but from thy hands: come giue her mée,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gris.</SPEAKER>
<L>I heere present you with an endlesse blisse,</L>
<L>Rich honour, beautious vertue, vertuous youth,</L>
<L>Long liue my Lord with her contentedly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>owe.</SPEAKER>
<P>Marg patience there <HI>Gwenthyan</HI> see you thade▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Grissill</HI> dost thou deliuer me this maide,</L>
<L>As an vntainted flower which I shall keepe,</L>
<L>Despite of enuies canker, till the rust,</L>
<L>Of all consuming death finish her lilfe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gri.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe my deare Lord, and as willingly</L>
<L>As I deliuered vp my maiden youth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>What saies <HI>Ianicola</HI>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ia.</SPEAKER>
<L>I say but thus,</L>
<L>Great men are Gods, and they haue power ore vs,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Grissill</HI> hold fast the right hand of my bride,</L>
<L>Thou wearst a willow wreath and she a crowne,</L>
<L>True bride take thou the crowne and she the wreath,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mari.</SPEAKER>
<L>My gratious Lord you doe mistake your selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace peace, thou Siccophant <HI>Grissil</HI> receiue</L>
<L>Large interests for thy loue and sufferance.</L>
<L>Thou gau'st me this faire maide, I in exchange,</L>
<L>Returne thee her: and this young Gentleman</L>
<L>Thy Sonne and daughter kisse with patience,</L>
<L>And breath thy vertuous spirit into their soules.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gwe.</SPEAKER>
<P>Owe Sir <HI>Owen</HI> marg you now, the man is yéel∣ded to her Latie, lerne now Sir <HI>owen</HI> learne, learne Knight your duetie, see you thade?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why stands my wronged <HI>Grissil</HI> thus amazed?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="38"/>
<SPEAKER>Gris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ioy feare, loue hate, hope doubts incompasse me.</L>
<L>Are these my children I supposed slaine?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are these my nephewes that were murdred?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Blessing distill on you like morning deaw,</L>
<L>My soule knit to your soules, knowes you are mine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are, &amp; I am thine: Lords looke not strange,</L>
<L>These two are they, at whose birthes enuies tongue,</L>
<L>Darted enuenom'd stings, these are the fruite</L>
<L>Of this most vertuous tree, that multitude,</L>
<L>That many headed beastes, nipt their sweet hearts,</L>
<L>With wrongs, with bitter wrongs, al you hane wrong'd her,</L>
<L>My selfe haue done most wrong, for I did try</L>
<L>To breake the temper of true constancie:</L>
<L>But these whom all thought murdred are aliue,</L>
<L>My <HI>Grissill</HI> liues, and in the booke of Fame,</L>
<L>All worldes in golde shall register her name.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Le. Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most dreaded Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Arise flatterers get you gone,
<STAGE>Exeunt Lep. Ma.</STAGE></L>
<L>Your soules are made of blacke confusion.</L>
<L>Father <HI>Ianicola.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh pardon me,</L>
<L>Though dumbe betwixt my griefe and ioy I be.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who stands thus sad, what brother <HI>Laureo</HI>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pardon me my gratious Lord, for now I see,</L>
<L>That Schollers with weake eyes, pore on their bookes,</L>
<L>But want true soules to iudge on Maiestie:</L>
<L>None else but Kings can know the hearts of Kings,</L>
<L>Hence foorth my pride shall fly with humbler wings.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our pardon and our loue circle thee round,</L>
<L>Lets all to banquet, mirth our cares confound.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ow.</SPEAKER>
<P>Holde, holde, holde, banquet? if you banquet so, Sir <HI>Owen</HI> is like to haue sheere, her Latie heere is cog a hoope now at this, pray Cozen keepe your promise, <HI>Rees</HI> the wandes <HI>Rees,</HI> your medicines and fine trigs to tame shrewes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Furio</HI> where be the wands that I bound vp?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="39"/>
<SPEAKER>Fur.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heere my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>I wreath'd them then sir <HI>Owen,</HI> and you see</L>
<L>They still continue so, wreath you these three.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ow.</SPEAKER>
<P>Owe winde them, yes is winde them and mag good mightie cudgell, to tame and knog her Latie, and she prawle, or crie, or giue preade and meate to peggers, or teare pondes, by God is well remembred too, Cozen you promis'd to helpe her to her Duckegs, for all her pa∣per and pondes is torne?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>And I wil kéep my promise, wreath your wands</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Owen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Owe Gods lid mine is stubberne like <HI>Gwen∣thians,</HI> Gods plude see it preakes in snip snap péeces, what now Cozen?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>But cozen these you see did gently bowe,</L>
<L>I tride my <HI>Grissils</HI> patience when twas greene,</L>
<L>Like a young Ouer, and I moulded it</L>
<L>Like waxe to all impressions: married men</L>
<L>That long to tame their wiues must curbe them in,</L>
<L>Before they néed a bridle, then they'll prooue</L>
<L>All <HI>Grissils</HI> full of patience, full of loue,</L>
<L>Yet that olde tryall must be tempered so,</L>
<L>Least seeking to tame them they master you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Owen.</SPEAKER>
<L>By God is true as Pistle and Gospel, oh true out a cry.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>But you Sir <HI>Owen</HI> giuing her the head,</L>
<L>As you gaue liberty to those three wandes,</L>
<L>Shee'll breake as those doe if you bend her now,</L>
<L>And then y'are past all helpe, for if you striue,</L>
<L>You'll gaine as gamesters doe that sildome thriue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>owe.</SPEAKER>
<P>What shall doe to her Latie then? is pest run a∣way cozen, or knog her braines out? for is as faliant as <HI>Mars</HI> if I be anger.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<P>That were a shame eyther to run away from a woman or to strike her, your best Phisicke Sir <HI>Owen,</HI> is to weare a veluet hand, leaden eares, and no tongue, you must not fight howsoeuer she quarrels, you must be deafe
<PB REF="39"/>
whensoeuer she brawles, and dumbe when your selfe should brabble: take this cawdle next your heart euery morning, and if your wife be not patient, the next reme∣dy that I know is, to buy your winding sheete.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gwe.</SPEAKER>
<P>Cozen <HI>Marquesse,</HI> cozen <HI>Iulia,</HI> and Lawrds and Laties all, it shall not need as her cozen has tryed <HI>Grissill,</HI> so <HI>Gwenthian</HI> has Sir <HI>Owen,</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ow.</SPEAKER>
<P>Owe, by Cod is thought should pull her downe, ah ha.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gwe.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is not pul'd downe neither, but sir <HI>Owen</HI> shal be her head, and is sorry has anger her head and mag it ake, but pray good Knight be not proude &amp; triumph too much &amp; freade her Latie downe, God vdge mee will tag her will againe doe what her can.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ow.</SPEAKER>
<P>By Cod is loue her out a cry now, sir <HI>owen</HI> could tame her before, but Prittish ploude scawrnes to fide w<SUP>t</SUP> Laties, yes faith scornes out a cry, a pogs ont tis nought: <HI>Gwenthian</HI> shall no more be call'd <HI>Gwenthian</HI> but patient <HI>Grissill,</HI> ah ha is.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<P>Our ioyes are compleate, forward to our feast, Patience hath won the prize and now is blest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay brother your pardon awhile: besides our selues there are a number héere, that haue behelde <HI>Grissils</HI> patience, you owne tryals, and Sir <HI>Owens</HI> sufferance, <HI>Gwenthians</HI> frowardnes, these Gentlemen louertine and my selfe a hater of loue: amongst this company I trust there are some mayden batchelers, and virgin maydens, those that liue in that freedome &amp; loue it, those that know the war of mariage and hate it, set their hands to my bill, which is rather to dye a mayde and leade Apes in hell, then to liue a wife and be continually in hell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gwen.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Iulia</HI> by your leaues a lidle while, you taug and you prable about shidings in mariages, and you abuse yong mens and damsels, &amp; fraide them from good sportes and honorable states: but heare you now, awl that bee sembled heere, know you that discord's mag good mu∣sicke,
<PB REF="40"/>
and when loners fall out is soone fall in, and tis good you knaw: pray you al be maried, for wedlocke increases peoples and cities, awl you then that haue husbands that you would pridle, set your hands to <HI>Gwenthians</HI> pill, for tis not fid that poore womens should be kept alwaies vnder.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Since <HI>Iulia</HI> of the maides, and <HI>Gwenthian</HI></L>
<L>Of froward wiues, intreate a kinde applaude,</L>
<L>See <HI>Grissill</HI> among all this multitude,</L>
<L>Who will be friend to gentle patience?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ow.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha ha ha, <HI>Grissil</HI> is weary, pray let sir <HI>owen</HI> speag <HI>Grissill</HI> is patient, and her cozen is patient, therefore is speage for two, Gods plude you see her Latie is spride of buttrie, yet sir <HI>owen</HI> tame her and teare her ruffes, &amp; mag her cry and put ou her parrels, and say is sorry Sir <HI>owen,</HI> marg that well: if sir <HI>owen</HI> was not patient, her Latie had not beene pridled, if <HI>Grissill</HI> had not beene patient her cozen <HI>Marquesse</HI> had not been pridled: well now if you loue sir <HI>owens</HI> Latie, I hope you loue sir <HI>owen</HI> too, or is grow mighty angry, sir <HI>owen</HI> loue you as God vdge mee out a cry, a terrible feale, doe you heare now, then pray awl that haue crabbed husbands and cannot mend them, as <HI>Grissils</HI> had, and awl that haue fixen wiues, and yet is tame her well enough as sir <HI>owen</HI> does, &amp; awl that haue scoldes as sir <HI>owen</HI> does, and awl that loue faire Laties as sir <HI>owen</HI> does, to sed her two hands to his pill, and by God shall haue sir <HI>owens</HI> heard and soule in his pellie: and so God saue you all. <HI>Man gras wortha whee, Man gras wor∣tha whee.</HI> God night Cozens awl.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
<PB REF="40"/>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

