<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2002-11-25</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Emma Leeson Huber</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, etc.). Checked for signatures. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, and UNCLEARs. Corrected 10 $s of 195. Converted 185 $s to GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech". Checked for EPIGRAPHs and ARGUMENTs. Checked for startqs, endqs, oes, q;s, and Qs. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Checked for CLOSERs, TRAILERs, and BYLINEs. DONE.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="A31672">
<STC T="W">C1948</STC>
<BIBNO T="oclc">12260930</BIBNO>
<VID>57887</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>REVENGE
FOR
HONOUR. A
TRAGEDIE,
BY
GEORGE CHAPMAN.</P>
<P><HI>LONDON,</HI>
Printed in the Yeer 1654.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dramatis personae">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>The Persons Acting.</HEAD>
<LIST>
<ITEM><HI>Almanzor</HI> Caliph of Arabia.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Abilqualit</HI> his eldest Son.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Abrahen</HI> his Son by a second Wife,
Brother to <HI>Abilqualit.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Tarifa</HI> an old General, Conqueror of
<HI>Spain,</HI> Tutor to <HI>Abilqualit.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Mura</HI> a rough Lord, a Souldier, Kins∣man
by his Mother, to <HI>Abrahen.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Simanthes</HI> a Court-Lord, allyed to
<HI>Abrahen.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Selinthus</HI> an honest, merrie Court
Lord.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Mesithes</HI> a Court Eunuch, Attendant
on <HI>Abilqualit.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Osman <HI>a Captain to</HI> Tarifa.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Gaselles</HI> another Captain.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Caropia</HI> Wife to <HI>Mura,</HI> first beloved of
<HI>Abrahen,</HI> then of <HI>Abilqualit.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Perilinda</HI> her Woman.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Souldiers, Guard.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Muts, Attendants.</ITEM>
</LIST>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="prologue">
<PB REF="3"/>
<HEAD>PROLOGUE.</HEAD>
<L>O<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> Author thinks 'tis not i'th power of Wit,</L>
<L>Invention, Art, nor Industrie, to fit</L>
<L>The several phantasies which in this age</L>
<L>With a predominant humour rule the Stage.</L>
<L>Some men cry out for Satyr, others chuse</L>
<L>Meerly to story to confine each Muse;</L>
<L>Most like no Play, but such as gives large birth</L>
<L>To that which they judiciously term mirth.</L>
<L>Nor wil the best works with their liking crown,</L>
<L>Except 't be grac'd with part of foole or clown.</L>
<L>Hard and severe the task is then to write,</L>
<L>So as may please each various appetite.</L>
<L>Our Author hopes wel though, that in this Play,</L>
<L>He has endeavour'd so, he justly may</L>
<L>Gain liking from you all, unlesse those few</L>
<L>Who wil dislike, be't ne're so good, so new;</L>
<L>The rather Gentlemen, he hopes, cause I</L>
<L>Am a main Actor in this Tragedie:</L>
<L>You've grac'd me sometimes in another Sphear,</L>
<L>And I do hope you'l not dislike me here.</L>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<HEAD><PB N="5" REF="3"/>REVENGE
FOR HONOUR.</HEAD>
<DIV1 N="1" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACTUS PRIMUS.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scena I.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Selinthus, Gaselles, and Osman.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<P>NO murmurings, Noble Captains.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gas.</SPEAKER>
<P>Murmurings, Cosen?
this Peace is worse to men of war and action
then fasting in the face o'th' fo, or lodging
on the cold earth. Give me the Camp, say I,
where in the Sutlers palace on pay-day
we may the precious liquor quaff, and kisse
his buxome wife; who though she be not clad
in Persian Silks, or costly Tyrian Purples,
has a clean skin, soft thighes, and wholsome corps,
fit for the trayler of the puissant Pike,
to sollace in delight with.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Os.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here in your lewd Citie,
the Harlots do avoid us sons o'th' Sword,
worse then a severe Officer. Besides,
here men o'th' Shop can gorge their mustie maws
with the delicious Capon, and fat limbs
of Mutton large enough to be held shoulders
o'th' Ram anco<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ge the 1<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Signes, while for pure want
your souldier oft dines at the charge o'th' dead,
'mong tombs in the great Mo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>que.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis beleev'd Coz,
and by the wisest few too, that i'th' Camp
you do not feed on pleasant: po<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lts; a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>allad,
<PB N="6" REF="4"/>
and without oyl or vinegar, appeases
sometimes your guts, although they keep more noise
then a large pool ful of ingendring frogs.
Then for accoutrements, you wear the Buff,
as you believ'd it heresie to change
for linnen: Surely most of yours is spent
in lint, to make long tents for your green wounds
after an onslaught.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gas</SPEAKER>
<P>Coz. these are sad truths,
incident to fraile mortals!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<P>You yet crie
out with more eagernesse stil for new wars,
then women for new fashions.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Os.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis confess'd,
Peace is more opposite to my nature, then
the running ach in the rich Usurers feet,
when he roars out, as if he were in hel
before his time. Why, I love mischief, Coz,
when one may do't securely; to cut throats
with a licencious pleasure; when good men
and true o'th Jurie, with their frostie beards
shall not have power to give the noble wesand,
which has the steele defied, to th' hanging mercy
of the ungracious cord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gentlemen both,
and Cozens mine, I do believe 't much pity,
to strive to reconvert you from the faith
you have been bred in: though your large discourse
and praise, wherein you magnifie your Mistriss,
Warr, shall scarce drive me from my quiet sheets,
to sleep upon a turfe. But pray say, Cozens.
How do you like your General, Prince,
is he a right Mars?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gas.</SPEAKER>
<P>As if his Nurse had lapt him
in swadling clouts of steele; a very <HI>Hector</HI>
and <HI>Alcibiades.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<P>It seems he does not relish
these boasted sweets of warre: for all his triumphs,
he is reported melancholy.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Os.</SPEAKER>
<P>Want of exercise
renders all men of actions, dul as dormise;
your Souldier only can dance to the Drum,
and sing a Hymn of joy to the sweet Trumpet:
there's no musick like it.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB N="7" REF="4"/>
Enter Abrahen, Mura, <HI>and</HI> Simanthes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ab.</SPEAKER>
<P>I'll know the cause,
he shall deny me hardly else.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mu.</SPEAKER>
<P>His melancholy,
known whence it rises once, 't may much conduce
to help our purpose.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gas.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray Coz. what Lords are these?
they seem as ful of plot, as General<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
are in Siege, they're very serious.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<P>That young Stripling
is our great Emperors son, by his last wife:
that in the rich Imbroidery's, the Court <HI>Hermes;</HI>
one that has hatcht more projects, then the ovens
in Egypt chickens; the other, though they cal
friends, his meer opposite Planet <HI>Mars,</HI>
one that does put on a reserv'd gravitie,
which some call wisdom, the rough Souldier <HI>Mura▪</HI>
Governour <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'th' <HI>Moroccos.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Os.</SPEAKER>
<P>Him we've heard of
before: but Cozen, shal that man of trust,
thy tailor, furnish us with new accoutrements?
hast thou tane order for them?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, yes, you shal
flourish in fresh habiliments; but you must
promise me not to ingage your corporal oathes
you wil see't satisfied at the next press,
out of the profits that arise from ransome
of those rich yeomans heites, that dare not look
the fierce foe in the face.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gas.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doubt not our truths,
though we be given much to contradictions,
we wil not pawn oaths of that nature.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wel then, this note does fetch the garments:
meet me Cozens anon at Supper.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ex<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>unt Gas. Os.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Os.</SPEAKER>
<P>Honourable Coz▪ we wil come give our thanks.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Abilqualis.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ab.</SPEAKER>
<P>My gracious brother,
make us not such a stranger to your thoughts,
to consume all your honors in close retirements;
perhaps since you from <HI>Spain</HI> return'd a victor,
with (the worlds conqueror) <HI>Alexander,</HI> you greive
Nature ordain'd no other earths to vanquish;
if't be so, Princely brother, we'le bear part
<PB N="8" REF="5"/>
in your heroique melancholy.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gentle youth.
press me no farther, I stil hold my temper
free and unshaken, only some fond thoughts
of trivial moment, cal my faculties
to private meditations.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<P>Howsoe're your Hignesse
does please to term them, 'tis meer melancholy,
which next to sin, is the greatest maladie
that can oppress mans soul.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<P>They say right:
and that your Grace may see what a meer madnesse,
a very mid-summer frenzy, 'tis to be
melancholy, for any man that wants no monie,
I (with your pardon) wil discusse unto you
all sorts, all sizes, persons and conditions,
that are infected with it; and the reasons
why it in each arises.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ab.</SPEAKER>
<P>Learned <HI>Selinthus,</HI>
Let's tast of thy Philosophie</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pish, 'Tis unwelcome
to any of judgment, this fond prate▪
I marvel that our Emperor dos permit
fools to abound ith' Court!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<P>What makes your grave Lordship
in it, I do beseech you? But Sir, mark me,
the kernel of the text enucleated,
I shall confute, refute, repel, refel,
explode, exterminate, expunge, extinguish
like a rush candle, this same heresie,
that is shot up like a pernicious Mushroom,
to poison true humanitie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ab.</SPEAKER>
<P>You shall stay and hear a lecture read
on your disease; you shal, as I love virtue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<P>First the cause then
from whence this <HI>flatus Hypocondriacus,</HI>
this glimmering of the gizard (for in wild fowl,
'tis term'd so by <HI>Hyp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>crates</HI>) arises,
is as <HI>Averroes</HI> and <HI>Avicen,</HI>
with <HI>Abenbucar, Baruch</HI> and <HI>Aboflii,</HI>
and all the Arabick writers have affirm'd,
a meer defect, that is as we interpret▪ a want of —</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Of what, <HI>Selinthus?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Of wit, and please your Highnesse,
<PB N="9" REF="5"/>
That is the cause in gen'ral, for particular
and special causes, they are all deriv'd
from severall wants; yet they must be considerd,
pondred, perpended, or premeditated.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord, y'ad best be brief,
your Patient will be wearie else.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<P>I cannot play the fool rightly, I mean▪ the Physician
without I have licence to expalcat
on the disease. But (my good Lord) more briefly,
I shall declare to you like a man of wisdom
and no Physician, who deal all in simples,
why men are melancholy. First, for your Courties,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<P>It concerns us all to be attentive, Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your sage and serious Courtier, who does walk
with a State face, as he had drest himself
ith' Emperors glasse, and had his beard turn'd up
by the' irons Roial, he will be as pensive
as Stallion after Catum, when he wants suits,
begging suits, I mean▪ Me thinks, (my Lord)
you are grown something solemn on the sudden;
since your Monopolies and Patents, which
made your purse swell like a wet spunge, have been
reduc'd to th' last gasp. Troth, it is far better
to confesse here, then in a worser place.
Is it not so indeed?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abil.</SPEAKER>
<P>What ere he does
by mine, I'me sure h'as hit the cause from whence
your grief springs, Lord <HI>Simanthes.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<P>No <HI>Egyptian</HI> Soothsayer
has truer inspirations, then your small Courtiers
from causes and wants manifold; as when
the Emperors count'nance with propitious noise
does not cry chink in pocket, no repute is
with Mercer, nor with Tailor; nay sometimes too
the humor's pregnant in him, when repulse
is given him by a Beautie: I can speak this
though from no Memphian Priest, or sage Caldean,
from the best Mistris (Gentlemen) an Experience.
Last night I had a mind t'a comly Semstress,
who did refuse me, and behold, ere since
how like an Ass I look.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Tarifa.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<P>What, at your Counsels, Lords? the great <HI>Almanzor</HI>
requires your presence, <HI>Mura;</HI> has decree'd
<PB N="10" REF="6"/>
the Warr for <HI>Persia.</HI> You (my gracious Lord)
Prince <HI>Abilqualet,</HI> are appointed Chief:
And you, brave spirited <HI>Abrahen,</HI> an Assistant
to your victorious Brother: You, Lord <HI>Mura,</HI>
destin'd Lieutenant General.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abil.</SPEAKER>
<P>And must I march against the foe, without
thy company? I relish not th' imployment.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas, my Lord,
<HI>Tarifa's</HI> head's grown white beneath his helmet;
and your good Father thought it charity
to spare mine age from travel: though this <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ase
will be more irksome to me then the toil
of war in a sharp winter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abr.</SPEAKER>
<P>It arrives just to our wish. My gracious brother, I
anon shall wait on you: mean time, valiant <HI>Mura,</HI>
let us attend my Father.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Ab. Mura, Sim.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good <HI>Selinthus,</HI>
vouchsafe a while your absence, I shall have
imployment shortly for your trust.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your Grace shall have as much power to command
<HI>Selinthus,</HI> as his best fanci'd Mistress. I am your creature.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now, my Lord,
I hope y'are cloath'd with all those resolutions
that usher glorious minds to brave a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>chievements.
The happy genius on your youth attendant
declares it built for Victories and Triumphs;
and the proud <HI>Persian</HI> Monarchie, the sole
emulous opposer of the Arabique Greatnesse,
eourts (like a fair Bride) your Imperial Arms,
waiting t' invest You Soveraigne of her beauties.
Why are you dull (my Lord?) Your cheerful looks
should with a prosp'rous augury presage
a certain Victory: when you droop already,
as if the foe had ravish'd from your Crest
the noble Palm. For shame (Sir) be more sprightly;
your sad appearance, should they thus behold you,
would half unsoul your Army,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abil.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis no matter,
Such looks best sute my fortune. Know (<HI>Tarifa</HI>)
I'm undispos'd to manage this great Voiage,
and must not undertake it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Must not, Sir!
Is't possible a love-sick youth, whose hopes
are fixt on marriage, on his bridal night
<PB N="11" REF="6"/>
should in soft slumbers languish? that your Arms
should rust in ease, now when you hear the charge,
and see before you the triumphant Prize
destin'd t' adorn your Valour? You should rather
be furnish'd with a power above these passions;
and being invok'd by the mighty charm of Honour,
flie to atchieve this war, not undertake it.
I'd rather you had said, <HI>Tarifa</HI> ly'd,
then utter'd such a sound, harsh and unwelcome.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abil.</SPEAKER>
<P>I know thou lov'st me truly, and durst I
to any born of woman, speak my intentions,
the fatal cause which does withdraw my courage
from this imployment, which like health I covet,
thou shouldst enjoy it fully. But (<HI>Tarifa</HI>)
the said discov'ry of it is not fit
for me to utter, much lesse for thy vertue
to be acquainted with.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why (my Lord?)
my loyaltie can merit no suspicion
from you of falshood: whatsoere the cause be
or good, or wicked, 't meets a trustie silence,
and my best care and honest counsel shall
indeavour to reclaim, or to assist you
if it be good, if ill, from your bad purpose.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, that I know (<HI>Tarifa.</HI>) 'Tis the love
thou bear'st to honour, renders thee unapt
to be partaker of those resolutions
that by compulsion keep me from this Voiage:
For they with such inevitable sweetnesse
invade my sense, that though in their performance
my Fame and Vertue even to death do languish,
I must attempt, and bring them unto act,
or perish i'th' pursuance.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heaven avert
a mischief so prodigious. Though I would not
with over-sawcie boldnesse presse your counsels;
yet pardon (Sir) my Loialtie, which <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>imorous
of your lov'd welfare, must intreat, beseech you
with ardent love and reverence, to disclose
the hidden cause that can estrange your courage
from its own <HI>Mars,</HI> with-hold you from this Action
so much ally'd to honour: Pray reveal it:
By all your hopes of what you hold most precious,
I do implore it; for my faith in breeding
<PB N="12" REF="7"/>
your youth in warrs great rudiments, relieve
<HI>Tarifa's</HI> fears, that wander into strange
unwelcome doubts, left some ambitious frenzy
'gainst your imperial fathers dignitie
has late seduc'd your goodness.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abr.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, <HI>Tarifa,</HI>
I ne're durst aim at that unholy height
in viperous wickednesse; a sinlesse, harmlesse
(ift can be truly term'd one) 'tis my soul
labours even to dispaire with: t'faine would out,
did not my blushes interdict my language:
'tis unchast love, <HI>Tarifa;</HI> nay, tak't all,
and when thou hast it, pity my misfortunes,
to fair <HI>Caropia,</HI> the chast, vertuous wife
to surly <HI>Mura.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<P>What a fool Desire is!
with Giant strengths it makes us court the knowledg
of hidden mysteries, which once reveal'd,
far more inconstant then the air, it fleets
into new wishes, that the coveted secret
had slept still in oblivion.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abil.</SPEAKER>
<P>I was certaine
'twould fright thy innocence, and look to be
besieged with strong disswasions from my purpose:
but be assur'd, that I have tir'd my thoughts
with all the rules that <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>each men moral goodnesse,
so to reclaime them from this love-sick looseness;
but they (like wholesome medicines misaplied)
fac'd their best operation, fond and fruitlesse.
Though I as wel may hope to kiss the Sun-beams
'cause they shine on me, as from her to gaine
one g<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ance of comfort; yet my mind, that pities
it self with constant tendernesse, must needs
revolve the cause of its calamity,
and melt i'th' pleasure of so sweet a sadness.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then y'are undone for ever; Sir, undon
beyond the help of councel or repentance.
'Tis most ignoble, that a mind unshaken
by fear, should by a vain desire be broken;
or that those powers no labour e're could vanquish,
should be orecome and thral'd by sordid pleasure.
Pray (Sir) consider, that in glorious war,
which makes Ambition (by base men termed <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>in)
a big and gallant Virtue, y'ave been nurs'd,
<PB N="13" REF="7"/>
lull'd (as it were) into your infant sleeps
by th' surly noise o'th' trumpet, which n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>w summons
you to victorious use of your indowments:
and shall a Mistrisse stay you! such a one too,
as to attempt, then war it self's more dangerous!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abil.</SPEAKER>
<P>All these perswasions are to as much purpose,
as you should strive to reinvest with peace,
and all the joyes of health and life, a soul
condemn'd to perpe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uity of torments.
No (my <HI>Tarifa</HI>) though through all disgraces,
losse of my honour, fame, nay hope for Empire,
I should be forc'd to wade to obtain her love;
those seas of mischief would be pleasing streams,
which I would hast to bath in, and passe through them
with that delight thou would'st to victory,
or slaves long chain'd to'th' oare, to sudden freedom<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Were you not <HI>Abilqualit,</HI> from this time then
our friendships (like two rivers from one head
rising) should wander a dissever'd course,
and never meet againe, unlesse to quarrel.
Nay, old and stiffe, now as my iron garments,
were you my son, my sword should teach your wildness
a swift way to repentance. Y'are my Prince,
on whom all hopes depend; think on your Father,
that lively Image of majestick goodness,
who never yet wrong'd Matron in his lust,
or man in his displeasure. Pray conjecture
your Father, Countrie, Army, by my mouth
beseech your pietie to an early pittie
of your yet unslain Innocence. No attention!
Farwel: my praiers shall wait you, though my Counsels
be thus despis'd. Farwel Prince!</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abil.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Las good man, he weeps.
Such tears I've seen fall from his manly eyes
once when ye lost a battel. Why should I
put off my Reason, Valor, Honour, Virtue,
in hopes to gain a Beautie, whose possession
renders me more uncapable of peace,
then I am now I want it? Like a sweet,
much coveted banquet, 'tis no sooner tasted,
but it's delicious luxury's forgotten.
Besides, it is unlawful. Idle fool,
there is no law, but what's prescribed by Love,
Natures first moving Organ; nor can ought
<PB N="14" REF="8"/>
what Nature dictates to us be held vicious.
On then, my soul, and destitute of fears,
like an adventrous Mariner, that knows
storms must attend him, yet dares court his peril,
strive to obtain this happy Port. <HI>Mesith<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s</HI>
(Loves cunning Advocate) does for me besiege
(with gifts and vows) her Chastitie. She is
compass'd with flesh, that's not invulnerable,
and may by Love's sharp darts be pierc'd. They stand
firm, whom no art can bring to Love's command.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Abrahen,</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abr.</SPEAKER>
<P>My gracious brother!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Dearest <HI>Abrahen,</HI> welcome.
Tis certainly decreed by our dread Father,
we must both march against th' insulting foe.
How does thy youth, yet uninur'd to travel,
relish the Imploiment?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abr.</SPEAKER>
<P>War is sweet to those
that never have experienc'd it. My youth
cannot desire in that big Art a nobler
Tutor then you (my Brother<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>) Like an Eglet
following her dam, I shall your honour'd steps
trace through all dangers, and be proud to borrow
a branch, when your head's coverd ore with Lawrel,
to deck my humbler temples.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abil.</SPEAKER>
<P>I do know thee
of valiant active soul; and though a youth,
thy forward spirit merits the Command
of Chief, rather then Second in an Armie.
Would heaven our Roial Father had bestow'd
on thee the Charge of General.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abr.</SPEAKER>
<P>On me, Sir!
Alas, 'tis fit I first should know those Arts
that do distinguish Valour from wild rashness.
A Gen'ral (Brother) must have abler nerves
of Judgment, then in my youth can be hop'd for.
Your self already like a flourishing Spring
teeming with early Victories, the Souldier
expects should lead them to new Triumphs, as
if you had vanquisht fortune.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abil.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am not so
ambitious (<HI>Abrahen</HI>) of particular glories,
but I would have those whom I love partake them.
This <HI>Persian</HI> war, the last of the whole East
<PB N="15" REF="8"/>
left to be managed, if I can perswade
the great <HI>Almanzor,</HI> shall be the trophee
of thy yet maiden Valour. I have done
enough already to inform Succession,
that <HI>Abilqualit</HI> durst on fiercest foes
run to fetch Conquest home, and would have thy name
as great as mine in Arms, that Historie
might register, our Familie abounded
with Heroes, born for Victorie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis an honour,
which, though it be above my powers, committed
to my direction, I would seek to manage
with care above my yeers, and courage equal
to his, that dares the horrid'st face of danger:
But 'tis your noble courtesie would thrust
this mas<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'line honor (far above his merits)
on your regardless Brother; for my Father,
he has no thought tending to your intentions;
nor though your goodness should desire, would hardly
be won to yeild consent to them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, my <HI>Abrahen,</HI>
w'are both his sons, and should be both alike
dear to's affections; and though birth hath given me
the larger hopes and Titles, 'twere unnatural,
should he not strive t' indow thee with a portion
apted to the magnificence of his Off-spring.
But thou perhaps art timorous, lest thy first
essayes of valour should meet fate disastrous.
The bold are Fortunes darlings. If thou hast
courage to venture on this great imploiment,
doubt not, I shall prevail upon our Father
t' ordain thee Chief in this brave hopefull Voiage.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abr.</SPEAKER>
<P>You imagine me
beyond all thought of gratitude; and doubt not
that I'll deceive your trust. The glorious Ensignes
waving i'th' air once, like so many Comets,
shall speak the Persians funerals, on whose ruines
we'l build to Fame and Victorie new temples,
which shall like Pyramids preserve our memories,
when we are chang'd to ashes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Be sure, continue
in this brave minde; I'll instantly solicite
our Father to confirm thee in the Charge
of General, I'll about it.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="16" REF="9"/>
<SPEAKER>Abr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Farewel gracious Brother.
This haps above my hopes. 'Las, good dull fool,
I see through thy intents, clear, as thy soul
were as transparent as thin air or Cristal.
He would have me remov'd, march with the Armie,
that he mean time might make a sure defeat
on our aged fathers life and Empire: 't must
be certain as the light. Why should not this
with equall heat, be like my thoughts, ambitious?
Be they as harmless as the prai'rs of Virgins,
I'll work his ruine out of his intentions.
He like a thick cloud stands 'twixt me and Greatnesse:
Greatnesse, the wise mans true felicity,
Honour's direct inheritance. My youth
wil quit suspicion of my subtil practice:
then have I surly <HI>Mura</HI> and <HI>Simanthes,</HI>
my allyes by my dead Mothers bloud, my assistants,
his Eunuch too <HI>Mesithes</HI> at my service.
<HI>Simanthes</HI> shall inform the King, the people
desire Prince <HI>Abilqualit</HI>'s stay; and <HI>Mura</HI>
whose blunt demeanour renders him oraculous,
make a shrewd inference out of it. He is my half Brother,
th' other's my Father; names, meer airie titles!
Soveraigntie's onely sacred, Greatnesse goodnesse,
true self-affection Justice, every thing
righteous that's helpfull to create a King.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Mura, Simanthes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abr.</SPEAKER>
<P>My trustie friends, y'are welcome:
our fate's above our wishes; <HI>Abilqualit</HI>
by whatso'ere pow'r mov'd to his own ruine,
would fain inforce his charge of General on me,
and stay at home.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, how can this conduce
t' advance our purpose?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis the mainest engine
could ever move to ruine him. <HI>Simanthes,</HI>
you shall inform our Father, tis the people
out of their tender love desires his stay.
You (<HI>Mura</HI>) shall infer my Brothers greatnesse
with people; out of it, how nice it is and dangerous.
The air is open here; come, wee'll discourse
with more secure privacie our purpose.
No<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hing's unjust, unsacred, tends to advance
us to a Kingdom; that's the height of chance.</P>
</SP>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="2" TYPE="act">
<PB N="17" REF="9"/>
<HEAD>ACTUS SECUNDUS.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scena I.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Almanzor, Mura, and Simanthes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<P>HOw? not go, <HI>Simanthes?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<P>My dread Soveraign,
I speak but what the well affected people
out of their loyal care and pious duty
injoyn'd me utter: they do look upon him
as on your eldest Son, and next Successor,
and would be loth the <HI>Persian</HI> War should rob
their eies of light, their souls of joy and comfort,
this flourishing Empire leave as it were widow'd
of its lov'd Spouse: They humbly do beseech
your Majesty would therefore destine some
more fitting General, whose loss (as heaven
avert such a misfortune) should it happen,
might lesse concern the State.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis not the least
among the blessings Heaven has showr'd upon us,
that we are happie in such loving Subjects,
to govern whom, when we in peace are ashes,
we leave them a Successor whom they truly reverence:
A loving people and a loving Soveraign
makes Kingdoms truly fortunate and flourishing.
But I beleeve (<HI>Simanthes</HI>) their intents,
though we confirm them, will scarce take effect:
My <HI>Abilqualit</HI> (like a Princely Lion,
in view of's prey) wil scarcely be orecom
to leave the honour of the <HI>Persian</HI> War,
in's hopes already vanquish'd by his valour▪
and rest in lazy quiet, while that Triumph
is ravish'd by another.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<P>With the pardon
of your most sacred Majestie, 'tis fit then
your great commands forbid the Princes Voyage:
boldnesse inforces youth to hard atchievements
before their time, makes them run forth like Lapwing<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
from their warm nest, part of the shel yet sticking
unto their downie heads. Sir, good successe
is oft more fatal far then bad; one winning
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>st from a flatt'ring Di<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> tempting a Gameste<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
<PB N="18" REF="10"/>
to hazard his whole fortunes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mur.</SPEAKER>
<P>This is dull,
fruitless Philosophy, he that falls nobly
winns as much honour by his loss, as conquest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<P>This rule may hold wel among common men,
but not 'mong Princes. Such a prince as ours is,
who knows as wel to conquer mens affections
as he does enemies, should not be expos'd
to every new cause, honourable danger.
Prince <HI>Abilqualit</HI>'s fair and winning carriage
has stolne possession of the peoples hearts,
they doate on him since his l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>te Spanish conquest,
as new made brides on their much coveted husbands;
and they would pine like melancholy turtles,
should they so soone lose the unvalued object
both of their love and reverence: Howsoe're,
what ere your awful wil (Sir) shall determine,
as heaven, is by their strict obedience
held sacred and religious.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good <HI>Simanthes,</HI> let them receive our thanks
for their true care of our dear <HI>Abilqualit.</HI>
Wee'l consider of their request, say.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your highnesse humblest creature.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mu.</SPEAKER>
<P>I do not like this.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<P>Like what? Valiant <HI>Mura,</HI>
we know thy counsels so supremely wise,
and thy true heart so excellently faithful,
that whatsoere displeases thy sage Judgment,
<HI>Almanzor's</HI> wisdome must account distastful.
What is't dislikes thee?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your Majestie knows me
a downright Souldier, I affect not words;
but to be brief, I relish not your son
should (as if you were in your tomb already)
ingross so much the giddie peoples favours.
'Tis neither fit for him, nor safe for you
to suffer it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, how can they, <HI>Mura,</HI>
Give a more serious testimony of reverence
to me, then by conferring their affections,
their pious wishes, zealous contemplations
on him that sits the nearest to my heart,
my <HI>Abilqualit,</HI> in whose hopeful virtues
my age more glorious then in all my conquests?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="19" REF="10"/>
<SPEAKER>Mu.</SPEAKER>
<P>May you prove fortunate in your pio<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s care
of the Prince <HI>Abilqualit.</HI> But (my Lord)
<HI>Mura</HI> is not so prone to idle language
(the Parasits best ornament) to utter
o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ght, but what (if you'l please to give him audie<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ce
hee'l show you a blunt reason for.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come, I see
into thy thoughts, good <HI>Mura;</HI> too much car<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
of us, informs thy loyal soul with fears
the Princes too much popularity
may breed our danger: banish those suspicions;
neither dare they who under my long raign
have been triumphant in so many blessings,
have the least thought may tend to disobedience:
or if they had, my <HI>Abilqualit</HI>'s goodnesse
would ne're consent with them to become impious.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mu.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis too secure a confidence betrays
minds valiant to irreparable dangers.
Not that I dare invade with a foule thought
the noble Princes loyalty; but (my Lord)
when this same many headed beast (the people)
violent, and so not constant in affections,
subject to love of novelty, the sicknesse
proper <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'all humane specially light natures,
do magnifie with too immoderate praises
the Princes actions, doate upon his presence,
nay chaine their souls to th'shadow of his foot-steps,
as all excesses ought to be held dangerous,
especially when they do aim at Scepters,
their too much dotage speaks, you in their wishes
are dead alreadie, that their darling hope
the Prince might have the Throne once.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis confess'd, all this a serious truth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Their mad applauses
oth'noble Prince, though he be truly virtuous,
may force ambition into him, a mischief
Seasing the soul with too much craft and sweetness,
as pride or lust do's minds unstay'd and wanton:
'tmakes men like poyson'd rats, which when they'ave swallow'd
the pleasing bane, rest not until they drink,
and can rest then much lesse, until they burst with't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thy words are stil oraculous.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray then think
with what an easie toil the haughty Prince,
<PB N="20" REF="11"/>
a demy God by th' popular acclamations,
nay, the world's Soveraign in the vulgar wishes,
had he a resolution to be wicked,
might snatch this diadem from your aged temples?
What law so holy, tye of blood so mightie,
which for a Crown, minds sanctified and religious
have not presum'd to violate? How much more then
may the soul dazling glories of a Scepter
work in his youth, whose constitution's fierie,
as overheated air, and has to fan it
into a flame, the breath of love and praises
blown by strong thought of his own worth and actions.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<P>No more of this, good <HI>Mura.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mu.</SPEAKER>
<P>They dare already limit your intentions,
demand (as 'twere) with cunning zeal (which rightly
interpreted, is insolence) the Princes
abode at home. I wil not say it is,
but I guess, 'tmay be their subtle purpose
while we abroad fight for new kingdomes purchase
depriv'd by that means of our faithful succors,
they may deprive you of this crown, inforce
upon the prince this Diadem; which however
he may be loth t' accept, being once possessed of't
and tasted the delights of supreme greatness,
hee'l be more loath to part with. To prevent this,
not that I think it wil, but that may happen,
'tis fit the Prince march. I'ave observed in him too
of late a sullen Melancholly, whence rising
i'le not conjecture; only I should grieve, Sir,
beyond a moderate sorrow, traitorous practise
should take that from you which with loyal blood
ours and your own victorious arms have purchas'd.
and now I have discharg'd my honest conscience
censure on't as you please; henceforth I'me silent.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<P>Would thou hadst been so now, thy loyal fears
have made me see how miserable a King is,
whose rule depends on the vain people suffrage.
Black now and horrid as the face of storms
appears al <HI>Abilqualits</HI> lovely vertues,
because to me they only make him dangerous,
and with great terror shall behold those actions
which with delight before we view'd, and dotage;
like Mariners that bless the peaceful seas,
which when suspected to grow up tempest<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ous,
<PB N="21" REF="11"/>
they tremble at. Though he may stil be virtuous,
'tis wisdome in us, to him no injustice,
to keep a vigilant eie o're his proceedings
and the wild peoples purposes.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Abil.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Abilqualit!</HI>
come to take your leave, I do conjecture.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Rather, Sir, to beg
your gracious licence, I may stil at home
attend your dread commands, and that you'd please
to nominate my hopeful brother <HI>Abrahen</HI>
(in lieu of me) chief of your now raised Forces
for th' <HI>Persian</HI> expedition.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<P>Dare you (Sir) presume to make this suit to us?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why? (my roial Lord)
I hope this cannot pull your anger on
your most obedient Son: a true affection
to the young Prince my brother, did beget
this my request; I willingly would have
his youth adorn'd with glorie of this conquest.
No tree bears fruit in Autumn, 'less it blossome
first in the Spring; 'tis fit he were acquainted
in these soft years with military action,
that when grown perfect man, he may grow up too
perfect in warlike discipline.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hereafter
we shall by your appointment guide our Counsels.
Why do you not intreat me to resigne
my Crown, that you the peoples much lov'd minion
may with't impale your glorious brow? Sir, henceforth
or know your duty better, or your pride
shall meet our just wak'd anger. To your Charge,
and march with speed, or you shall know what 'tis
to disobey our pleasure. When y'are King,
learn to command your Subjects; I will mine (Sir.)
You know your Charge, perform it.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Alm. <HI>and</HI> Mura.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abil.</SPEAKER>
<P>I have done.
Our hopes (I see) resemble much the Sun,
that rising and declining cast large shadows;
but when his beams are dress'd in's midday brightnesse,
yeelds none at all: when they are farthest from
successe, their guilt reflection does display
the largest shows of events fair and prosp'rous.
With what a setled confidence did I promise
<PB N="22" REF="12"/>
my self, my stay here, <HI>Mura</HI>'s wish'd departure?
when stead of these, I finde my fathers wrath
destroying mine intentions. Such a fool
is self-compassion, soothing us to faith
of what we wish should hap▪ while vain desire
of things we have not, makes us quite forget
those w'are possess'd of.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Abrahen.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alone the engine works
beyond or hope or credit. How I hug
with vast delight, beyond that of stoln pleasures
forbidden Lovers taste, my darling Mistriss,
my active Brain! If I can be thus subtle
while a young Serpent, when grown up a Dragon
how glorious shall I be in cunning practise?
My gracious brother!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gentle <HI>Abrahen.</HI> I
am griev'd my power cannot comply my promise:
my Father's so averse from granting my
request concerning thee, that with angrie frowns
he did express rather a passionate rage,
then a refusall civil, or accustom'd
to his indulgent disposition.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hee's our Father,
and so the tyrant Custome doth inforce us
to yeeld him that which fools call natural,
when wise men know 'tis more then servile duty,
a slavish, blind obedience to his pleasure,
be it nor just, nor honourable.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abil.</SPEAKER>
<P>O my <HI>Abrahen,</HI>
these sounds are unharmonious, as unlookt for
from thy unblemish'd innocence: though he could
put off paternal pietie, 't gives no priviledg
for us to wander from our filial dutie:
though harsh, and to our natures much unwelcom
be his decrees, like those of Heaven, we must not
presume to question them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not, if they concern
our lives and fortunes? 'Tis not for my self
I urge these doubts; but 'tis for you, who are
my Brother, and I hope, must be my Soveraigne,
my fears grow on me almost to distraction:
Our Father's age betrayes him to a dotage,
which may be dang'rous to your future safetie;
<PB N="23" REF="12"/>
he does suspect your loyaltie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abil.</SPEAKER>
<P>How, <HI>Abrahen?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ab.</SPEAKER>
<P>I knew 'twould start your innocence; but 'tis truth,
a sad and serious truth; nay his suspicion
almost arriv'd unto a setled faith
that y'are ambitious.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abil.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis impossible.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ab.</SPEAKER>
<P>The glorious shine of your illustrious vertues
are grown too bright and dazling for his eyes
to look on as he ought, with admiration;
and he with fear beholds them, as it were,
through a perspective, where each brave action
of yours survey'd though at remotest distance,
appears far greater then it is. In brief,
that love which you have purchas'd from the people
that sing glad Hymns to your victorious fortunes,
betraies you to his hate; and in this Voiage
which he inforces you to undertake,
he has set spies upon you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abil.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis so: afflictions
do fal like hailstones, one no sooner drops,
but a whole Showre does follow. I observ'd
indeeed, my <HI>Abrahen,</HI> that his looks and language
was dress'd in unaccustom'd clouds, but did not
imagine they'd presag'd so fierce a tempest.
Ye gods, why do you give us gifts and graces,
share your own attributes with men, your virtues,
when they betray them to worse hate then vices?
But <HI>Abrahen,</HI> prithee reconfirm my feares
by testimonial how this can be truth;
for yet my innocence with too credulous trust
sooths up my soul, our father should not thus
put that off which does make him so, his sweetnesse,
to feed the irregular flames of false suspicions
and soul tormenting jealousies.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ab.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, to me,
to me (my Lord) he did with strong Injunctions
give a solicitous charge to overlook your actions.
My <HI>Abrahen</HI> (quoth he) I'me not so unhappie,
that like thy brother thou shouldst be ambitious,
who does affect, 'fore thy ag'd Fathers ashes,
with greedie lust my Empire. Have a strict
and cautious diligence to observe his carriage,
'twil be a pious care. Mov'd with the base
<PB N="24" REF="13"/>
indignity, that he on 'me should force
the office of a spy; your spy, my noble
and much lov'd brother: my best manhood scarce
could keep my angry tears in; I resolv'd
I was in duty bound to give you early
intelligence of his unjust intentions,
that you in wisedome might prevent all dangers
might fall upon you from them, like swift lightning,
killing 'cause they invade with sudden fiercenesse</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abil.</SPEAKER>
<P>In afflicting me, misery is grown witty.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ab.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay besides (Sir)
the sullen <HI>Mura</HI> has the self same charge too
consign'd and setled on him; which his blind
duty will execute. O brother, your
soft passive nature, do's like jet on fire
when oyls cast on't, extinguish: otherwise,
this base suspicion would inflame your sufferance,
nay make the purest loyalty rebellious.
However, though your too religious piety
forces you 'ndure this foul disgrace with patience,
look to your safety, brother, that dear safety
which is not only yours, but your whole Empires:
for my part, if a faithfull brothers service
may ought avail you, tho against our father,
since he can be so unnaturally suspicious,
as your own thoughts, command it.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Selinthus</HI> and <HI>Mesithes.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come, I know,
although th'ast lost some implements of manhood
may make thee gracious in the sight of woman,
yet th'ast a little engine, cal'd a tongue,
by which thou canst orecome the nicest female,
in the behalf of friend. Insooth, you Eunuchs
may well be stil'd Pimps-royal, for the skill
you have in quaint procurement.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mes.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your Lordship's merry,
and would inforce on me what has been your
office far oftner than the cunningst Squire belonging
to the smock transitory. May't please your Highnesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha! <HI>Mesithes.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ab.</SPEAKER>
<P>His countenance varies strangely, some affaire
the Eunnch gives him notice of, 't should seem,
begets much pleasure in him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is this truth?
<PB N="25" REF="13"/>
<HI>Mes.</HI> Else let me taste your anger.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abil.</SPEAKER>
<P>My dear <HI>Abrahen,</HI>
wee'l march to night, prethee give speedie Notice
to our Lieutenant <HI>Mura,</HI> to collect
the forces from their several quarters, and
draw them into Battalia on the plain
behind the Citie, lay a strict command
he stir not from the Ensigns til our self
arrive in person there. Be speedie, brother,
a little hastie business craves our presence.
We wil anon be with you, my <HI>Methises.</HI></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Abil. &amp; Mes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Can your grace imagine
whether his highness goes now?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ab.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, <HI>Selinthus;</HI>
canst thou conjecture at the Eunuchs business?
what ere it was, his countenance seem'd much altred:
Il'd give a talent to have certain knowledg
what was <HI>Mesithes</HI> message.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<P>I'll inform you
at a far easier rate. <HI>Mesithes</HI> businesse
certes concern'd a limber pett<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>coate,
and the smock soft and slipperie; on my honour,
has been providing for the Prince, some female
that he takes his leave of Ladies flesh
ere his departure.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ab.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not improbable, it may be so.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, certain (Sir) it is so:
and I believe, your little bodie earnes
after the same sport. You were once reported
a wag would have had business of ingendring
with surly <HI>Mura</HI>'s Lady: and men may
conjectute y'are no chaster then a vot'rie:
yet though she would not solace your desire<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,
there are as handsome Ladies wil be proud
to have your Grace inoculate their stock<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
with your graft-royal.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ab.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou art <HI>Selinthus</HI> stil,
and wilt not change thy humor. I must go
and find out <HI>Mura;</HI> so farwel <HI>Selinthus,</HI>
thou art not for these warrs, I know.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<P>No truly,
nor yet for any other, 'less't be on
a naked yeilding enemie; though there may
be as hot service upon such a foe
<PB N="26" REF="14"/>
as on those clad in steel: the little squadron,
we civill men assault body to body,
oft carry wild-fire▪ about them privately,
that <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>indges us ith' service from the crown
even to the sole, nay sometimes hair and all off.
But these are transitory perills.
<STAGE>Enter Gasilles, Osman.</STAGE>
Couzens,
I thought you had been dancing to the drum.
Your General has given order for a march
this night, I can assure you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gas.</SPEAKER>
<P>It is Couzen,
something of the soonest; but we are prepar'd
at all times for the journey.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<P>To morrow morning
may serve the turn though. Hark you, Couzens mine;
if in this <HI>Persian</HI> War you chance to take a
handsome she Captive, pray you be not unmindfull
of us your friends at home; I will disburse
her ransome, Couzens, for I've a months mind
to try if strange flesh, or that of our own
Countrey has the compleater relish.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Os.</SPEAKER>
<P>We will accomplish thy pleasure, noble Couzen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<P>But pray do not
take the first say of her your selves. I do not
love to walk after any of my kindred
ith' path of copulation.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gas.</SPEAKER>
<P>The first fruits
shall be thy own, dear Couz. But shall we part
(never perhaps to meet agen) with dry
lips, my right honoured Coz?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<P>By no means,
though by the <HI>Alcharon</HI> wine be forbidden,
you Souldiers in that case make't not your faith.
Dr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nk water in the Camp, when you can purchase
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o other liquor; here you shall have plenty
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>f wine, old and delic<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ous. I'le be your leader,
and bring you on, let who will bring you off.
To the encounter, come let us march, Couzens.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Omnes.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Song.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<PB N="27" REF="14"/>
<HEAD>Scena Secunda.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Abilqualit, Caropia, <HI>and</HI> Mesithes, Perilinda.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<P>No more, my gracious Lord, where real love is
needlesse are all expressions ceremonious:
the amorous Turtles, that at first acquaintance
strive to expresse in murmuring notes their loves,
do when agreed on their affections change
their chirps to billing▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abil.</SPEAKER>
<P>And in feather'd arms
incompasse mutually their gawdy necks.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mes:</SPEAKER>
<P>How do you like
these love tricks, <HI>Perilinda?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<P>Very well;
but one may sooner hope from a dead man
to receive kindness, than from thee, an Eunuch.<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
You are the coldest creatures in the bodies,
no snow-balls like you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mes.</SPEAKER>
<P>We must needs, who have not
that which like fire should warm our constitutions,
the instruments of copulation, girle,
our toyes to please the Ladies.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abil.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Caropia,</HI> in your well becoming pity
of my extream afflictions and stern sufferings,
you've shown that excellent mercy as must render
what ever action you can fix on, virtuous.
But Lady, I till now have been your tempter,
one that desired hearing, the brave resistance
you made my brother, when he woo'd your love,
only to boast the glory of a conquest
which seem'd impossible, now I have gain'd it
by being vanquisher, I my self am vanquish'd
your everlasting Captive.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then the thraldome
will be as prosperous as the pleasing bondage
of palms, that flourish most when bowd down fastest;
Constraint makes sweet and easie things laborious,
when love makes greatest miseries seem pleasures.
Yet 'twas ambition (Sir) join'd with affection
that gave me up a spoil to your temptations.
I was resolv'd, if ever I did make
a breach on matrimonial faith, 't should be
<PB N="28" REF="15"/>
with him that was the darling of kind fortune
as well as liberall nature; who possess'd
the height of greatnesse to adorn his beauty;
which since they both conspire to make you happy,
I thought 't would be a greater sin to suffer
your hopefull person, born to sway this Empire,
in loves hot flames to languish, by refusal
to a consuming feaver▪ then t'infringe
a vow which ne're proceeded from my heart
when I unwillingly made it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abil.</SPEAKER>
<P>And may break it with confidence, secure from the
least guilt, as if 't had only in an idle dream
been by your fancy plighted. Madam, there
can be no greater misery in love,
than separation from the object which
we affect; and such is our misfortune
we must ith'infancy of our desires
breath at unwelcome distance; ith'mean time,
lets make good use of the most precious minuts
we have to spend together.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<P>Else we were unworthy to be titled lovers; but
I fear loath'd <HI>Mura</HI> may with swift approach
disturb our happinesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abil.</SPEAKER>
<P>By my command hee's mustring up our forces.
Yet <HI>Mesithes,</HI> go you to <HI>Abrahen,</HI> and with intimations
from us, strengthen our charge. Come my <HI>Caropia,</HI>
love's wars are harmlesse, for who ere do's yeild,
gains as much honor as who wins the field.</P>
</SP>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="3" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACTUS TERTIUS</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA I.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Abilqualit and Caropia, as rising from
bed, Abrahen without, Perili<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>a.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ABr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Open the door, I must and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ill have entrance
unto the Prince my brother, as y<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> love
your life and safety and that Ladies <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>nor,
whom you are lodg'd in amorous twi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>s▪ with, do not
deny me entrance to you, I am <HI>Abra<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>n,</HI>
your loyal brother <HI>Abrahen.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abil.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis his voice,
<PB N="29" REF="15"/>
and there can be no danger in't, <HI>Caropia,</HI>
be not dismaid, though w'are to him discover'd.
your fame shall taste no blemish by't. Now brother,
'tis something rude in you, thus violently
to presse upon our privacies.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abr.</SPEAKER>
<P>My affection
shall be my Advocate, and plead my care
of your lov'd welfare, as you love your honour,
haste from this place, or you'l betray the Lady
to ruin most inevitable. Her husband
has notice of your being here, and's comming
on wings of jealousie and desperate rage
to intercept you in your close delights.
In breif, I over heard a trusty Servant
of his ith'Camp come and declare your highnesse
was private with <HI>Caropia:</HI> at which tidings
the sea with greater haste when vext with tempests,
so sudden and boystrous, flies not towards the shore,
then he intended homewards. He by this
needs must have gain'd the City; for with all my power
I hasted hitherward, that by your absence
you might prevent his veiw of you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why? the slave
dare not invade my person, had he found me
in fair <HI>Caropias</HI> armes: 'twould be ignoble,
now I have caus'd her danger, should I not
defend her from his violence. I'le stay
though he come arm'd with thunder.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abr.</SPEAKER>
<P>That will be
a certain means to ruin her: To me
count that cure, I'le stand between the Lady,
and <HI>Mura's</HI> fury, when your very sight,
giving fresh fire to th'injury, will incense him
'gainst her beyond all patience.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, besides
his violent wrath breaking through his allegiance,
may riot on your person. Dear my Lord
withdraw your self, there may be some excuse
when you are absent thought on, to take off
<HI>Mura's</HI> suspition: by our loves, depart
I do beseech you. Hapless I was born
to be most miserable.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abil.</SPEAKER>
<P>You shall over-rule me▪
Better it is for him with unhallowed hands
<PB N="30" REF="16"/>
to act a sacriledg on our Prophets tom
then to profane this purity with the le<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>
offer of injurie; be careful <HI>Abrahen,</HI>
to thee I leave my heart. Farwel <HI>Car<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ia,</HI>
your tears inforce my absence.</P>
<STAGE>Exit. Abil.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray hast my Lord
lest you should meet the inrag'd <HI>Mur.</HI> now Madam
where are the boasted glories of that v<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>tue,
which like a faithful Fort withstood m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> bat<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ries?
demolish'd now, and ruin'd they app<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>r;
like a fair building toter'd from its b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>
by an unruly whirlewind, and are no
instead of love the objects of my pitie</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<P>I'me bound to thank you Sir <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>et credit me;
my sin's so pleasing't 'cannot meet re<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>ntance.
Were <HI>Mura</HI> here, and arm'd with al<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> the horrors
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>age could invest his powers with; n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t forgiven
Hermits with greater peace shal hast t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> death,
then I to be the Martyr of this cause,
which I so love and reverence.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abr.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis a noble
and wel becoming constancie, and merits
a lover of those Supreme eminent graces,
that do like ful winds swel the glorious Sails
of <HI>Abilqualit's</HI> dignitie and beautie!
yet Madam, let me tel you, though I could not
envie my brothers happinesse, if he
could have enjoy'd your priceless love with safetie,
free from discoverie, I am afflicted
beyond a moderate sorrow, that my youth
which with as true a zeal, courted your love,
should appear so contemptible to receive
a killing scorn from you: yet I forgive you,
and do so much respect your peace, I wish
you had not sin'd so carelessly to be
betray'd ith' first fruitions of your wishes
to your suspicious husband.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis a fate Sir,
which I must stand, though it come dress'd in flames,
killing as circular fire, and as prodigious
as death presaging Comets: there's that strength
in love, can change the pitchie face of dangers
to pleasing formes, make ghastly fears seeme beauteous;
and I'me resolv'd, since the sweet Prince is free
<PB N="31" REF="16"/>
from <HI>Mura</HI>'s anger, which might have been fatal
if he should here have found him, unresistless
I dare his utmost fury.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abr.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Twil bring death with't
sure as stifling dampe; and 'twere much pitie
so sweet a beautie should unpitied fall,
betrai'd to endlesse infamie; your husband
knowes only that my brother in your chamber
was entertained; the servant that betrayed you,
curse on his diligence, could not affirm
he saw you twin'd together: yet it is
death by the law, you know, for any Ladie
at such an hour, and in her husbands absence▪
to entertain a stranger.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis considered Sir,
and since I cannot live to enjoy his love,
I'le meet my death as willingly as I
met <HI>Abilqualit</HI>'s dear embraces.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abr.</SPEAKER>
<P>That were too severe a crueltie. Live <HI>Caropia,</HI>
til the kind destinies take the loath'd <HI>Mura</HI>
to their eternal Mansions, til he fal
either in war a sacrifice to fortune,
or else by stratagem take his destruction
from angry <HI>Abilqualit,</HI> whose fair Empresse
you were created for: there is a mean yet
to save th' opinion of your honour spotlesse,
as that of Virgin innocence, nay to preserve,
(though he doth know (as certainly he must do)
my Brother have injoy'd thee) thee stil precio<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s
in his deluding fancie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let me adore you
if you can give effect to your good purpose.
But tis impossible.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abr.</SPEAKER>
<P>With as secure an ease
't shal be accomplish'd as the blest desires
of uncross'd lovers: you shal with one breath
dissolve these mists that with contagious darknesse
threaten the lights both of your life and honour.
Affirm my brother ravish'd you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<P>How my Lord?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Obtained by violence entry into your chamber
where his big lust seconded by force,
despight of yours and your Maids weak resistance
surpris'd your honor: when 't shall come to question,
<PB N="32" REF="17"/>
my brother cannot so put off the truth,
he owes his own affection and your whiteness,
but <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o acknowledg it a rape.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<P>And so by saving mine, betray his fame and safety,
to the lawes danger, and your fathers justice,
which with impartial doome will most severely
sentence the Prince, although his son.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your fears
and too affectionate tendernesse will ruine
all that my care has builded. Sure, <HI>Mesithes</HI>
has (as my charge injoin'd him) made relation
<STAGE>Enter Mura.</STAGE>
to him of <HI>Abilqualit</HI>'s action. See your Husband,
resolve on't, or y' are miserable.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Furies,
where is this lustful Prince, and this lascivious
Strumpet? ha <HI>Abrahen,</HI> here?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Cozen <HI>Mura,</HI>
be not so passionate, it is your Prince
has wrought your injury; resolve to bear
your crosses like a man: the great'st afflictions
should have the greatest fortitude in their suff'rings
from minds resolv'd and noble. 'Las poor Ladie,
'twas not her fault; his too unruly lust
'tis, has destroi'd her puritie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha, in tears!
Are these the liverie of your fears and penitence,
or of your sorrows (minion) for being rob'd
so soon of your Adulterer?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fie, your passion
is too unmannerly; you look upon her
with eyes of rage, when you with grief and pitie
ought to surveigh her innocence. My Brother,
degenerate as he is from worth, and meerly
the beast of lust, (what <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>fiends would fear to violate)
has with rude insolence destroyed her honor,
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y him inhumane ravished,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good Sir be
so merciful as to set free a wretch
from loath'd mortalitie, whose lifes so great
and hateful burden now sh'as lost her honor:
'Twil be a friendly charitie to deliver
her from the torment of it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mu.</SPEAKER>
<P>That I could
contract the soul of universal rage
<PB N="33" REF="17"/>
into this swelling heart, that it might be
as ful of poisonous anger as a dragons
when in a toile insnar'd. <HI>Caropia</HI> ravished!
Me thinks the horror of the sound should fright
to everlasting ruine, the whole world,
start natures Genius.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gentle Madam, pray
withdraw your self, your sight, til I have wrought
a cure upon his temper, wil but adde
to his affliction.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<P>You're as my good Angel,
I'll follow your directions.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Cozen <HI>Mura,</HI>
I thought a person of your masculine temper,
in dangers fostred, where perpetual terrors
have been your play-fellowes, would not have resented
with such effeminate passion a disgrace,
though ne're so huge and hideous.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mu.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am tame,
collected now in all my faculties,
which are so much oppress'd with injuries,
they've lost the anguish of them: can you think, Sir,
when all the winds fight, the inrag'd billows
that use to imprint on the black lips of clouds
a thousand brinie kisses, can lie stil,
as in a lethargie? that when baths of oyl
are pou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'d upon the wild irregular flames
in populous Cities, that they'll then extinguish?
Your mitigations adde but seas to seas,
give matter to my fires to increase their burning,
and I ere long enlightned by my anger
shall be my owne pile, and consume to ashes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, then I see indeed your injuries
have ravished hence your reason and discourse,
and left you the meere prostitute of passion.
Can you repaire the ruins you lament so
with these exclaimes? was ever dead man call'd
to life again by fruitful sighs? or can
your rage reedifie <HI>Caropias</HI> honour,
slain and betrai'd by his foul lust? Your manhood,
that heretofore has thrown you on all dangers,
me thinks should prompt you to a noble vengance,
which you may safely prosecute with Justice,
to which this crime, although he be a Prince,
<PB N="34" REF="18"/>
Renders him liable.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, I'le have justice
or I'le awake the sleepy Deities,
or like the ambitious Gyants wage new wars
with heaven it self, my wrongs shall steel my courage,
and on this vicious Prince like a fierce Sea-breach
my just wak'd rage shall riot till it sink
in the remorcelesse eddie, sink where time
shall never find his name but with disgrace
to taint his hatefull memory.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abr.</SPEAKER>
<P>This wildnesse neither befit your wisdom nor your courage,
which should with setled and collected thoughts
walk on to noble vengeance. He before
was by our plots proscrib'd to death and ruine
to advance me to the Empire; now with ease
we may accomplish our designs</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Would heaven
I nere had given consent, o'recome by love
to you to have made a forfeit on my allegiance,
tis a just punishment, I by him am wrong'd,
whom for your sake I fearlesse sought to ruin.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Are you repentant grown, <HI>Mura?</HI> this softnese?
ill suits a person of your great resolves,
on whom my fortunes have such firm dependance.
Come, let <HI>Caropia's</HI> fate in<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ke thy vengeance
to gain full mastry o're all other passions,
leave not a corner in the spacious heart
unfurnish'd of a noble rage, which now
will be an attribute of glorious justice:
the law you know with loss of sight doth punish
all rapes, though on mean persons; and our father
is so severe a Justicer, not blood
can make a breach upon his faith to justice.
Besides, we have already made him dangerous
in great <HI>Almanzors</HI> thoughts, and being delinquent
he needs must suffer what the meanest offender
merits for such a trespass.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mu.</SPEAKER>
<P>I'me awake now,
the lethargy of horror and amaze
that did obscure my reason, like those dul
and lazy vapors that o'reshade the Sun,
vanish, and it resumes its native brightness.
And now I would not but this devil Prince
had done this act upon <HI>Caropia's</HI> whiteness,
<PB N="35" REF="18"/>
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>nce't yeilds you free access unto the Empire,
The deprivall of's sight do's render him incapable
of future soveraignty.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou'rt in the right,
and hast put on manly considerations:
<HI>Caropia</HI> (since shee's in her will untainted)
ha's not forgon her honor: he dispatc'd once,
as we will have him shortly,'t shall go hard else▪
a tenant to his marble, thou agen<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
wedded in peace maist be to her pure vertues,
and live their happy owner.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mu.</SPEAKER>
<P>I'le repair
to great <HI>Almanzor</HI> instantly, and if
his partial piety do descend to pitty,
I will awake the Executioner
of justice, death, although in sleep more heavy
than he can borrow from his natural coldness;
on this good sword I'le wear my causes justice
till he do fall its sacrifice.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abr.</SPEAKER>
<P>But be sure
you do't with cunning secresie, perhaps,
should he have notice of your just intentions,
he would repair to th' Army, from which safegard
our best force could not pluck him without danger
to the whole Empire.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doubt not but I'le manage
with a discreet severity my vengeance,
invoke <HI>Almanzors</HI> equity with sudden
and private haste.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mean time
I will go put a new design in practice
that may be much conducing to our purpose.
Like clocks, one wheele another on must drive,
affairs by diligent labor only thrive.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scena Secunda.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Selinthus, Gaselles, Osman, and Souldiers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel</SPEAKER>
<P>No quarrelling good Couzens, le<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ft it be
with t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e glass, 'cause 'tis not of size sufficient
to gi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e you a magnificent draught. You will
have <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ighting work enough<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> when you're i'th' wars,
do n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t fall out among your selves.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="36" REF="19"/>
<SPEAKER>Os.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not pledg
my peerlesse Mistresse health? Souldier, thou'<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t mortall,
if thou refuse it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gas.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come, come, he shall pledg it,
and 'twere a Tun. Why, w'are all as dull
as dormise in our liquor: Here's a health
to the Prince <HI>Abilqualit.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soul.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let go round:
I'ld drink't, were it an Ocean of warm bloud
flowing from th'enemie. Pray, good my Lord
what news is stirring?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<P>It should seem, Souldier,
thou canst not read; otherwise the learn'd Pamphlets
that flie about the streets, would satisfie
thy curiositie with news; they'r true ones,
full of discreet intelligence.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Os.</SPEAKER>
<P>Cosens, shal's have a Song? here is a Souldier
in's time hath sung a dirge unto the foe
oft in the field.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soul.</SPEAKER>
<P>Captain, I have a new one,
the Souldiers Joy 'tis call'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<P>That is an harlot.
Preethee be musicall, and let us taste
the sweetnesse of thy voice.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>A Song.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gas.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whist, give attention.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soul.</SPEAKER>
<P>How does your Lordship like it?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Very well.
And so here's to thee. There's no drum beats yet,
and 'tis cleer day; some hour hence 'twill be
<STAGE>Enter Abr. Mes.</STAGE>
time to break up the Watch. Ha! young Lord <HI>Abrahen,</HI>
and trim <HI>Mesithes</HI> with him! what the divel
does he make up so early? He has been
a bat-fowling all night after those Birds,
those Ladie-birds term'd wag<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ails; what strange business
can he have here, tro?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abr.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Twas wel done, <HI>Mesithes!</HI>
and trust me, I shal find an apt reward,
both for thy care and cunning. Prethee hast
to Lord <HI>Simanthes,</HI> and deliver this
note to him with best diligence, my dear Eunuch;
thou'rt halfe the soul of <HI>Abrahen:</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mes.</SPEAKER>
<P>I was borne
to be intituled your most humble vassal;
I'll hast to the Lord <HI>Simanthes.</HI></P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="37" REF="19"/>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<P>How he cringes!
These youths that want the instruments of Manhood,
are very supple in the hams.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good-morrow
to noble Lord <HI>Selinthus:</HI> what companions
have you got here thus early?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Blades of metal,
tall men of war, and't please your Grace, of my
own blood and family, men who gather'd
a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>allad on the enemies ground, and eaten it
in bold defiance of him;
and not a Souldier here but's an <HI>Achylles,</HI>
valiant as stoutest <HI>Mirmidon.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abr.</SPEAKER>
<P>And they
never had juster cause to show their valor;
the Prince my dearest brother, their Lord General's
became a forfeit to the stern laws rigour;
and 'tis imagin'd, our impartial father,
wil sentence him to lose his eyes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gas.</SPEAKER>
<P>Marry heaven
defend, for what, and 't like your Grace!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abr.</SPEAKER>
<P>For a fact
which the severe law punishes with loss
of natures precious lights; my tears wil scarce
permit me utter 't: for a rape committed
on the fair wife of <HI>Mura.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Os.</SPEAKER>
<P>Was it for nothing else, and please your Grace?
ere he shal lose an eie for such a trifle,
or have a haire diminish'd, we wil
lofe our heads; what, hoodwink men like sullen hawks
for doing deeds of nature! I'me asham'd
the law is such an Ass.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Some Eunuch Judg,
that could not be acquainted with the sweets
due to concupiscencial parts, invented
this law, I'll be hang'd else. 's Life, a Prince,
and such a hopeful one, to lose his eyes,
for satisfying the hunger of the stomack
beneath the wast, is crueltie prodigious,
not to be suffer'd in a common-wealth
of ought but geldings.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abr.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis vain to sooth
our hopes with these delusions, he wil suffer
less he be reskued. I would have you therfore
<PB N="38" REF="20"/>
if you ow any service to the Prince,
my much lamented brother, to attend
without least tumult 'bout the Court, and if
there be necessity of your ayd, I'le give you
notice when to imploy it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sweet Prince, wee'l swim
in blood to do thee or thy brother service.
Each man provide their weapons.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abr.</SPEAKER>
<P>You will win
my brothers love for ever, nay my father,
though hee'l seem angry to behold his justice
deluded, afterwards when his rage is past,
will thank you for your loyalties: Pray be there
with all speed possible, by this my brothers
commanded 'fore my father, I'le go learn
the truth, and give you notice: pray be secret
and firm to your resolves.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<P>For him that flinches
in such a cause, I'le have no more mercy
on him. Heres <HI>Tarifa</HI>
<STAGE>Enter Tarifa and Mura<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></STAGE>
the Princes sometimes Tutor, <HI>Mura</HI> with him
a walking towards the Court, let's take no notice
of them, lest they discover our intentions
by our grim looks. March fair and softly Couzens,
wee'l be at Court before them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<P>You will not do this, <HI>Mura!</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mu.</SPEAKER>
<P>How <HI>Tarifa?</HI>
will you defend him in an act so impious?
Is't fit the drum should cease his surly language,
when the bold Souldiers marches, or that I
should passe o're this affront in quiet silence,
which Gods and men invoke to speedy vengeance?
which I will have, or manhood shall be tame
as Cowardice.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<P>It was a deed so barbarous,
that tr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>th it self blushes as well as justice
to hear it mention'd: but consider <HI>Mura,</HI>
he is our Prince, the Empires hope, and pillar
of great <HI>Almanzors</HI> age How far a publick
regard should be prefer'd before your private
desire of vengeance! which if you do purchace
from our impartial Emperors equity,
his loss of sight, and so of the succession,
will not restore <HI>Caropia</HI> to the honor
<PB N="39" REF="20"/>
he ravish't from her. But so foule the cause is,
I rather should lament the Princes folly
than plead in his behalf.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mur.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis but vain,
there is your warrant, as you are high Marshal,
to summon him to make his speedy appearance
'fore the Tribunall of <HI>Almanzor;</HI>
so pray you execute your office.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<P>How one vice
can like a small cloud when't breaks forth in showers,
black the whole heaven of vertues! O my Lord,
<STAGE>Enter Abil∣qualit, Muts, whis∣pring, seem to make pro∣testations. Exeunt.</STAGE>
that face of yours which once with Angell brightnesse
cheer'd my faint sight, like a grim apparition
frights it with ghastly terror: you have done
a deed that startles vertue till it shakes
as it got a palsie. I'me commanded
to summon you before your father, and
hope you'l obey his mandate.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Willingly,
what's my offence, <HI>Tarifa?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Would you knew not,
I did presage your too unruly passions
would hurry you to some disast'rons act,
but ne're imagin'd you'd have been so lost
to masculine honor, to commit a rape
on that unhappy object of your love,
whom now y'ave made the spoil of your foul lust,
the much wrong'd wife of <HI>Mura.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, do's <HI>Mura</HI> charge me with his <HI>Caropia</HI>'s rape?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<P>This warrant sent by your angry father, testifies
he means to appeach you of it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abil.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis my fortune, all natural motions when they
approach their end, hast to draw to't with accustom'd
swiftnesse. Rivers with greedier speed run neere
their out-falls, than at their springs. But I'me resolv'd,
let what happen that will, I'le stand it, and defend
<HI>Carpoia</HI>'s honor, though mine own I ruin;
Who dares not dye to justifie his love,
deserves not to enjoy her. Come, <HI>Tarifa,</HI>
what e're befall, I'me resolute. He dies
glorious, that falls loves innocent sacrifice.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="4" TYPE="act">
<PB N="40" REF="21"/>
<HEAD>ACTUS QUARTUS.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scena I.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Almanzor, Abilqualit, Tarifa and Mura.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<P>NO more <HI>Tarifa,</HI> you'l provoke our anger,
if you appear in this cause so solicitous,
the act is too apparent: nor shal you
need (injur'd <HI>Mura</HI>) to implore our justice,
which with impartial doome shall fal on him
more rigorously, then on a strange offender.
O <HI>Abilqualit,</HI> (for the name of Son,
when thou forsookst thy native virtue, left thee;)
Were all thy blood, thy youth and fortunes glories
of no more value, then to be expos'd
to ruine for one vice; at whose name only
the furies start, and bashful fronted justice
hides her amaz'd head? But it is now bootless
to shew a fathers pitie, in my grief
for thy amiss. As l'me to be thy Judg,
be resolute, I'll take as little notice,
thou art my off-spring, as the wandring clouds
do of the showers, which when they've bred to ripenesse,
they straight disperse through the vast earth forgotten.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abil.</SPEAKER>
<P>I'me sorrie Sir, that my unhappie chance
should draw your anger on me; my long silence
declares I have on that excelling sweetnesse,
that unexampled pattern of chast goodnesse; <HI>Caropia</HI> acted
violence. I confess,
I lov'd the Ladie, and when no perswasions
serv'd to prevail on her, too stubborn, incenss'd,
by force I sought my purpose and obtain'd it;
nor do I yet (so much I prize the sweetnesse
of that unvalued purchase) find repentance
in any abject thought; what ere fals on me
from your sterne rigor in a cause so precious,
wil be a pleasing punishment.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yon are grown
a glorious malefactor, that dare brave thus
the awful rod of justice! Lost young man,
for thou'rt no child of mine; dost not con<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>der
to what a state of desperate destruction
thy wild lust has betrai'd thee! What rich blessings
<PB N="41" REF="21"/>
(that I may make thee sensible of thy sins
by showing thee thy suffering) hast thou lost
by thy irregular folly! First my love,
which never more must meet thee, scarce in pitie;
the glorie flowing from thy former actions
stopt up for ever; and those lustful eies,
by whose deprival (thou'rt depriv'd of being
capable of this Empire) to the law,
which wil exact them, forfeited. Cal in there
a Surgeon, and our Mutts to execute this act
<STAGE>Enter Surg. Muts.</STAGE>
of justice on the unworthie traitor, upon whom
my just wak'd wrath shall have no more compassion,
then the incens'd flames have on perishing wretches
that wilfully leap into them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<P>O my Lord,
that which on others would be fitting justice,
on him your hopeful though offending son,
wil be exemplar crueltie; his youth Sir,
that hath abounded with so many vertues▪
is an excuse sufficient for one vice:
he is not yours only. hee's your Empires,
destin'd by nature and successions priviledg,
when you in peace are shrowded in your marble,
to weild this Scepter after you. O do not,
by putting out his eies, deprive your Subjects
of light, and leave them to dul mournful darknesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis but in vain, I am inexorable.
If those on which his eyes hang, were my heart strings,
I'de cut them out rather then wound my Justic<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>;
nor dos't befit thy vertue intercede
for him in this cause horrid and prodigious;
the crime 'gainst me was acted; 'twas a rape
upon my honour, more then on her whitenesse;
his was from mine derivative, as each stream
is from its spring; so that he has polluted
by his soul fact, my fame, my truth, my goodnesse,
strucken through my dignitie by his violence:
nay, started in their peaceful urnes, the ashe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
of all my glorious Ancestors; defil'd
the memorie of their stil descendent vertues;
nay with a killing frost, nipt the fair blossomes,
that did presage such goodly fruit arising
from his own hopeful youth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mur.</SPEAKER>
<P>I ask but justice;
<PB N="42" REF="22"/>
those eyes that led him to unlawful objects,
tis fit should suffer fo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'t a lasting blindnesse;
the Sun himself, when he darts rayes lascivious,
such as ingender by too piercing fervence
intemperate and infectious heats, straight wears
obscuritie from the clouds his own beams raises.
I have been your Souldier Sir, and fought your battails;
for all my services, I beg but justice,
which is the Subjects best prerogative,
the Princes greatest attribute; and for a fact,
then which, none can be held more black and hideous,
which has betrai'd to an eclipse the brightest
star in th' heaven of vertues: the just law
does for 't ordain a punishment, which I hope
you the laws righteous guider, wil according
to equitie see executed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why! that law
was only made for common malefactors,
but has no force to extend unto the Prince,
to whom the law it self must become subject.
This hopeful Prince, look on him, great <HI>Almanzor;</HI>
and in his eyes, those volumes of all graces,
which you like erring Meteors would extinguish▪
read your own lively figure, the best storie
of your youths noblest vigor; let not wrath (Sir)
o'recome your pietie, nay your humane pity.
'Tis in your brest, my Lord, yet to shew mercie;
that precious attribute of heavens true goodnesse,
even to your self, you<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> son! me thinks that name
should have a power to interdict your Justice
in its too rigorous progress.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Dear <HI>Tarifa,</HI>
I'me more afflicted at the intercessions,
then at the view of my approaching torments,
which I wil meet with fortitude and boldness,
too base to shake now at one personal danger,
when I've incountred thousand perils fearless;
Nor do I blame my gracious fathers Justice,
though it precede his nature. I'ld not have him
(for my sake) forfeit that for which hee's famous,
his uncorrupted equitie, nor repine
I at my destinie; my eies have had
delights sufficient in <HI>Caropia</HI>'s beauties,
to serve my thought<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> for after contemplations;
<PB N="43" REF="22"/>
nor can I ever covet a new object,
since they can ne're hope to incounter any
of equal worth and sweetness.
Yet hark <HI>Tarifa,</HI> to thy secresie
I wil impart my dearest, inmost counsels;
if I should perish, as 'tis probable
I may, under the hands of these tormentors;
thou maist unto succession show my innocence;
<HI>Caropia</HI> yeilded without least constraint,
and I injoy'd her freely.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<P>How my Lord?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abil.</SPEAKER>
<P>No words on't,
as you respect my honour! I'ld not lose
the glorie I shall gain by these my sufferings;
come grim fures, and execute your office. I wil stand you,
unmov'd as hills at whirlewinds, and amidst
the torments you inflict, retain my courage.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<P>Be speedie villaines.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<P>O stay your cruel hands,
you dumb ministers of injur'd Justice,
and let me speak his innocence ere you further
afflict his precious eye-sight.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<P>What does this mean, <HI>Tarifa!</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<P>O my Lord,
the too much braverie of the Princes spirit
'tis has undone his fame, and pul'd upon him
this fatal punishment; 'twas but to save
the Ladies honour, that he has assum'd
her rape upon him, when with her consent
the deed of shame was acted.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mur.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis his fears
makes him traduce her innocence: he who did not
stick to commit a riot on her person,
can make no conscience to destroy her fame
by his untrue suggestions.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis a basenesse
beyond thy other villanie (had shee yeilded,)
thus to betraie for transitorie torture,
her honour, which thou wert ingag'd to safeguard
even with thy life. A son of mine could never
show this ignoble cowardize: Proceed
to execution, I'll not hear him speak,
he is made up of treacheries and falshoods.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wil you then
<PB N="44" REF="23"/>
be to the Prince so tyrannous? Why, to me
just now he did confess his only motive
to undergoe this torment, was to save
<HI>Caropia</HI>'s honour blameless.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abil.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am more troubled▪
Sir, with his untimely frenzie,
then with my punishment; his too much love
to me, has spoild his temperate reason. I
confess <HI>Caropia</HI> yeilded! Not the light
is half so innocent as her spotlesse virtue.
'T was not wel done, <HI>Tarifa,</HI> to betray
the secret of your friend thus: though Shee yeilded,
the terror of ten thousand deaths shall never
force me to confess it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Agen, my Lord, even now
he does confess, she yeilded, and protest<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
that death shall never make him <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ay shee'<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> guilti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>:
the breath scarce pass'd his lips yet.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Haplesse man,
to run in<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o this lunacie!
Fie <HI>Tarifa,</HI>
so treacherous to your Friend!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Agen, agen.
Wil no man give me credit?</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Abrahen.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Where is our roial fathe?: where our brother?
As you respect your life and Empires safetie,
dismiss these tyrannous instruments of death
and crueltie unexemplified. O Brother,
that I should ever live to enjoy my eie-sight,
and see one halfe of your dear lights indanger'd.
My Lord, you've done an act, which my just fears
tels me, wil shake your Scepter! O for heavens sake,
look to your future safetie; the rough Souldier
hearing their much lov'd General, My good Brother
was by the law betrai'd to some sad danger,
have in their pietie beset the pallace;
think on some means to appease them, ere their furie
grow to its ful unbridled height; they threaten
your life, great Sir: pray send my brother to them,
his sight can only pacifie them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<P>Have you your Champions!
We wil prevent their insolence, you shal not
boast, you have got the Empire by our ruine.
<PB N="45" REF="23"/>
Muts, Strangle him immediately.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Avert
such a prodigious mischief, heaven. Hark, hark
<STAGE>Enter, Enter.</STAGE>
they're entred into th' Court; desist you monsters,
my life shal stand betwixt his and this violence,
or I with him wil perish. Faithful Souldiers,
hast to defend your Prince, curse on your slowness.
Hee's dead; my fathers turn is next. O horror,
would I might sink into forgetfulnesse▪
What has your furie urg'd you to?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<P>To that
which whoso murmurs at, is a faithlesse traitor
<STAGE>Enter Simanthe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</STAGE>
to our tranquilitie. Now Sir, your b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>siness?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord, the Citie
is up in arms, in rescue of the Prince;
the whole Court throngs with Souldiers.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<P>'T was high time
to cut this viper off, that would have eat his passage
through our very <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>owels to our Empire.
Nay, we wil stand their furies, and with terror
of Majestie strike dead these insurrections.
<STAGE>Enter Souldiers.</STAGE>
Traitors, what means this violence?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abr.</SPEAKER>
<P>O dear Souldiers,
your honest love's in vain; my Brother's dead,
strangled by great <HI>Almanzor</HI>'s dire command,
ere your arrival. I do hope they'l kill him
in their hot zeal.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why do you stare so, traitors?
'twas I your Emp'ror that have done this act,
which who repines at, treads the self same steps
of death that he has done. Withdraw and leave us,
wee'ld be alone. No motion▪ Are you statues?
Stay you, <HI>Tarifa</HI> here. For your part, <HI>Mura,</HI>
you cannot now complain but you have justice;
so quit our presence.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Os.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faces about, Gentlemen.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abr.</SPEAKER>
<P>It has happ'ned
above our wishes, we shall have no need now
to imploy your handkercher. Yet give it me.
You'r sure 'tis right, <HI>Simanthes.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tarifa,
I know the love thou bearst Prince <HI>Abilqualit</HI>
makes thy big heart swell as 't had drunk the fome
of angry Dragons. Speak thy free intentions,
<PB N="46" REF="24"/>
Deserv'd he not this fate?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<P>No: You're a Tyrant,
one that delights to feed on your▪ own bowels,
and were not worthie of a Son so vertuous.
Now you have <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ane his, add to your injustice,
and take <HI>Tarifa</HI>'s life, who in his death,
should it come flying on the wings of torments,
would speak it out as an apparant truth▪
the Prince to me d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cla<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'d his innocence,
and that <HI>Caropia</HI> yeelded.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<P>Rise <HI>Tarifa;</HI>
we do command thee, rise: a sudden chilnesse,
such as the hand of winter casts on brooks,
thrils our ag'd heart. I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ll not have thee ingross
sorrow alone for <HI>Abilqualii</HI>'s death:
I lov'd the boy well, and though his ambition
and popularitie did make him dangerous,
I do repent my furie, and will vie
with thee in sorrow. How he makes death lovely!
Shall we fix here, and weep till we be statues?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Til we grow stiff as the cold Al<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>bl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sters
must be erected over us▪ Your rashnesse
has rob'd the Empire of the greatest hope
it ere shall boast agen. Would I were ashes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<P>He breathes (me thinks:) the over-hastie soul
was too discourteous to forsake so fair
a lodging, without taking solemn leave
first of the owner. Ha, his handkercher!
Thou'rt lib'ral to thy Father even in death,
leav'st him a legacie to drie his tears,
which are too slow; th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y should create a deluge.
O my dear <HI>Abilqualit!</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<P>You exceed now
as much in grief as you did then in rage,
One drop of this pious paternal softnesse
had ransom'd him from ruine. Dear Sir, rise:
my grief's divided, and I know not whether
I should lament you living, or him dead.
Good Sir, erect your looks. Not stir! His sorrow
makes him insensible. Ha, there's no motion
left in his vital spirits: The excesse
of grief has stifled up his pow'rs, and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rack'd
(I fear) his ag'd hearts cordage. Help, the Emperor,
he Emperor's dead; Help, help.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB N="47" REF="24"/>
Abrahen, Simanthes, Mesithes, Muts</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abr.</SPEAKER>
<P>What dismal outcrie's this?
our royal father dead! The handkercher has wrought I see.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes; his big heart
vanquish'd with sorrow, that in's violent rage,
he doom'd his much lov'd son to timeless death,
could not endure longer on its weak strings,
but crack'd with weight of sorrow. Their two spirits,
by this, are met in their delightful passage
to the blest shades; we in our tears are bound
to cal you our dread Soveraign.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<P>Long live <HI>Abrahen</HI>
Great <HI>Caliph</HI> of <HI>Arabia.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abr.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis a title
we cannot covet, Lords, it comes attended
with so great cares and troubles, that our youth
start at the thought of them, even in our sorrows
which are so mightie on us; ou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> weak spirits
are readie to relinquish the possession
they've of mortalitie, and take swift flight
after our roial friends. <HI>Simanthes,</HI> be it
your charge to see all fitting preparation
provided <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>or the funerals.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Selinthus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Where's great <HI>Almanzor?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abr.</SPEAKER>
<P>O <HI>Selinthus,</HI> this
day is the hour of funerals grief; for his
crueltie to my brother, has translated
him to immortalitie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hee'll have attendants
to wait on him to our great prophets paradise,
ere he be readie for his grave. The Souldiers
all mad with rage for the Princes slaughter,
have vow'd by all oaths Souldiers can inve<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t,
(and that's no smal store) with death and destruction,
to pursue sullen <HI>Mura.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tarifa,
use your authoritie to keep their violence
in due obedience. We're so fraught with grief,
we have no room for any other passion
in our distracted bosome. Take these roial bodies
and place them on that couch; here where they fell,
they shal be imbalm'd. Yet put them out of our sight,
their veiw<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> draw fresh drops from our heart.
<PB N="48" REF="25"/>
Anon we'l shew our selves to chear the afflicted
Subject.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>a Sho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes</SPEAKER>
<P>Long live <HI>Abrahen,</HI> great Caliph of Arabia.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abr.</SPEAKER>
<P>And who can say now, <HI>Abrahen</HI> is a villain?
I am saluted King with acclamations
that dea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> the Heavens to hear, with as much joy
as if I had atchiev'd this Scepter by
means fair and ver<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uous. 'Twas this handkercher
that did to death <HI>Almanzor;</HI> so infected,
its least insensible vapour has full power;
apply'd to th' eye, or any other Organ,
can drink its poyson in to vanquish Nature,
though nere so strong and youthful. 'Twas <HI>Simanthes</HI>
devis'd it for my brother, and my cunning
transferr'd it to <HI>Almanzor;</HI> 'tis no matter,
my worst impiety is held now religious.
'Twixt Kings and their inferiors there's this ods,
These are meer men, we men, ye<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> earthly gods.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abil.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Twas well the Muts prov'd fai<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hful, otherwise
I'd lost my breath with as much speed and silence
as those who do expire in dreams, their health
seeming no whit abated. But 'twas wisely
consider'd of me, to prepare those sure
instruments of destruction: The suspicion
I had by <HI>Abrahen</HI> of my fathers fears
of my unthought ambition, did instruct me
by making them mine, to secure my safety.
Would the inhumane Surgeon had tane
these blessed lights from me; that I had liv'd for ever
doom'd to perpetual darkness, rather then
<HI>Tarifa</HI>'s fears had so appeach'd her honour.
Well, villain Brother, I have found, that by
my seeming death, which by my lives best arts
I ne're should have had knowledg of. Dear Father,
though thou to me wert pitilesse, my heart
weeps tears of blood, to see thy age thus like
a lofty pine fall, eaten through by th' gin
from its own Stock descending: He has agents
in his ungracious wickednesse: <HI>Simanthes</HI>
he has discover'd: Were they multitudes
as numerous as collected sands, and mighty
in force as mischief, they should from my Justice
meet their due punishment. <HI>Abrah<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n</HI> by this
is proclaim'd Caliph, yet my undoubted right▪
<PB N="49" REF="25"/>
when 't shall appear I'me living, wil reduce
the people to my part; the armie's mine,
whither I must withdraw unseen: the night
wil best secure me. What a strange <HI>Chimera</HI>
of thought possesses my dul brain! <HI>Caropia,</HI>
thou hast a share in them: Fate, to thy mercie
I do commit my self; who scapes the snare
once, has a certain caution to beware.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scen. 2.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Caropia <HI>and</HI> Perilinda.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your Lord is not returned yet!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, good Madam:
pray do not thus torment your self, the Prince
(I warrant you) wil have no injurie
by saving of your honour; do you think
his father wil be so extreme outragious
for such a trifle, as to force a woman
with her good liking?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<P>My ill boding soul
beats with presages ominous. Would heaven
I'd stood the hazard of my incens'd Lords furie,
rather then he had run this imminent danger.
Could you ne're learn, which of the slaves it was
betray'd our close loves to loath'd <HI>Mura</HI>'s notice?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<P>No indeed could I not; but here's my Lord,
pray Madam do not grieve so!</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Mura.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mu.</SPEAKER>
<P>My <HI>Caropia,</HI>
dress up thy looks in their accustom'd beauties,
cal back the constant spring into thy cheeks,
that droope like lovely Violets, o're charg'd
with too much mornings dew; shoot from thy eie<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
a thousand flames of joy. The lustful Prince,
that like a foul thief, rob'd thee of thy honour
by his ungracious violence▪ has met
his roial fathers Justice.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now my fears
carry too sure an augury! you would fain
sooth me, my Lord, out of my floud of sorrows▪
what reparation can that make my honour,
though he have tasted punishment?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mu.</SPEAKER>
<P>His life
is faln the off-spring of thy chastitie,
which his hot lust polluted: nay, <HI>Caropia,</HI>
<PB N="50" REF="26"/>
to save himself, when he but felt the torment
applied to his lascivious eies; although
at first he did with impudence acknowledg
thy rape, he did invade thy spotless virtue,
protested, only 'twas to save thy honor,
he took on him thy rape, when with consent
and not constrain'd, thou yeildedst to the loosness
of his wild vicious flames.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<P>Could he be so unjust, my Lord?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mu.</SPEAKER>
<P>He was, and he has paid for't;
the malicious Souldier, while he was a losing
his eies, made violent head to bring him reskue, which
pul'd his ruine on him. But no more
of such a prodigie; may his black memorie
perish even with his ashes. My <HI>Caropia,</HI>
the flourishing trees widow'd by winters violence
of their fair ornaments, when 'tis expir'd once,
put forth again with new and virgin freshness,
their bushie beauties; it should be thy emblem.
Display agen those chast immaculate glories▪
which the harsh winter of his lust had wither'd;
and I'll agen be wedded to thy vertues,
with as much joy, as when thou first inrich'd me
with their pure maiden beauties. Thou art dul,
and dost not gratulate with happie welcome▪
the triumphs of thy vengeance.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<P>Are you sure, my Lord, the Prince is dead?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pish, I beheld him breathlesse.
Take comfort best <HI>Caropia,</HI> thy disgrace
did with his loath'd breath vanish.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<P>I could wish though,
that he had falne by your particular vengance,
rather then by th' laws rigor; you're a Souldier
of glorie, great in war for brave performance:
me thinks 't had been far nobler, had you call'd him
to personal satisfaction: had I been
your husband, you my wife, and ravished by him;
my resolution would have arm'd my courage
to've stroke him thus: The dead Prince sends you that.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Stab him▪</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mu.</SPEAKER>
<P>O, I am slain!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<P>Would it were possible
to kil even thy eternitie. Sweet Prince,
how shal I satisfie thy unhappie ruins!
Ha,<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> not yet breathlesse! To increase thy ang<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ish
<PB N="51" REF="26"/>
even to despair, know, <HI>Abilqualit</HI> was
more dear to me, then thy foul selfe was odious,
and did enjoy me freely.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mu.</SPEAKER>
<P>That I had
but breath enough to blast thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Twas his brother
(curse on his art) seduc'd me to accuse
him of my rape. Do you groane, prodigie!
take this as my last bountie.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Stab again.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Perilinda.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<P>O Madam, Madam,
what shal we do? the house is round beset
with Souldiers; Madam, they do sweare they'le tear
my Lord, for the sweet Princes death, in pieces.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<P>This hand has sav'd
their furie that just labour: yet I'le make
use of their malice, help to convey
him into 's Chamber.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Osman, Gasselles, Souldiers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gas.</SPEAKER>
<P>Where is this villain, this traitor <HI>Mura?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heaven knowes what violence
their furie may assault me with; be't death,
't shall be as welcome, as sound healthful sleeps
to men oppress'd with sicknesse. What's the matter?
what means this outrage?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Os.</SPEAKER>
<P>Marry, Ladie gay,
We're come to cut your little throat; pox on you,
and all your sex; you've caus'd the noble Princes
death, wild-fire take you fort, weel talk with you
at better leisure: you must needs be ravished!
and could not like an honest woman, take
the curtesie in friendly sort!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gas.</SPEAKER>
<P>We trifle:
her husband may escape us. Say, where is he?
or you shall die, ere you can pray</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sold▪</SPEAKER>
<P>Here, here I have found the vallain! what, do you
sleep so soundly? ne're wake more, this for the
Prince, you rogue: let's tear him piecemeale.
Do you take your death in silence, dog!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<P>You appear indow'd with some humanitie,
you have <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ane his life; let not your hate last
after death; let me embalm his bodie with
my tear<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, or kil me with him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Os.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now you 've said the word,
<PB N="52" REF="27"/>
we care not if we do.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Tarifa.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Slaves, unhand
the Ladie, who dares offer her least violence,
from this hand meets his punishment. <HI>Gaselles,
Osman,</HI> I thought you had been better temper'd,
then thus to raise up mutinies. In the name
of <HI>Abrahen</HI> our now Caliph, I command you,
desist from these rebellious practises,
and quietly retire into the Camp,
and there expect his pleasure.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gas.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Abrahen</HI> Caliph!
There is some hopes then, we shall gaine our pardons:
Long live great <HI>Abrahen.</HI> Souldiers, slink away,
our vow is consummate.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<P>O my deare Lord!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Be gone.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Os.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, as quietly
as if we were in flight before the foe;
the general pardon at the coronation,
wil bring us off▪ I' me sure.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas, good Madam!
I'me sorrie that these miseries have faln
with so much rigor on you; pray take comfort▪
your husband prosecuted with too much violence
Prince <HI>Abilqualit</HI>'s ruine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<P>It appeared so!
what worlds of woes have hapless I given life to,
and yet survive them!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Do not with such furie
torment your innocent self. I'me su<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e the Emperor
<HI>Abrahen,</HI> wil number 't 'mongst his greatest sorrows,
that he has lost your husband. I must give him
notice of these proceedings. Best peace keep you,
and settle your distractions.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<P>not until
I'me setled in my peaceful urne. This is yet
some comfort to me, 'midst the floods of woes,
that do overwhelm me for the Princes death,
that I reveng'd it safely; though I prize
my life at no more value then a foolish
ignorant Indian does a Diamond,
which for a bead of Jet or glass, he changes:
Nor would I keep it, were it not with fuller,
more noble braverie, to take revenge
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>or my Lord <HI>Abilqualit</HI>'s timelesse slaughter.
<PB N="53" REF="27"/>
I must use craft and mysterie. Dissembling
is held the natural qualitie of our Sex,
nor wil't be hard to practice. This same <HI>Abrahen,</HI>
that by his brothers ruine weilds the Scepter,
whether out of his innocence or malice,
'twas that perswaded me to accuse him of
my rape. The die is cast, I am resolv'd
to thee my <HI>Abilqualit</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> wil come.
A death for love, 's no death but Martyrdom.</P>
<STAGE>Exit</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="5" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACTUS QUINTUS.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scena 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Abilqualit, Selinthus, Gasselles, Osman,
Souldiers, <HI>and</HI> Muts▪</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abil.</SPEAKER>
<P>NO more, good faithful Souldiers; thank the powers
divine, has brought me back to you in safety;
the traitorous practises against our life,
and our deare fathers, poison'd by our b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>other;
we have discoverd, and shall take just vengan<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e
on the unnatural paricide: Retire
into your tents, and peacefully expect
the event of things, you <HI>Osman</HI> and <HI>Gasselles</HI>
shall into th' Citie with me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Os.</SPEAKER>
<P>We wil march
through the world with thee, dear Soveraign,
great <HI>Abilqualit.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Selinthus,
give you our dear <HI>Tarif<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> speedie notice
we are again among the living: pray <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>im
to let our loyal Subjects in the Citie,
have sure intelligence of our escape;
and dearest friends and fellowes, let not your
too loud expressions of your joy, for our
unlook'd for welfare, subject to discoverie
our unexpected safety.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Never fear: they'r trustie M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rmidons, and wil stick close
to you their dear <HI>Achilles;</HI> but my Lord,
the wisest may imagine it were safer
for you to rest here 'mong your armed legions,
then to intrust your person in the City,
whereas it seems by the pass'd storie, you'le
not know friends from enemies.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="54" REF="28"/>
<SPEAKER>Abil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Selinthus,
Thy honest care declares the zealous duty
thou ow'st thy Soveraign: but what danger can
assault us there, where there is none suspects
we are alive? we'l go surveigh the state
of things, i'th' morning we will seize the Palace,
and then proclaim our Right. Come, valiant Captains,
you shall be our companions.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gas.</SPEAKER>
<P>And w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'l guard you
safe, as you were encompass'd with an Army.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<P>You guard your own fools heads: Is 't fit his safety,
on which our lives and fortunes have dependance,
should be expos'd unto your single valour?
Pray once let your friends rule you, that you may
rule them hereafter. Your good brother <HI>Abrahen</HI>
has a strong faction, it should seem i'th' Court:
and those these Blood-hounds follow'd the sent ho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ly
till they had worried <HI>Mura</HI> He has other
allies of no mean consequence; your E<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nuch
<HI>Mesithes</HI> his chief Favourite, and <HI>Simanthes.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abil.</SPEAKER>
<P>It was that Villain that betray'd my Love
to him and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>laught'red <HI>Mura.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Very likely.
An arranter, falser Parasite, never was
cut like a Colt. Pray Sir, be wife this once,
at my intreaties; and for ever after
use your discretion as you please: these night works
I do not like; yet e're the morning I will bring
<HI>Tarifa</HI> to you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abil.</SPEAKER>
<P>You shall o're rule us. Poor <HI>Caropi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</HI> these
thoughts are thy vot'ries; love thy active fire,
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ames out when present, absent in desire.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scen. 2.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Abrahen, Simanthes <HI>and</HI> Mesithes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abr.</SPEAKER>
<P>What State and Dignitie's like that of Scepters?
With what an awful Majesty resembles it
the Powers above? the inhabitants of that
Superior world are not more subject
to them, then these to us; they can but tremble
when they do speak in thunder; at our frowns
these shake like Lambs at light 'ning. Can it be
impie<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y by any means to purchase
this earthly Deity▪ Soveraignty▪ I did sleep
<PB N="55" REF="28"/>
this night with as secure and calme a peace,
as in my former innocence. Conscience,
thou'<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t but a terror, first devis'd by th' fears
of Cowardise, a sad and fond remembrance,
which men should shun, as Elephants clear springs,
lest they behold their own deformities,
<STAGE>Enter Mesithes.</STAGE>
and start at their grim shadowes. Ha, <HI>Mesithes!</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mes.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Royal Lord!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Call me thy Friend, <HI>Mesithes,</HI>
thou equally dost share our heart, best Eunuch;
there is not in the stock of earthly blessings
another I could wish to make my state
completely fortunate, but one; and to
atcheive possession of that bliss, thy diligence
must be the fortunate Instrument.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mes.</SPEAKER>
<P>Be it dangerous
as the affrights Sea men do fain in Tempests,
I'll undertake it for my gracious Soveraign,
and perish, but effect it,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abr.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, there is
not the least shew of peril in't; 'tis the want
of fair <HI>Caropia</HI>'s long coveted beauties
that doth afflict thy <HI>Abrahen.</HI> Love, <HI>Mesithes,</HI>
is a most stubborn Malady in a Lady, not cur'd
with that <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>elicity, that are other passions,
and creeps upon us by those ambushes,
that we perceive our selves sooner in love,
then we can think upon the way of loving.
The old flames break more brightly from th'ashes
where they have long layn hid, like the young Phenix
that from her spi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>le pile revives more glorious.
Nor can I now extinguish't; it has pass'd
the limits of my reason, and intend
my wil, where like a fixt Star 't settles,
never to be removed thence.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mes.</SPEAKER>
<P>Cease your fears;
I that could win her for your brother, who
could not boast half your masculine Perfections,
for you will vanquish her.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Simanthes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord, the widow
of slaughtered <HI>Mura,</HI> fair <HI>Caropia</HI> does
humbly intreat access to your dread presence;
Shall we permit her entrance?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abr.</SPEAKER>
<P>With all freedom
<PB N="56" REF="29"/>
and best regard. <HI>Mesithes,</HI> this arrives
beyond our wish. I'll trie my eloquence
in my own cause; and if I fail, thou then
shalt be my Advocate.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mes.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your humblest vassal.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abr.</SPEAKER>
<P>With-draw and leave us, and give strict order
none approach our presence
till we do call. It is not fit her sorrows
<STAGE>Enter Car.</STAGE>
should be survey'd by common eie. <HI>Caropia,</HI> welcom;
and would we could as easily give thee comfort
as we allow thee more then mod'rate pitie.
In tears those eyes cast forth a greater lustre,
then sparkling rocks of Diamonds inclos'd
in swelling seas of Pearl.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your Majestie
is pleas'd to wanton with my miseries,
which truly you, if you have nature in you,
ought to bear equall part in your deer brothers
untimely losse, occasion'd by my falshood,
and your improvident counsel: 'Tis that calls
these hearty sorrows up, I am his Murdresse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abr.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Twas his own destinie, not our bad intentions
took him away from earth; he was too heavenly,
fit only for th' societie of Angels,
'mongst whom he sings glad hymns to thy perfections,
celebrating with such eloquence thy beauties,
that those immortal essences forget
to love each other by intelligence,
and doat on the Idea of thy Sweetnesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<P>These gentle blandishments▪ and his innocent carriage
had I as much of malice as a Tigresse
rob'd of her young, would melt me into meeknesse.
But I'll not be a woman.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sing out, Angel,
and charm the world (were it at mortal diff'rence)
to peace with thine inchantments. What soft murmurs
are those that steal through those pure rosie organs,
like aromatick west-winds, when they flie
through fruitful mists of fragrant mornings dew,
to get the Spring with child of flowers and spices?
Disperse these clouds, that like the vail of night,
with unbecoming darknesse shade thy beauties,
and strike a new day from those orient eies,
to gild the world with brightnesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="57" REF="29"/>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, these flatteries
neitheir befit the ears of my true sorrows,
nor yet the utt'rance of that reall sadnesse
should dwel in you. Are these the fun'ral rites
you pay the memorie of your roiall Father,
and much lamented Brother?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abr.</SPEAKER>
<P>They were mortall,
and to lament them, were to shew I envi'd
th' immortal joyes of that true happinesse
their glorious souls (disfranchis'd from their flesh)
possess to perpetuitie and fulnesse.
Besides, <HI>(Caropia)</HI> I have other griefs
more neer my heart, that circle 't with a sicknesse
will shortly number me among their fellowship▪
if speedier remedie be not apply'd
to my most desp'rate maladie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<P>I shall
(if my hand fail not my determin'd courage)
send you to their societie far sooner
then you expect or covet. Why, great Sir,
what grief, unlesse your sorrow for their losse,
is't can afflict you, that command all blessings
men wittie in ambition of excesse
can wish, to please their fancies?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abr.</SPEAKER>
<P>The want only
of that which I've so long desird; thy love
thy love, <HI>Caropia,</HI> without which my Empire,
and all the pleasures flowing from its greatnesse,
wil be but burdens, soul-tormenting troubles.
There's not a beam shot from those grief drown'd Comets
but (like the Sun's, when they break forth of showers)
dart flames more hot and piercing. Had I never
doated before on thy divine perfections,
viewing thy beautie thus adorn'd by sadnesse,
my heart, though marble, actuated to softnesse,
would burn like sacred incense, it self being
the Altar, Priest, and Sacrifice.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<P>This is
as unexpected, as unwelcome, Sir.
Howere you're pleas'd to mock me and my griefs
with these impertinent, unmeant discourses,
I cannot have so prodigal a faith,
to give them the least credit; and it is
unkindly done; thus to deride my sorrows.
<PB N="58" REF="30"/>
the virgin Tur<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>les hate to joyn their pureness
with widow'd mates; my Lord, you are a Prince,
and such as much detest to utter falshoods,
as Saints do perjuries: why should you strive then
to lay a bait to captivate my affections, when your
greatnesse conjoin'd with your youths masculine beauties,
are to a womans f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ailtie, strong temptations?
You know the storie too of my misfortunes,
that your dead brother, did with vicious loosenesse,
corrupt the chast streams of my spotlesse vertues,
and left me soiled like a long pluck'd rose,
whose leaves dissever'd, have forgon their sweetnesse</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou hast not (my <HI>Caropia;)</HI> thou to me
art for thy sent stil fragrant, and as precious
as the prime virgins of the Spring, the violets,
when they do first display their early beauties,
til all the winds in love, do grow contentio<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s,
which from their lips should ravish the first kisses.
<HI>Caropia,</HI> thinkst thou I should fear the Nuptials
of this great Empire, 'cause it was my brothers?
As I succeeded him in all his glories,
'tis fit I do succeed him in h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s love.
'Tis true, I know thy fame fel by his practise,
which had he liv'd, hee'd have restored by marriage,
by it repair'd thy injur'd honors ruines.
I'me bound to do it in religious conscience;
It is a debt his incens'd ghost would quarrel
me living for, should I not pay't with fulnesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<P>Of what frail temper is a womans weaknesse!
words writ in waters, have more lasting Essence,
then our determinations.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come, I know,
thou must be gentle, I perceive a combat
in thy soft heart, by th' intervening blushes
that strive to adorn thy cheek with purple beauties,
and drive the lovely liverie of thy sorrows,
the Ivorie paleness, out of them. Think, <HI>Caropia,</HI>
with what a setled unrevolting truth
I have affected thee; with what heat, what pureness;
and when upon mature considerations,
I found I was unworthie to enjoy
a tre<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sure of such excellent grace and goodnesse,
I did desist, smothering my love in anguish;
anguish! to which the soul of humane torments,
<PB N="59" REF="30"/>
compar'd, were pains not easie, but delicious;
yet stil the secret flames of my affections,
like hidden virtues in some bashful man,
grew great and ferventer by those suppression<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.
Thou wert created only for an Empresse;
despise not then thy destinie, now greatnesse,
love, Empire, and what ere may be held glorio<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s,
courts thy acceptance like obedient Vassals.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<P>I have consider'd, and my serious thought<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
tel me, tis folly to refuse these profers:
to put off my mortalitie, the pleasures
of life, which like ful streams, do flow from greatnesse,
to wander i'th' unpeopled air, to keep
societie with ghastly apparitions,
where's neither voice of friends, n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r visiting suitors
breaths to delight our ears, and a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l this for
the fame of a fell murdress. I have blood
enough alreadie on my soul, more then
my tears can e're wash off. My roial Lord,
if you can be so merciful and gracious,
to take a woman laden with afflictions,
big with true sorrow, and religious penitence
for her amiss, her life and after actions,
shal studie to deserve your love. But surely
this is not serious.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not the vowes which votries
make to the powers above, can be more fraught
with binding sanctitie.
This holy kiss
confirms our mutual vows: never til now
was I true Caliph of <HI>Arabia.</HI></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter, Enter, Enter,</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha, what tumult's that!
Be you all furies, and thou the great'st of divels,
<HI>Abrahen</HI> wil stand you all, unmov'd as mountains.
This good sword
if you be air, shal disinchant you from
your borrow'd figures.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abil.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, ill-natur'd monster,
we're all corporeal, and survive to take
revenge on thy inhumane acts, at name
of which, the bashful elements do shake
as if they teem'd with prodigies. Dost not tremble
a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> thy inhumane villaines? Dear <HI>Caropia,</HI>
<PB N="60" REF="31"/>
quit the infectious viper, lest his touch
poison thee past recoverie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abr.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, she shall not;
nor you, until this body be one wound.
Lay a rude hand upon me! <HI>Abilqualit,</HI>
how ere thou scapst my practises with life,
I am not now to question; we were both
sons to one father, whom, for love of Empire,
when I beleev'd thee strangled by those Muts,
I sent to his eternal rest; nor do I
repent the fact yet, I have been titled <HI>Caliph</HI>
a day, which is to my ambitious thoughts,
honor enough to eternize my big name
to all posteritie. I know thou art
of valiant noble soul; let not thy brother
fal by ignoble hands, oppress'd by number;
draw thy bright weapon; as thou art in Empire,
thou art my rival in this Ladies love,
whom I esteem above all joyes of life:
for her and for this Monarchie, let's trie
our strengths and fates<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>: the impartial fates
to him, who has the better cause, in justice
must needs design the victorie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abil.</SPEAKER>
<P>In this offer,
though it proceed from desperatenesse, not valor;
thou showst a masculine courage, and we wil not
render our cause so abject as to doubt,
but our just arme has strength to punish
thy most unheard of treacheries</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<P>But you shall not
be so unjust to us and to your right,
to try your causes most undoubted Justice,
'gainst the dispairing ruffian; Souldiers, pul
the Lady from him, and disarm him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Stay!
though he doth merit multitudes of death,
we would not murder his eternitie
by sudden execution; yeild your self,
and we'l allow you libertie of life,
til by repentance you have purg'd your sin;
and so if possible, redeem your soul
from future punishment.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pish, tel fools of souls,
and those effeminate cowards that do dreame
<PB N="61" REF="31"/>
of those fantastick other worlds: there is
not such a thing in nature; all thesoul
of man is resolution, which expires
never from valiant men, till their last breath,
and then with it like to a flame extinguisht'd
for want of matter, 't dos not dy, but rather
ceases to live. Injoy in peace your Empire,
and as a legacy of <HI>Abrahens</HI> love,
take this fair Lady to your Bride.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>stab her.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Inhumane Butcher!
has slain the Lady. Look up, best <HI>Caropia,</HI>
run for our surgeons: I'le give half my Empire
to save her precious life.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abr.</SPEAKER>
<P>She has enough,
or mine aym fail'd me, to procure her passage
to the eternal dwellings: nor is this
cruelty in me; I alone was worthy
to have injoy'd her beauties. Make good haste
<HI>Caropia,</HI> or my soul, if I have any,
will hover for thee in the clouds. This was
the fatal engine which betray'd our father
to his untimely death, made by <HI>Simanthes</HI>
for your use, <HI>Abilqualit:</HI> and who has this
about him and would be a slave to your base mercy,
deserved death more than by dayly tortures;
and thus I kiss'd my last breath. Blast you all.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>dies.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Damn'd desperate villain.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abil.</SPEAKER>
<P>O my dear <HI>Caropia,</HI>
my Empire now will be unpleasing to me
since I must lose thy company. This surgeon,
where's this surgeon?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Drunk perhaps.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis but needlesse,
no humane help can save me: yet me thinks
I feel a kind of pleasing ease in your
imbraces. I should utter something,
and I have strength enough, I hope, lest yet
to effect my purpose. In revenge <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>or your
suppos'd death, my lov'd Lord, I slew my husband,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abil.</SPEAKER>
<P>I'me sorry thou hast that sin to charge thy soul with,
'twas rumour'd by the souldiers.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Couzens mine, your necks are safe agen now.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<P>And came hither
with an intent to have for your sake slain your brother
<PB N="62" REF="32"/>
<HI>Abrahen,</HI> had not his curtesie and winning carriage
alter'd my resolution, with this poniard
I'de struck him here about the heart.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Stabs <HI>Abil.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abil.</SPEAKER>
<P>O <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> am slain, <HI>Caropia,</HI>
and by thy hand. Heavens, you are just, this is
revenge for thy dear honor which I murdred,
though thou wer't consenting to it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<P>True, I was so,
and not repent it yet, my sole ambition
was to have liv<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d an Empresse, which since fate
would not allow, I was resolv'd no woman
after my selfe should ere <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>njoy that glory,
you dear <HI>Abilqualit:</HI> which since my
weak strength has serv'd me to performe, I dye
willingly as an infant. O now I faint,
life's death to those that keep it by constraint.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>dye.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<P>My dear Lord,
is there no hopes of life? must we be wretched?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Happier, my <HI>Tarifa,</HI> by my death:
but yesterday I playd the part in jest
which I now act in earnest My <HI>Tarifa,</HI>
the Empire's thine, I'me sure thou'lt rul't
with justice, and make the subject happy. Thou hast a Son
of hopefull growing vertues to succeed thee,
commend me to him, and from me intreat him
to shun the temptings of lascivious glances.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Las good Prince!
heele dy indeed. I fear, he is so full
of serious thoughts and Counsels.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abil.</SPEAKER>
<P>For this slaughtred body,
let it have decent burial with slain <HI>Muras,</HI>
but let not <HI>Abrahens</HI> corps have so much honor
to come ith' royal monument: lay mine
by my dear fathers: for that trecherous Eunuch,
and Lord <HI>Simanthes,</HI> use them as thy justice
tells thee they have merited; for Lord <HI>Selinthus,</HI>
advance him (my <HI>Tarif<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>)</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>'s of faithfull
and well deserving vertues.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l:</SPEAKER>
<P>So I am,
I thought t'would come to me anon:
poor <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ince, I e'ne could dy with him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ab<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l.</SPEAKER>
<P>And for those souldiers, and those our most faithfull
<HI>Muts,</HI> that my life once sav'd, let them be
well rewarded; death and I are almost now
<PB N="63" REF="32"/>
at unitie. Farewell.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>dyes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sure I shall not
survive these sorrows long. Muts, take those Traitors
to prison; we will shortly passe their sentence,
which shall be death inevitable. Take up
that fatal instrument of poisonous mischief,
and see it burn'd, <HI>Gaselles.</HI> Gentlemen,
Fate has made us your King against our wishes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Long live <HI>Tarifa,</HI> Caliph of <HI>Arabia.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<P>We have no time now for your acclamations▪
these are black sorrows Festival. Bear off
in state that royal Bodie; for the other,
since twas his will, let them have burial,
but in obscuritie. By this it may,
as by an ev'dent rule be understood,
they're onely truly great, wh' are truly good.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Recorders
Flourish.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Exeunt omnes.</STAGE>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
<BACK>
<DIV1 TYPE="epilogue">
<HEAD>EPILOGUE.</HEAD>
<L>I'M much displeas'd the Poet has made me</L>
<L>The Epilogue to his sad Tragedie.</L>
<L>Would I had dy'd honestly amongst the rest,</L>
<L>Rather then live to th' last, now to be prest</L>
<L>To death by your hard Censures. Pray you say,</L>
<L>What is it you dislike so in this Play,</L>
<L>That none applauds? Beleeve it, I should faint,</L>
<L>Did not some smile, and keep me by constraint</L>
<L>From the sad qualm. What pow'r is in your breath,</L>
<L>That you can save alive, and doom to death,</L>
<L>Even whom you please? thus are your judgme<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ts free,</L>
<L>Most of the rest are slain, you may save me.</L>
<L>But if death be the word, I pray bestow it</L>
<L>Where it best fits. Hang up the Poet.</L>
</DIV1>
</BACK>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

