<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2005-08-24</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Judith Siefring</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, etc.). Checked for signatures. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, and UNCLEARs. Corrected 5 $s of 184. Converted 179 $s to GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech". Checked spacing of foreign GAPs. Checked for EPIGRAPHs and ARGUMENTs. Checked for startqs, endqs, oes, q;s, and Qs. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Checked for CLOSERs, TRAILERs, and BYLINEs. DONE.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="A37212">
<STC T="W">D370</STC>
<BIBNO T="oclc">12547435</BIBNO>
<VID>63108</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>King Iohn
AND
MATILDA,
A
TRAGEDY.
As it was Acted with great Applause
by her <HI>Majesties</HI> Servants at the
Cock-pit in <HI>Drury-lane.</HI></P>
<P>Written
by ROBERT DAVENPORT Gent.</P>
<P><HI>LONDON,</HI>
Printed for <HI>Andrew Pennycuicke,</HI> in
the Year 1655.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dramatis personae">
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>The Names of the Persons in the Play,
And of the Actors that first Acted it on the
Stage, and often before their Majesties.</HEAD>
<LIST>
<LABEL>King <HI>John,</HI></LABEL>
<ITEM><HI>M.</HI> Bowyer.</ITEM>
<LABEL>Fitzwater,</LABEL>
<ITEM><HI>M.</HI> Perkins Whose action gave Grace to the Play.</ITEM>
<LABEL>Old Lord <HI>Bruce,</HI></LABEL>
<ITEM><HI>M.</HI> Turner.</ITEM>
<LABEL>Young <HI>Bruce,</HI></LABEL>
<ITEM><HI>M.</HI> Sumner.</ITEM>
<LABEL>Chester,</LABEL>
<ITEM><HI>M.</HI> Iackson.</ITEM>
<LABEL>Oxford,</LABEL>
<ITEM><HI>M.</HI> Goat.</ITEM>
<LABEL>Leister,</LABEL>
<ITEM><HI>M.</HI> Young.</ITEM>
<LABEL>Hubert,</LABEL>
<ITEM><HI>M.</HI> Clarke.</ITEM>
<LABEL>Pandolph,</LABEL>
<ITEM><HI>M.</HI> Allen.</ITEM>
<LABEL>Brand,</LABEL>
<ITEM>M. <HI>Shirelock,</HI> who
performed excellently well.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<HEAD>Other Lords and Gentlemen,
Attendants on the King.</HEAD>
<ITEM><HI>Queen</HI> Isabel.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Matilda.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Ladies of honour.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Lady <HI>Abbesse.</HI></ITEM>
</LIST>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="to the reader">
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>To the knowing Reader.</HEAD>
<P><HI>A</HI> Good Reader, helps to make a Book; a bad
injuries it: The <HI>Author</HI> of this, had no
mind to be a man in Print; nor tooke he any care
for a Sculpture, to illustrate the Frontis-piece by
crowning himselfe with Laurel: Neither did he
write his owne <HI>Encomiums,</HI> and (to prejudicate
the simple) say his friends forc'd them upon him;
they may help to sell the Book, not better the Mat∣ter.
And since this <HI>Tragedy</HI> is come to tell its own
tale, and to speak for it self, he wil he glad to know
it able to ca<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ry its own commendation; And (being
an Infant, newly deliver'd to the world from the
wombe of the Press) he hopes the knowing Rea∣der
will rather Crown it by his Candor, then kill
it in the Cradle.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>R. D.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="3"/>
<HEAD>To the Right Honourable, Mountague
Berty, Earle of Lindsey, Lord
Willougbby to Eresby &amp;c.</HEAD>
<P>YOu are no stranger to things of this nature, and
therefore the Dedication will not startle
you; such there are (my Lord) whose soules are
confin'd to their Chinck, and these looke squint-ey'd upon
a Dedication, because they feare there is a Spirit in't will
separate them: But my Lord, your Noblenesse to learning,
and wit raiseth your estimate to so high an accompt among
knowing men, thi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> from thence I have derived this bold∣nesse,
which I hope is pardonable not onely for that your
justice calls upon me for a duty I long since owed your Ho∣nour,
but also in regard the Thing presented is no sleight
Piece, but such (my Lord) at I presume will accord with
your judgement and likeing: It past the Stage with gene∣rall
Applause (my selfe being the last that that Acted <HI>Ma∣tilda</HI>
in it) and since through the absurdity of times, it
hath laine obscured. My Lord, though it doth not appeare
in it's ancient and full glory, yet it comes drest; first, with
an humble regard to your Honour, and then a confidence of
it's naked worth, but both it and my selfe, are willingly
subjected unto your Honours sentence, which I hope will not
be too heavy, especially upon</P>
<CLOSER><SALUTE>My Lord,</SALUTE>
<SIGNED><HI>Your Honours
Honourer,</HI>
Andrew Pennycuicke.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<HEAD><PB REF="3"/>King Iohn
AND
Matilda.</HEAD>
<DIV1 N="1" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus 1. Scoena 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>King, Queen,</HI> and <HI>Oxford.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King</SPEAKER>
<L><SEG REND="decorInit">T</SEG>Hey will not come?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ox.</SPEAKER>
<L>They will not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King</SPEAKER>
<L>They had been better—</L>
<L>What was their answer?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ox.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thus said <HI>Fitzwater,</HI> father of the faction,</L>
<L>That was Generall for the Barrons against your Majestie:</L>
<L>Tell <HI>John,</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ki.</SPEAKER>
<L>John!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ox.</SPEAKER>
<L>That was his Epithite;</L>
<L>(Alledging how you stood at <HI>Rome,</HI> put from</L>
<L>Your Kingly office.) Tell <HI>John,</HI> quoth he, (and frown'd)</L>
<L>That here at <HI>Baynards</HI> Castle, we intend</L>
<L><PB REF="4"/>
A settled stay for private reformations.</L>
<L>Of conceiv'd injuries, which by the peace</L>
<L>The King made with us, were not throughly search'd,</L>
<L>But like green wounds, clos'd with too swift a salve,</L>
<L>(Upon your private ends) are with more danger</L>
<L>Doubts and distracted difficulties again</L>
<L>Broke forth; but having drawn them to a head,</L>
<L>They would send them to you to be ratified,</L>
<L>And then give their attendance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is brave;</L>
<L>Who was there else?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ox.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Richmond,</HI> imperious <HI>Leister,</HI> and old <HI>Bruce.</HI></L>
<L>(The second in this revolt,) who sent the same return.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nest of Rebels; to try the truth of these fine florishes,</L>
<L>You with Lord <HI>Mowbray,</HI> post unto <HI>Guilford,</HI></L>
<L>And being there, (pretending a visite unto <HI>Bruces</HI> Lady,)</L>
<L>Wind into observation of the Castle so from her,</L>
<L>(The engine upon which these factions move,)</L>
<L>Discover the intent of their disignes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sure sir, the Lady is noble; but your Majesties</L>
<L>Injunction shall be obey'd.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.
Enter Chester.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>This not onely advantages</L>
<L>Our meeting with <HI>Fitzwaters</HI> Daughter,</L>
<L>(O how the thought) startles my blood)</L>
<L>But likewise furthers our resolv'd proceedings:</L>
<L><HI>Chester</HI> the news?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chest.</SPEAKER>
<L>Conceal your selfe sir,</L>
<L>I have trapt her with a snare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Agen, then I shall see he<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>—</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.
Enter Matilda.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>You told me <HI>Chester</HI></L>
<L>That the Queen did earnestly request my attendance:</L>
<L>You said she was here i'th Garden,</L>
<L>But it seems you were mis-inform'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ches.</SPEAKER>
<L>Excellent innocence how art thou trapt!</L>
<L>I must attend the King; please you walk Madam</L>
<L>But towards the Grove, I was told the <HI>Queen</HI> and Ladies</L>
<L>Retyred there for shade.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="4"/>
<SPEAKER>Ches.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I must vanish</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Chest.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Ent. King.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh heaven, the King!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy friend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>False <HI>Chester!</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fair <HI>Matilda,</HI></L>
<L>Mistresse of youth and beauty, sweet as a spring,</L>
<L>And comely as the holy shining Priest</L>
<L>Deckt in his glorious sacerdotall vestment;</L>
<L>Yet heare the passions of a love sick Prince,</L>
<L>And crown thy too too cruell heart with pitty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet let fall your too too passionate plea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ings,</L>
<L>And crown your royall heart with excellent reason.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hear me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Queen will heare you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speak but a word that—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>What?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>That may sound like something,</L>
<L>That may but busie my strong labouring heart,</L>
<L>With hope that thou wilt grant, and every morning</L>
<L>I will walk forth and watch the early Lark,</L>
<L>And at her sweetest note I will protest,</L>
<L><HI>Matilda</HI> spake a word was like that note.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh how you tempt: remember pray your vows</L>
<L>To my betroth'd Earl <HI>Robert Huntington;</HI></L>
<L>Did you not wish just as the poyson toucht</L>
<L>His manly heart, i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> ever you again</L>
<L>Laid battery to the fair fort of my unvanquish'd</L>
<L>Vertue, your death might be like his untimely,</L>
<L>And be poyson'd. Oh take heed sir,</L>
<L>Saints stand upon heavens silver battlements,</L>
<L>When Kings make vows, and lay their</L>
<L>Listening ears to Princes Protestations.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>So did <HI>Matilda</HI> swear to live and die a maid,</L>
<L>At which fair Nature like a Snail shrunck back,</L>
<L>As loath to hear from one so fair, so foul</L>
<L>A wound: my vow was vain, made without</L>
<L>Recollection of my reason; and yours, Oh madnesse!</L>
<L><PB REF="5"/>
Maids have sure forsworne such vowes:</L>
<L>For <HI>Huntington,</HI> he like a heap of summers</L>
<L>Dust into his Grave is swept; and bad vows</L>
<L>Still are better broke then kept.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas great sir, your Queen you cannot make me;</L>
<L>What is it then instructs your tongue? Oh sir!</L>
<L>In things not right,</L>
<L>Lust is but loves well languag'd hypocrite.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Words shall convert to deeds then; I am the King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe but touch me,</L>
<L>And as I graspe steel in my trembling hand,</L>
<STAGE>Offers violence,
she drawes a knife.</STAGE>
<L>So sure the King shall see <HI>Matilda</HI> fall</L>
<L>A sacrifice to vertue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cruell Maid,</L>
<L>Crueller then the Kid that eanes her young</L>
<L>On the rough bosome of a ragged flint:</L>
<L>Go get thee to the woods, for thou art wild</L>
<L>As flame, or winter; where so e're thou walk'st</L>
<L>May wild winds chide thee, and the reeling Trees</L>
<L>Like a confus'd fall of many waters</L>
<L>Rail on thy rudeness; may the birds that build</L>
<L>Among the wanton branches, stead of teaching</L>
<L>Notes to their young, sing something like thy niceness:</L>
<L>And lastly, may the Brooks when thou shalt lie</L>
<L>And cast a pair of cruell busie eyes</L>
<L>Upon their subtill slydings, may the water,</L>
<L>The troubled image of my passions war</L>
<L>With the stones, the matter of thy heart, that thou maist learn</L>
<L>Thy hardnesse and my sufferings to discern;</L>
<L>And so whilst I (if it be possible) study to forget you,</L>
<L>May beasts, and bird<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, and brooks, and trees, and wind,</L>
<L>Hear me, and call <HI>Matilda</HI> too unkind.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile unto <HI>Baynards</HI> Castle to my father,</L>
<L>Oh she had a violent need of Castles, where a King</L>
<L>Layes such violent seige; but Oh truth,</L>
<L>Thou art (whilst tenant in a noble brest,)</L>
<L>A crown of Christall in an Ivory chest.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<PB REF="5"/>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>King</HI> and <HI>Chester.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall I be dazled with effeminate darings?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ches.</SPEAKER>
<L>With a womans ward, a knife too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here I left her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ch.</SPEAKER>
<L>But here she is not now sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh <HI>Chester</HI> run, run as thou lov'st my peace,</L>
<L>Feather thy feet with lovers wishes, let but my desires</L>
<L>Dwel in thy eyes, thou'lt find her, were she compast</L>
<L>With a Cimerian mist.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ch.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will do my best sir.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy best; do every thing, do any thing,</L>
<L>Do all things that may find her; whether Love</L>
<L>Leads thy dark Labyrinth; cannot Kings be free</L>
<L>From thy impetuous buffets? I have de<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>'d</L>
<L>A heardned heart, obdurate to thy shafts,</L>
<L>And some times am so, when in the very minute</L>
<L>Calling to mind <HI>Matilda's</HI> tears, like drops</L>
<L>Continued upon marble, they pierce through,</L>
<L>And I am soft again. Hast found her?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ent. Chester</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ch.</SPEAKER>
<L>No sir, she is by this in <HI>Baynards</HI> Castle,</L>
<L>Where her Father and the Lords—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Command our Barge, wee'l after her like lightning:</L>
<L>We must have pledges <HI>Chester</HI> for their faiths; if they refuse,</L>
<L>Thunder shall meet with thunder, and each eye</L>
<L>Shall see strange Comets in this troubled skie.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Fitzwater,</HI> old <HI>Bruise,</HI> young <HI>Bruise, Richmond</HI>
and <HI>Leister,</HI> as in <HI>Baynards</HI> Castle.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>My noble Lords, and honourable friends,</L>
<L>Not to particularlize (what need plain dealing</L>
<L>Be apparelled in particulars?) to a short supper,</L>
<L>Or a poor pittance rather, ye are all</L>
<L>Heartily welcome, very heartily, I must tell truth still.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>Brother we thank you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would we had my sister your wife, at <HI>Guilford</HI> with us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rich.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where are the Ladies?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="6"/>
<SPEAKER>Leis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Comfo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ting <HI>Matilda,</HI> sad return'd from Court.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Betraid by <HI>Chester,</HI> and again escap'd</L>
<L>Like a chaste Dove out of the fowlers Net,</L>
<L>The lustfull King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh <HI>John, John,</HI> wilt thou never</L>
<L>Leave thy wags tricks? but let it passe, tis best</L>
<L>Because indeed tis past.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leís.</SPEAKER>
<L>I wonder how he receiv'd our resolv'd answer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>u.</SPEAKER>
<L>No matter how, he's like to have no other;</L>
<L>Now by my blood, you vext my very soul</L>
<L>That you s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nt any.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sonne, have a tamer spirit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, and like horses,</L>
<L>Be held by'th nose by frivilous respect,</L>
<L>Whilst he casts Copperis into our sores, and searches</L>
<L>Past honours patience.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nephew, Nephew, hear me,</L>
<L>Lets bear a little; faith he is the King,</L>
<L>And though at <HI>Rome</HI> he does stand interdicted,</L>
<L>Yet now and then takes a good start or two</L>
<L>Towards regularity, till the fit comes on him;</L>
<L>And for your neat horse simile observe me,</L>
<L><HI>Richmond</HI> and you are young men, we three old,</L>
<L>But not too old to tell truth; the horse that will not</L>
<L>Stand till and endure searching, how e're in summer</L>
<L>With warmth and pasture, he may strike at flies,</L>
<L>And play the wanton in a wealthy meadow,</L>
<L>For all his summer pastime, yet tis said,</L>
<L>Winter will leave him but a lean scal'd jade;</L>
<L>Come, come, y'ar fooles, y'ar fooles.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well let us—bear then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>et us? Oh my blood!</L>
<L>Besides, our in uries in his breach of promise,</L>
<L>He made by stains and publique grievances,</L>
<L>How in the flames of his adulterate heart</L>
<L>Pursues he my chaste Cousin, by flights gets her</L>
<L>Within his tallon, and but this afternoon,</L>
<L><PB REF="6"/>
(Had not her friendly knife enfranchis'd her)</L>
<L>Even in the face of he<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ven, in his own Garden</L>
<L>He would have ravish'd her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>her, we are bound in honour not to bear it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let him know our griefs, and if—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, well, with <HI>iss</HI> and <HI>ands</HI></L>
<L>Mad men leave Rocks, and leap into the Sands;</L>
<L>But something shall be thought on.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ent. Richmond.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rich<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></SPEAKER>
<L>The King attended</L>
<L>Onely with the Earle of <HI>Chester, Oxford,</HI> and some</L>
<L>Other Gentlement, is new landed on the Stairs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Om.</SPEAKER>
<L>The King!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shut the stairs Gate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Twere better Gate and stairs</L>
<L>Were floating through bridg; we are safe my cholerick cousin,</L>
<L>As in a Sanctuary; tis enough</L>
<L>(A man would think,) to see a great Prince thus,</L>
<L>Cause wee'd not go to him, to come to us,</L>
<STAGE>Ent. King,
Oxford, Chester.
and other Lords</STAGE>
<L>Indeed, indeed, you speak unkindly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Behold great Lords,</L>
<L>The Cedars of the Kingdome, how the King</L>
<L>(A shrub) shrincks out of majestie.</L>
<L>And comes to you; here's a fine Conventicle,</L>
<L>Are ye blowing up new sires? and must <HI>Fitz<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>waters</HI></L>
<L>(Plain-breasted as his unaffected habite,)</L>
<L>Be Generall again, again be call'd</L>
<L>The Marshall of Heavens Army and the Churches?</L>
<L>Are you Planet st uck<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> you cannot talke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your pardon sir,</L>
<L>I led the Barrons, but twas when they could not choose</L>
<L>But choose a leader, and then me they chose;</L>
<L>And why so think ye? they all lov'd your Grace,</L>
<L>And grieve, grieve very heartily, I tell you,</L>
<L>To see you by some state mice so misled:</L>
<L>This state mice that nibble so upon the Lands impaired freedom</L>
<L>That would not so play in the Lyons eare,</L>
<L>But that by tickling him themselves to advantage;</L>
<L><PB REF="7"/>
This troubl'd us, and griev'd the body Politique,</L>
<L>And this we sought to mend; I tell truth <HI>John,</HI> I,</L>
<L>We are thy friends <HI>John,</HI> and if ye take from friendship</L>
<L>The liberty of modest admonition,</L>
<L>Ye leave no mark whereby to distinguish it</L>
<L>From the fawning passion of a Dog-base flattery;</L>
<L>If I speak plain, this truth be my desence,</L>
<L>A good mans comsort is his Conscience:</L>
<L>And so much for plain <HI>Robin.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Fitzwater, Bruce, Richmond,</HI> and stubborn <HI>Leister,</HI></L>
<L>This is the last of our admonitions,</L>
<L>Either lay by those Arms, those lawlesse arms,</L>
<L>Which you have listed 'gainst your Lord the King,</L>
<L>And give such pledges as we shall accept</L>
<L>For settling of your loyalties, or here</L>
<L>By the abused sufferings of a King,</L>
<L>And by the unkind scars with which you have</L>
<L>Deform'd the face of <HI>England;</HI> misery</L>
<L>Shall over take you in a shape shall fright</L>
<L>The Iron heart of faction, and the King</L>
<L>Shall come no more acquainted with compassion,</L>
<L>But call the bloodiest ends a righteous vengeance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leis.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will not leave mine arms,</L>
<L>Nor break my word to you,</L>
<L>Unlesse provok'd, and justly; you have my faith,</L>
<L>If you mislike that pledge—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>We do.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leis.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I reply that I can spare no nother.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ches.</SPEAKER>
<L>D'ce hear sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Already we have pawn'd the now scorn'd gage</L>
<L>Of our afflicted honours, which refus'd</L>
<L>Flies back again, and so we stand discharg'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>King <HI>John,</HI> King <HI>John,</HI></L>
<L>Perform but the seal'd Covenants you are fled from,</L>
<L>The Charter running thus, given by our hand</L>
<L>The seventeenth day of <HI>June,</HI> and in the year</L>
<L>215 (the whole Realm being sworn to't,)</L>
<L><PB REF="7"/>
And six and twenty Peers and Barrons sworn</L>
<L>To the execution (who if you fail) are perjur'd</L>
<L>Do this, and like a plat of Osier wands</L>
<L>We shall bow any way, and you shall work us</L>
<L>Into what fashion you shall fancy; but</L>
<L>if you be melancholly, love-sick <HI>John,</HI></L>
<L>Or Lyon, unyoak'd Heifer, head-strong <HI>John,</HI></L>
<L>(As in the matter of the Losse of <HI>Normandie,</HI></L>
<L>When <HI>Anjou, Brittain, Main, Poictou,</HI> and <HI>Turwin,</HI></L>
<L>Were deliver'd up to <HI>Philip</HI>) you'l find your friends</L>
<L>Not facile Willowes, but abrupt brambles,</L>
<L>Whose intricate irregularity</L>
<L>Whilst you shall go about to rectifie,</L>
<L>They'l prick your fingers, and with unkind scratches,</L>
<L>Expose you to a late deplor'd experience:</L>
<L>Come, come, know this, when love in our side sings,</L>
<L>The unkindest wounds are those we take from Kings;</L>
<L>I am plain <HI>Robin.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>A down right Rebell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rebell!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>So are ye all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Om.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rebells!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Traytors.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Om.</SPEAKER>
<L>Traytors!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rebels and Traytors; <HI>Chester, Oxford,</HI> Gentlemen,</L>
<L>Stand on your guards, there's danger in the room.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>You ate too passionate, perform with us,</L>
<L>You shall walk over us, if not, we stand</L>
<L>Our injur'd Countries Justicers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Proud boaster.</L>
<L>This night shall raise a storme: Brav'd? with you <HI>Bruce</HI></L>
<L>We will begin; and yet he is the Brother</L>
<STAGE>aside</STAGE>
<L>Unto <HI>Matilda's</HI> Father, but his insolence,</L>
<L>Oh love; a little while let revenge raigne,</L>
<L>This night shall beget passages shall prove</L>
<L>Your King a Lyon (vext) as (pleas'd) a Dove.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ox.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lights for the King; there Gentlemen.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Kings party.</STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="8"/>
<SPEAKER>Y. Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>What will you do? a tempest curl'd his forehead</L>
<L>Into the fashion of an angry Ocean,</L>
<L>Made wild with winds.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rich.</SPEAKER>
<L>We must resolve on something.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ol. Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>And suddenly, for in his executions</L>
<L>He is swift as lightning, ayr is not more light.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leis.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Pandulph</HI> the <HI>Popes</HI> stern Legate, tis divulg'd,</L>
<L>Is againe come over from the <HI>Pope,</HI> to proffer</L>
<L>The King his readmission into the Church,</L>
<L>And take off his six years interdiction</L>
<L>Upon some propositions yet conceal'd,</L>
<L>And this may busie the King yet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>This? the Greyhound</L>
<L>Is not more eager at his flying game,</L>
<L>Then I know King <HI>John</HI> is in his passions</L>
<L>Gf love or anger.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ol. Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why Brother, is this a time to study?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Troth I was thinking of—stay, stay, I hav't,</L>
<L>I was thinking brother <HI>Bruce,</HI>—now tis gone again,</L>
<L>And farewell it, lets ply our businesse now:</L>
<L>If you mark't, he said he would begin with you;</L>
<L>I Would have you to night (stay not for the Sun,</L>
<L>Which sure will rise blushing at this nights brawling)</L>
<L>Do you and <HI>Richmond,</HI> with some score of men</L>
<L>Post to your house, tis but an hours riding,</L>
<L>And something more; there fortifie your selves,</L>
<L>Your Ladie, and your pretty little Sonnne,</L>
<L>Poor knave he dreams not of these Thunderbolts:</L>
<L>You my young mad cap, with your Cuz my daughter,</L>
<L>Shall unto <HI>Hartford</HI> Castle, she is the brand</L>
<L>I feare will fire our <HI>Troy; Leister</HI> and I</L>
<L>Will gather Powers, and thither after you;</L>
<L>You two for <HI>Guilford,</HI> you two for <HI>Hartford,</HI></L>
<L>And we two, wheither wast we two must go?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Go? we two must stay i'th City.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Passion of me, where was my memory;</L>
<L><PB REF="8"/>
But come, come, when Kings our Dials retrograde do run,</L>
<L>We leave to look on them, and go by'th Sun:</L>
<L>Lights, lights, good Gentlemen:</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Queene, Lady, Bruce, <HI>and</HI>
Hubert.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good Lady take not on so, <HI>Oxford</HI> sayes all</L>
<L>Is very well at <HI>London.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, very well;</L>
<L>Why then follow'd he your Grace with a Troop of horse,</L>
<L>A band of men? why hath he seizd the Castle,</L>
<L>Cashierd my Servants? Oh Madam can it be,</L>
<L>Your Grace (the Alter where I ever paid</L>
<L>A Subjects devout Love,) should by a slight,</L>
<L>a fained accidentall visite make,</L>
<L>An entrance for hostility and terror.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Hubert,</HI> redeem you in this Ladies faith,</L>
<L>And relate the truth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Only upon mine honour</L>
<L>Was I sent to seize this Ladies young Son <HI>George,</HI></L>
<L>As a pledge to'th King for her Lords loyalty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>No <HI>Hubert,</HI> my Son is far enough from thee,</L>
<L>Thou fatall keeper of poor Boys.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hub.</SPEAKER>
<L>You mean</L>
<L>Concerning <HI>Arthur,</HI> the unfortunate Sonne</L>
<L>Of <HI>Jeffery Plantaganet;</HI> Oh mad rumour!</L>
<L>Who would trust thee but with so much reputation</L>
<L>An honest begger boasts of?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q.</SPEAKER>
<L>In that beleeve me Madam, report hath wronged him,</L>
<L>Which I can witnesse Lady.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter King and
Chester.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>The King come to,</L>
<L>Oh my sweet <HI>George,</HI> my joy; what wilt thou do?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>All is to our desire; where's <HI>Bruces</HI> Sonne?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Convey'd to <HI>Wales</HI> she affirms Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where thou shalt never see him <HI>John.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good Madam,</L>
<L>Wee'l speak with you anon, Queene <HI>Isabell,</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="9"/>
Thou must be still an agent to secure</L>
<L>Me and my Kingdome, straight with the Earl of <HI>Chester;</HI></L>
<L>Post thou to <HI>Hartford</HI> Castle, whither we are certifi'd</L>
<L>Young <HI>Bruce</HI> is fled with old <HI>Fitzwaters</HI> daughter,</L>
<L>Try if by fair means thou canst win her to</L>
<L>Attend on thee at Court; if we have not her</L>
<L>A pledge, (as this) for her Fathers faith, we stand</L>
<L>The food of faction, get her any way;</L>
<L>If she deny, <HI>Chester</HI> with forces ready,</L>
<L>Of from the Castle, shall give them fierce assault,</L>
<L>And force them past entreaties; go my love</L>
<L>And play the Amazon, with her surprisall,</L>
<L>Secure a Kingdome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>This craves hast and care; come noble <HI>Chester</HI></L>
<L>You shall along; but good my Lord forget not</L>
<L>That Ladies kindnesse to me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh my sweet.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Kisse.
Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>What a fine thing he makes the Queen; Oh lust,</L>
<L>With what smooth craft thou creeptst to things unjust.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh my <HI>Matilda,</HI> if power or policy</L>
<L>may get thee once more in these arms, I will hazard</L>
<L>Even to a Kingdom for thee; come Madam fear not</L>
<L>I wear no frowns, I am all mirth, lets see your pretty Son.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<L>I fear your mirth is like the Porpoist pastimes,</L>
<L>My Son hath been in <HI>Wales</HI> this moneth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Hubert,</HI> see the Gates lock'd, a guard upon the Walls,</L>
<L>Whilst we take some to search.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where will you search King <HI>John?</HI></L>
<L>For heavens sake do not search.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay and't be come to that.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me go,</L>
<L>In these proceedings the Kings safety rests,</L>
<L>The Lyon must not bend to baser breasts.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heaven to thee I kneel, who affrighted Mother am,</L>
<L>Oh from this Lyons claws keep my poor Lambe.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<PB REF="9"/>
<STAGE>Enter old <HI>Bruce,</HI> and <HI>Richmond,</HI> and above
<HI>Oxford.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ol. Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Castle Gates are shut, swift footed Tyranie,</L>
<L>That canst when thou pursu'st thy wild desires,</L>
<L>Out run the wantan Roe; Oh <HI>Richmond, Richmond,</HI></L>
<L>I fear our stay all night, ha's made me witness</L>
<L>Of a day darker then night.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rich.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yonr fears and your afflictions</L>
<L>Meet in one Center, for it seems the King</L>
<L>Sent <HI>Oxford</HI> in the night on the walls;</L>
<L>Behold where <HI>Oxford</HI> stands, I fear they have seiz'd</L>
<L>Your Sonne, your Wife and Castle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ol. Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Oxford,</HI> thou signe</L>
<L>Set up to shew me where my sorrows dwell,</L>
<L>Martyr me not with circumstances; but tell me,</L>
<L>Is it (as from thy ominous presence there)</L>
<L>We may conjecture.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ox.</SPEAKER>
<L>Because you request brevity,</L>
<L>Then by my ominous presence here great Lords</L>
<L>You conjecture that you come too late.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rich.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let force our entrance,</L>
<L>We have tweuty men of spirit to dare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ol. Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>A score of Cowards, <HI>Oxford,</HI></L>
<L>Dar'st thou be honourable?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ox.</SPEAKER>
<L>An other time,</L>
<L>But now I have no leisure, the King is here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rich.</SPEAKER>
<L>In person.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ox.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, and power;</L>
<L>And if the <HI>Queen</HI> and <HI>Chester</HI> speed as the King has,</L>
<L>We shall have a pledget too for <HI>Fitzwaters</HI> loyalty,</L>
<L>And so good day, ye meet the proverb here,</L>
<L>Ye both are early up but near the neare.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rich.</SPEAKER>
<L>We strongly may conclude from their intelligence</L>
<L>Of your Son, and fair <HI>Matilda's</HI> flight to <HI>Hartford,</HI></L>
<L>Thither the <HI>Queen</HI> and <HI>Chester</HI> are repair'd,</L>
<L>Either by force or policy to obtaine her,</L>
<L><PB REF="10"/>
So that the nearest path to our proceedings.</L>
<L>Is to post back to <HI>London,</HI> and to hasten</L>
<L>Her Father thither with his powers, and so</L>
<L>Secure your Sonne, his Daughter, and it may be,</L>
<L>Surprise the <HI>Queen</HI> and <HI>Chester.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ol. Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>If we do,</L>
<L>If but a hair of my betrayed wife,</L>
<L>Or my poor boy do perish, a head royall</L>
<L>Shall be sent back, slight scratches leave no scars</L>
<L>But deep wounds are seeds of Civill wars.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="2" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus 2. Scoena 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> King, Hubert, Lady, <HI>and</HI> Bruce.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>YOu would not then produce him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Think of it Madam,</L>
<L>And for your own discharge, give up your Son.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have him not to give.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>We will no more be mock'd, are all the people,</L>
<STAGE>Enter 2
Souldiers
with a
Hamper, the Boy
in it.</STAGE>
<L>Horses, and Cattel voided forth the Castle?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hub.</SPEAKER>
<L>All but this Hamper which stood underneath</L>
<L>The stairs that led into the Dungeon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>A place suspicious, search it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let not rudenesse boast sir,</L>
<L>She was born i'th presence of a Prince.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis lock'd my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where is the Key?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know not, lost.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cut it open.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do not, do not, indeed you'l spoile it then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well then they shall not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now the King is gracious.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<P>But fetch each man a Torch, and here before me
Set it a fire.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh rather cut it sir in a thousand peeces;</L>
<L><PB REF="10"/>
Why did you tell me that they should not cut it,</L>
<L>And now would burn it? who did teach you sir</L>
<L>To mock a wounded heart? look, look, and they do not go</L>
<L>To cut it too; good sir, I have a Jewel</L>
<L>Lyes conceal'd there, which I hid for feare o'th souldiers,</L>
<L>Of infinite value.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>The Boy rises.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis open my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>what's in't?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hub.</SPEAKER>
<P>Marry youth in a basket sir, here is the prety Jewel
Of infinite value.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold him fast fellow, <HI>Hubert</HI> keepe back the mother.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would be kept back, is that a Boy</L>
<L>To crush with a rude hand, alas a grisle</L>
<L>Look, and his very looks do not fright my Child.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh mother here is a man lookes very black,</L>
<L>(Pray do not hurt me) indeed, and if you doe,</L>
<L>You'l make my mother cry</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>For heavens sakellet me kisse him, I warrant you the
Childe was almost smotherd, come from him <HI>George.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<L>A wo'not let me go, if I were your match,</L>
<L>Ide give you a good sound box o'th eare,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, Come, 'we will not part you, <HI>Hubert</HI> there waits</L>
<L>One <HI>Brand</HI> without, servant to the Earle of <HI>Chester,</HI></L>
<L>With a guard, let him Convey them both to <HI>Winsor</HI> Castle,</L>
<L>And by this signet to sir <HI>Walter Blunt,</HI></L>
<L>Deteyne them in his custody, untill</L>
<L>We shall direct him further.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh brave, mother I have heard of <HI>Wiusor</HI> Castle, my father</L>
<L>Told me there are brave bowes and arrowes; and drums there.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh happy Innocent, who in spight of foes</L>
<L>Can play the pretty wanton with thy woes.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hub.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Lord Steward sir</L>
<STAGE>Enter Winchester.</STAGE>
<L>Is come it seemes from <HI>London.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord of <HI>Winchester</HI> the meaning of your speed?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Win.</SPEAKER>
<L>The <HI>Popes</HI> legate Sir,</L>
<L>The Cardinal <HI>Pandulp</HI> is ariv'd at <HI>London,</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>What newes with him; Six yeares we have stood</L>
<L><PB REF="11"/>
An inte<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>dicted man, can he bring lowder thunder?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Win.</SPEAKER>
<L>He brings proffers of peace sir,</L>
<L>Advantagable peace too, if that you please</L>
<L>To make a resignation of your Crowne:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Win.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good sir suffer mee,</L>
<L>And that to him to the <HI>Popes</HI> use; withall;</L>
<L>(Paying an Annuall tribute for your Kingdomes</L>
<L>Of <HI>England,</HI> and of <HI>Ircland,</HI> in the presence</L>
<L>Of the whole body of the Peers,) he has power</L>
<L>From his Holiness to reinvest your temples</L>
<L>With the rich Diadem; and with all pronounce you</L>
<L>Again admitted into the Church, your power</L>
<L>Weakned and wounded, yet may by this meanes</L>
<L>Lyon like, rowse it selfe and remove all obstacles</L>
<L>Twixt you and the high calling of a King,</L>
<L>Which by the reason you stood Curst at <HI>Rome,</HI></L>
<L>Receiv'd affronts so frequent; besides <HI>Fitzwaters,</HI></L>
<L>With <HI>Leister</HI> (who by the return of <HI>Bruce</HI> and <HI>Richmand</HI></L>
<L>From thence to <HI>London,</HI> were upon expedition,</L>
<L>With there powers for <HI>Hartford</HI> Castle to intercept</L>
<L>The proceedings of the Queen and <HI>Chester;</HI>)</L>
<L>I have staid upon the Legats special chardge</L>
<L>To attend your resignation, potent nessesity</L>
<L>(The great dispenser with all Cerimony,)</L>
<L>Calls it a point of Policy, whereby</L>
<L>You build your selfe, ruine your enemy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>And then you stand again, sir a King absolute</L>
<L>And dazel faction.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ki.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come we will catch craft</L>
<L>With imitation, he that would screw his ends</L>
<L>To his own aims, must mingle (when he wins)</L>
<L>Secret dissemblings 'mongst his venial sinnes.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Souldiers,</HI> and young <HI>Bruce</HI> prisoner.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ches.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are mine Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis false, I am Fortunes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="11"/>
<SPEAKER>Ches.</SPEAKER>
<L>This day to fortune then I sacrifice,</L>
<L>As to my Mistresse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Whore is then your Mistresse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ches.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Whore!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>A rascall Jade,</L>
<L>That takes with the dixterity she gives; tell me</L>
<L>Of your Mistresse and the Devil: Oh my stars.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ches.</SPEAKER>
<L>O sir we have wayes to tame you, you remember</L>
<L>You brav'd me in the presence of the King,</L>
<L>At <HI>Baynards</HI> Castle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh I am mad,</L>
<L>Yet not so mad, but I dare still brave <HI>Chester,</HI></L>
<L>And from the top of my affliction,</L>
<L>Upon thy light heel'd Mrs. wanton fortune,</L>
<L>Cast from the manly temper of my blood</L>
<L>A noble scorn.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ch.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall be fetter'd first.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fetter'd:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, and sent</L>
<L>Up to the King as an arch Rebel, to whom,</L>
<L>To whom (before) we have by Letters sent our happy fortune.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rebell:</L>
<L>By that boyling sea of blood which thou hast troubl'd,</L>
<L>Had my desires but bodies, I would burst</L>
<L>Fetters of steele, tear off thy canker'd flesh,</L>
<L>And with thy Jaw-bone, (thou honour wounding man)</L>
<L>I would kill a thousand of these Rascals.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Drag him</L>
<L>Into the Castle, since your fortunes move you,</L>
<L>We<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'l force you to a madnesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fool thou canst not;</L>
<L>Frost makes fire fervent, he that wisely knows</L>
<L>His wealthy fate, bravely becomes his woes.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Charge.
Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ches.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you so arm'd, away with him.</L>
</SP>
<PB REF="12"/>
<STAGE>Enter the <HI>Queene,</HI> dragging in <HI>Matilda,</HI> her hair loose,
and Face bloody.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come forward furie, witch.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas, why thus</L>
<L>Great <HI>Queen</HI> do you mis-use me? credite me</L>
<L>I do not feare to die, young Infants do it;</L>
<L>Nor wish I life, the murtherer enjoyes it;</L>
<L>But let me know my trespasse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'me made your stale,</L>
<L>The King, the King your strumpet; oh thou wretch,</L>
<L>The matter my spleen!</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>tears her.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hear me but speak.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, I will thee speak,</L>
<L>That every syllable may serve instead</L>
<L>Of a fierce wind to blow my fiercer fury</L>
<L>Into the fashion of a punishmen,</L>
<L>Fitting the daring of thy trespasse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heare me;</L>
<L>By these red marks, registers of your rashnesse,</L>
<L>And by these tears, the fruits of my affliction,</L>
<L>That the King passionately pursues my love,</L>
<L>Is truth uncontr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>dicted; but if I</L>
<L>Did ever think you wrong, let mine honour be</L>
<L>buried in dark oblivion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sin's a sweet tame Serpent, they must beguile</L>
<L>Cloath rude errors, in a soft smooth stile:</L>
<STAGE>Enter
Chester.</STAGE>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ut str<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mpst thou shalt ruin't.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Charge.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ches.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shift for your selfe Madam,</L>
<L><HI>Richmond</HI> escap'd from <HI>London</HI> with the powers</L>
<L>Leavied by <HI>Leister,</HI> and <HI>Fitzwater,</HI> (who</L>
<L>Were stai'd by <HI>Winchester,</HI> and the Legate <HI>Pandulph</HI>)</L>
<L>Hath rescued <HI>Bruce,</HI> got again the Castle,</L>
<STAGE>Ent. Y. Bruce,
and Richmond
with Souldiers.</STAGE>
<L>And make you now their search.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rich.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cease on the Queen;</L>
<L>Madam you are our prisoner,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Keep <HI>Chester</HI> safe good <HI>Ricmond;</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="12"/>
Ha! oh what rude hand</L>
<L>Hath ras'd this Book of beauty? a face where vertue</L>
<L>Intelligibly stood to charm the Reader: Tell me Cozen,</L>
<L>And by the thousands of thy tears, and fears</L>
<L>No tittle, place, degree, the very Grave</L>
<L>Shall not secure the offender.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>There is death in's angry eyes.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>aside.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat</SPEAKER>
<L>The rude Souldiers</L>
<L>My noble Cozen hail'd me thus, and tore me,</L>
<L>And would have sure done worse, but that the Queen,</L>
<L>The wondrou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> kind Queen in her royall person,</L>
<L>Came with a troop of well appointed Souldiers,</L>
<L>and rescued me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>She mocks me sure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Queen so kind.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>O Cousin had you seen</L>
<L>How good she was in her quick speed, how zealous</L>
<L>To relieve innocence, you would have thought</L>
<L>She'd kil'd them with her frowns e're she came at them,</L>
<L>So lamentably miserable were my sufferings,</L>
<L>So excellently noble was her charity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now by my life, 'twas honour in the highest,</L>
<L>Because a foe, and gracious Madam, not</L>
<L>To be out bid in this brave Mart of honour,</L>
<L>You shall have a safe Convoy, and of quality</L>
<L>Fitting your person, to convey (with your freedome)</L>
<L>To th'angry King our loves, that he may see</L>
<L>How plain to him we mean, and how nobly</L>
<L>Unto a goodnesse of so fair deservings</L>
<L>As this now showne; see there be present order</L>
<L>For her Majesties attendance, and swee Coz</L>
<L>With-draw from the cold ayr.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit,</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Farewell <HI>Matilda;</HI></L>
<L>Oh pardon me for heavens sake, now I find</L>
<L>Thy soul is Christall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Remember to the King</L>
<L>Good Madam my great sorrows; and forget not</L>
<L><PB REF="13"/>
To tell him this, that woman in whose heart</L>
<L>Vertue and honour stand a paire of Centinels;</L>
<L>The Sea may sooner flame, fire admit frost,</L>
<L>E're such a woman fall from heaven: Oh she,</L>
<L>Who as a regular star, keeps vertues speare,</L>
<L>Shews like a Pearl hung in an Angel<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> eare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou noble soul of goodnesse.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE>A Chaire of state discover'd Tables and Chaires responcible, a Guard making a
lane: Enter between the<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, <HI>King John, Pandulph</HI> the Popes Legate, <HI>Chester
Oxford,</HI> and all the Kings Party: After them, <HI>Fitzwater, Richmond,
Leister,</HI> and <HI>Bruce;</HI> the <HI>King</HI> (holding the Crown) kneeling on the
left side of the Chaire, <HI>Pandulph</HI> possessing it.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lo in the sight of Prelates Peers,</L>
<L>Of Earth and Heaven, of all that heares</L>
<L>My words; I <HI>John Plantagaent,</HI></L>
<L>(VVith all submissive reverence,) set</L>
<L>My Crowne at the most sacred foot</L>
<L>Of Innocent the Third, unto't</L>
<L>I joyne my Kingdom<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, giue them free</L>
<L>Unto his pious clemencie:</L>
<L>And for the follies of my Raigne,</L>
<L>Heats of my youth, and the rough straine</L>
<L>Of riper years, my Rebellions, my high hand,</L>
<L>My six yeares Interdictien, and</L>
<L>A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l my mis-doings; I this, and those,</L>
<L>Submit to the Popes power to disclose.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have by times recracted, and your foot now</L>
<L>Beats out a certain path; in these Lords sights of I do</L>
<L>Produce the Letter, drawn Obligatory</L>
<L>From <HI>John</HI> of <HI>England</HI> to his Holinesse,</L>
<L>Peruse it sir, you are there oblig'd to pay,</L>
<L>(As yearly from this day Renting your Kingdoms)</L>
<L>To <HI>Innocent</HI> the Third, and to his Successors</L>
<L>A thousand marks <HI>per annum.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>It runnes so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, three hundred for <HI>Ireland,</HI> &amp; seven for <HI>England.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do not peruse it <HI>John,</HI> though thou and we</L>
<L>Have had some bickerings, yet let me counsell thee,</L>
<L>This is my Countries Cause.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="13"/>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>You, and your Country</L>
<L>Have cause in this Cause to rejoyce.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good, good, Sir <HI>Pandvlph,</HI></L>
<L>Though in our filiall love to our Mother Church,</L>
<L>By his Holinesse command, we stay'd from <HI>Hartford,</HI></L>
<L>Yet lets have fair play, do not wrong that mother,</L>
<L>Apparelling her comely holy face,</L>
<L>With a forehead full of frowns, pleited proceedings.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>You raile.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>I do not raile,</L>
<L>Although I hold and reverence the Chair,</L>
<L>(We had been at <HI>Hartford</HI> else, and not at <HI>London,</HI>)</L>
<L>Yet in a true breast we should nothing see,</L>
<L>But holy pure, unmixt simplicy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Give me the pen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you then signe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, you rough Sonnes of faction,</L>
<L>And hook your stubborn nostrils, this is Rubarb</L>
<L>To your smooth pallats: give me the pen to write.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do not write <HI>John.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do not prate fool.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>In sooth that write</L>
<L>Will wrong thee; Children and Fools tell truth,</L>
<L>Remember that.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>There was no way like this,</L>
<L>To beat a path out to your peace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ki.</SPEAKER>
<L>Right Reverend</L>
<STAGE><HI>Pand.</HI> proffers to descend.</STAGE>
<L>And holy Sir, receive to the Popes use,</L>
<L>His will, and your own charge: Sir, descend not,</L>
<L>But ere you re-invest me, hear me tell</L>
<L>A tale of sorrow, behold here these Lords,</L>
<L>Who had been now bruising the face of peace</L>
<L>With unkind buffets, but for <HI>VVinchester,</HI></L>
<L>Your strict compulsion, and their seeming fear</L>
<L>Of deserv'd interdiction; but oh spright,</L>
<L>No Devill deceives like th'houshold hypocrite,</L>
<L>These of my Court, with young <HI>Brace</HI> now insconc'd</L>
<L><PB REF="14"/>
At <HI>Hartford,</HI> whither it may hair brain'd <HI>Richmond</HI></L>
<L>hath retir'd his discontents.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>We misse our hopes else.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>These bandy faction with me, and with their drum<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>(Lew'd linguists to interpret their disloyalties)</L>
<L>Brave me i'th field, deform th' afflicted face</L>
<L>Of trembling <HI>England</HI> with foul bloody stain<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</L>
<L>Larums at hideous midnight, they break my sleeps,</L>
<L>Fill them with fearfull dreams, terrible startings,</L>
<L>And with the griefe of my unfriendly fears,</L>
<L>Force me to pierce my pillow with my tears.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Unnaturall cruellty,</L>
<L>Able to melt marble into compassionate tears.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ox.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dainty dissembler.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now may it please you—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace untill his holinesse command be sinished;</L>
<L>Ascend your now true Seat sir, and from the hand</L>
<STAGE>Pan. gives
John the Chair.</STAGE>
<L>Of my selfe <HI>Pandulph,</HI> Legate for the Pope,</L>
<L>Observing the due payments specified,)</L>
<L>Receive your Crown and Kingdoms; and with them</L>
<L>We here pronounce your absolute readmission</L>
<L>Into the Church, and from his holnesse</L>
<L>We re-invest you, with all Powers, Prerogatives,</L>
<L>Freedomes, Communities, (and in the strength of effecacy,)</L>
<L>That constantly adhears to lawfull Princes,</L>
<L>And an obedient Son unto the Church,</L>
<L>Long life to <HI>John</HI> of <HI>England, VVales</HI> and <HI>Ireland,</HI></L>
<L>The lawfull King!</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Florish.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leis.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am mad.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>So, so, now we must suffer</L>
<L>The Kingdoms ancient Liberties, Land, lives,</L>
<L>And all to run the course that he shall steere,</L>
<L>Good heaven that I were dead, what do I here.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>weeps.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>But i'le not asse-like bear my Countries wrongs,</L>
<L>Mine own at home, and like a Court Camelion,</L>
<L>Give thanks unto mine injurer: hear me King <HI>John.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall hear us sir first; we have been clouded</L>
<L><PB REF="14"/>
Six years, but like the Sun in his Meridian,</L>
<L>We now again are glorious; thus in briefe,</L>
<L><HI>Leister</HI> we require strong pledge for your loyalty;</L>
<L><HI>Bruce</HI> call your mad Son home from <HI>Hartford,</HI></L>
<L>Your Wife and Sonne shall better speed at <HI>Guilford,</HI></L>
<L>For <HI>Richmond</HI> in our re-assumed power.</L>
<L>We will proclaime him Traytor, and <HI>Fitzwater,</HI></L>
<L>Either give up <HI>Matilda</HI> for your faith, or heare</L>
<L>What we shall sentence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leis.</SPEAKER>
<L>We must stand then</L>
<L>What thunder you shall throw, perform with us,</L>
<L>We kisse your royall hands.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>If not, we stand</L>
<L>Rocks in our resoluton.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>D'ee heare them now sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, nay, let him hear me too then:</L>
<L>Lord Legate <HI>Pandulph;</HI> thus 'tis,</L>
<L>And thus you may informe his holinesse,</L>
<L>In a field cal'd running-<HI>Mead'</HI> twixt <HI>Staines</HI> and <HI>VVinsor,</HI></L>
<L>After some bloody noses on both sides,</L>
<L>I tell truth I; there the King and Barrons</L>
<L>Met for discussion of conceiv'd wrongs,</L>
<L>And indeed not misconceiv'd, our Houses, Honours,</L>
<L>Our Fathers freedomes, the Lands ancient Liberties</L>
<L>(Unjustly to encrease some private Cofers)</L>
<L>Felt daily Demunition, there to Covenants drawn,</L>
<L>(Bearing the name and sence of <HI>Magna Charta,</HI></L>
<L>Which many hundred years may be seen hereafter)</L>
<L>King <HI>John</HI> subscrib'd, we swore him fealty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Which fealty they deny'd, till our assoylment</L>
<L>Of our six years Interdiction, forcing us therefore</L>
<L>To seal unlawfull liberties.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Upon our honours,</L>
<L>They were but what Antiquity prov'd lawful.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ox.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh but my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tut, tut, Lord me no Lords,</L>
<L>He broak, we powted, I tell plain truth I,</L>
<L><PB REF="15"/>
Yet fell into no relapse of hostility,</L>
<L>But wot ye what, he casts a covetous eye,</L>
<L>Upon my Daughter, passionately pursues her,</L>
<L>There had been other pledges but our oathes else,</L>
<L>(For heaven knows thtm he had) and (amongst the rest)</L>
<L><HI>Matilda</HI> must be my pledge, for well he deem'd</L>
<L>They yielding their<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, shame would brand my denyall,</L>
<L>But catch craft, when we put truth to triall,</L>
<L>Kings should have shining souls, and white desires</L>
<L>Enflam'd with zeale, not parch'd by Paphian fires;</L>
<L>So shines the soul in which vertue doth shrowd,</L>
<L>Is a serene skie bespotted with no cloud,</L>
<L>But a Copper conscience whil'st the head wears Gold,</L>
<L>Is but a plain down-right untruth well told,</L>
<L>Come, come, I cannot fawn.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>But in the passion</L>
<L>Gf a Dog sir you can snarl; have you talk all your words?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have told truth I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then we will fall to deeds,</L>
<L><HI>Oxford</HI> command a Guard, and presently</L>
<L>Take them to'th Tower; we can now talk and do,</L>
<L>Away with them, and muzzel those fierce Mastiffes,</L>
<L>That durst leap at the face of Majestie,</L>
<L>And strike their killing fangs into honours heart;</L>
<L>Are they not gone? we shall be passionate</L>
<L>In your delay.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come <HI>Leister,</HI> let us wear</L>
<L>Our sufferings like Garland.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tempest nor death,</L>
<L>Could never ou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> do <HI>Leister,</HI> who dares dye</L>
<L>Laughing at times poyson'd integrity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz</SPEAKER>
<L>Now by my troth 'twas very nobly spoken,</L>
<L>Shall I turne tale; no, no, no, lets go,</L>
<L>But how things will be carried; ha! are these teares</L>
<L>Body of me? they are; Shall I go like a sheep</L>
<L>With this pair of Lyons; ha, ha, ha,</L>
<L>I do laugh now <HI>John,</HI> and i'le tell thee why,</L>
<L><PB REF="15" MS="y"/>
Th'art yet in thy green <HI>May,</HI> twenty seven summers</L>
<L>Set in our Kalends, but when forty Winters more</L>
<L>Shall roun'd thy forehead with a field of snow,</L>
<L>And when thy comely veins shall cease to flow,</L>
<L>When those majestick eyes shall float in rhumes,</L>
<L>When giant Nature her own selfe consumes,</L>
<L>When thy swift Pulses shall but slowly pant,</L>
<L>When thou art all a Volum of my want,</L>
<L>(That like a tale-sp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nt fire thou shalt s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nck,)</L>
<L>Then <HI>John</HI> upon this lesson thou wilt think<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>He dyes a happy old man, whose sweet youth</L>
<L>Was a continued sacrifice to truth;</L>
<L>I must weep now indeed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ki.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away with them.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Unto King <HI>John,</HI> the favour of his holinesse,</L>
<L>With peace and happinesse.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Which we return</L>
<L>With all filiall obedience—look up <HI>Oxford,</HI></L>
<L>The day breaks, and the Sun hath chaste the night</L>
<L>Out of our Hemispheare.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter a Gentleman.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ox.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your news sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Letters from the Queen sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Was the Earl <HI>Richmond</HI> there with any powers</L>
<L>E're your departure.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>K reads.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<L>No may it please your Majestie, we heard not of him,</L>
<L>But all on your part went fair and fortunate</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh <HI>Oxford</HI> now they have her, flie back like lightning,</L>
<L>Tell him this day wee'l meet them all at <HI>Barnet.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Gent.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ox</SPEAKER>
<L>But her Father and her friends imprisonment</L>
<L>May obdurate her hea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t, they dare not sure</L>
<L>On the great perill of a curse to fall</L>
<L>Into a Relapse now you are absolute.</L>
<L>Faith <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> trie smooth paths to your ends, to release them,</L>
<L>I hold the winningst way to captivate</L>
<L>Their duties, and <HI>Matilda</HI> to your wishes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good, do not kill me <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oy before our going</L>
<L>Instantly thou shalt flie with the Lords release,</L>
<L><PB REF="16"/>
We pine in our delayes, oh <HI>Cupid</HI> swiftly</L>
<L>Fly into <HI>Paphoes,</HI> and from thy Mothers shrine,</L>
<L>Catch but a nimble wanton flame, and cast it</L>
<L>Into the busie Kingdome of my heart,</L>
<L>That it may teach my tongue the art of victory,</L>
<L>And every year unto thy well-spent Quiver</L>
<L>I'le add a shaft, and call it <HI>Cupids</HI> love Dart;</L>
<L>Come <HI>Oxford,</HI> I tread methinks on aire,</L>
<L>Untill I read that Volum of sweet grace,</L>
<L>The well writ story of <HI>Matild<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'s</HI> face.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ox.</SPEAKER>
<L>She yeelds at last my life on't sir.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="3" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus 3. Scoena 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE>En<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>er <HI>Brand</HI> reading of a Letter.</STAGE>
<SP>
<P>WIll Brand, <HI>these are to certifie,</HI> That Fortune, Mistresses
of Changes, with my unluckie stars, hathrendred m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> a pri∣soner
to my most mortall Enemy young <HI>Bruce.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<P>That mad Tamberlaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Let.</SPEAKER>
<P>My entreaty is none of the noblest, but direct against my
blood, my desires, and my deservings.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh that I had a leg of that young <HI>Bruce,</HI> but minc'd
and butter'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Let.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am credibly possest, his Majestie hath into your custody
comm<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ited his Mother, and her young Sonne <HI>George,</HI> whereby you
have occasion cast into your hand to parallel their; sufferings with
my fortunes, not that I would have you banish humanity.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<P>He need never have writ that Bawds and Serjeants have
sav'd me the labour.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Let.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nor give to deep a wound to Conscience.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Another labour sav'd too,</L>
<L>Usurers do it daily</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Let.</SPEAKER>
<P>But as I let you understand how I am here accommodated,
so shape the duty of a Servant to parallel in their persons, your vil∣lified
Mr <HI>Ralph Chester.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="16"/>
<SPEAKER>Bran.</SPEAKER>
<P>Brave Lord, the Laddar of my fortunes, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
suffer on that side, and for humanities sake, and thred-b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
conscience (a couple of cousin-<HI>Germans,</HI> that thrice a weeke
know not where to get a supper;) shall the friends of him that
stands Lord of thy fortunes, and thy profest foe, fare well
here; now I talk of fare, I receiv'd this Letter yesterday, and
since they have uei<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r eaten bit, nor drunk drop, nor by these
ten stealers shall not, till I heare againe from my Lord—:
Come o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lt madam Mother, and your youg prating brat—they
do look hungry already.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Lady <HI>and</HI> Boy.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<L>What would our unkind Jaylor?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sure Mother Mr. <HI>Brand</HI> hath brought us v<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ctuals.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<L>No sirrah, I come to tell you to day i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> fasting day.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<L>Two dayes together,</L>
<L>Good Mr. <HI>Brand,</HI> 'tis not mine own want beggs,</L>
<L>But my poor Boyes; I have held him pretty pastime,</L>
<L>To have him yet forget that wild woolf hunger,</L>
<L>And still the harmlesse soul would point each period</L>
<L>Of his sport, erying Mother give me bread.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<L>She has a winning way,</L>
<L>Her carriage and her person are both exquisite:</L>
<L>Fai<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> tell me Madam, what would you give for some victuals</L>
<L>To give your Son?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<L>Any thing, set thou the price thou shalt have Gold.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<L>And truly sir, if you'l but give me a Cake,</L>
<L>Or a Capons legge, when I am a man,</L>
<L>I'le give you twenty shillings to buy your Boy fine things.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you dare lye with me,</L>
<L>You and your Sonne shall both have sustenance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hearken good heaven, what saies the man?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<L>He would Ile with you Mother,</L>
<L>But then when I am a bed too, there</L>
<L>Will be no room for my, Father.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be as plain and briefe as I was, dare yee do'<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<L>No thou bad man, I dare no<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<L>No body shall see<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> by this hand,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou lyest thou feind, shouldst thou <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Ca<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>e do'<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</L>
<L><PB REF="17"/>
The Towers would tremble, and turn Intelligencers</L>
<L>To all the passengers; the walls would shudder,</L>
<L>The E<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cutchions, Streamers, Baune<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> s, all the Reliques</L>
<L>Of fame and honour, would fall down, to see</L>
<L>Honour and Fame so wounded.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<L>See! I am asham'd to hear you,</L>
<L>If such sinnes could not be done without being seen,</L>
<L>Informers would have a fine trade on't, a Parators place</L>
<L>Would counvaile five Serjeants; ha, ha, seen kither;</L>
<L>Why there would not be sheets en ugh in the Land</L>
<L>For the penitent, and innocent Beadles enough to correct the</L>
<L>Guilty; Come, come, we'l do't i'<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h dark then,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<L>In he dark said'st thou?</L>
<L>Oh in the deepest darknesse, the white Angels</L>
<L>Will stare upon thee, and with flaming eyes.</L>
<L>Will make make the room appear to thy wild conscience,</L>
<L>Twice lighter then the Sunne:</L>
<L>'Tis a foul Devil that insinuates to thee,</L>
<L>The sower sweetnesse of a d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>uded minute;</L>
<L>He has borrowed a white robe, pluck it off from him,</L>
<L>And thou wilt see him a black hideous monster,</L>
<L>How with a slavish look he will creep from thee,</L>
<L>Displeas'd that thou art falne again in love,</L>
<L>With holy goodnesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<L>How my Conscience wambles.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do, do, good sir, think of it,</L>
<L>It will make you give's some bread.</L>
<L>And then you'l be a very honest man,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have heard you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<L>And with a thirsty soul I hope.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, as Usurers heare Sermons, more for novelty then
integrity, I love good words when I pay nothing for <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>;
what do you see in me that I should appear unworthy of your
grant<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<L>Because in that request,</L>
<L>Thou appear'st to me as ugly as a Toad.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Toad <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="17"/>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, and a Frog to if you go to that,</L>
<L>Doe not cry Mother.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<L>Get you both in, by this victorious sword,</L>
<L>And by the horrid odious comparison,</L>
<L>(for such a one first <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>u e made comparisons odious)</L>
<L>Ye get not a bit this seven dayes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>By that time</L>
<L>My Boy and I shall make a pair of happy ones</L>
<L>In youder glorious Kingdom; tell me <HI>George,</HI></L>
<L>Shall this bad man abnse thy Fathers bed?</L>
<L>Or shall we fast yet longer?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<L>The boy will consent I warrant you,</L>
<L>The Pages have instructed him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeed I am very hungry:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did I not tell you so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<L>But rather then this Goat shall lie in my fathers place,</L>
<L>Indeed <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'le fast this seven years.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ah noble boy,</L>
<L>Sweet plant of goodnesse, thou hast prov'd it true,</L>
<L>Vertue will wish the good it cannot do.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<L>Aterribly ugly Toad.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> King, Queen, <HI>and</HI> Oxford.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ox.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good sir ye must be patient.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Patient,</L>
<L>Bitternesse dwels with me: if I do not put him</L>
<L>To an eternall patience, that shall dare</L>
<L>To witch me into that dull fit of fools;</L>
<L><HI>Matilda</HI> won and lost<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good sir</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away;</L>
<L>Struggle not with the tempest of my blood,</L>
<L>That will undo th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Richmond</HI> Lyon like,</L>
<L>(After we sent our Letter with the Foree<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>The Barrous had prepar'd,) clouded our day,</L>
<L><PB REF="18"/>
And made our fortunes his.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ches.</SPEAKER>
<L>They <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>out o'th Tower to,</L>
<L><HI>Fitzwater Bruce,</HI> and <HI>Leister,</HI> with fresh powers,</L>
<L>Are not a league hence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Lyon <HI>Richmond,</HI> a Hare had he met with any</L>
<L>But field Mice, Rats, Run-awayes, and Weezles,</L>
<L>Frighted even with the waving of a Flag,</L>
<L>They would have call'd<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> scar-crow stufi'd with straw,</L>
<L>And bound upon a ten groats Irish Garron,</L>
<L>The Glorious <HI>Richmond</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pon his firie Steed;</L>
<L>Oh there is nothing certaine but our sorrows,</L>
<L>Our borrow'd blisse is but the shuttl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>-cock</L>
<L>Of a dayes pastime.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have pastim'd her, if tearing be a pastime,</L>
<L>Let that comfort you,</L>
<L>I have torne her almost to d: ath.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Matilda.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>And would you have it comfort me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know it does, call but up your Troops</L>
<L>Brayely again, recover her, and read</L>
<L>Upon her face my fury.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh ye cruell one,</L>
<L>Crueller then the flame that turn'd to Clnders</L>
<L>The fair <HI>Ephesian</HI> Temple; wilde as a Woolf,</L>
<L>The Bear is not so bloody, teare her hairs,</L>
<L>Which when they took their <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>astime with the winds,</L>
<L>Would charm the astonish'd gazer; tear that face,</L>
<L>Lovely as is the morning in whose eyes</L>
<L>Stands writ the history of her heart, intioing</L>
<L>The ravish'd Reader to runne on, 'pon whose eye lids</L>
<L>Discretion dwels, which when a wilde thought</L>
<L>Would at those Casements like a Theefe steale in,</L>
<L>Playes her heart's noble friend, and shuts out sin.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>O why then sir, if she be such a volum</L>
<L>Of white unvanquish'd <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> would you stain.</L>
<L>And blot the sair leaves with your <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> desir<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L><PB REF="18"/>
Ghaste, frostie bosomes, brook no lust-born fires.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>She has put me to my sophistry.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>I knew I was made</L>
<L>Your staie for her obtaining.</L>
<L>Oh why</L>
<L>Raise you so high a Piramis to her praise,</L>
<L>And prostrate your own vertue? if she be</L>
<L>Such a Book of goodnesse (with bad desires)</L>
<L>Why do you read her? He no truth intends,</L>
<L>Seeks to corrupt that Text which he commends,</L>
<L>Good sir consider it.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Hubert.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, I will think on'<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, and you will have done.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now is the time my Lord,</L>
<L>If e're you would be fortunate in your desires,</L>
<L><HI>Richmond,</HI> young <HI>Bruce, Matilda,</HI></L>
<L>(With the Earl of <HI>Chester</HI> prisoner,) <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>and a slight convoy</L>
<L>But of some threescore Horse, and two hundred Archer<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Are now i'th valley crossing of the County,</L>
<L>'Tis thought for <HI>Essex.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where are their main Forces?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Inscon'st in <HI>Hartford</HI> Castle, our Forces yet</L>
<L>Not so diminish'd, or in rout for want</L>
<L>Of their lost Generall, but if you please,</L>
<L>We dare with hope assail them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will be Generall,</L>
<L>Order the Powers you have for present on-set.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, you said you would consider.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am considering bravely how to charge</L>
<L>The Foe just in the face: <HI>Matilda</HI> I am now thy Souldier,</L>
<L>Friend of my heart, the King himselfe comes for thee,</L>
<L>Who shall in this dayes doings amply prove,</L>
<L>Honour takes fire from the flame of love.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good fortune on our side sir.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt. Manet Queen.
A Charge afar off.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hear not that prayer</L>
<L>Good heaven, oh tempt not vertue to adorn</L>
<L>A foul Cause with fair fortunes: Hark, hark, they meet,</L>
<L>And now pell mell the angry Lords do list</L>
<L><PB REF="19"/>
Unnaturall swords, good heaven keep safe the King,</L>
<L>But let his Cause miscarry; I w ll not stay</L>
<L>To see him so pursue those wild desires,</L>
<L>Which cannot sure end well; i'le to the Lords</L>
<L>So near at hand, and with <HI>Matilda's</HI> Father,</L>
<L>Accommodate my griefs, and let there be</L>
<L>Her feares, my tears, the Kings infirmity.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> King, Oxford, <HI>and</HI> Matilda.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Oxford,</HI> sh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'s now the Kings.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most miserable Maid.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most excellent <HI>Matilda</HI> all are thy friends,</L>
<L>Imperious love fat on my l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ance just then,</L>
<L>When on the pan<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ing brest of daring <HI>Richmond.</HI></L>
<L>(Who like a me<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ancholly sullen Cloud,</L>
<L>Eclips'd thy Chariot) thou didst see me print</L>
<L>My re<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>lesse passion: <HI>Oxford</HI> keep my happinesse,</L>
<L>Just with that care thou wouldst oreserve that pair</L>
<L>Of pr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>c ous things, thine eye; <HI>Chesters</HI> ingag'd</L>
<L>Deep in the Cha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e, and we must te<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ch him off;</L>
<L>Pardon me honour that I plac<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d love first,</L>
<L>My doings now are thine.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ox.</SPEAKER>
<L>Keep near the King, Gentlemen,</L>
<L>His unbounded spirit may loose him el<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e; good Madam</L>
<L>Do not lament so, though your friends are <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>catter'd,</L>
<L>Y'are in a spheare of happinesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh that great power,</L>
<L>That many times out of this toy I hath taken me,</L>
<L>Deliver me again, because again,</L>
<L>Vertue hath made me miserabl.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ent. <HI>young</HI> Bruce.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh that necessity</L>
<L>Should force us unto flight, base flight, repugnant</L>
<L>To man and honour. Ha! nappy flight now,</L>
<L>That brought me this way.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cozen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Oxford,</HI> either give back</L>
<L><PB REF="19"/>
That pure unspotted Dove, from the killing Tallon</L>
<L>Of the forgetfull King, or thou or I</L>
<L>Must never see him more. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ox.</SPEAKER>
<L>That to our fortunes,</L>
<L>I must not faile the King sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must not faile then</L>
<STAGE>Enter Richmond.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Fight, Oxford falls!</STAGE>
<L>To get her as I can sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rich.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are scatter'd now</L>
<L>Paste making head againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>But I have made shift to get my Cuz agen sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rich.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let us not stay now to expostulate, Necessity</L>
<L>Directs us to our friends not a league distant,</L>
<L>If we not fly we are lost.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good Cuz lets flie,</L>
<L>Tis no difgrace to obey necessity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh I could stamp and tear that hagge necessity,</L>
<L>Bitter necessity, thou scourge of things</L>
<L>That forces Lyons to wear Swallows wings.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exe. Manet Ox.
to him enter King,
Chester,
&amp; others.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ches.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have plaid the Souldier sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Souldier <HI>Chester;</HI> I am so light with joy,</L>
<L>I could do any thing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ches.</SPEAKER>
<L>Troth sir would it might please you then to grace</L>
<L>Me with the President-ship of <HI>Picardy,</HI></L>
<L>Falne in this last Rebellion from the Lord</L>
<L><HI>Bruce</HI> un<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o your Crown.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis thine as certaine</L>
<L>As <HI>Matilda</HI> is the Kings: Oh <HI>Chester,</HI> now <HI>Matilda</HI></L>
<L>Is in the Kings power.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ox.</SPEAKER>
<L>No sir, she is in heavens.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ches.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who's this, <HI>Oxford,</HI> lets help to raise him up.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>What saist thou man? <HI>Matilda,</HI> where is <HI>Matilda?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ox.</SPEAKER>
<L>Young <HI>Bruce</HI> in his flight happening upon this way</L>
<L>For her recovery gave me fierce assault;</L>
<L>I did stand for you sir as much as man could,</L>
<L>Till my mis-fortune found me, then I fell;</L>
<L>To him eame <HI>Richmond,</HI> and with all speed possible</L>
<L>They have carried her to'th Lords on tother side the h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ath.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="20"/>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh villaine, villaine<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Suppose he had cut thy hear<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> strings, hadst thou cast<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Thy dying eye upon <HI>Matilda's</HI> face?</L>
<L>She would have shot another spirit into thee,</L>
<L>More daring then the first, at least more fortunate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ches.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let him be convey'd to'ch Town and drest,</L>
<L>Our best course is now to with-draw, the Lords</L>
<L>Are strong, and may give us dangerous chase else.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>What are our hopes</L>
<L>Like Garlands, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pon afflictions forehead worn,</L>
<L>Kist in the morning, and at evening torne.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.
A Table and Chaires set out.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Fitzwater, <HI>Old</HI> Bruce, <HI>young</HI> Bruce, Richmond,
<HI>and</HI> Leister.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>The day is then the Kings.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rich.</SPEAKER>
<L>White victory</L>
<L>Clapt on her silver wings, with a sullen face,</L>
<L>Took leave of us, and pitched upon his Tent,</L>
<L>Where she sat smiling, while necessity.</L>
<L>Enforced our flight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh that witch Necessity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, well, away with the witch,</L>
<L>Tis well you brought <HI>Matilda</HI> off; come, come,</L>
<STAGE>Sit to
Council.</STAGE>
<L>Aud brther <HI>Bruce</HI> you have a Wife and Sonne</L>
<L>Unjustly detayn'd from you, I am injur'd,</L>
<L>I pray set you our feet into the path</L>
<L>Of our proceedings.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lets with our powers</L>
<L>Raze <HI>Winsor</HI> walls.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now you are i'th field straight,</L>
<L>Give old men leave; you would raze! what would you raze<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Your reputation with your rash proceedings;</L>
<L>Come, come, hear your Father.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why let him speak them,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>First let us take up our affronts in order,</L>
<L>And fix by ours, the Generalls grievances,</L>
<L>The crying groans of <HI>England,</HI> whose blubberd cheeks</L>
<L><PB REF="20"/>
Are stiffe with tears, to see their privildedges</L>
<L>Daily impair'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rich.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's to be done?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let's send to the <HI>French</HI> King,</L>
<L>Proffer him our assistance, to trans-fer</L>
<L>The Crown from <HI>John</HI> to him, if at such a day</L>
<L>He will put over a strong Navie Royall,</L>
<L>With an Army for the attempt, with which (our Forces</L>
<L>Making one body) both at at Sea and Land,</L>
<L>We bid fair for our freedoms.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>I do not like it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Eru.</SPEAKER>
<L>S'foot, you will like nothing;</L>
<L>Let us be ring'd and nooz'd,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Besides, being assoil'd of his six years Interdiction,</L>
<L>Those that before fled from him as a Leaper,</L>
<L>Will now flock to him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rich.</SPEAKER>
<L>They begin already,</L>
<L>(Although we seek (with our own) their good,) to censure</L>
<L>And call hostility plain faction.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leis.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is my resolve, I say there is no way</L>
<L>To fix our freedomes, but to call in <HI>Philip</HI></L>
<L>And make him King.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Richmend.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Om.</SPEAKER>
<L>So think we all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>I but I think not so,</L>
<L>Though y'are all wise for <HI>Philip,</HI> he'l be a gainer,</L>
<L>But what will you get by't? They run on Rocks and shelves,</L>
<L>Can can counsell others, not secure themselves.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>We must and will do something.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>You will send to <HI>Philip,</HI></L>
<L>Instruct him to proceed, it may be furnish</L>
<L>His Navie with our Pilots, he lands, we proffer</L>
<L>Change, <HI>John</HI> for <HI>Philip;</HI> oh can you think,</L>
<L>That we can undergo a heavier stroke</L>
<L>From a Naturall, then from a Forreigne yoak;</L>
<L>Go to, go to, who in no estate can rest,</L>
<L>They may change oft, but seldome comes the best.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ol. Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am diverted.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="21"/>
<SPEAKER>Leis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Which way would you steer then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>By the same Compasse, but not upon this parallel,</L>
<L>I do not like the line; but this wee'l do,</L>
<L>Wee'l send for <HI>Lewis, Philips</HI> Sonne the Dolphine,</L>
<L>And to him (seemingly) preter the proffer,</L>
<L>A Crown will fire him; may be he shall land,</L>
<L>But with no more Force then we please; and it may be</L>
<L>He shall take a fisher Town, for every Nation</L>
<L>Can take away their trading as the time goes,</L>
<L>Our m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ine Force being ready, we will hover</L>
<L>'Twixt <HI>John</HI> and <HI>Lewis;</HI> if <HI>John</HI> deny an oath</L>
<L>To redresse our griefes, and become regular</L>
<L>And Hostage for the keeping it, we joyne</L>
<L>With the <HI>French</HI> and fright him further; If he consent,</L>
<L>We fall on his part then, expulse <HI>Lewis,</HI></L>
<L>And send him to the Seas again; the Dolphine</L>
<L>Is young and may be wrought on, but old <HI>Philip</HI></L>
<L>Is dangerously politick, with foot ashore,</L>
<L>Hee'l brook no jugling, both ease, and safety</L>
<L>We work on Willowes, but when we strike at Oaks,</L>
<L>We sweat, and sometimes hurt with our own strokes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Om.</SPEAKER>
<L>It shall be thus effected.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leis.</SPEAKER>
<L>But let report divulge his Landing,</L>
<L>With more eminent danger then we will let him practise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>For this time</L>
<STAGE>Ent. Queen, Matilda &amp; Ladies.</STAGE>
<L>Rise then; See the Queen and Ladies,</L>
<L>Good Madam cast off sadnesse,</L>
<L><HI>Matilda</HI> we are all here i'th City safe;</L>
<L>The very hearts o'th Citizens (men injur'd</L>
<L>In their priviledges as we are) they are ours,</L>
<L>What should we fear then?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Richmond.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are all such friends,</L>
<L>I am poor in my well-meaning thankfuln̄esse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rich.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Barge with divers youthfull Citizens,</L>
<L>Apparell'd rich like Masquers, is now land'd</L>
<L>Upon the Stairs, hearing the Queen was here,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ithall this meeting of their noble friends,</L>
<L><PB REF="21"/>
Proffer their loves and duties to conclude</L>
<L>And grace the evening with their Revels.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>In the Hall wee'l meet them. Did not I tell you</L>
<L>These Citizens were noble lads our friends?</L>
<L>Waite on the Ladies Lords, I am here your Graces servant,</L>
<L>By my troth I thank'em, they will crown our feast,</L>
<L>And credite me, having such a princely guest.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Loud Musick.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter at one doore <HI>Fitzwater,</HI> old <HI>Bruce,</HI> young <HI>Bruce,
Leister, Matilda</HI> and <HI>Ladies;</HI> at the other doore,
the <HI>King, Chester, Oxford, Masquers.</HI></STAGE>
<STAGE>A Dance.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now by my troth they are gallants,</L>
<L>Citizens said you; now I remember to,</L>
<L>Ye do go gallant in your Shops, no wonder then,</L>
<L>If in Masques you cut it. I remember Gentlemen,</L>
<L>Your Fathers wore a king of comely habite,</L>
<L>Comely, because it wel became the reverend name of Citizens,</L>
<L>But now let a Knight walk with you in your shops,</L>
<L>(And I commend you for't, ye keep the fashion)</L>
<L>We know not which is which—; how my tongue ranges,</L>
<L>And night grows old, mad times, must have mad changes;</L>
<L>Come, come, a Hall, a hall.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>The Masquers take the Ladies,
and fall to the Dance.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beleeve me you have done well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pox a' these Cats guts, how they squeak.</L>
<L>Methinks a rattling sheep-skin lustily boxt,</L>
<L>Would thunder brave amongst them.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>One of the Torch bearers
takes <HI>Matilda.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>I can dance no more indeed sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am deceiv'd if that fellow did not carry</L>
<L>A Torch e'n now;</L>
<L>Will you shame the Gentleman?</L>
<L>Dance when I bid you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh me, that graspe was like the Kings.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O. Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dance Cuz.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>In good deed dance,</L>
<L>Or you will make me angry.</L>
<STAGE>The K. pulls her violently.</STAGE>
<L>Body of me, that's too much for a Torch-bearer,</L>
<L><PB REF="22"/>
You sir Jack, sir Jack, she is no whit-leather,</L>
<L>She will not stretch I assure you, if you come hither</L>
<L>For love so 'tis.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>For love.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>But if you and your Company,</L>
<L>Put on forgetfull rudenesse, pray take your <HI>Cupid</HI> yonder,</L>
<L>Your thing of feathers, and your Barge stands ready</L>
<L>To bear ye all aboard the ship of Fools,</L>
<L>I am plain <HI>Robin</HI>—passion of me!</L>
<L>Look if he do not threaten me; I will see thee,</L>
<L>Wert thou King <HI>John</HI> himselfe.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Pulls off his Vizard.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Om.</SPEAKER>
<L>The King!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh which way shall I flie?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would not leave so sweet a chaste companion.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Qu. Mat. Rich, and Ladies. In the bussle, <HI>Fitzwater</HI>
drops one of his Gloves, <HI>Hubert</HI> takes it up, and goes after the Ladies.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hub.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's this, one of her Fathers Gloves?</L>
<L>This shall be drawn upon the luckie hand of a thriving plot.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Behold thy King, thine <HI>Bruce,</HI> one of the Fathers</L>
<L>Of these retir'd factions; <HI>Richmond,</HI> the King,</L>
<L>And thine <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ough <HI>Leister;</HI> is this still your nest</L>
<L>Wherein to hatch another Scorpions Egge,</L>
<L>To sting the afflicted bosome of your Country,</L>
<L>To bruise her sides with the earth-wounding hoofes</L>
<L>Of War-apparell'd Horses, whose dreadful neighings</L>
<L>May fright her pale face to a bloody blush,</L>
<L>And again make her groane.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your pardon sir,</L>
<L>By my good Sword I knew ye not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ches.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, if you had,</L>
<L>Your dangerous Brother <HI>Bruce</HI> and you, had laid</L>
<L>Some plot for his sacred person; then pleaded ignorance,</L>
<L>That ye took him as he seem'd, a sawcy stranger.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Chester,</HI> Thou art not noble in thy c<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nsure,</L>
<L>And sawn 'st thy selfe into the abus'd favour</L>
<L>Of the to-credulous King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ches.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh temptation, what a Devill art thou;</L>
<L>Now by my blood young man, you court my spleen</L>
<L>In a vain glorious shape; <HI>Chester</HI> fawne,</L>
<L>Just heaven forbid it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="22"/>
<SPEAKER>Y. Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>An Axe upon your neck, che just heavens give you<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>And that in heaven were justice—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ol. Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sonne, y'are too full of choller.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Choller, Halter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>By the masse that's neer the choller.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Upon your lives no more, the King is here;</L>
<L><HI>Fitzwater,</HI> I did not come to quarrell with thee,</L>
<L>I would have such a good man ever neer me,</L>
<L>And for a florish to the rest (of whom</L>
<L>As of old <HI>Bruce</HI> we have) we will require strict pledges, and</L>
<L><HI>Fitzwater</HI> let thy Daughter live at Court, she shall be kept.</L>
<L>I'th custody of the Queen, but as no pledge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Queen is gracioue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, to their ruines leave these turbulent Lords.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>But suppose the Queen should ride abroad to hunt,</L>
<L>And leave <HI>Matilda</HI> solitary at home,</L>
<L>I think the King would come and comfort her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ki.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am of thy mind, I think he would.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would he so?— I would have no one hear.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Takes
the K. aside,</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>They cannot man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray tell the King, ile keep my Girle at home,</L>
<L>And comfort her my selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>You will.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>John, John,</HI> now I speak out;</L>
<L>You made your Masque for this, a Masque indeed,</L>
<L>And we-aday! that it should prove a Cover</L>
<L>For such a night of Tempests, such wilde affections,</L>
<L>Such an ill-favour'd night.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Hubert.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Hubert,</HI> is't done?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Past expectation, I have better'd your plot,</L>
<L>And got the Queene too,</L>
<L>And will bring them early in the morning to'th Court.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Have the Torch-bearers given fire to the plot?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hub.</SPEAKER>
<L>They mixt with oppertunity.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Richmond.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>I do not like this whispering,</L>
<L>Where are the Ladies and <HI>Matilda?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rich.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Ladies are at the further side the Castle,</L>
<L><PB REF="23"/>
But by a Glove you sent by a Gentleman,</L>
<L>That said he serv'd Earle <HI>Leister,</HI> that with him</L>
<L>She and the Queene should flie for safety whither</L>
<L>You had directed him, glad of any scare,</L>
<L>They took a Barge, another leapt in after them,</L>
<L>But whom he was I know not.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ol. Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sent you a Glove.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Glove indeed I misse, but I sent none.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leis.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is a Riddle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will play <HI>Oedipus,</HI> and expound it for you,</L>
<L>As <HI>Hubert</HI> has infus'd; you drop'd your Glove,</L>
<L>Ingenius <HI>Hubert</HI> found it, and (though we</L>
<L>Had directed otherwise,) he employ'd a Gentleman</L>
<L>Of our own Chamber, one unknown to <HI>Matilda,</HI></L>
<L>To bring it as your close intellige ce</L>
<L>For her flight with him; he that leapt into 'th Barge,</L>
<L>As they put of, was <HI>Oxford,</HI> now we have her</L>
<L>Never again to lose her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leis.</SPEAKER>
<L>By my vext blood</L>
<L>King <HI>John,</HI> this is not honourable.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Richmond.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rich.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are betray'd,</L>
<L>All that bore Torches in the Masque to night,</L>
<L>Were of the Guard, who upon a receiv'd watch-word,</L>
<L>Fell to their Arms, beat down all oppos'd them,</L>
<L>And are shaping their course this way.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lets meet'em,</L>
<L>We have an injur'd patience, came death in whirle-winds,</L>
<L>Ile be the first shall front him; to thy prayers <HI>John,</HI></L>
<L>Pray heartily, that thy friends fatall points</L>
<L>May pierce these hearts; for if they misse 'tshall prove</L>
<L>The bloodi st beauty story ever told</L>
<L>To fright the Readers souls; a purple cloud</L>
<L>Shall shaddow <HI>England,</HI> the whole Land shall <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ele,</L>
<L>The Center gr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s, thy very Crown shall stand</L>
<L>Trembling upon thy Temples, till it fall</L>
<L>A Mourner at thy fames black funerall.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh noble Nephew.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Barrons.</STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="23"/>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, ha, ha, let 'em rave on; Ingenious <HI>Hubert<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI></L>
<L>That couldst so swifty apprehend a smooth</L>
<L>Path to'th possession of <HI>Matilda!</HI></L>
<L>Quit <HI>Oxford</HI> from her charge; unto thy care</L>
<L>The King commends the Mistresse of his heart,</L>
<L>I'th morning let me see her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>She shall waite upon you sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ches.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Barrons threaten high sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let them burst.</L>
<L>Come Gentlemen, to'th Barge, and so to'th Court,</L>
<L>To clip our wishes, perills appear sport.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="4" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus 4. Scoena 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Brand.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bran.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>I</HI> Wonder how my pair of Prisoners fadge?</L>
<L>I am something dogged too a to'ther side,</L>
<L>That thus long have not seen them, nor have they eate<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>I <HI>am</HI> sure since they came in; in yon Madams eye</L>
<L>I am as ugly as a Toad, I will see her,</L>
<L>And contemn her—, you and your brat come out,</L>
<STAGE>Ent. Lady
and Boy.</STAGE>
<L>Heres meat, I am sure you are hungry.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<L>O Mother, will you be sick now?</L>
<L>Mr. <HI>Boand</HI> hath brought us meat.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh on my knee sir</L>
<L>I thank you, not for my want, for I feel</L>
<L>Nature almost quite vanquish'd; but for my Sonne;</L>
<L>He may live long to thank you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Give but my Mother</L>
<L>A little piece of bread, and if I live,</L>
<L>(as yet I may do, if you can be mercifull)</L>
<L>I will tell my Father such good things of you,</L>
<L>He shall return your kindnesse treble back</L>
<L>To your honest bosome; Oh Mother for some bread.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Era.</SPEAKER>
<L>Some bread?</L>
<L><PB REF="24"/>
Why to have an honest bosome (as the world goes)</L>
<L>Is the next way to want bread; i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> faith tell me,</L>
<L>How have you past the time you wanted Victu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>Very hardly,</L>
<L>And still the poor Boy sighin<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, would say, Mother</L>
<L>You look very hungry, I did think straight how ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d</L>
<L>Your heart was, then we both did fall a weeping,</L>
<L>Cling'd our lean armes about each others neck,</L>
<L>And sat a pair of mou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<L>Delicate pastime, Toads love no other;</L>
<L>Look yee, here is bread.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh if you be a good man, give me but a bit</L>
<L>To give my Mother, poor soul look how she looks!</L>
<L>Indeed she's very hungry.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, so is my Dogge,</L>
<STAGE>Puts it up again.</STAGE>
<L>I must keep this for his breakfast.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<L>Give but my boy one bi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</L>
<L>And the Saints sure will look how good you are,</L>
<L>They will be glad to see you charitable,</L>
<L>And call it excellent compassion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, cunning from a Toad 'twill p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>yson him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<L>It will not sir, indeed I am so hungry,</L>
<L>I could eat Rats or Mice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your to'ther hair braine,</L>
<L>Your wilde mad Sonne, retaines my Lord a Prisoner,</L>
<L>Uses him basely, and you must suffer for't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>Give me but Paper, Pen and Inck, i'le wrile,</L>
<L>And charge him to fall down, and li<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>k the dust.</L>
<L>Thy Lord shall set his foot on, I will conjure him:</L>
<L>And woe away his wildnesse by the groars</L>
<L>I su<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>fer'd for him, I'le threaten his denyall</L>
<L>With a Mothers family-consounding curse:</L>
<L>This I will do, or any thing that may</L>
<L>But purchase my poor Boy one bit of bread.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<L>No.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<L>O harder then the Rocks, more mercilesse</L>
<L>Then the wilde evening Woolf.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>falls.</STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="24"/>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mother do not die,</L>
<L>For heavens sake helpe my Mother; look up</L>
<L>And ye shall see me dance, and then the Gentleman</L>
<L>Will sure bestow a piece of bread upon us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<L>Look here thou Iron-hearted man. upon</L>
<L>A palre of piercing miseries.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Scoene of mirth;</L>
<L>I am all hard, the heat of lust which stood</L>
<L>To clip revenge, we stem a stream of blood.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<L>How do ye Mother?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<L>How doth my Boy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Very sick indeed; but I warrant you are more hungry</L>
<L>Then I a great deale, are you not?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh no,</L>
<L>Thou art weake, and famine plaies the Tyrant with thee;</L>
<L>Look here my boy, bite on thy Mothers arme,</L>
<L>The blood will nourish thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will your blood nourish me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, yes, I pre<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hee try.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why should not mine then nourish you? 'tis the same;</L>
<L>Good Mother eat my arme, bite but a bite,</L>
<L>Truly I shall hurt you if I bite yours,</L>
<L>I warrant you'l be better presently.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall my Sonne, and so shalt thou, come neere me,</L>
<L>Let us go hand in hand to Heaven.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh mother, something pinch'd my very heart,</L>
<L>And I shall die, my dear, dear mother.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>Art thou gone my Sonne?</L>
<L>My soule shall overtake thee: oh friendly death</L>
<L>That gav'st that gripe, sure when thou kill'st the guilty,</L>
<L>Frowns curle thy angry forehead; but when thou steal'st</L>
<L>Towards innocence, (their pale fears to beguile)</L>
<STAGE>Enter Brand
reading
a Letter.</STAGE>
<L>Thou deck'st thy lean face with a lovely smile.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Dyes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord recover'd by the valiant King!</L>
<L>In all his battels he is fortunate,</L>
<L>And now tdey shall have meate; ha! meat said I?</L>
<L>I have made them worms meat;</L>
<L><PB REF="25"/>
Oh what a talking is within me! if I stay,</L>
<L>The building sure will crush me, i'le ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> to'<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h Court,</L>
<L>My Lord here intimates the Kings observance of me,</L>
<L>I must hence; oh gnilt, thou draw'st deaths image horrid,</L>
<L>When we begin to like our ills, how sweet a face hath sin!</L>
<L>Which but past by, a cheater she appears,</L>
<L>Joyes are her promise, but she paies us fears.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Hubert, Queen, and Matilda, a Gentleman.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your care in the conveyance of <HI>Matilda</HI></L>
<L>To this appoited place, the King shall recompence,</L>
<L>With-draw your selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gent.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Matilda,</HI> where's that spirit that kept thy vertue</L>
<L>Valiant and bold<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>If vertue so ill pay us,</L>
<L>Who would be vertuous?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vertue! pale poverty</L>
<L>Reproach, disaster, shame sits on her forehead,</L>
<L>Despisings fill her sleep<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, ill <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></L>
<L>Meet her at every turne, tears are her triumphs,</L>
<L>Her drink affliction, Calumny attends her,</L>
<L>The unclean tongue of slaunder daily licks her</L>
<L>Out of her fashion; but if you be Kings <HI>Johns</HI> friend—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh strong temptation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Matilda—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hub.</SPEAKER>
<L>You may like</L>
<L>A nimble wind, play on the ruslling bosome</L>
<L>Of that phantastick wood, the world; your sleeps a paradice</L>
<L>hung round with glittering dreames, then your dissemblings</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> call'd dev<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tions, your rigged <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> hypocrisie</L>
<L>Religions holy heats, mirth dee<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> the Court d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s,</L>
<L>The wanton minutes glide just like a streame,</L>
<L>That clips the bosome of a wealthy meade,</L>
<L>Till't get it great with child, a sweet green blassing.</L>
<L>Consider, 'tis the King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="25"/>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, I, the King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Trust not this tempter, lusts irreligious linguist,</L>
<L>Remember vertue is a holy flame,</L>
<L>A sacred inclination of the soul</L>
<L>To all things honest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>I can resist no longer,</L>
<L>Oh <HI>Hubert,</HI> you are a victorious tempter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can this be possible?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Forget not, at the beginning</L>
<L>Of this sweet race, honour hold out for you</L>
<L>A golden Garland.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh remember,</L>
<L>At the end of chastities white race, an Angell</L>
<L>Holds in his hand (shot through a silver Cloud,)</L>
<L>A Crown for Conquerers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hub</SPEAKER>
<L>Will ye loose the pleasure that—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, I, those pleasures <HI>Hubert,</HI> there is a voyce</L>
<L>Of flesh and frailty in me, that still cryes,</L>
<L><HI>Matilda</HI> take those pleasures, and I am now</L>
<L>The Kings for ever.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let the Queen then cut from earth</L>
<L>Such a dissembler.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Offers violence to <HI>Matil. Hubert</HI>
stayes her.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay but you shall not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shame and death dwell</L>
<L>With a goodnesse so short-si<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'d, thou hansome hypocrite,</L>
<L>Thou faith-defrauder, a religious qualme</L>
<L>Crossing the stomack of a seeming Saint,</L>
<L>Which falls straight into humoor, all thy devotions</L>
<L>Prove now but well-clad cheaters of Times Charity,</L>
<L>Thy griefs, and sighs, are but sins crafty games,</L>
<STAGE>Matilda
and <HI>Hub.</HI>
whisper.</STAGE>
<L>Their soon sp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nt flashes play like holy flames.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hub.</SPEAKER>
<L>It shall be so: to some remote place, shut</L>
<L>from the danger of the angry Queen i'le carry you,</L>
<L>And thither bring the King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>I long to see him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Hubert,</HI> wilt thou play the Court Camclion,</L>
<L>The persum'd Pander.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="26"/>
<SPEAKER>Hub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes marry will I, Panders have need of perfumes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh merry sinne!</L>
<L>We smile towards Hell, but howl when we are in,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Name but the place Madam, and religiously I vow,</L>
<L>By th'unstain'd honour of my Name and Hou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e,</L>
<L>By the white reputation of a Gentleman,</L>
<L>And as I wish for after happinesse, my care</L>
<L>Sha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l I see it instantly in execution.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Cousen <HI>Bruce,</HI> Earl <HI>Richmond,</HI> with the convoy,</L>
<L>The King discomfited, they would madly have carried me</L>
<L>To <HI>Dunmow Abbey</HI> in fruitfull <HI>Essex.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hub.</SPEAKER>
<L>S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>oot a thousand Kings</L>
<L>could not thence recover ye, but name the place</L>
<L>Whither I shall carry you, good Madam whither?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good <HI>Hubert</HI> thither.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Falls on her knees.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hub.</SPEAKER>
<L>What to a Monastory?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Call her dissembling,</L>
<L>No <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>nne good heaven, for she is still a Saint.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Upon my knee I begge it, and every day</L>
<L>When I shall drop a Bead, I'le strongly pray</L>
<L>That you may find a blessing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hark <HI>Hubert.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hub.</SPEAKER>
<L>There is something telis me there is honour in it,</L>
<L>To grant her good request.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mark how your Oath ran,</L>
<L>By the honour of your House,</L>
<L>By the white reputation of a Gentleman.</L>
<L>And as you wish for after happinesse.</L>
<L>You'd put my wish in speedy execution.</L>
<L>Oh <HI>Hubert</HI> mark, he his house pulls down,</L>
<L>That wounds his honour, though to please a Crown,</L>
<L>By Heraul'ds he's a Gentleman maintain'd,</L>
<L>Whose reputations whitenesse stands unstain'd,</L>
<L>And he in after happinesse stands high,</L>
<L>That dares not with a sinne by soveraignty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Excellent Oratory!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Hubert,</HI> for truths sake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="26"/>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh <HI>Hubert,</HI> for the glorious Crown of chastity,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>For the victorious Palme of Wedlock faith,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>By the immaculate souls of holy Maids,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>And by the unstain'd truth of honest wives,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>By the tears of Virgins,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>By the truth of vertue,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh now to honour <HI>Hubert</HI> give thy name,</L>
<L>Sweet blooming vertue knows no blush of shame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hub.</SPEAKER>
<L>The rarenesse of your souls has ravish'd me,</L>
<L>Wee'l change our course, steere through bridge, and so</L>
<L>For <HI>Essex</HI> and for <HI>Dunmow,</HI> victorious Maid,</L>
<L>Rhetorick is poor in thy praise, whom a King,</L>
<L>Nor soveraignty, (the soul of womens longings,)</L>
<L>Cannot corrupt!—Oh women! Men-subduers!</L>
<L>Natures extreames! no meane is to be had;</L>
<L>Excellent Good, or infinitely bad!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ambo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most noble <HI>Hubert.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> King, Fitzwater, Chester <HI>and</HI> Oxford.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twas well yet that the trick has catch'd this old one,</L>
<L>Where are the rest?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ches.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Richmond</HI> is gone for <HI>France,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Leister</HI> escap'd to <HI>Winsor.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>How I thirst</L>
<L>To make mine arms walthy with sweet <HI>Matilda.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh if a Fathers prayers, an old mans tears,</L>
<L>An injur'd old mans tears, were ever prevalent,</L>
<L>Good heaven keep my Girle a Christall Fort,</L>
<L>Firme and unvuanquish'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Hnbert</HI> my friend now has her:</L>
<L>Will it please the mighty Emporor of the Barrons,</L>
<L>The King may kisse <HI>Matilda,</HI> she will be here presently,</L>
<L>Then<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> shall the great <HI>Fitzwater</HI> sit in state,</L>
<L>And see <HI>Matilda</HI> and the poor King dallie,</L>
<L>And teach the winds to wanton; <HI>Hubert</HI> now has her,</L>
<L>The faithful'st of my friends, from contrari<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ties</L>
<L><PB REF="27"/>
We will produce soft pleasures, sweet perfections;</L>
<L>Sir<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ah, <HI>Chester</HI> shall tell me when she then frowns, and</L>
<L>Wee'l Court her checks into a comely smile;</L>
<L>If she but raise that milkie hill, her breast,</L>
<L>With respirations, <HI>Oxford</HI> shall swear</L>
<L>it is a sigh, and I will seem to chide</L>
<L>His rashnesse, and protest love rais'd that gale,</L>
<L>Just as her heart for my heart had set sale.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heare heaven!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Chester</HI> shall watch her when she weeps, and tell me</L>
<L>They are <HI>Matilda',</HI> tears, when I will presently</L>
<L>With a lovers pleasing fervency, protest</L>
<L>They are Pearls, by passion forc'd from <HI>Cupids</HI> Chest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oxf.</SPEAKER>
<L>But what shall <HI>Hubert</HI> do,</L>
<L>Your bosome friend?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ki.</SPEAKER>
<L>He shall with pretty thwarting passages</L>
<L>(To please <HI>Matilda,</HI>) seeme to make me angry,</L>
<L>And tell me'tis impossible now t'obtain her;</L>
<L>Whereupon (impatient, to illustrate love</L>
<L>With a new passion) oh how I will rave!</L>
<L>Misuse him strangely, and close up the sweet Sco<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ne</L>
<L>Upon <HI>Matilda's</HI> lip.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter a Gentleman.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gent.</SPEAKER>
<L>Letters from th'Earl <HI>Hubert</HI> sir,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>His name but now,</L>
<L>(Like a beloved passenger,) took leave</L>
<L>Of my unwilling lips, he waits directions</L>
<L>Concerning her from me, good <HI>Chester</HI> read it,</L>
<L>I cannot read and rejoyce too, <HI>Fitzwater</HI></L>
<L>Listen, and rave.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Chester reads.</STAGE>
<P><HI>Letter.</HI> May it please your excellent Majestie, it hath, pleas'd
heaven so throughly to captivate my reason by the potent pleadings
of your vertuous Queene, and unmatch'd <HI>Matilda,</HI> that I hold it
now impossible for your Majestie ever to obtain her.</P>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>That last was musick.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay kill us all, kill us all; will ye read on sir?</L>
</SP>
<LETTER>
<HEAD>Let.</HEAD>
<P> Briefly, by that time these Letters kisse your Royall hands,
<PB REF="27"/>
she will be cloysterd up in <HI>Dunmow Abbey,</HI> and end her dayes a
Vestall, wheither I could not choose but convey her, being thereun∣to
forcibly charmed by her teares and entreaties, and especially
forc'd by a secret command from heaven to mine owne conscience;
I remaine your most excellent Majesties transgressing servant</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Hubert.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</LETTER>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most excellent villaine!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Observe King <HI>John,</HI> e're heaven will vertue faile,</L>
<L>Contrary meanes, all winds shall sill her saile.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ches.</SPEAKER>
<L>How like a Hare, the Greyhounds chaps still at her,</L>
<L>Yet still she scapes! the King is full of tempest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>She's gone for ever.</L>
<L>Oh <HI>Hubert</HI> let us never meet again,</L>
<L>Never more meet; <HI>Fitzwater</HI> fetch herbut back,</L>
<L>As from the first, so from this <HI>Isabell</HI></L>
<L>Wee'l be divorc'd, marry and set <HI>Matilda</HI></L>
<L>I'th regall Chaire, the Kings admired Mistresse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>But will ye say and do sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet there is hope; now by my Crown I will,</L>
<L>We shall be Sonne and Father, thou and I</L>
<L>Will walke upon our Pallace battlements,</L>
<L>And thou shalt carty up a covetous eye,</L>
<L>And thou shalt cast that covetous eye about</L>
<L>The fair, delightful village-spotted valleyes,</L>
<L>Thou shalt stand still, and think, and recollect</L>
<L>The troubl'd longings of thy large desires,</L>
<L>And whatsoever thou shalt aske the King,</L>
<L>(Of all thou see'st) the King shall give it thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, let one one ride before, and certifie</L>
<L>That we are comming.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Chester,</HI> put on wings:</L>
<STAGE>To himselfe.</STAGE>
<L>Thou good old man, the bird that croak'd now sings.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt</STAGE>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="5" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="28"/>
<HEAD>Actus 5. Scoena 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>King</HI> and <HI>Fitzwater, Oxford</HI> meeting them.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>THese are the Abby walls, <HI>Oxford</HI> what news?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ox.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Matilda</HI> is afraid to venture forth,</L>
<L>But on yon battlements it was her promise,</L>
<STAGE>Ent. Abbess and
Matilda above.</STAGE>
<L>With the Lady <HI>Abbess</HI> to appear—and see sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Give us leave<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Oh were that habite</L>
<L>Not so unkind, a foe to faire increase,</L>
<L>I'de call it then celestiall, and swear.</L>
<L>A bright star mov'd in that immaculate spheare:</L>
<L><HI>Matilda!</HI> Mistresse of many Graces!</L>
<L>And lovely as the blush that breaks the day!</L>
<L>Cast thy commanding eyes upon a King,</L>
<L>Whom love hath made a begger;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ab.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why hunts the King</L>
<L>With such a violent poursuit, a chaste Dove,</L>
<L>That hath given up her name to heaven, and stands</L>
<L>White as her spotlesse vesture.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lady <HI>Abbesse,</HI></L>
<L>Pray give me leave, and hearken my <HI>Matilda,</HI></L>
<L>I bring thee gol<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n news my Girle, we have cast</L>
<L>An ill-becomming Calumnie upon</L>
<L>The Kings love all this while; for he protest<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>To be divorc'd from <HI>Isabell</HI> the Queene,</L>
<L>And by marriage set thee in his B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d,</L>
<L>A plant to spring and prosper; women naturally</L>
<L>Do aflect soveraignty; wilt thou runne retrograde</L>
<L>In <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> faire Zodiack? though all wayes yet</L>
<L>Have fail'd, this will take I am sure.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>To the King.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who hath taught my Father</L>
<L>To tum Apostate to that integrity</L>
<L>Slept in his noble breast? through a divorce</L>
<L>I run to golden ruine; the King marry me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="28"/>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>And make thee Queen of him, and two large Kingdoms,</L>
<L>The Christian world when they shall hear, shall wonder,</L>
<L>And magnifie in their abundant praises,</L>
<L>The glory of our Marriage.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh my Lord, here I can call necessity,</L>
<L>Excellent Pyhsick for a vast desire,</L>
<L>Our wants are holy waters, cast on lust's fire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh brave, brave Girle!</L>
<L>That I had thee here to buss thee,</L>
<L>Her very breath did smell of heaven.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Matilda!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have found thee Gold my Girle,</L>
<L>These are glorious wrestlings,</L>
<L>Celestial struglings; passion of me, that joy</L>
<L>Should carry Aprill eyes.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>weeps.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Matilda,</HI> Look upon thy soveraigne courting,</L>
<L>Thy cruelty with a paire of wooing eyes,</L>
<L>Labouring for mercy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, no, <HI>Matilda,</HI> look upon thy soveraigne,</L>
<L>Thy chastity with tempting wanton eyes,</L>
<L>Labouring in lust.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou man of rude defects, let me alone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou man of wilde desires, let me alone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tut, tut, I know whose Cause I have in hand,</L>
<L>And neither ha's nor hems can fright plain <HI>Robin,</HI></L>
<L>The wound that foolish love-Boy there (what call ye him?)</L>
<L>Had struck your heart with, because your smooth tongue,</L>
<L>You could not come to supple it, as the Dog does his foot,</L>
<L>With fair fine words you could lick me, and then</L>
<L>Lift me to stroak it, and heale it by Atturney,</L>
<L>He steers not steddy thae delights to roame,</L>
<L>Craft sets out swift, but ever comes short home:</L>
<L>I tell ye truth I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Abbesse,</HI> deliver up <HI>Mattlda,</HI></L>
<L>Or with an Army fill'd with Ruffians, Ra<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ishers,</L>
<L>The very Sonnes of darknesse, we will levell</L>
<L><PB REF="29"/>
This building to the bottome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>A.</SPEAKER>
<L>We know the King,</L>
<L>(Being reconcil'd unto his mother Church,)</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>annot conceive such out-rage.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Appears passionate</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now ye stamp, do ye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Father farewell, and to my Lord my King,</L>
<L>The service of his most obseq<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ous Hand-maid,;</L>
<L>And good your Maiestie be <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>as'd to remember,</L>
<L>How excellently-admirable your Crown</L>
<L>Will then become ye, when you shall <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ast off</L>
<L>The habite of your passions, I will pray for you sir,</L>
<L>And if't be possible with prayers and teares,</L>
<L>Quench your de<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>res, and fortifie my feares.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Fathers blessing, like a welcome cloud</L>
<L>With child of friendly showers, hover o're thy goodnesse,</L>
<L>And keep it evergreen—; she is gone sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Go thou and runne into the Sea.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, ha, So the great Emperor of the Ba<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rons,</L>
<L>As you cal'd him,</L>
<L>May come out aagin i'th guts of a poor John:</L>
<L>No, no, I will live and laugh, you would have made her</L>
<L>The mistresse of the King, and she is married</L>
<L>To <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he Kings Master, oh to the noblest King</L>
<L>Poore supplicant ever kneel'd to, to your King,</L>
<L>And her King, and to my King she's married;</L>
<L>Oh married, married, let the Satyrs dance it,</L>
<L>The sweet Birds sing it, let the winds be wanton,</L>
<L>And as they softly with an evening whisper,</L>
<L>Steal through the curl'd locks of the lofty woods,</L>
<L>Let them in their sweet language seem to say,</L>
<L>This, this was chaste <HI>Matilda's</HI> Marriage day.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Fitz.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>It resolv'd irrevocable; who waits?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Chester.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ches.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Confessor.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Have an eye apon that Fox; where's our <HI>Confessor?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>Attending sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your ear—do this,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="29"/>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>And hark you, without all expostulation, speedily</L>
<L>Make <HI>Brand</HI> the Instrument.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall not fail sir.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>All my blood turns, she is now past all recovery;</L>
<L>Oh day draw in thy light, Time do not keep</L>
<L>This Deed for story; Memory fall asleep</L>
<L>In black oblivions Cavern; let this day</L>
<L>Still skip the Kalend, and be wip'd away</L>
<L>From all discourse; oh let no chaste Maid.</L>
<L>(Remembring how <HI>Matilda</HI> was betray'd,)</L>
<L>With bitter teares, curse the too cruell King;</L>
<L>No Satyr dance this day, no sweet bird sing,</L>
<L>But let the Raven and Screcth. Owl cry,</L>
<L><HI>Matilda</HI> the chaste Maid, must this day dye.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Brand</HI> and the <HI>Abbesse</HI> reading a Letter.</STAGE>
<LETTER>
<HEAD>Lett. </HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>Madam,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P> These are to giye you to understund, that instant∣ly,
and without any the least expostulation, you see convey'n into the
outward Garden adjoyning to the Abby, your new Votary <HI>Matilda,</HI>
that the bearer (this Gentleman) may without the least intercep∣tion,
have freedome of accesse unto her; let this from me be your
safety, and forget not, the wills of Princes are indisputable—</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED><HI>Fustace</HI> Confessor to his Majestie.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</LETTER>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ab.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, no, no cloud of niceness, order, or regularity,</L>
<L>Must intercept this Mandate; Sir, the Kings will,</L>
<L>The Confessors advertizement, and your hopes,</L>
<L>Shall meet this minute; but vertue is I hope</L>
<L>The Rudder of your voyage.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<L>I tell you Madam, 'tis unspotted truth,</L>
<L>The King is chang'd so excellent, such a lover</L>
<L>Now of <HI>Matilda's</HI> noble constancy,</L>
<L>That therefore as his (Confessor there certifies,)</L>
<L>Your duty is expected</L>
<L>To work my admittance to her, which is onely</L>
<L>To let her know, how heartily his Majestie</L>
<L>Admires and commends her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="30"/>
<SPEAKER>Ab.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis a joyful hearing,</L>
<STAGE>Enter Matilda.</STAGE>
<L>See where she walks, souls <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o heavenly simple,</L>
<L>It seems the Court digests not, and (being cloy'd,)</L>
<L>Commends them to the Cloyster.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<L>And she be so simple,</L>
<L>She's the fitter for the Saints, things I near think of,</L>
<L>Unlesse to stuffe our similies—excellent Lady.</L>
<L>There's such a deale of heaven in her face,</L>
<L>It makes my black soul tremble—excellent Lady,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your will sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<L>To let you understand the will of him,</L>
<L>Whose will the will of heaven hath new made;</L>
<L>Thus said King <HI>John</HI> in briefe, tell that sweet Saint,</L>
<L>(And there he wept as I do at the thought on't)</L>
<STAGE>weeps.</STAGE>
<L>The immaculate Mistresse of my dear devotions.</L>
<L>The King by this (with her eye not unacquainted)</L>
<L>Commends to her his hate of all that love,</L>
<L>The feavor of his blood contaminated:</L>
<L>Oh tell her (and he sigh'd there bitterly)</L>
<L>That as I was her tempter, I am now</L>
<L>Mine own despiser; as mine own despiser,</L>
<L>I will remain her vertues strong admirer;</L>
<L>And there just thus he kist it—; if't chance, quoth he,</L>
<L>Her gentle lip return the Kings chaste meaning,</L>
<L>Mark but which place of this (then happy (Glove</L>
<L>Receives that heavenly print, and bring it back,</L>
<L>That my lips there (like a paire of willing Pilgrims)</L>
<L>May pay my hearts devotions. This was all,</L>
<L>And this, his Glove, the Token.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Excellence Change!</L>
<L>Heaven now hath heard my praiers, return his goodnesse;</L>
<L>I am sorry thou hast kist the Glove before me,</L>
<L>For feare thy lips have lay'n where the Kings did,</L>
<L>And cosen'd mine of that grace fell from them,</L>
<L>When he spake things thus good, Give me the Glove.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Ha:</HI> He looks towards the Garden door, and whilst she
turns her self that way, he changes the Glove, and gives her the other poyson'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy looks made me beleeve, that some were coming.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="30"/>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<L>No Madam, I have cosen'd you, twas but the wind.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>No wind shall keep my duty from his Majestie</L>
<L>With my observance; say thus, I return'd</L>
<STAGE>Kisses the poyson'd Glove.</STAGE>
<L>My love of his great goodnesse; and if he aske thee</L>
<L>How I receiv'd the news of his rare change,</L>
<L>Say, as a teeming soyle after a drought,</L>
<L>Welcomes a wish'd for shower: what a strange sent</L>
<L>Strongly beats up into my braines, while I hold this Glove</L>
<L>So neer my breast! thou art not honest sure?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<L>Neer death we prophesie, and 'tis so sure,</L>
<L>You cannot breath three minutes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis neatly don, and there's no dallying,</L>
<L>I know 'tis strong and swift, as by a Glove</L>
<L>You were carryed from your Fathers to this Cloyster,</L>
<L>So by a Glove you are from this Cloyster sent</L>
<L>To the chaste Court of Saints.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heaven! is this right?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, 'twas a left-handed Glove, look ye,</L>
<L>I kist the right and cosen'd you,</L>
<L>So that a sinister act with a left-handed Glove, very prettily</L>
<L>Imports a wittynesse in wickednesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art a merry murderer, the King was wont</L>
<L>To call me friend; oh if he bestowes</L>
<L>On's friends such guifts, what sends he to his foes?</L>
<L>Uncharitable love-token; oh what harsh hand</L>
<L>Temperd this dram of death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<L>I could do't no better.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mercilesse man, Tyg<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rs to thee are tame;</L>
<L>Oh cozening Crocadile, that with thy tears couldst take me<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>How wilt thou howse</L>
<L>When thou and I meet next? when I shall sit</L>
<L>Above my sufferings, then will my blood be</L>
<L>A cloud betwixt eternity and thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<L>Clouds? yes, much clouds.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>There was the last call; to the King, commend me,</L>
<L>And tell him, when in stories he shall stand,</L>
<L><PB REF="31"/>
When men shall read the Conquerors great name,</L>
<L>Voluptuous <HI>Rusus,</HI> that unkind brother <HI>Beaucla<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>k,</HI></L>
<L>Comely King <HI>Steven, Henry</HI> the Wedlock-breaker,</L>
<L>And Lyon-hearted <HI>Richard;</HI> when they come</L>
<L>unto his name, with sighs it shall be said,</L>
<L><HI>This was King</HI> John—<HI>the murderer of a Maid;</HI></L>
<L>Oh tell him I am past his strong temptations,</L>
<L>And though wild burning back'd his hot desire,</L>
<L>Like perfect Gold I did out-live the fire.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Dyes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<L>She's dead and I must shift for one,</L>
<L>I heare some trampling,</L>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>young</HI> Bruce.</STAGE>
<L>What's he has leap'd the Garden walls? has awenching look,</L>
<L>And should be a good Vaulter, guilty knaves make excellent</L>
<L>Eves droppers, and I love to sound strange bosomes, I will lye</L>
<L>To see and heare, and yet not heard nor seen,</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>stands aside.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here rumour gives, my cousin, chaste <HI>Matilda</HI></L>
<L>To live a Votary: ha! on the ground!</L>
<L>Murder'd most certainly, and so warme, that yet</L>
<L>The murderer at my approach, may lurk</L>
<L>About the Garden, for through the Abbey tis</L>
<L>Impossible to passe; oh my griev'd blood,</L>
<L>Who made it so unfortunate to be good.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<L>He mumbles something to himselfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>This parallels my Mother and my Brother:</L>
<L>Ha! something sti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s i'th Grove, passion I know thee not,</L>
<L>With a new art we must catch old Blood-hounds: well,</L>
<L>Although I am the Kings well-wishing friend,</L>
<L>And have rais'd forces for his part at <HI>Winsor,</HI></L>
<L>Yet with my heart I am glad, a friendly hand</L>
<L>Hath ma le thee happy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<L>S'foot this is one of our side,</L>
<L>But it seems he knows not twas the Kings injunction.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now businesse will be minded, state affairs,</L>
<L>With vigilance effected, which before</L>
<L>Were so intangled in your hair forsooth,</L>
<L>Suiters could find no end of their beginnings.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<L>By this light I have done a good deed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="31"/>
<SPEAKER>Y. Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou honest soul,</L>
<L>That (by the heat of thy happy hany-work,)</L>
<L>Canst not I am sure but be in hearing; If</L>
<L>My irregular start (upon private necessity)</L>
<L>Frighted thee off, be not asham'd to let</L>
<L>Thy unknown friend possesse thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh braze young spark.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Eru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or if thy modesty must keep thee off,</L>
<L>So well I love thy work (and as I the Kingdom)</L>
<L>Let this Purse of Gold, this Diamond fasten'd to't,</L>
<L>Tell thee thy friend was here, if thoul'dst know him,</L>
<L>He is a kinsman to the Earl of <HI>Chester;</HI></L>
<L>And because thou shalt not doubt thy friends fair meanings,</L>
<L>I will return the way I came, although</L>
<L>With danger to my person.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here is one sir, wishes better to his friends.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>What art thou?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Shewes himselfe.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<L>One that will take your honoorable Purse,</L>
<L>And yet passe quit at the Common Law.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wert thou the expert Master of this peece.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<L>You being kinsman to my Lord and Master,</L>
<L>(Who ever hated this blood;) I dare tell you,</L>
<L>I practi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'d first a businesse late at <HI>Winsor,</HI></L>
<L>Upon a Mother and her Sonne—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold heart, old <HI>Bruces</HI> Lady,</L>
<L>And the brat her Sonne?</L>
<L>Wer't thou the happy instrument</L>
<L>To cut these Houses down? didst thou do that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<L>It would deserve (well priz'd) another Purse sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gold must not part us, didst do't?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Gives him
more Gold.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<L>Both that and this, by this stand sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sonne of the Devill have I sound thee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sure he knows me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fool, dost thou draw a sword;</L>
<L>What a loud lye thou dost give heaven, to think</L>
<L>A sword can shield the guilty, look here villaine</L>
<L>Upon my horrid point, where death in tempest</L>
<L><PB REF="32"/>
And whirle-winds, stares upon thee, thou murderer:</L>
<L>Of my Mother, Brother, and my Kinswoman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<L>S'root here was a Purse wi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h a bob at the end ont,</L>
<L>Pray take your Purse againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Toad, I will take thy heart first.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<L>I deny nothing then,</L>
<L>Resolution crowns my craft; for those at <HI>Winsor,</HI></L>
<L>(Let me free the King) I <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ami<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>'d them, because</L>
<L>Your Mother was too coy, you may guess the rest;</L>
<L>For this it was King <HI>Johns</HI> in junction,</L>
<L>And I have done it daintily by this light.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>By darknesse and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>er Angels,</L>
<L>Thy near kinsmen,</L>
<L>Thou shalt not live five minutes for't.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>They fight, Bran<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
falls, <HI>young</HI> Bruce keeps him down.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<L>O sir, what mean ye?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>To aske thee for a Mother, a sweet Brother,</L>
<L>A chaste kinswoman; oh that thou couldst be</L>
<L>Ten daies a dying; Slave! i'le stick thy Trunck</L>
<L>So thick with wounds, it shall appear a Book</L>
<L>Full of red Letters,</L>
<L>Characters of thy cruelty</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>stabs him.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is no bleeding moneth fir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thon lyest, look yonder;</L>
<L>There lyes mine Almanack, a celestiall body,</L>
<STAGE>Points to <HI>Ma∣tilda's</HI>
Course.
Stabs.</STAGE>
<L>Whose revolution, period, pale aspect,</L>
<L>All tell me'tis high time that thou shouldst bleed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy veines are all corruption,</L>
<L>Toads belch not fouler;</L>
<L>And should thy Trunck be thrown upon a dunghill,</L>
<L>(As it deserves no better buriall)</L>
<L>The sent would poyson swine, the very dogs</L>
<L>Would with howlings fly as from a mid-night <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>end,</L>
<L>And every Raven that should <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> upon't,</L>
<L><PB REF="32"/>
Would seek forsaken Deserts, and there die</L>
<L>Full of infection.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Stabs.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh that last has finish't me,</L>
<L>And where I go I know not, a bloody Cloud</L>
<L>Hath hid heaven from me like a purple shrowd.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Dyes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Feast thou the Crows,</L>
<L>This body i'le convey to <HI>Winsor,</HI> where my Mother,</L>
<L>And my sweet murther'd Brother, wee'l expose</L>
<L>(As spurs of righteous vengeance) to all eyes;</L>
<L>Conscience, and Blood, are strong incessant cryes.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.
<HI>Enter</HI> King <HI>and Lords below, old</HI> Bruce, Leister
Oxford <HI>and</HI> Fitzwater <HI>above.</HI>
Charge.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>You Sonnes of death and disobedience;</L>
<L>Why is the King kept out?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ol. Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall know sir;</L>
<L>Is't not enough the whole Lands Liberties</L>
<L>Lye yet a gasping by your head strong passions,</L>
<L>Wounded by your neglect, but through blood</L>
<L>D'<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e chase your vast desires, my Wife and Sonne sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>A game as we are Prince, in our Royall word,</L>
<L>The villaine past our precept.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ol. Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>As you past heavens</L>
<L>In your bloody masquing night at <HI>Baynards</HI> Castle,</L>
<L>When all the floores, and the white walls wore bloody</L>
<L>Deep crimson blushes, to behold a Prince</L>
<L>In blood pursue his passions.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bar'd out and brav'd,</L>
<L>You bate and chafe a Lyon; bring old <HI>Fitzwater,</HI></L>
<L>Thou <HI>Bruce</HI> and grumbling <HI>Leister,</HI> either speedily</L>
<L>Give up the Castle, and upon your knees</L>
<L>Fall to the mercy you have scorn'd, or here</L>
<L>Before a paire of minutes passe, the sword</L>
<L>Of incens'd justice shall even in your eyes,</L>
<L>Leave this old Rebell headlesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now by the blood</L>
<L>I lost in holy <HI>Palestine</HI> with <HI>Richard,</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="33"/>
Oh that right reall Souldier! King <HI>John</HI> I sweare,</L>
<L>That foul-word Rebel ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>unrivited</L>
<L>The ba<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s of reason, and made me very angry;</L>
<L>Is it to take truths part to be a Rebel?</L>
<L>To ease my groaning Country, is that Rebellion?</L>
<L>To preserve the unstain'd honour of a Maid,</L>
<L>(And that maid my daughter) to preserve your glory,</L>
<L>That you stand not branded in our Chronicles,</L>
<L>By the black name of Wedlock-breaker; is this</L>
<L>(Good, heaven!) is this Rebellion? Come, come, the Axe;</L>
<L>Oh that wrong'd soul to death so falsely given,</L>
<STAGE>Ent. Mowbra<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></STAGE>
<L>Flies sweetly singing her own truth to heaven.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mow.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stand on your guard-sir,</L>
<L>Young <HI>Bruce</HI> with twenty thousand</L>
<L>Strong able men from <HI>Cambridge</HI> and <HI>Essex,</HI></L>
<L>With a speedy march, and with as dreadful threatnings,</L>
<L>Comes thundering towards <HI>Winsor,</HI> all his Ensigns</L>
<L>Crimson and black, which in their want<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n wavings,</L>
<L>Cry to the frighted Country (as he marches)</L>
<L>Nothing but blood and d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ath.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ol. Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh noble Sonne of a murpered M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ther.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Honourable young man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Draw up our forces like a pair of angry winds,</L>
<L>That have got a hollow Cloud with child of tempests,</L>
<L>Wee'l make the valleyes tremble.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Chester.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ches.</SPEAKER>
<L>Resist now sir,</L>
<L>Or the whole Kingdome trembles, <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ewis</HI> the Dolphines</L>
<L>By th'politique working of ingenius <HI>Richmond,</HI></L>
<L>(Who was sent for him) with six hundred sayle,</L>
<L>And fourscore Flat-boats is let in at <HI>Dover,</HI></L>
<L>Subduing as they march, and the Towns willingly</L>
<L>Givin<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hem way; they have reach'd <HI>Rochester,</HI></L>
<L>And if a speedy swift prevention meet not,</L>
<L>They will for <HI>London</HI> certainly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now <HI>John</HI> thy Crown sits quivering.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ches.</SPEAKER>
<L>These here so resolute—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mow.</SPEAKER>
<L>Youug <HI>Bruce</HI> so potent—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="33"/>
<SPEAKER>Ox<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L>And which strikes deepe, a factious forraigne foot</L>
<L>Upon our earth, 'tis a dangerous triplcity,</L>
<L>So that our Forces were they three times trebl'd,</L>
<L>(Distracted with a division thus trianguler)</L>
<L>Cannot promise safety.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take it not Time, for now</L>
<L>The goodliest Oak in the whole wood must bow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh that was very well said sir, nor shall ye bow,</L>
<L>But unto heaven and vertue, for Kings have boasted</L>
<L>To be her servants; oh in this tempest sir,</L>
<L>Give her the helme, good brother <HI>Bruce,</HI> the King</L>
<L>Has faithfully acquitted him of the bloods</L>
<L>Of your Wife and Sonne,; <HI>Leister,</HI> the King now looks</L>
<L>Upon his passions with a displeased eye,</L>
<L>Trust to our faiths sir, give the Land her Liberties,</L>
<L>And do but look upon my poor <HI>Matilda.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, oh.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>With Kingly chaste eyes; and a holy soul;</L>
<L>My brother shall command his Sonne to obedience,</L>
<L><HI>Leister</HI> and he shall give ye up the Castle,</L>
<L>We will call <HI>Richmond</HI> with his powers from <HI>Lewis,</HI></L>
<L>We will be all one soule againe, and force</L>
<L>The skipping <HI>French</HI> to put to Sea again,</L>
<L>And you shall stand a King then absolute;</L>
<L>Good brother <HI>Leister,</HI> sir upon my knee,</L>
<L>I urge your goodnesse now; shall we still stand</L>
<L>And chaine our freedomes to a forraign hand?</L>
<L>When we shun seen Rocks, then we safely sayle;</L>
<L>Good, good, King <HI>John,</HI> let the old man prevaile.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh <HI>Chester</HI> run to <HI>Dunmow,</HI> and if <HI>Brand</HI> yet</L>
<L>Have kept his hand whi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e, bid that <HI>Brand</HI> forbear,</L>
<L>For feare of burning everlastingly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ches.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall sir.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Mowbray,</HI> with the bendings of the King,</L>
<L>Go meet that angry young man <HI>Bruce,</HI> and tell him,</L>
<L>Here's now no use for steele.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mow.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twill be good news sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="34"/>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Meet us at least (you stubborn men,)</L>
<L>In our facile affections:</L>
<L>Why send ye not for <HI>Richmond?</HI> must we bend, and</L>
<L>And beseech too?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Passe but your Royal promise</L>
<L>In the words of a King, to performe what</L>
<L>Y'are fled from, the wind not with more swiftnesse,</L>
<L>Shall fly to play with <HI>Richmonds</HI> lofty Plume,</L>
<L>Then shall be shown in his repeale.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis granted upon our Kingly word—that time in me,</L>
<L>shall read that Giants force necessity!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ol. Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>With all submissive reverence we descend,</L>
<L>And kisse your Highnesse hand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Right happy day,</L>
<L>My Girle is safe, and all clouds blown away.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt from
the walls</STAGE>
<STAGE>Hoboyes sound, whilst the <HI>Barrons</HI> descend, each on
his knee kissing the Kings hand, both Parties joyful∣ly
embrace; suddenly the Hoboyes cease and a
sad Musick of Flutes heard. Enter to the <HI>King</HI> and
<HI>Lords,</HI> the Lady <HI>Abbess,</HI> Ushering <HI>Matilda's</HI> Herse,
born by Virgins, this Motto fasmed unto it—<HI>To
Piety and Chastity.</HI> The Body of <HI>Matilda</HI> lying on
the Herse, and attended by the <HI>Queene,</HI> bearing in
her hand a Garland, compos'd of Roses and Lillies;
after her, young <HI>Bruce, Hubert, Chester,</HI> and other
Gentlemen, all in mourning habites.</STAGE>
<LG>
<HEAD>The Song in parts.</HEAD>
<LG N="1">
<HEAD>1</HEAD>
<L>LOoke what Death hath done! here laid</L>
<L>(In one) a Martyr, and a Maid.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="2">
<HEAD>2.</HEAD>
<L>Angels Crown Those with just applause.</L>
<L>Dye in defence of Vertues Lawes.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="3">
<PB REF="34"/>
<HEAD>Chorus</HEAD>
<L>Such was her cause! Death! boast not of thy hands<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Cruelty, since the uanquish'd victor stands.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="4">
<HEAD>2.</HEAD>
<L>Her Chastity, to Time shall last</L>
<L>Like Laurel, which no lightning can blast.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="5">
<HEAD>1.</HEAD>
<L>Sweet Maids, with Roses deck her Herse,</L>
<L>Whose Vertue stands above the reach of Verse.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="6">
<HEAD>Chorus</HEAD>
<L>Heaven hath her pure part, whil'st on Earth, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>her Name</L>
<L>Moves in the Spheare of aresulgent Fame.</L>
</LG>
</LG>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Hubert</HI> interpret this Apparition.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Behold sir,</L>
<L>A fad writ Tragedy so ferlingly,</L>
<L>Languag'd, and cast, with such a crafty cruelty,</L>
<L>Contriv'd and acted, that wild Savages,</L>
<L>Satyrs, and the rude rabble of the Woods,</L>
<L>Would weep to lay their ears to, and (admiring</L>
<L>To see themselves out done) they would conceive</L>
<L>Their wildnesse, mildness to this deed, and call</L>
<L>Men more then Savage, themselves rationall;</L>
<L>And thou <HI>Fitzwater,</HI> reflect upon thy name,</L>
<L>And turn the sonne of tears, oh forget</L>
<L>That <HI>Cupid</HI> ever spent a dart upon thee,</L>
<L>That <HI>Hymen</HI> ever coupled thee, or that ever</L>
<L>The hasty, happy, willing messenger,</L>
<L>Told thee thou hadst a Daughter; oh look here,</L>
<L>Look here King <HI>John,</HI> and with a tembling eye,</L>
<STAGE>Unvailes
her face.</STAGE>
<L>Read your sad act, <HI>Matilda's</HI> Tragedy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Om.</SPEAKER>
<L>Matilda!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>By the labouring soul of a much injur'd man,</L>
<L>It is my childe <HI>Matilda.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh cruell King, go <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ate thy bloody eye</L>
<L>With thy black command, which there lyes executed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ol. Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweet Neece,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="35"/>
<SPEAKER>Leis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Chaste soule,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>King, go and read thy cruelty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do I stirre <HI>Chester?</HI></L>
<L>Good <HI>Oxford,</HI> do I move? stand I not still</L>
<L>To watch the when the griev'd friends of dead <HI>Matilda,</HI></L>
<L>Will with a thousand stabs turn me to dust?</L>
<L>That in a thousand prayes they may be happy;</L>
<L>Wil no one do't? then give a mourner room,</L>
<STAGE>Falls passionately
upon the Herse.</STAGE>
<L>A man of tears; oh immaculate <HI>Matilda,</HI></L>
<L>These sheed but sayling heat drops, missing showers,</L>
<L>The faint dews of a doubtful April-morning;</L>
<L>But from mine eyes, ship-sincking Ca<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aracts,</L>
<L>Whold clouds of waters, wealthy exhalations</L>
<L>Shall fall into the Sea of my affliction,</L>
<L>Till it amaze the Mourners.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Unmatch'd <HI>Matilda,</HI></L>
<L>Celestiall Souldier that keep'st a Fort of Chastity</L>
<L>'Gainst all temptations.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not to be a Queene</L>
<L>Would she break her chaste vow, truth crowns your reed,</L>
<L>Unmatch'd <HI>Matilda</HI> was her name indeed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh take into your spirit-piercing praise,</L>
<L>My Scoene of sorrow; I have wel-clad woes,</L>
<L>Pathetick epethites to illustrate passion,</L>
<L>And steale true teares so sweetly from all these,</L>
<L>'tshall touch the soule, and at one pierce and please.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ches.</SPEAKER>
<L>What will he doe?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>The Ki. takes the Gar and from
the Queen, and peruses the Motto of the Herse.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>To <HI>Prety</HI> and <HI>Purity,</HI> and Lillies mixt with Roses.</L>
<L>How well you have apparell'd woe, this pendant</L>
<L>To <HI>Piety</HI> and <HI>Purity</HI> directed,</L>
<L>Insinuates a chaste soule in a clean body:</L>
<L>Vertues white Virgin, Chastities red Martyr,</L>
<L>Suffer me then with this well-suited wreath,</L>
<L>To make our griefs ingenious, let all be dumb,</L>
<L>Whilst the King speaks her Epicedium.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ches.</SPEAKER>
<L>His very soul speaks sorrow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="35"/>
<SPEAKER>Ox.</SPEAKER>
<L>And it becomes him sweetly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hail Maid and Marty! loe on thy breast,</L>
<L>Devotions Alter, chaste truths chest,</L>
<L>I offer (as my guilt imposes)</L>
<L>Thy merrits Laurel, Lillies and Roses,</L>
<L>Lillies, intimating plaine,</L>
<L>Thy immaculate life stuck with no staine;</L>
<L>Roses red, and sweet, to tell</L>
<L>How sweet red sacrifices smell;</L>
<STAGE>Sets the Garland on her
breast.</STAGE>
<L>Hang round then as you walk about this Herse,</L>
<L>The songs of holy hearts, sweet, vertuous verse,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bring Persian silks to deck her Monument,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Arabian spices quick'ning by their sent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Numidian Marble to preserve her praise,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Corinthian Ivory her sweet shape to raise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>And write in gold upon it, in this brest,</L>
<L>Virtue sat Mistresse passion but a guest;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Virtue is sweet, and since griefs bitter be.</L>
<L>Strew her with Roses, and give Rue to me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ol. Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>My noble Brother, I have lost a Wife and Son,</L>
<L>You a sweet Daughter, look on the Kings penitence,</L>
<L>His promise for the Kindomes peace, perfer</L>
<L>A publique benefit. When it shall please,</L>
<L>Let heaven question him, let us secure,</L>
<L>And quit the Land of <HI>Lewis.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do any thing,</L>
<L>Do all things that are honourable, and the great King,</L>
<L>Make you a good King sir; and when your soul.</L>
<L>Shall at any time reflect upon your follies,</L>
<L>Good King <HI>John</HI> weep, weep very heartily,</L>
<L>It will become you sweetly, at your eyes</L>
<L>Your sin stole in, there pay your sacrifie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Back unto <HI>Dunmow Abby,</HI> where wee'l pay</L>
<L>To sweet <HI>Matilda's</HI> memory and her sufferings,</L>
<L>A monthly obsequie, which (sweetned by</L>
<L>The wealthy woes of a tear-troubl'd eye)</L>
<L>Shall by those sharp afflictions of my face,</L>
<L><PB REF="36"/>
Court Mercy, and make Grief <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></L>
<L>Let my wil'd errors, tell to time this truth;</L>
<L>Wh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l'st passion holds the Helm, Reason and Honour.</L>
<L>Do suffer wrack; but they saile safe, and cleer,</L>
<L>Who constantly by Virtues Compasse steer.</L>
</SP>
<LG>
<HEAD>Song.</HEAD>
<LG N="1">
<HEAD>1.</HEAD>
<L><HI>MAtilda!</HI> Now goe take thy Bed,</L>
<L>In the darke dwellings of the dead.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="2">
<HEAD>2.</HEAD>
<L>And rise in the great Waking-day,</L>
<L>Sweet as Incense, fresh as May.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="3">
<HEAD>1.</HEAD>
<L>Rest thou chaste soule, (fixt in thy proper spheare,)</L>
<L>Amongst heauens faire Ones; All are fair ones there.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="4">
<HEAD>Cho.</HEAD>
<L>Rest there chaste soul, whilst we (here troubl'd) say,</L>
<L>Time gives us Griefs, Death takes our joyes away.</L>
</LG>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exeunt omnes.</STAGE>
<PB REF="36"/>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

