<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2004-06-17</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Amanda Watson</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page. Checked for N=""s. Checked for GROUP tags. Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, etc.). Checked for signatures. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, and UNCLEARs. Corrected 14 $s and $$word$$s etc. of 14. Checked for EPIGRAPHs and ARGUMENTs. Checked for &amp;cs with incorrect spacing. Checked for LBs. Checked for startqs, endqs, oes, q;s, and Qs. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Checked for CLOSERs, TRAILERs, and BYLINEs. Checked for missing page GAPs. Fixed I / Js. Sample: 15 minutes. Proofing: 40 minutes. Tag review and corrections: 125 minutes. DONE.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A50796">
<STC T="W">M1986</STC>
<BIBNO T="oclc">12086229</BIBNO>
<VID>53753</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>THE SPANISH GIPSIE. As it was Acted (with great Applause) at the Privat House in DRURY-LANE, and <HI>SALISBURY COURT.</HI></P>
<P>Written by <HI>THOMAS MIDLETON,</HI> Gent. AND <HI>WILLIAM ROWLEY.</HI> Gent.</P>
<P><HI>Never Printed before.</HI></P>
<P><HI>LONDON,</HI> Printed by <HI>I. G.</HI> for <HI>Richard Marriot</HI> in St. <HI>Dunstans</HI> Church-yard, <HI>Fleetstreet,</HI> 1653.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dramatis personae">
<PB REF="2" MS="y"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>Drammatis Personae.</HEAD>
<LIST>
<ITEM><HI>FErnando, Corigidor</HI> of Madrill.</ITEM>
<ITEM><LIST>
<LABEL><LIST>
<ITEM><HI>Pedro de Cortes.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Francisco de Carcomo.</HI></ITEM>
</LIST></LABEL>
<ITEM>Two old Dons.</ITEM>
</LIST></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Roderigo,</HI> Son to <HI>Fernando.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Lewys,</HI> Son to <HI>De Castro,</HI> slaine by <HI>Alvarez.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Diego,</HI> Friend to <HI>Don Lewys.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Don John,</HI> Son to <HI>Francisco De Carcomo,</HI> and a Lover of <HI>Constanza.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Sancho,</HI> A foolish Gentleman, and Ward to <HI>Don Pedro.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Soto,</HI> A merry fellow his Man.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Alvarez,</HI> An old Lord disguised like the Father of the Gipsies.</ITEM>
<ITEM><LIST>
<LABEL><LIST>
<ITEM><HI>Claro.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Antonio.</HI></ITEM>
</LIST></LABEL>
<ITEM>Two Gentlemen, disguised like Gipsies.</ITEM>
</LIST></ITEM>
<ITEM><LIST>
<LABEL>Women</LABEL>
<ITEM><LIST>
<ITEM><HI>Maria,</HI> Wife to <HI>Don Pedro.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Clara,</HI> Their Daughter.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Guiamara,</HI> Wife to Count <HI>Alvarez,</HI> and Sister to <HI>Fernando,</HI> disgus'd like the Mother of the Gipsies, and call'd by the Name of <HI>Eugenia.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Constanza,</HI> Daughter to <HI>Fernando,</HI> disguis'd like a young Spanish Gipsie, and call'd by the Name of <HI>Pretiosa.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Christiana,</HI> A Gentleman, disguis'd like a Gipsie.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Cardochia,</HI> A young Hostes to the Gipsies.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Servants.</ITEM>
</LIST></ITEM>
</LIST></ITEM>
</LIST>
<P>The Scene, <HI>Allegant.</HI></P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="play">
<PB REF="3"/>
<PB REF="3"/>
<HEAD>THE SPANISH GIPSIE.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACTUS PRIMUS.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Roderigo, Lewys, and Diego.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">R</SEG>Oderigo.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Die.</SPEAKER>
<P>Art mad?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, not so much with Wine; its as rare to see a Spaniard a drunkard, as a Germane sober, an Italian no Whoremonger, an English man to pay his debts. I am no Borachia, Sack, Maligo, nor Canary breeds the Calenture in my braines, mine eye mads me, not my cups.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<P>What would'st have us do?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Die.</SPEAKER>
<P>So far as tis fit for a Gentlemen wee'l venture.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<P>I aske no more, I ha seen a thing has bewitched me, a delicate body, but this in the waste, Foot and Leg tempting, the Face I had a glimpse of: but the Fruit must needs be delicious, the Tree being so beautifull.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<P>Prithee to the point.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here tis, an old Gentleman, (no matter who he is) an old Gentlewoman (I ha nothing to do with her) but a young creature that followes them, Daughter or Servant, or whatsoever shee be her I must have, they are comming this way, shall I have her? I must have her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="4"/>
<SPEAKER>Die.</SPEAKER>
<P>How, how?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou speak'st impossibilities.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Easie, easie, easie, i'le seize the young girle: stop you the old man, stay you the old woman.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<P>How then?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<P>I'le fly off with the young Bird, that's all, many of our Spanish Gallants act these merry parts every night, they are weak and old, we young and sprightly, will you assist me?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<P>Troath <HI>Roderigo</HI> any thing in the way of honour.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<P>For a wench Man any course is honorable.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay not any, her Father, if he her Father may be noble.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am as noble.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<P>Would the adventure were so.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Stand close, they come.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Pedro, Maria, and Clara.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ped.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis late would we were in Madrill.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Go faster my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ped.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Clara,</HI> keep close.</L>
<STAGE>They seize them.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Helpe, helpe, helpe!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you crying out? I'le be your Midwife.</L>
<STAGE>Exit with Clara!</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ped.</SPEAKER>
<L>What mean you Gentlemen?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Villaines, Thieves, Murderers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ped.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do you know me? Iam <HI>De Cortes, Pedro de Cortes!</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>De Cortes, Diego,</HI> come away.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ped.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Clara,</HI> where is my Daughter?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Clara</HI> I these Villaines</L>
<L>Have rob'd us of our comfort, and will, I feare,</L>
<L>Her of her honour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ped.</SPEAKER>
<L>This had not wont</L>
<L>To be our Spanish Fashion, but now our Gallants,</L>
<L>Our Gentry, our young Dons heated with Wine,</L>
<L>(A fire our Country-men doe seldome sit at)</L>
<L>Commit these outrages, <HI>Clara!—Maria,</HI></L>
<L>Let's homeward, I will raise <HI>Madrill</HI> to finde</L>
<L>These traytors to all goodness, <HI>Clara.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ma. Clara. Exit. Enter Lewys and Diego.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh <HI>Diego</HI> I am lost, I am mad!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Die.</SPEAKER>
<L>So we are all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="4"/>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis not with wine, i'me drunk with too much horror,</L>
<L>Inflam'd with rage, to see us two made Bawds</L>
<L>To <HI>Roderigo's</HI> lust, did not the old man</L>
<L>Name <HI>Decortes, Pedro de Cortes?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Die.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sure he did.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh <HI>Diego,</HI> as thou lov'st me, nay on the forfeit</L>
<L>Of thine own life or mine, seale up thy lips,</L>
<L>Let 'em not name <HI>De Cortes,</HI> stay, stay, stay,</L>
<L><HI>Roderigo</HI> has into his Fathers house</L>
<L>A passage through a Garden.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Die.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thither I must finde <HI>Roderigo</HI> out,</L>
<L>And check him, ckeck him home, if he but dare</L>
<L>No more; <HI>Diego</HI> along my soule does fight</L>
<L>A thousand battailes blacker then this night.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Roderigo and Claria.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tho the black veyle of night hath over-clowded</L>
<L>The World in darknesse, yet e're many howers</L>
<L>The Sun will rise again, and then this act</L>
<L>Of my dishonor will appear before you;</L>
<L>More black then is the Canopy that shrowds it,</L>
<L>What are you, pray what are you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Husht, a friend! a friend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>A friend, be then a gentle Ravisher,</L>
<L>An honorable villaine, as you have</L>
<L>Disroab'd my youth of natures goodliest portion,</L>
<L>My Virgin purity, so with your Sword</L>
<L>Let out that blood which is infected now,</L>
<L>By your soule-stayning lust.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pish.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you noble?</L>
<L>I know you then will marry me, say.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Umh.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not speak to me! are want on Divells dumbe?</L>
<L>How are so many harmelesse Virgins wrought</L>
<L>By falshood of prevailing words to yeild</L>
<L>To easie forfeits of their shames and liberty,</L>
<L>If every Orator of folly plead</L>
<L>In silence, like this untongu'd piece of violence?</L>
<L>

<PB REF="5"/>
You shall not from me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Phew no more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall not,</L>
<L>Who e're you are, Disease of natures sloth:</L>
<L>Birth of some monstrous sinne, or scourge of virtue,</L>
<L>Heavens wrath and mankinds burthen, I will hold you,</L>
<L>I will, be rough and therein mercifull,</L>
<L>I will not loose my hold else.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>There, 'tis gold.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gold, why! alas for what? the hire of pleasure,</L>
<L>Perhaps is payment, mine is misery;</L>
<L>I need no wages for a ruin'd name,</L>
<L>More then a bleeding heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay then y'are troublesome,</L>
<L>I'le lock you safe enough.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>They cannot feare</L>
<L>Whom grief hath arm'd with hate and scorn of life.</L>
<L>Revenge I kneele to thee, alas'gainst whom?</L>
<L>By what name shall I pull Confusion down</L>
<L>From Justice on his head that hath betrayd me?</L>
<L>I know not where I am, up I beseech thee</L>
<L>Thou Lady regent of the aire, the Moon,</L>
<L>And lead me by thy light to some brave vengeance,</L>
<L>It is a Chamber sure, the guilty Bed.</L>
<L>Sad evidence against my losse of honour</L>
<L>Assures so much, what's here, a window curtaine?</L>
<L>Oh Heaven! the stars appeare 'too, ha! a chamber,</L>
<L>A goodly one, dwells Rape in such a paradice!</L>
<L>Help me my quickned senses, 'tis a garden</L>
<L>To which this window guides the covetous prospect,</L>
<L>A large one and a faire one, in the midst</L>
<L>A curious Alablaster Fountaine stands,</L>
<L>Fram'd like-like what? no matter, swift remembrance,</L>
<L>Rich furniture within too! and what's this?</L>
<L>A precious Crucifix? I have enough,</L>
<L>Assist me oh you powers that guard the innocent.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Roderigo.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Welcome, if you come arm'd in destruction,</L>
<L>

<PB REF="5"/>
I am prepar'd to die.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tell me your Name,</L>
<L>And what you are.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>You urge me to a sinne</L>
<L>As cruell as your lust, I dare not grant it,</L>
<L>Thinke on the violence of my defame,</L>
<L>And if you meane to write upon my Grave</L>
<L>An Epitaph of peace, forbear to question,</L>
<L>Or whence, or who I am; I know the heate</L>
<L>Of your desires are after the performance</L>
<L>Of such a hellish act, by this time drown'd</L>
<L>In cooler streams of penance; and for my part</L>
<L>I have wash'd off the Leaprosie that cleaves</L>
<L>To my just shame, in true and honest teares;</L>
<L>I must not leave a mention of my wrongs,</L>
<L>The staine of my unspotted birth to memory,</L>
<L>Let it lie buried with me in the dust,</L>
<L>That never time hereafter may report</L>
<L>How such a one as you have made mee live;</L>
<L>Be resolute, and do not stagger, doe not,</L>
<L>For I am nothing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweet let me enjoy thee</L>
<L>Now with a free allowance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, enjoy me!</L>
<L>Insufferable villaine!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace: speak low,</L>
<L>I meane no second force, and since I find</L>
<L>Such goodness in an unknown frame of virtus:</L>
<L>Forgive my soule attempt, which I shall grieve for</L>
<L>So hartily, that could you be your self</L>
<L>Eye-witness to my constant vow'd repentance,</L>
<L>Trust me you'd pitty me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, you can speak now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>So much I am the Executioner</L>
<L>Of mine own trespasse, that I have no heart,</L>
<L>Nor reason to disclose my name or quality;</L>
<L>You must excuse me that, but trust me (faire one)</L>
<L>Were this ill deede undone, this deed of wickednesse,</L>
<L>I would be proud to court your love like him,</L>
<L>Whom my first birth presented to the World: this for your satisfacti∣on,</L>
<L>

<PB REF="6"/>
What remaines, that you can challenge as a service from me?</L>
<L>I both expect and beg it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>First, that you swear neither</L>
<L>In riot of your Mirth, in Passion</L>
<L>Of Friendship, or in folly of Discourse,</L>
<L>To speak of wrongs done to a ravish'd Maide.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>As I love truth I sweare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Next that you leade me</L>
<L>Neere to the place you met me, and there leave me</L>
<L>To my last fortunes e're the morning rise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Say more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lay a new man, if e're you marry</L>
<L>(Oh me! my heart's a breaking) but if e're</L>
<L>You marry in a constant love to her</L>
<L>That shall be then your Wife, redeem the fault</L>
<L>Of my undoing, I am lost for ever,</L>
<L>Pray use no more words.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>You must give me leave</L>
<L>To veile you close.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do what you will, no time</L>
<L>Can ransome me from sorrows or dishonors,</L>
<L>Shall we now goe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>My shame may live without me,</L>
<L>But in my soul I beare my guilt about me,</L>
<L>Lend me your hand, now follow.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Lewys, Diego, and a servant.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not yet come in, not yet?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>No i'le assure your Lordship, I have seldom known</L>
<L>Him keep out so long, my Lord usually observes</L>
<L>More seasonable houres.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>What time of night is't?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>On the stroake of three.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>The stroake of three! 'tis wondrous strange!</L>
<L>Dost heare?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>E're six I will be here againe,</L>
<L>Tell thy Lord so: e're six,—a must not sleepe,</L>
<L>Or if a doe, I shall be bold to wake him:</L>
<L>Be sure thou tell'st him—doe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="6"/>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord I shall.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Diego.</HI></L>
<L>Walke thou the street that leads about the Perado,</L>
<L>I'le round the West part of the City, meet me</L>
<L>At the Inquisition Chappell; if we misse him</L>
<L>Wee'l both back to his Lodgings.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Die.</SPEAKER>
<L>At the Chappell?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>I there wee'l meete.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Die.</SPEAKER>
<L>Agreed, I this way.</L>
<STAGE>Exit. Lewys.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Don Iohn <HI>Reading.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Jo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee is not noble, true, wise nature meant</L>
<L>Affection should enable her discent,</L>
<L>For love and beauty keeps as rich a seat</L>
<L>Of sweetnesse in the meane borne, as the great—</L>
<L>I am resolv'd.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Die.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis <HI>Roderigo</HI> certainly,</L>
<L>Yet his voyce makes me doubt, but I'le o're-hear him</L>
<STAGE>Ex.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Lewys.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>That if only I should be the Man</L>
<L>Made accessary, and a party both</L>
<L>To mine own torment, at a time so neere</L>
<L>The birth of all those comforts I have travell'd with,</L>
<L>So many, many howers of hopes and fears;</L>
<L>Now at the instant—Ha, stand! thy name,</L>
<L>Truly and speedily.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Roderigo.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Don Lewys!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>The same; but who art thou—speake?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Roderigo.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tell mee,</L>
<L>As y'are a noble Gentleman, as ever</L>
<L>You hope to be enrowl'd amongst the vertuous,</L>
<L>As you love goodnesse, as you wish to inherit</L>
<L>The blessednesse and fellowship of Angels,</L>
<L>As you are my friend, as you are <HI>Roderigo,</HI></L>
<L>As you are any thing that would deserve</L>
<L>A worthy name, where have you been to night?</L>
<L>Oh! how have you dispos'd of that faire Creature</L>
<L>

<PB REF="7"/>
Whom you led captive from me, speak, oh speak,</L>
<L>Where, how, when, in what usage have you left her?</L>
<L>Truth I require all truth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tho I might question</L>
<L>The strangenesse of your importunity;</L>
<L>Yet cause I note distraction in the height</L>
<L>Of curiosity, I will be plaine, and briefe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lu.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thank you sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Instead of feeding</L>
<L>Too wantonly upon so rich a Banquet,</L>
<L>I found even in that beauty that invited me</L>
<L>Such a commanding majesty of chaste</L>
<L>And humbly glorious vertue, that it did not</L>
<L>More check my rash attempt, then draw to ebb</L>
<L>The float of those desires, which in an instant</L>
<L>Were cool'd in their own streames of shame and folly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now all encrease of honours.</L>
<L>Fall in full showers on thee <HI>Roderigo,</HI></L>
<L>The best man living.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are much transported</L>
<L>With this discourse methinks.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, <HI>I</HI> am.</L>
<L>Shee tould yee her Name too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>I could not urge it</L>
<L>By any importunity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Better still;</L>
<L>Where did you leave her?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where <HI>I</HI> found her, farther</L>
<L>Shee would by no means grant me to waite on her,</L>
<L>Oh <HI>Luys</HI> I am lost.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lu.</SPEAKER>
<L>This selfe-same Lady</L>
<L>Was shee to whom <HI>I</HI> have been long a Suiter,</L>
<L>And shortly hope to marry.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee your Mistris then? <HI>Luys,</HI> since friendship,</L>
<L>And noble honesty conjures our loves</L>
<L>To a continued league, here <HI>I</HI> unclaspe</L>
<L>The secrets of my heart. Oh I have had</L>
<L>A glimpse of such a Creature, that deserves</L>
<L>A Temple, if thou lov'st her, (and <HI>I</HI> blame thee not)</L>
<L>For who can look on her, and not give up</L>
<L>

<PB REF="7"/>
His life unto her service? if thou lov'st her,</L>
<L>For pitties sake conceale her; let me not</L>
<L>As much as know her Name, there's a temption in't,</L>
<L>Let me not know herDwelling, Birth or Quality,</L>
<L>Or any thing that she calls hers, but thee</L>
<L>In thee my friend, I'le see her, and to avoyd</L>
<L>The surfeits and those rarities that tempt me,</L>
<L>So much I prize the happiness of friendship,</L>
<L>That I will leave the City.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Leave it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speede me!</L>
<L>For <HI>Salamanca,</HI> court my studies now</L>
<L>For Phisick 'gainst infection of the minde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>You doe amaze me!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here to live, and live</L>
<L>Without her, is impossible and wretched.</L>
<L>For Heavens sake never tell her what I was,</L>
<L>Or that you know me, and when I finde that absence</L>
<L>Hath lost her to my, memory, I'le dare</L>
<L>To see yee againemeane time the cause that drawes mee</L>
<L>From hence, shall be to all the World untol'd;</L>
<L>No friend but thou alone, for whose sake only</L>
<L>I undertake this voluntary exile</L>
<L>Shall be partaker of my griefes; thy hand</L>
<L>Farwell: and all the pleasures, joyes, contents</L>
<L>That blesse a constant Lover, henceforth crown thee</L>
<L>A happy Bridegroom.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have conquer'd friendship</L>
<L>Beyond example.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Diego.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Die.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, ha, ha! some one</L>
<L>That hath slept well to night, should a but see mee</L>
<L>Thus merry by my selfe, might justly think</L>
<L>I were not well in my wits.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Diego!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Die.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes 'tis I, and I have had a fine fegary,</L>
<L>The rarest, Wild-goose chase.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thad made thee melancholy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Die.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Don Roderigo</HI> here? 'tis well you met him;</L>
<L>For tho I mist him, yet I met an accident</L>
<L>

<PB REF="8"/>
Has almost made me burst with laughter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>How so?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Die.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le tell you, as we parted, I perceiv'd</L>
<L>A walking thing before me strangely tickled</L>
<L>With rare conceited raptures, him I dogg'd,</L>
<L>Supposing 'thad been <HI>Roderigo</HI> landed</L>
<L>From his new Pinnace, deepe in contemplation</L>
<L>Of the sweet voyage he stole to night.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'are pleasant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prithee who was't?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Die.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'ate i' the right, not you indeed;</L>
<L>For 'twas that noble Gentleman <HI>Don John,</HI></L>
<L>Son to the Counte <HI>Francisco de Carcomo.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>In love it seems.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Die.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, pepperd on my life,</L>
<L>Much good may't do him, Ide not be so lind</L>
<L>For my Cap full of double Pistolets.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>What should his Mistris be?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Die.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's yet a Riddle</L>
<L>Beyond my resolution, but of late</L>
<L>I have observ'd him oft to frequent</L>
<L>The sports the <HI>Gipsies</HI> newly come to th'City present.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis said there is a Creature with'em,</L>
<L>Tho young of years, yet of such absolute beauty,</L>
<L>Dexterity of wit, and generall qualities,</L>
<L>That Spaine reports her not without admiration.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Die.</SPEAKER>
<L>Have you seen her?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Never.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Die.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor you my Lord?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>I not remember.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Die.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why then you never saw the prettiest toy</L>
<L>That ever Sung or Danc'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is shee a Gipsie?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Die.</SPEAKER>
<L>In her condition, not in her complexion.</L>
<L>I tell you once more, 'tis a sparke of beauty</L>
<L>Able to set a World at gaze, the sweetest,</L>
<L>The wittiest rogue, shalls see 'em? they have fine gambolls,</L>
<L>Are mightily frequented, Court and City</L>
<L>Flock to 'em, but the Country does 'em worship.</L>
<L>

<PB REF="8"/>
This little Ape gets money by the sack full,</L>
<L>It troules upon her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will yee with us friend?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>You know my other projects, sights to me</L>
<L>Are but vexations.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh you must be merry,</L>
<L><HI>Diego,</HI> wee'l toth' Gipsies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Die.</SPEAKER>
<L>Best take heed</L>
<L>You be not snap'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>How snap'd?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Die.</SPEAKER>
<L>By that little Faire,</L>
<L>'Thas a shrewd tempting Face, and a notable Tongue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>I fear not either.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Die.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>will you with us?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le come after.</L>
<L>Pleasure and youth like smiling evills wooe us,</L>
<L>To taste new follies; tasted, they undoe us.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACTUS SECUNDUS.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Alvarez, Carlo, and Antonio.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come my brave boyes, the Taylors sheers has cut us into shapes fitting our Trades.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<P>A trade free as a Masons.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>A trade brave as a Courtiers, for some of them doe but shark, and so do we.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gipsies, but no tann'd ones, no Red-oker rascalls umberd with soot and bacon as the English Gipsies are, that sally out upon Pullen, lie in ambuscado for a rope of Onions, as if they were Welsh Free-booters; no, our stile has higher steps to climbe over, Spanish Gipsies, noble Gipsies.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<P>I never knew nobility in basenes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Basenes! the arts of <HI>Cocoquismo,</HI> and <HI>Germania</HI> us'd by our Spanish Pickeroes (I meane Filching, Foysting, Niming, Iilting) we defie; none in our Colledge shall study 'em, such Graduates we degrade.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>An.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am glad Spaine has an honest company.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="9"/>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee'l entertaine no Mounty-bancking Stroule,</L>
<L>No Piper, Fidler, Tumbler through small hoopes;</L>
<L>No Ape carrier, Baboon bearer,</L>
<L>We must have nothing stale, triviall or base:</L>
<L>Am I your <HI>Major domo,</HI> your <HI>Teniente,</HI></L>
<L>Your Captaine, your Commander?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>An.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who but you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<P>So then, now being enter'd <HI>Madrill</HI> the inchanted Circle of Spaine, have a care to your new Lessons.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Both.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wee listen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<P>Plow deepe furrowes, to catch deep root in th' opinion of the best, <HI>Grandos,</HI> Dukes, Marquesses, Condes, and other Titulados, shew your sports to none but them, what can you doe with 3. or 4. Fooles in a dish, and a block-head cut into sippets?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>An.</SPEAKER>
<P>Scurvy meate.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<P>The <HI>Lacedemonians</HI> threw their Beards over their shoulders, to observe what men did behinde them as well as before, you must do.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Both.</SPEAKER>
<P>We shall never doo't, our muzzles are too short.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<P>Be not English Gipsies, in whose companie a man's not sure of the eares of his head they so pilfer; no such angling; what you pull to Land catch faire; there is no Iron so foule but may be guilded, and our Gipsie profession how base soever in shew, may acquire com∣mendations.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gipsies, and yet pick no pockets?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<P>Infamous and roguy, so handle your Webbs, that they never come to be woven in the Loome of Justice, take any thing that's given you, Purses, Knives, Handkerchers, Rosaries, Tweezes, any toy, any money, refuse not a Maruade, a blanck, Feather by Feather birds build Nests, graine peckd up after graine, makes Pullen fat.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>An.</SPEAKER>
<P>The best is we Spaniards are no great feeders.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<P>If one City cannot maintaine us, away to another, our horses must have wings; does <HI>Madrill</HI> yeild no money? <HI>Sivell</HI> shall; is <HI>Sivell</HI> close fisted? <HI>Vallidoly</HI> is open; so <HI>Cordica,</HI> so <HI>Toledo:</HI> doe not our Spanish Wines please us? Italian can then, French can, preferments bow is hard to draw, set all your strengths to it, what you get, keep, all the World is a second <HI>Rochill,</HI> make all sure, for you must not look to have your Dinner serv'd in with Trumpets.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, no, Sackbuts shall serve us.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ala.</SPEAKER>
<P>When you have money, hide it; sell all our horses but one.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why one?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="9"/>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis enough to carry our apparell and trinkets and the lesse our ambler eates, our cheere is the better; none be fluttish, none theevish, none lazy, all Bees, no Drones, and our hives shall yeild us Honey.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Eugenia, Pretiosa, Christiana, Cardochia.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pre.</SPEAKER>
<P>See Father, how I am fitted; how do you like This our new stock of cloaths?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<P>My sweet Girle excellent; see their old robes be safe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>That sir, I'le looke to,</L>
<L>Whilst in my house you lie, what thiefe so ever</L>
<L>Layes hands upon your goods, call but to me</L>
<L>I'le make the satisfaction.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thanks good Hostesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>People already throng into the Inne,</L>
<L>And call for you into their private rooms.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<P>No Chamber Comedies, Hostesse plie you your tide; flow let 'em to a full Sea, but wee'l shew no pastime till after dinner, and that in a full ring of good people, the best, the noblest, no closset sweet meates, pray tell 'em so.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<P>I shall. <STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alu.</SPEAKER>
<P>How old is <HI>Pretiosa?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eug.</SPEAKER>
<P>Twelve and upwards.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pre.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am in my teenes assure you Mother, as little as I am, I have been taken for an Elephant, Castles and Lordships offer'd to be set upon me, if I would beare 'em; Why your smallest Clocks are the pretiest things to carry about Gentlemen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eug.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay Child thou wilt be tempted.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pre.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tempted! tho I am no marke in respect of a huge But, yet I can tell you great bubbers have shot at me, and shot golden Arrowes, but I my selfe gave ayme, thus; wide, foure Bowes; short, three and a halfe; they that crack me shall finde me as hard as a Nut of <HI>Galisia,</HI> a Parrot I am, but my teeth too tender to crack a wantons Almond.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art my noble Girle, amany Dons</L>
<L>Will not believe but that thou art a Boy</L>
<L>In Womens Cloaths, and to try that conclusion</L>
<L>To see if thou beest <HI>Alcumy,</HI> or no,</L>
<L>They'l throw down Gold in Musses, but <HI>Pretiesa</HI></L>
<L>Let these proud Sakers and Jer-falcons flie,</L>
<L>Do not thou move a wing, be to thy selfe,</L>
<L>And not a changeling.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pre.</SPEAKER>
<L>How! not a Changeling!</L>
<L>

<PB REF="10"/>
Yes Father, I will play the changeling,</L>
<L>I'le change my selfe into a thousand shapes</L>
<L>To court our brave Spectators; I'le change my postures</L>
<L>Into a thousand different variations,</L>
<L>To draw even Ladies eyes to follow mine;</L>
<L>I'le change my voyce into a thousand tones</L>
<L>To chaine attention; not a changeling Father,</L>
<L>None but my selfe shall play the changeling.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do what thou wilt <HI>Pretiosa.</HI></L>
<L>What noise is this?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>A beating within. Enter Cardochia.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here's Gentlemen swear all the oaths in Spaine they have seen you, must see you, and will see you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<P>To drown this noyse let 'em enter.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Sancho and Soto.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is your Play-house an Inne? a Gentleman cannot see you with∣out crumpling his Taffaty cloake.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay more then a Gentleman, his man being a deminitive Don too.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is this the little ape does the fine tricks?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pre.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come aloft Jack little ape!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>Would my Jack might come aloft, please you to set the water Mill, with the Ivory cogs in't a grinding my handfull of purging comfetts.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Master desires to have you loose from your company.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ped.</SPEAKER>
<P>Am I a Pigeon thinke you to be caught with Cummin-seeds? a flie to glew my wings to sweete-meates and so be tane?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>When do your gambolls begin?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not till we ha din'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>Foote then your bellies will be so full you'l be able to do no∣thing, <HI>Soto</HI> prithee set a good face on't for I cannot, and give the little Monkey that Letter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<P>Walke off and hum to your selfe: I dedicate (sweet destiny, into whose hand every Spaniard desires to put a Distaffe) these lines of Love.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<P>What Love, what's the matter?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<P>Grave Mother <HI>Bumby</HI> the markes out a your mouth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<P>What's the Paper, from whom comes it?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<P>The comodity wrapd up in the Paper, are Verses, the warm∣ing Pan that puts heat into 'em, you fire-braind bastard of <HI>Helicon.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="10"/>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<P>What's your Masters Name?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<P>His name is <HI>Don Tomazo Portacareco,</HI> Nunckle to young <HI>Don Hortado de Mendonza,</HI> Cosen german to the <HI>Conde de Tindilla,</HI> and naturall brother to <HI>Francisco de Bavadilla,</HI> one of the Commendadors of <HI>Aleantaro,</HI> a Gentleman of long standing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pre.</SPEAKER>
<P>Verses! I love good ones, let me see 'em.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good ones! if they were not good ones, they should not come from mee, at the name of Verses I can stand on no ground.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pre.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here's gold too, who's is this?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whoe's but yours? if there been any fault in the Verses, I can mend it <HI>extempore;</HI> for a stich in a mans stocken not taken up in time ravells out all the rest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<P>Botcherly Poetry, botcherly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pre.</SPEAKER>
<P>Verses and gold! these then are golden Verses.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>Had every Verse a Pearle in the eye it should be thine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pre.</SPEAKER>
<P>A pearle in mine eye! I thanke you for that, doe you wish mee blinde?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>I by this light doe I, that you may look upon nobodies crime but mine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pre.</SPEAKER>
<P>I should be blind indeede!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray Sir read your Verses.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shall I sing 'em or say 'em?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<P>Which you can best.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<P>Both scurvily.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le set out a throate then.</L>
<L><HI>Oh that I were a Bee to sing</HI></L>
<L><HI>Hum buz, buz, hum, I first would bring</HI></L>
<L><HI>Home Honey to your Hive, and there leave my sting.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<P>He manders.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Oh that I were a Goose to feede</HI></L>
<L><HI>At your barne-dore, such Corne I need,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Nor would I bite, but Gozlings breede.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<P>And Ganders.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Oh that I were your Need'les eye,</HI></L>
<L><HI>How through your Linnen would I flie;</HI></L>
<L><HI>And never leave one stich awry!</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hee'l towze yee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Oh would I were one of your haires,</HI></L>
<L><HI>That you might combe out all my cares;</HI></L>
<L><HI>And kill the Nits of my dspaires,</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh Lowzie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="11"/>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>How! Lowzie I can Rimes be Lowzie?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, no, th'are excellent.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<P>But are these all your own?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mine own! wud I might never see Inck drop out of the nose of any Goose quil more, if velvet Cloaks have not clap'd me for 'em, doe you like 'em?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pre.</SPEAKER>
<L>Past all compare, they shall be writ out</L>
<L>When y'have as good or better.</L>
<L>For these and those pray booke me down your debtor.</L>
<L>Your Paper is long liv'd, having two soules,</L>
<L>Verses and Gold.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>Would both those were in thee pritty little body, sweets Gipsie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pre.</SPEAKER>
<P>A Pistolet and this Paper, 'twould choake me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<P>No more then a bribe does a Constable; the Verses will easily into your head, then buy what you like with the Gold, and put it into your belly, I hope I ha chaw'd a good reason for you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>Will you chaw my Jennet ready sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<P>And eate him down if you say the word. <STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now the coxcombe my man is gon, because y'are but a Country company of Strowles, I thinke your stock is thred-bare, here mend it with this Cloake.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<P>What do you meane sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>This Scarfe, this Feather, and this Hat.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<P>Deare Signior.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>If they be never so deare, pox'o this hot Ruffe; little Gipsie, wear thou that.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your meaning sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>My meaning is not to be an Asse, to carry a burthen when I need not, if you shew your Gambols forty Leagues hence, I'le gallop to 'em; Farwel old Gray-beard, adue Mother mumble-crust, morrow my little Wart of beauty. <STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Don John Muffled.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<P>So harvest will come in, such Sunshine days Will bring in golden sheafes, our Markets raise, Away to your taske. <STAGE>Exit. Don John pulls Pretiosa back.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pre.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mother, Grand-mother!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Jo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Two rowes of Kindred in one mouth!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Be not uncivill sir, thus have you us'd her thrice.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Jo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thrice! three thousand more: may I not use mine own?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="11"/>
<SPEAKER>Pre.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your own! by what tenure?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Jo.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Cupid</HI> entailes this Land upon me, I have wooed thee, thou are coy, by this aire I am a Bull of <HI>Tarisa,</HI> wild, mad for thee: you told I was some copper coyne, I am a Knight of <HI>Spaine, Don Fran∣cisco de Carcomo</HI> my Father, I <HI>Don John</HI> his Sonne, this paper tells you more, grumble not old Granam, (heeres gold) for I must by this white hand, marry this cherry-lip'd, sweet-mouth'd villaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pre.</SPEAKER>
<P>There's a thing call'd <HI>quando.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Jo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Instantly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Art thou so willing?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Jo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Peace threescore and five.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pre.</SPEAKER>
<P>Marry me! eate a Chicken e're it be out o'th shell! I'le weare no shackles, liberty is sweet; that I have, that I'le hold, marry me! can Gold and Lead mix together? a Dimond, &amp; a button of Christal fit one ring? you are too high for me, I am too low; you too great, I too little.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<P>I pray leave her sir, and take your Gold againe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pre.</SPEAKER>
<P>Or if you dote, as you say, let me try you do this.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Jo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Any thing, kill the great Turke, pluck out the Magul's Eye∣teeth; in earnest <HI>Pretiosa</HI> any thing!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pre.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your taste is soon set down, turne Gipsie for two years, be one of us, if in that time you mislike not me, nor I you, here's my hand farwell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<P>There's enough for your Gold, witty Child. <STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Jo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Turne Gipsie I for two years! a capering Trade.</L>
<L>And I in th'end may keepe a dancing Schoole,</L>
<L>Having serv'd for't, Gipsie! I must turne,</L>
<L>Oh beauty! the Suns fires cannot so burne.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Clara.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have offended, yet oh Heaven! thou knowst</L>
<L>How much I have abhor'd even from my birth,</L>
<L>A thought that tended to immodest folly;</L>
<L>Yet I have fallen, thoughts with disgraces strive,</L>
<L>And thus I live, and thus I die alive.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Pedro, and Maria.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pe.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fie <HI>Clara,</HI> thou dost court calamity too much.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes Girle, thou dost.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why should we fret our eyes out with our teares?</L>
<L>Weary complaints, 'tis fruitlesse, childish,</L>
<L>Impatience, for when mischiefe hath wound up</L>
<L>The full weight of the Ravishers foul Life,</L>
<L>

<PB REF="12"/>
To an equall height of ripe iniquity,</L>
<L>The poyse will by degrees, sinke down his Soule</L>
<L>To a much lower, much more lasting ruine</L>
<L>Then our joynt wrongs can challenge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ped.</SPEAKER>
<L>Darknesse it selfe</L>
<L>Will change nights sable brow, into a Sun-beame</L>
<L>For a discovery, and be sure</L>
<L>When ever we can learne what monster 'twas</L>
<L>Hath rob'd thee of the Jewell held so precious,</L>
<L>Our vengeance shall be noble.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Royall, any thing;</L>
<L>Till then lets live securely: to proclaime</L>
<L>Our sadnesse were meere vanity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>A needs not,</L>
<L>I'le study to be merry.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pe.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are punish'd</L>
<L><HI>Maria</HI> justly, covetousnesse to match</L>
<L>Our Daughter to that matchlesse piece of ignorance,</L>
<L>Our foolish Ward, hath drawn this curse upon us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>I feare it has!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Off with this face of griefe.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Lewys, and Diego.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Die.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here comes Don <HI>Lewys;</HI> noble sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord,</L>
<L>I trust I have you and your Ladies leave</L>
<L>To exchange a word with your faire Daughter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Leave and welcome, harke <HI>Maria,</HI> your eare too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Die.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mine my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Deare <HI>Clara,</HI> I have often su'd for Love,</L>
<L>And now desire you would at last be pleas'd</L>
<L>To stile me yours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mine eyes ne'r saw that Gentleman</L>
<L>Whom I more nobly in my heart respected,</L>
<L>Then I have you, yet you must Sir excuse me,</L>
<L>If I resolve to use a while that freedome</L>
<L>My younger dayes allow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>But shall I hope?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>You will do injury to better fortunes</L>
<L>To your own Merit, Greatnesse, and Advancement,</L>
<L>Which I beseech you not to slack.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="12"/>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then heare me,</L>
<L>If ever I embrace another choyce,</L>
<L>Untill I know you elsewhere match'd, may all</L>
<L>The chiefe of my Desires finde scorne and ruine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh me!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why figh you Lady?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Deede my Lord I am not well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then all Discourse is tedious,</L>
<L>I'le chuse some fitter time; till when faire <HI>Clara.—</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall not be unwelcome hither sir;</L>
<L>That's all that I dare promise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Diego!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Die.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>What says <HI>Don Pedro?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Die.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee'l goe with you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Leave us:</L>
<L>Shall I my Lord, entreate your privacy?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Withdraw <HI>Maria,</HI> wee'l follow presently,</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>The great Corigidor, whose politick streame</L>
<L>Of popularity, glides on the shore</L>
<L>Of every vulgar praise, hath often urged me</L>
<L>To be a Suitor to his Catholick Majesty,</L>
<L>For a repeale from banishment for him</L>
<L>Who slew my Father, complements in vowes,</L>
<L>And strange well studied promises of friendship,</L>
<L>But what is new to mee, still as he Courts</L>
<L>Assistance for <HI>Alvarez</HI> my grand enemy,</L>
<L>Still he protests how ignorant he is,</L>
<L>Whether <HI>Alvarez</HI> be alive or dead?</L>
<L>To morrow is the day we have appointed</L>
<L>For meeting at the Lord <HI>Francisco's</HI> house,</L>
<L>The Earle of <HI>Carcomo;</HI> now my good Lord,</L>
<L>The sum of my request is, you will please</L>
<L>To lend your presence there, and witnesse wherein</L>
<L>Our joynt accord consists.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ped.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall command it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>But first as you are noble, I beseech you</L>
<L>Helpe mee with your advice, what you conceave</L>
<L>Of great <HI>Fernando's</HI> importunity,</L>
<L>Or whether you imagine that <HI>Alvarez</HI></L>
<L>

<PB REF="13"/>
Survive or not?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pe.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is a question sir</L>
<L>Beyond my resolution, I remember</L>
<L>The difference betwixt your noble Father,</L>
<L>And <HI>Conde de Alvarez,</HI> how it sprung</L>
<L>From a meer trifle first, a cast of Hawks,</L>
<L>Whose made the swifter flight, whose could mount highest,</L>
<L>Lie longest on the wing. From change of words</L>
<L>Their controversie grew to blows, from blowes</L>
<L>To Parties, thence to Faction, and in short</L>
<L>I well remember how our streets were frighted</L>
<L>With brawles, whose end was bloud, till when no friends</L>
<L>Could mediate their discords: by the King</L>
<L>A reconciliation was enforc'd,</L>
<L>Death threaten'd the first occasioner</L>
<L>Of breach, besides the confiscation</L>
<L>Of Lands and Honours, yet at last they met</L>
<L>Againe; againe they drew to sides, renew'd</L>
<L>Their ancient quarrell, in which dismall uprore</L>
<L>Your Father hand to hand fell by <HI>Alvarez,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Alvarez</HI> fled, and after him the doome</L>
<L>Of exile was set out; He as Report</L>
<L>Was bold to voyce, retir'd himselfe to <HI>Rhodes,</HI></L>
<L>His Lands and Honours by the King bestow'd</L>
<L>On you, but then an Infant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, an Infant!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pe.</SPEAKER>
<L>His Wife the sister to the <HI>Corigidor,</HI></L>
<L>With a young Daughter, and some few that follow'd her</L>
<L>By stealth were shipt for <HI>Rhodes,</HI> and by a storme</L>
<L>Ship-wrack'd at Sea, but for the banish'd <HI>Conde,</HI></L>
<L>'Twas never yet known what became of him,</L>
<L>Here's all I can informe you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>A repeale,</L>
<L>Yes, I will sue for't, beg for't, buy it, any thing</L>
<L>That may by possibility of friends,</L>
<L>Or Money, I'le attempt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pe.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis a brave charity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas poore Lady, I could mourne for her!</L>
<L>Her losse was Usury more then I covet;</L>
<L>But for the Man, I'de sell my patrimony</L>
<L>

<PB REF="13"/>
For his repeale, and run about the World</L>
<L>To finde him out, there is no peace can dwell</L>
<L>About my Fathers Tombe, till I have sacrific'd</L>
<L>Some portion of revenge to his wrong'd ashes.</L>
<L>You will along with me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pe.</SPEAKER>
<L>You neede not question it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have strange thoughts about me, two such furies</L>
<L>Revell amidst my joyes as well may move</L>
<L>Distraction in a Saint, Vengance and Love,</L>
<L>I'le follow sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray lead the way: you know it.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Sancho, and Soto.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now! from whence come you sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>From fleaing my selfe sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<P>From playing with Fencers sir, and they have beat him out of his Cloaths sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cloake, Band, Rapier, all lost at Dice!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor Cards neither.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<P>This was one of my Masters dog-dayes, and he would not sweat too much.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>It was mine own Goose, and I laid the Jiblets upon an other Coxcombs trencher, you are my Gardian, best beg me for a fool now.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<L>He that begs one begs tother.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Does any Gentleman give away his things thus?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, and Gentlewomen give away their things too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<L>To Gulls sometimes, and are Cony-catch'd for their labour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wilt thou ever play the Coxcombe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>If no other parts be given me, what would you have me do?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy Father was as brave a Spaniard</L>
<L>As ever spake the haute <HI>Castilian</HI> Tongue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>Put me in Cloaths, I'le be as brave as he.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pe.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is the ninth time thou hast plaid the Asse,</L>
<L>Flinging away thy trappings and thy cloath</L>
<L>To cover others, and goe nak'd thy selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le make 'em up ten, because I'le be even with you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Once more your broken walls shall have new hangings.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<L>To be well hung, is all our desire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pe.</SPEAKER>
<L>And what course take you next?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>What course? why my man <HI>Soto</HI> and I wil go make some maps.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pe.</SPEAKER>
<L>What maps?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="14"/>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not such Mapps as you wash houses with, but Mapps of Countries.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>I have an Unckle in <HI>Sivell,</HI> I'le go see him, an Aunt in <HI>Siena</HI> in <HI>Italy,</HI> I goe see her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Cosen of mine in <HI>Rome,</HI> I goe to him with a Morter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>There's a Curtizan in <HI>Venice,</HI> I'le goe tickle her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Another in <HI>England;</HI> I'le goe tackle her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pe.</SPEAKER>
<L>So, so, and where's the money to do all this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>If my wookes being cut down cannot fill this Pocket, cut 'em into Trapsticks.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<P>And if his Acres being sould for a <HI>Maruedi,</HI> a Turffe for markes in Cages, cannot fill this Pocket, give 'em to Gold-finders.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pe.</SPEAKER>
<L>You'l gallop both to the Gallowes, so fareyou well.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>And be hang'd you, new cloaths y'ad best.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Foure cloaks, that you may give away three, and keep one.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee'l live as merrily as beggers, lets both turne Gipsies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<L>By any means, if they cog wee'l lie, if they tosse wee'l tumble.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>Both in a belly, rather then faile.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come then, wee'l be Gipsified.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>And tipsified too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<L>And we will shew such tricks, and such rare gambolls.</L>
<L>As shall put down the Elephant and Camels.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACTUS TERTIUS.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Roderigo Disguiz'd like an Italian.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>A thousand stings are in me! oh what vild prisons</L>
<L>Make we our bodies, to our immortall souls!</L>
<L>Brave Tenants to bad houses! 'tis a deare rent</L>
<L>They pay for naughty Lodging: the soule, the Mistresse,</L>
<L>The body, the Caroach that carries her,</L>
<L>Sinnes the swift wheeles that hurry her away;</L>
<L>Our Will the Coachman rashly driving on,</L>
<L>Till Coach and Carriage both are quite o're throwne;</L>
<L>My body yet scapes bruizes, that known thiefe</L>
<L>Is not yet cal'd toth' bar, there's no true sence</L>
<L>Of paine, but what the Law of conscience</L>
<L>

<PB REF="14"/>
Condemns us to, I feele that, who would loose</L>
<L>A Kingdome for a Cottage? an Estate</L>
<L>Of perpetuity, for a mans Life?</L>
<L>For annuity of that Life (pleasure) a sparke</L>
<L>To those Celestiall fires that burne about us!</L>
<L>A painted Star to that bright Firmament</L>
<L>Of constellations, which each night are set</L>
<L>Lighting our way, yet thither how few get?</L>
<L>How many thousand in <HI>Madrill</HI> drink off</L>
<L>The cup of lust, (and laughing) in one moneth</L>
<L>Not whining as I doe? should this sad Lady</L>
<L>Now meet me, do I know her? should this Temple</L>
<L>(By me prophan'd) lie in the ruines here,</L>
<L>The pieces would scarce shew her me:—would they did</L>
<L>Shee's Mistris to <HI>Don Lewys—</HI>by his steps,</L>
<L>And this disguise I'le finde her; to <HI>Salamanca</HI></L>
<L>Thy Father thinks th'art gon; no close here stay</L>
<L>Where e're thou travell'st, Scorpions stop thy way: these.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Sancho, and Soto as Gipsies.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Soto,</HI> how doe I shew?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Like a rusty Armor new scour'd, but Master how shew I?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>Like an Asse with a new pibal'd saddle on his back.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<P>If the Devil were a Taylor, he would scarce know us in these gaberdines.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>If a Taylor were the Divel, I'de not give a Lowse for him, if he should bring up this fashion amongst Gentlemen, and make it common.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>The freshnesse of the Morning be upon you both.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>The saltnesse of the Evening be upon you single.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be not displeas'd, that I abruptly thus</L>
<L>Breake in upon your favors, your strange habits</L>
<L>Invite me with desire, to understand</L>
<L>Both what you are, and whence, because no Country</L>
<L>(And I have measur'd some) shew me your like.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<P>Our like! no we should be sorry, we or our cloaths should be like fish, new, stale, and stinking in three days.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>If you aske whence we are, we are <HI>Egyptian</HI> Spaniards; if what, we are, <HI>ut, re, mi, fa, sol.</HI> Juglers, Tumblers, any thing any where, every where.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>A good fate hither leades me by the hand,</L>
<L>

<PB REF="15"/>
Your quality I love, the scenicall Schoole</L>
<L>Has been my Tutor long in <HI>Italy,</HI></L>
<L>(For that's my Country,) there have I put on</L>
<L>Sometimes the shape of a Comedian,</L>
<L>And now and then some other.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Player! a brother of the tyring house.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Bird of the same feather.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>Welcome, wut turne Gipsie?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>I can nor Dance, nor Sing, but if my Pen</L>
<L>From my invention can strike Musick tunes,</L>
<L>My head and braines are yours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Calves head and braines were better for my stomack.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>A rib of Poetry.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<L>A modicum of the Muses, a horse-shooe of <HI>Helicon.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>A Mag-py of <HI>Parnassin,</HI> welcome agen, I am a fire-brand of <HI>Phoebus</HI> my selfe, wee'l invoke together, so you will not steale my Plot.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis not my fashion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>But now adayes 'tis all the fashion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<L>What was the last thing you writ, a Comedy?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>No 'twas a sad, too sad a Tragedy.</L>
<L>Under these eves I'le shelter me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>See here comes our company,</L>
<L>Doe our tops spinne as you would have 'em?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<L>If not whip us round.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>I sent you a Letter to tell you we were upon a march.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Alvarez, Eugenia, Pretiosa, and the Gipsies.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>And you are welcome—yet these fooles will trouble us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rich fooles shall buy our trouble.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hang Lands, it's nothing but Trees, Stones and Durt, old Father I have Gold to keepe up our stock, pretious <HI>Pretiosa,</HI> for whose sake I have thus transform'd my selfe out of a Gentleman into a Gipsie, thou shalt not want sweete Rimes my little Musk-cat, for besides my selfe here's an <HI>Italian</HI> Poet, on whom I pray throw your welcomes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee's welcome!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pre.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, y'are most welcome, I love a Poet,</L>
<L>So hee writes chastely, if your Pen can sell me</L>
<L>Any smooth queint Romances, which I may sing,</L>
<L>You shall have Bayes and Silver.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="15"/>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pretty heart no selling:</L>
<L>What comes from me is free.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>And me too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>We shall be glad to use you sir, our sports</L>
<L>Must be an Orchard bearing severall Trees</L>
<L>And Fruits of severall taste; one pleasure dulls.</L>
<L>A time may come, when we (besides these pastimes)</L>
<L>May from the Grandoes and the Dons of <HI>Spaine</HI></L>
<L>Have leave to try our skill even on the Stage,</L>
<L>And then your witts may helpe us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>And mine too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are your servants.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pre.</SPEAKER>
<L>Trip softly through the streets, till we arrive</L>
<L>You know at whose house Father.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<HEAD>Song.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L>Trip it Gipsies, trip it fine,</L>
<L>Shew tricks and lofty Capers;</L>
<L>At threading Needles we repine,</L>
<L>And leaping over Rapiers.</L>
<L>Pindy Pandy rascall toyes,</L>
<L>We scorne cutting Purses,</L>
<L>Tho we live by making noyse,</L>
<L>For cheating none can curse us.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Over High-wayes, over low,</L>
<L>And over Stones and Gravell,</L>
<L>Tho we trip it on the Toe,</L>
<L>And thus for Silver travell.</L>
<L>Tho our Dances waste our backs,</L>
<L>At night fat Capons mend them;</L>
<L>Eggs well brew'd in Butterd'-sack,</L>
<L>Our Wenches say befriend them.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Oh that all the World were mad,</L>
<L>Then should we have fine Dancing,</L>
<L>Hobby horses would be had,</L>
<L>And brave Girles keepe a prancing,</L>
<L>Beggers would on Cock-horse ride,</L>
<L>And Boobies fall a roaring,</L>
<L>And Cuckolds tho no Hornes be spide,</L>
<L>Be one another goring.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="16"/>
<L>Welcome Poet to our Ging,</L>
<L>Make Rimes wee'l give thee reason,</L>
<L>Canary Bees thy braines shall sting</L>
<L>Mull-sack did ne're speake Treason.</L>
<L><HI>Peter-</HI>see-me shall wash thy nowle,</L>
<L>And Malligo Glasses fox thee,</L>
<L>If Poet thou tosse not bowle for bowle</L>
<L>Thou shalt not kisse a Doxie.</L>
</LG>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Fernando, Francisco de Carcomo, Don Iohn Pedro, Maria, Lewys, and Diego.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Lewys de Castro,</HI> since you circled are</L>
<L>In such a golden Ring of worthy friends,</L>
<L>Pray let me question you about that business</L>
<L>You and I last conferd on.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord I wish it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then Gentlemen tho you all know this man,</L>
<L>Yet now looke on him well, and you shall finde</L>
<L>Such mines of Spanish honor in his bosome,</L>
<L>As but in few are treasur'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh my good Lord!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee's Son to that <HI>de Castro,</HI> o're whose Tombe</L>
<L>Fame stands writing a booke which will take up</L>
<L>The age of time to fill it with the stories</L>
<L>Of his great acts, and that his honor'd Father</L>
<L>Fell in the quarrell of those Families</L>
<L>His own, and <HI>Don Alvarez de Castilla.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fra.</SPEAKER>
<L>The volume of those Families is too large,</L>
<L>And too wide Printed in our memory.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would it had ne're come forth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<L>So wish we all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>But heer's a Son as matchlesse as the Father,</L>
<L>For hee mindes bravery: he lets blood his Spleene,</L>
<L>Teares out the Leafe in which the Picture stands</L>
<L>Of slaine <HI>de Castro,</HI> casts a Hill of Sand</L>
<L>On all revenge, and stifles it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis done nobly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>For I by him am courted to sollicite</L>
<L>The King for the repeale of poore <HI>Alvarez,</HI></L>
<L>Who lives a banish'd man some say in <HI>Naples,</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="16"/>
<SPEAKER>Pe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Some say in <HI>Arragon.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>No matter where,</L>
<L>That Paper foulds in it my hand and heart,</L>
<L>Petitioning the royalty of <HI>Spaine</HI></L>
<L>To free the good old man, and call him home;</L>
<L>But what hope hath your Lordship that these beames</L>
<L>Of grace shall shine upon me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>The word Royall!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<L>And that's enough.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then since this sluce is drawn up to encrease</L>
<L>The streame, with pardon of these honord friends</L>
<L>Let me set ope another, and that's this,</L>
<L>That you my Lord <HI>Don Pedro,</HI> (and this Lady</L>
<L>Your noble Wife) would in this faire assembly</L>
<L>(If still you hold me Tenant to your favor)</L>
<L>Repeale the promise, you so oft have made me,</L>
<L>Touching the beautious <HI>Clara</HI> for my Wife.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pe.</SPEAKER>
<L>What I possesse in her before these Lords</L>
<L>I freely once more give you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>And what's mine?</L>
<L>To you (as right heire to it) I resigne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<L>What would you more?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>What would I more? the tree bowes down his head</L>
<L>Gently to have me touch it, but when I offer</L>
<L>To pluck the fruite, the top branch growes so high</L>
<L>To mock my reaching hand, up it does flie;</L>
<L>I have the Mothers smile, the Daughters frown.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh you must wooe hard!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wooe her well shee's thine own.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Jo.</SPEAKER>
<L>That Law holds not 'mongst Gipsies, I shoot hard,</L>
<L>And am wide off from the Marke.</L>
<STAGE>Florish.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Soto, with a Cornet in his hand.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is this my Lord your Musick?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fra.</SPEAKER>
<L>None of mine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<L>A crew of Gipsies with desire,</L>
<L>To shew their sports are at your Gates afire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fra.</SPEAKER>
<L>How, how, my Gates afire Knave!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Jo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Art panting? I am a fire l'me sure!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>What are the things they doe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<L>They Friske, they Caper, Dance and Sing,</L>
<L>

<PB REF="17"/>
Tell fortunes too (which is a very fine thing)</L>
<L>They tumble—how? not up and down</L>
<L>As Tumblers doe, but from Towne to Towne.</L>
<L>Anticks they have, and Gipsie-masking,</L>
<L>And toyes which you may have for asking;</L>
<L>They come to devoure, nor Wine, nor good Cheere,</L>
<L>But to earne money, if any be here.</L>
<L>(But being ask'd, as I suppose,</L>
<L>Your answer will be in your tother hose)</L>
<L>For there's not a Gipsie amongst'em that begs,</L>
<L>But gets his living by his Tongue and Legs.</L>
<L>If therefore you please Dons they shall come in,</L>
<L>Now I have ended, let them begin.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, I, by any means.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fra.</SPEAKER>
<L>But fellow bring you Musick along with you too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes my Lord, both lowd Musick, and still Musick, the loud is that which you have heard, and the still is that which no man can heare. <STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>A fine Knave.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fra.</SPEAKER>
<L>There is report of a faire Gipsie,</L>
<L>A pretty little toy, whom all our Gallants</L>
<L>In <HI>Madrill</HI> flock to looke on: this shee trow?</L>
<L>Yes sure 'tis shee—I should be sorry else.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Alvarez, Eugenia, Pretiosa, Roderigo, Sancho, Soto, and all the Gipsies.</STAGE>
<SP>
<LG TYPE="song">
<HEAD>Song.</HEAD>
<LG N="1">
<HEAD>1.</HEAD>
<L>Come follow your Leader follow</L>
<L>Our Convoy be <HI>Mars</HI> and <HI>Apollo,</HI></L>
<L>The Van comes brave up here,</L>
<L><STAGE>Ans.</STAGE> As hotly comes the Reare.</L>
<L><STAGE>Omn.</STAGE> Our Knackers are the Fifes and Drums,</L>
<L>Sa, sa, the Gipsies Army comes.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="2">
<HEAD>2.</HEAD>
<L>Horsemen we need not feare</L>
<L>There's none but footemen here;</L>
<L>The Horse sure charge without;</L>
<L>Or if they wheele about,</L>
<L><STAGE>Omn.</STAGE> Our Knackers are the shot that flie</L>
<L>Pit a pat ratling in the Sky.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="3">
<HEAD>3.</HEAD>
<PB REF="17"/>
<L>If once the great Ordnance play</L>
<L>That's laughing, yet runne not away;</L>
<L>But stand the push of Pike</L>
<L>Scorne can but baesely strike.</L>
<L><STAGE>Omn.</STAGE> Then let our Armies joyne and sing</L>
<L>And pit a pat make our Knackers ring.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="4">
<HEAD>4.</HEAD>
<L>Arme, Arme, what Bands are those?</L>
<L>They cannot be sure our foes;</L>
<L>Weele not draw up our force,</L>
<L>Nor muster any Horse,</L>
<L><STAGE>Omn.</STAGE> For since they pleas'd to view our sight</L>
<L>Let's this way, this way, give delight.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="5">
<HEAD>5.</HEAD>
<L>A Councell of War lets call,</L>
<L>Looke either to stand or fall;</L>
<L>If our weake Army stands</L>
<L>Thanke all these noble hands;</L>
<L>Whose gates of Love being open throwne</L>
<L>We enter, and then the Town's our owne.</L>
</LG>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>A very dainty thing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fra.</SPEAKER>
<L>A handsome Creature.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Looke what a pretty pit there's in her chin.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Jo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pit' 'tis a Grave to bury Lovers in.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Fathers disguise guard me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Soto,</HI> there's <HI>de Cortez</HI> my guardian; but he smells not us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace brother Gipsie, wud any one here know his fortune?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good fortunes all of us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pe.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis I sir needs a good one, come sir what's mine?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mine and my husbands fortunes keepe together,</L>
<L>Who is't tels mine?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, I, hold up Madam, feare not your pocket, for I ha but two Hands.</P>
<L>You are sad, or mad, or glad</L>
<L>For a couple of Cockes that cannot be had,</L>
<L>Yet when abroad they have pick'd store of grains</L>
<L>Doodle doo they will cry on your Dunghills againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeed I misse an idle Gentleman,</L>
<L>And a thing of his a foole, but neither sad</L>
<L>Nor mad for them, would that were all the Lead</L>
<L>

<PB REF="18"/>
Lying at my heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ped.</SPEAKER>
<L>What look'st thou on so long?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<P>So long I do you thinke good fortunes are fresh Herrings, to come in sholes? bad fortunes are like Mackerell at Midsummer, you have had a sore losse of late.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pe.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have indeed, what is't?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>I wonder it makes you not mad; for</HI></L>
<L>Through a gap in your Ground</L>
<L>Thence late hath been stole</L>
<L>A very fine Asse, and a very fine Fole,</L>
<L>Take heede for I speake not by habs and by nabs,</L>
<L>E're long you'l be horribly troubled with scabbs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pe.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am now so, goe silly foole.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<L>I ha gin't him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh <HI>Soto,</HI> that Asse and Foale fattens me!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Mother of the Gipsies, what can shee do?</L>
<L>I'le have about with her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Jo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I with the Gipsie Daughter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fra.</SPEAKER>
<L>To her Boy I</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>From you went a Dove away</L>
<L>Which e're this had been more white,</L>
<L>Then the silver Roabe of, Day,</L>
<L>Her Eyes the Moone has none so bright.</L>
<L>Sate shee now upon your hand</L>
<L>Not the Crowne of <HI>Spaine</HI> could buy it;</L>
<L>But 'tis flowne to such a Land,</L>
<L>Never more shall you come nie it;</L>
<L>Ha! yes if Palmestrie tell true,</L>
<L>This Dove agen may flie to you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art a lying Witch, I'le heare no more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you be so hot sit, we can coole you with a Song.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<L>And when that Song's done, wee'l heat you agen with a dance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay deare sir, send for <HI>Clara,</HI> let her know her fortune:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis too well known.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twill make her merry to be in this brave Company.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good <HI>Diego</HI> fetch her.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Diego.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fra.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's that old man! has he cunning too?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<L>More then all we.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Has he! I'le try his Spectacles.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha! <HI>Roderigo</HI> there! the Scholler</L>
<L>

<PB REF="18"/>
That went to <HI>Salamanca,</HI> takes he degrees</L>
<L>I'th Schoole of Gipsies? let the fish alone,</L>
<L>Give him Line, this is the Dove, the Dove: the Raven</L>
<L>That Beldam mock'd me with.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Low.</SPEAKER>
<L>What Wormes pick you out there now?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>This—when this Line the other crosses</L>
<L>Art tells me 'tis a booke of losses,</L>
<L>Bend your hand thus, Oh! here I finde</L>
<L>You have lost a Ship in a great winde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lying Rogue I ne're had any.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Harke, as I gather,</L>
<L>That great Ship was <HI>de Castro</HI> call'd your Father.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I must hew that Rock that split him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay and you threaten.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fra.</SPEAKER>
<L>And what's <HI>Don John</HI> thy fortune? th'art long fumbling at it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Jo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee tells me tales of the Moone sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pre.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>And now 'tis come to the Sun sir.</HI></L>
<L>Your Sun wud ride, the youth wud runne,</L>
<L>The youth wud sayle, the youth wud flie;</L>
<L>Hee's tying a knot will ne're be done,</L>
<L>He shoots, and yet has ne're an eye.</L>
<L>You have two, 'twere good you lent him one,</L>
<L>And a heart too, for he has none.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fra.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hoyday, lend one of mine eyes!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>They give us nothing, hee'd best put on a bold face and ask it.</L>
</SP>
<Q><TEXT LANG="eng">
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="song">
<HEAD>Song.</HEAD>
<SP>
<LG>
<L>Now that from the Hive</L>
<L>You gather'd have the Honey,</L>
<L>Our Bees but poorely thrive,</L>
<L>Unlesse the Bankes be sunny.</L>
<L>Then let your Sun and Moone</L>
<L>Your gold and silver shine,</L>
<L>My thanks shall huming fly to you.</L>
<L><STAGE>Omnes.</STAGE> And mine, and mine, and mine.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>See, see, your Gipsie toyes,</L>
<L>You mad Girles, you merry Boyes.</L>
<L>A boone voyage we have made</L>
<L>Loud Peales must then be had,</L>
<L>If I a Gipsie be</L>
<L>A crack rope I am for thee;</L>
<L>

<PB REF="19"/>
Oh here's a Golden Ring,</L>
<L>Such clappers please a King;</L>
<L>Such clapers please a King: you pleas'd may pass away</L>
<L>Then let your Bell-ropes stay,</L>
<L>Now chime 'tis Holy-day,</L>
<L>Now chime 'tis Holy-day.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT></Q>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pre.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more of this pray Father, fall to your Dancing. <HI>Dance.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Clara</HI> will come too late now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis great pitty,</L>
<L>Besides your Songs, Dances and other Pastimes,</L>
<L>You do not as our Spanish Actors doe, make triall of a Stage.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are sir about it,</L>
<L>So please your high authority to signe us</L>
<L>Some warrant to confirme us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<P>My hand shall doo't—and bring the best in <HI>Spaine</HI> to see your Sports.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Which to set off this Gentleman a Scholler</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pox on you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will write for us:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Spaniard sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>No my Lord an Italian.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Denies his Country too—my Son sings Gipsie Ballads,</L>
<L>Keepe as you are, wee'l see your Poets vaine,</L>
<L>And yours for playing; time is not ill spent</L>
<L>That's thus laid out in harmelesse merriment.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Gipsies Dancing.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pe.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord of <HI>Carcomo,</HI> for this entertainment,</L>
<L>You shall command our loves.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fra.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'are nobly welcome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pe.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Evening growes upon us, Lords to all</L>
<L>A happy time of day.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>The like to you <HI>Don Pedro.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>To my hearts sole Lady,</L>
<L>Pray let my service humbly be remembred,</L>
<L>We onely mist her presence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall truly</L>
<L>Report your worthy love.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Ped. Ma.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall no further,</L>
<L>Indeed my Lords you shall not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fra.</SPEAKER>
<L>With your favour</L>
<L>Wee will attend you home.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>

<PB REF="19"/>
Enter Diego.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Die.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where's <HI>Don Pedro?</HI> oh sir!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why what's the matter?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Die.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Lady <HI>Clara,</HI></L>
<L>Passing neere to my Lord <HI>Corigidors</HI> house,</L>
<L>Met with a strange mischance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>How, what mischance?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Die.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Jester that so late arrived at Court,</L>
<L>And there was welcome for his Countries sake,</L>
<L>By importunity of some friends, it seemes</L>
<L>Had borrow'd from the Gentleman of your Horse,</L>
<L>The backing of your mettl'd Barbary:</L>
<L>On which being mounted, whil'st a number gaz'd</L>
<L>To heare what Jests hee could performe on Horse back,</L>
<L>The head strong beast unus'd to such a Rider,</L>
<L>Beares the Presse of People before him;</L>
<L>With which throng, the Lady <HI>Clara</HI> meeting,</L>
<L>Fainted, and there fell down; not bruis'd I hope;</L>
<L>But frighted and intranc'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ill destin'd mischiefe!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where have you left her?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Die.</SPEAKER>
<L>At your house my Lord,</L>
<L>A servant comming forth, and knowing who</L>
<L>The Lady was, convey'd her to a Chamber,</L>
<L>A Surgeon too is sent for.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Had shee been my Daughter,</L>
<L>My care could not be greater, then it shall be</L>
<L>For her recure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>But if shee miscarry,</L>
<L>I am the most unhappy Man that lives.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Diego</HI> Coast about the Fields,</L>
<L>And over-take <HI>Don Pedro</HI> and his Wife,</L>
<L>They newly parted from us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Die.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le runne speedily.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>A strange mischance, but what!</L>
<L>I have my Lord <HI>Francisco</HI> this day noted,</L>
<L>I may tell you, an accident of merriment and wonders</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fra.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeed my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have not thoughts enough</L>
<L>About me to imagine what th'event</L>
<L>

<PB REF="20"/>
Can come to, 'tis indeed about my Son;</L>
<L>Hereafter you may counsell me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fra.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most gladly—how fares the Lady?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Lewys.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Call'd back to Life, but full of sadnesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Talkes shee nothing?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nothing, for when the women that attend on her</L>
<L>Demanded how shee did, shee turn'd about,</L>
<L>And answered with a sigh, when I came neere,</L>
<L>And by the Love I bore her, begg'd a word</L>
<L>Of hope to comfort mee in her well-doing;</L>
<L>Before shee would reply, from her faire Eyes</L>
<L>Shee greetes me with a Bracelet of her teares;</L>
<L>Then wish'd me not to doubt, shee was too well,</L>
<L>Entreates that shee may sleepe without disturbance,</L>
<L>Or company untill her Father came.</L>
<L>And thus I left her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fra.</SPEAKER>
<L>For shee's past the worst,</L>
<L>Young Maides are oft so troubled.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Pedro and Maria.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here come they</L>
<L>You talke of—sir, your Daughter for your comfort</L>
<L>Is now upon amendment.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh my Lord!</L>
<L>You speake an Angels voyce.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray in and visit her.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Ped. Ma.</STAGE>
<L>I'le follow instantly—you shall not part</L>
<L>Without a cup of Wine my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fra.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis now too troublesome a time;</L>
<L>Which way take you <HI>Don Lewys?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>No matter which, for till I heare</L>
<L>My <HI>Clara</HI> be recover'd I am nothing,</L>
<L>My Lord <HI>Corigidor,</HI> I am your servant</L>
<L>For this free entertainment.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have conquer'd me</L>
<L>In noble courtesie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh! that no art</L>
<L>But Love it selfe can cure a Love-sick heart.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Clara in a Chaire, Pedro and Maria by her.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Clara,</HI> hope of mine age!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="20"/>
<SPEAKER>Ped.</SPEAKER>
<L>Soule of my comfort,</L>
<L>Kill us not both at once; why dost thou speede</L>
<L>Thine Eye in such a progresse 'bout these Walls?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yon large Window</L>
<L>Yeilds some faire prospect, good my Lord looke out,</L>
<L>And tell mee what you see there.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Easie suite,</L>
<L><HI>Clara</HI> it over-viewes a spacious Garden,</L>
<L>Amidst which stands an Alablaster Fountaine,</L>
<L>A goodly one.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeed my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>The griefes grow wide,</L>
<L>And will mislead thy judgement through thy weaknesse</L>
<L>If thou obey thy weakenesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who ownes these glorious buildings?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pe.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Don Fernando</HI></L>
<L><HI>De Azeutda,</HI> the <HI>Corigidor</HI></L>
<L>Of <HI>Mardrill,</HI> a true noble Gentleman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>May I not see him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>See him <HI>Clara,</HI> why?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>A truly noble Gentleman you said sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pe.</SPEAKER>
<L>I did: loe here he comes in person,</L>
<L>We are my Lord your servants.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Fernando.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good no complement,</L>
<L>Young Lady there attends below a Surgeon</L>
<L>Of worthy fame and practice, is't your pleasure</L>
<L>To be his Patient?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>With your favour sir,</L>
<L>May I impart some few, but needefull words</L>
<L>Of secresie to you, to you your selfe,</L>
<L>None but your selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>You may.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Must I not heare 'em?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh yes, pray sit my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Say on.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have been Married.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>To a Wife young Lady,</L>
<L>Who whiles the Heavens did lend her me was fruitfull</L>
<L>

<PB REF="21"/>
In all those vertues which stiles Woman good.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>And you had Children by her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Had 'tis true,</L>
<L>Now have but one, a Son, and hee yet lives,</L>
<L>The Daughter, as if in her Birth, the Mother</L>
<L>Had perfected the errand shee was sent for</L>
<L>Into the World, from that houre tooke her Life</L>
<L>In which the other that gave it her, lost hers;</L>
<L>Yet shortly shee unhappily, but fatally</L>
<L>Perish'd at Sea.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sad story!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Roderigo,</HI></L>
<L>My Sonne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>How is hee call'd sit?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Roderigo.</HI></L>
<L>Hee lives at <HI>Salamanca,</HI> and I feare</L>
<L>That neither Time, Perswasions nor his Fortunes</L>
<L>Can draw him thence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, d'ee know this Crucifig?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>You drive me to amazement, 'twas my Sonnes,</L>
<L>A Legacy bequeathed him from his Mother</L>
<L>Upon her Death-bed, deare to him as Life;</L>
<L>On Earth there cannot be another treasure</L>
<L>Hee values at like rate as hee does this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh then I am a cast-away!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>How's that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas shee will grow frantick.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>In my bosome,</L>
<L>Next to my Heart my Lord I have laid up,</L>
<L>In bloody Characters a Tale of horror,</L>
<L>Pray read the Paper, and if there you finde</L>
<L>Ought that concernes a Maide undone, and miserable</L>
<L>Made so by one of yours, call back the piety</L>
<L>Of nature, to the goodnesse of a Judge,</L>
<L>An upright Judge, not of a partiall Father,</L>
<L>For doe not wonder that I live to suffer</L>
<L>Such a full weight of wrongs, but wonder rather</L>
<L>That I have liv'd to speak them; thou great man</L>
<L>Yet read, read on, and as thou read'st consider</L>
<L>What I have suffer'd, what thou ought'st to doe;</L>
<L>

<PB REF="21"/>
Thine owne Name, Father-hood, and my dishonour</L>
<L>Be just as Heaven and fate are, that by miracle</L>
<L>Have in my weakenesse wrought a strange discovery;</L>
<L>Truth copied from my heart is texted there:</L>
<L>Let now my shame be throughly understood,</L>
<L>Sinnes are heard farthest, when they cry in blood.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>True, true, they doe not cry but hollow here,</L>
<L>This is the Trumpet of a Soule drown'd deepe</L>
<L>In the unfathom'd Seas of matchlesse sorrowes.</L>
<L>I must lock fast the dore.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have no words</L>
<L>To call for vengeance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pe.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am lost in marvaile.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Fernando.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, pray fit as you sat before: white paper</L>
<L>This should be innocence, these Letters Gules</L>
<L>Should be the honest Oracles of Revenge.</L>
<L>What's Beauty but a perfect white and red?</L>
<L>Both here well mixt, limne truth so beautifull,</L>
<L>That to distrust it as I am a Father;</L>
<L>Speakes mee as foule, as rape hath spoken my Sonne,</L>
<L>'Tis true.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis true.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then marke mee how I kneele</L>
<L>Before the high tribunall of your Injuries;</L>
<L>Thou too too much wrong'd Maid scorne not my teares,</L>
<L>For these are teares of Rage, not teares of Love.</L>
<L>Thou Father of this too too much wrong'd Maide,</L>
<L>Thou Mother of her counsells and her cares;</L>
<L>I doe not plead for pitty to a Villaine,</L>
<L>Oh! let him die as hee hath liv'd dishonorably,</L>
<L>Basely and cursedly, I plead for pitty,</L>
<L>To my till now untainted blood and honour,</L>
<L>Teach mee how I may now be just and cruell;</L>
<L>For henceforth I am Childlesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray sir rise,</L>
<L>You wrong your place and age.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Point mee my Grave</L>
<L>In some obscure by path, where never memory</L>
<L>Nor mention of my Name may be found out.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="22"/>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, I can weep with you, nay weepe for yee</L>
<L>As you for mee, your passions are instructions,</L>
<L>And prompt my faltering Tongue to beg at least</L>
<L>A noble satisfaction, tho not revenge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speak that agen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can you procure no Balme</L>
<L>To heale a wounded Name?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh th'art as faire</L>
<L>In Mercy as in Beauty, wilt thou live,</L>
<L>And I'le be thy Physitian?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le be yours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Don Pedro,</HI> wee'l to counsaile</L>
<L>This Daughter shall be ours, sleepe, sleepe, young Angell,</L>
<L>My care shall wake about thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heaven is gracious,</L>
<L>And I am eas'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee will be yet more private,</L>
<L>Might curtaines o're the world, soft dreams rest with thee.</L>
<L>The best revenge is to reforme our crymes,</L>
<L>Then time crowns sorrowes, sorrowes sweeten times.</L>
<STAGE>Ex.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACTUS QUARTUS.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Alvarez, Sancho, Soto, Antonio, Carlo, Eugenia, Pretiosa, Christiana, and Don John. A showte within.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>OMnes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Welcome, welcome, welcome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<L>More Sacks to the Mill.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>More Theeves to the Sacks.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pre.</SPEAKER>
<L>I give you now my welcome without noyse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Jo.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis Musick to me.</L>
<STAGE>He offers to kisse her.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh sir!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>You must not be in your Mutton before we are out of our Veale.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay for Vineger to your Oysters, no opening till then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>No kissing till y'are sworne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="22"/>
<SPEAKER>Jo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweare me then quickly.</L>
<L>I have brought Gold for my Admission.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>What you bring leave, and what you leave count lost.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>I brought all my Teeth, two are struck out, them I count lost, so must you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<L>I brought all my wits, halfe I count lost, so must you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Jo.</SPEAKER>
<L>To be as you are, I lose Father, Friends,</L>
<L>Birth, Fortunes, all the World; what will you doe</L>
<L>With the beast I rode on hither?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>A Beast is't a Mule? send him to <HI>Muly Crag</HI> a whee in <HI>Barbary.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is't an Asse? give it to a Lawyer, for in Spaine they ride up∣on none else.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Jo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Kill him by any means, lest being pursu'd</L>
<L>The beast betray mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee's a beast betrays any man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>Except a Bayliffe to be pump'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Jo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray buy the Carcasse and the furniture.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doe, doe, bury the Asses House-hold-stuffe, and in his skin sow any Man that's mad for a Woman.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do so then, bury it, now to your Oath.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>All things are ready.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy best hand lay on this Turffe of Grasse,</L>
<L>(There thy Heart lies) vow not to passe</L>
<L>From us two yeares for Sun nor Snow,</L>
<L>For hill nor dale (how e're Winds blow.)</L>
<L>Vow the hard Earth to be thy Bed,</L>
<L>With her greene Cushions under thy Head;</L>
<L>Flowre bancks or Mosse to be thy bourd,</L>
<L>Water thy Wine,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>And drinke like a Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Kings can have but Coronations,</L>
<L>Wee are as prowd of Gipsie Fashions;</L>
<L>Dance, Sing, and in a well-mixt border,</L>
<L>Close this new Brother of our Order.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>What we get, with us come share,</L>
<L>You to get must vow to care;</L>
<L>Nor strike Gipsie, nor stand by,</L>
<L>When strangers strike, but fight or die;</L>
<L>Our Gipsie Wenches are not common,</L>
<L>

<PB REF="23"/>
You must not kisse a fellowes Leman;</L>
<L>Nor to your owne (for one you must)</L>
<L>In Songs send, errands of base lust.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dance, Sing, and in a well mix'd border,</L>
<L>Close this new Brother of our Order.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Jo.</SPEAKER>
<L>On this Turffe of Grasse I vow</L>
<L>Your Laws to keepe, your Lawes allow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Gipsie, a Gipsie, a Gipsie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now choose what Maide has yet no mate, shee's yours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Jo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here then fix I my fate.</L>
<STAGE>Offers to kisse.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>Agen fall too before you ha wash'd!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Nose in the Manger, before the Oates are measur'd.</L>
<L>Jade so hungry!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Set foote to foote, those Garlands hold,</L>
<L>Teach him how, now marke what more is told;</L>
<L>By crosse Armes the Lovers signe,</L>
<L>Vow as these flowers themselves entwine,</L>
<L>Of Aprills wealth building a throne</L>
<L>Round; so your love to one or none,</L>
<L>By those touches of your Feete,</L>
<L>You must each night embracing meete;</L>
<L>Chaste how e're disjoyn'd by Day,</L>
<L>You the Sun with her must play;</L>
<L>Shee to you the Marigold</L>
<L>To none but you her Leaves unfold;</L>
<L>Wake shee or sleepe, your Eyes so charme,</L>
<L>Want, wee, nor weather doe her harme.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is your Market now of kisses,</L>
<L>Buy and sell free each other Blisses.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Jo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most, willingly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Holy dayes, high dayes, Gipsie Faires,</L>
<L>When kisses are Fairings, and hearts meete in paires.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<P>All Ceremonies end heere; Welcome Brother, Gipsie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>And the better to instruct thee, marke what a brave Life 'tis all the yeare long.</P>
<LG>
<PB REF="23"/>
<HEAD>Song.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L>Brave Don cast your eyes on our Gipsie Fashions,</L>
<L>In our antique hey de guize, wee goe beyond all Nations;</L>
<L>Plumpe Dutch at us grutch, so do English, so do French,</L>
<L>He that loapes on the Ropes, shew me such an other wench.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>We no Camells have to shew, nor Elephant with growte head,</L>
<L>We can Dance, he cannot goe, because the Beast is Corne-fed;</L>
<L>No blinde Beares shedding teares, for a Colliers whipping,</L>
<L>Apes nor Dogs, quick as Frogs, over Cudgells skipping.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><HI>Jack</HI> in Boxes, nor Decoyes, Puppets nor such poore things,</L>
<L>Nor are we those roring Boys, that cosen Fooles with guilt Rings;</L>
<L>For an Ocean, not such a motion, as the City Ninivie,</L>
<L>Dancing, Singing, and fine Ringing, you these sports shall hear and see.</L>
<L>Come now what shall his Name be?</L>
</LG>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pre.</SPEAKER>
<L>His Name shall now be <HI>Andrew,</HI> friend <HI>Andrew</HI> marke mee:</L>
<L>Two yeares I am to try you, prove fine Gold,</L>
<L>The uncrack'd Diamond of my Faith shall hold.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Jo.</SPEAKER>
<L>My vowes are Rocks of Adamant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pre.</SPEAKER>
<L>Two years you are to try me, black when I turne</L>
<L>May I meete youth and want, old age and scorne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Jo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Kings Diadems shall not buy thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe you thinke</L>
<L>You can endure the Life and love it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Jo.</SPEAKER>
<L>As Usurers dote upon their treasure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<L>But when your Face shall be tand, like a Saylors workie∣day hand:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>When your Feete shall be gall'd, and your Noddle be mall'd:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<P>When the Woods you must forredge, and not meete with poore Pease-porridge:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be all to be dabled, yet lie in no Sheete:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<L>With Winters Frost, Hayle, Snow and Sleete;</L>
<L>What Life will you say it is then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Jo.</SPEAKER>
<L>As now the sweetest.</L>
<L>Away, away, the Corigidor has sent for you.</L>
<STAGE>Diego within.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="24"/>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<HEAD>Song.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L>Hence merily fine to get Money,</L>
<L>Dry are the Fields, the Bancks are Sunny;</L>
<L>Silver is sweeter far then Honey.</L>
<L>Flie like Swallowes,</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Wee for our Coneys must get Mallowes,</L>
<L>Who loves not his <HI>Dill,</HI> let him die at the Gallowes;</L>
<L>Hence bonny Girles foote it trimly.</L>
<L>Smug up your beetle Browes, none looke grimly,</L>
<L>To shew a pretty foote, Oh! 'tis seemly.</L>
</LG>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Cardochia, stayes Soto.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe you heare you Gipsie? Gipsie?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>There's a young Gipsie newly entertain'd,</L>
<L>Sweete Gipsie call him back for one two words,</L>
<L>And here's a Jewell for thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le send him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's his Name?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Andrew.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>A very handsome fellow, I ha seene Courtiers</L>
<L>Jet up and down in their full bravery,</L>
<L>Yet here's a Gipsie worth a drove of 'em.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Don John.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Jo.</SPEAKER>
<L>With mee sweet Heart?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Name is <HI>Andrew.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Jo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>You can tell Fortunes <HI>Andrew.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Jo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I could once,</L>
<L>But now I ha lost that knowledge, I am in haste,</L>
<L>And cannot stay to tell you yours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>I cannot tell yours then,</L>
<L>And cause you are in hast, I am quick,</L>
<L>I am a Maide.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Jo.</SPEAKER>
<L>So, so, a maide quick.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Juanna Cardochia,</HI></L>
<L>That's mine owne Name, I am my Mothers Heire</L>
<L>Here to this House, and two more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Jo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I buy no Lands.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>They shall be given you, with some Plate and Money,</L>
<L>

<PB REF="24"/>
And free possession (during life) of me,</L>
<L>So the match like you, for so well I love you</L>
<L>That I in pitty of this Trade of Gipsying</L>
<L>(Being base, idle and slavish) offer you</L>
<L>A state to settle you, my youth and beauty,</L>
<L>(Desir'd by some brave <HI>Spaniards)</HI> so I may call you</L>
<L>My husband, shall I <HI>Andrew?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Jo.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Lass pretty Soule,</L>
<L>Better Starrs guide you, may that hand of <HI>Cupid</HI></L>
<L>Ake, ever shot this arrow at your heart,</L>
<L>Sticks there one such indeede?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would there did not,</L>
<L>Since you'l not pluck it out.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Jo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good sweete I cannot;</L>
<L>For marriage 'tis a Law amongst us Gipsies</L>
<L>We match in our own tribes, for me to weare you</L>
<L>I should but weare you out.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe not care</L>
<L>Weare what you can out, all my life, my wealth,</L>
<L>Ruine me, so you lend me but your love,</L>
<L>A little of your love.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Jo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would I could give it,</L>
<L>For you are worth a World of better men,</L>
<L>For your free noble minde, all my best wishes</L>
<L>Stay with you, I must hence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Weare for my sake</L>
<L>This Jewell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Jo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le not rob you, I'le take nothing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Weare it about your neck but one poore Moon;</L>
<L>If in that time your eye be as 'tis now,</L>
<L>Send my Jewell home agen, and I protest</L>
<L>I'le never more thinke on you; deny not this,</L>
<L>Put it about your neck:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Jo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well then 'tis done.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>And vow to keepe it there.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Jo.</SPEAKER>
<L>By all the Goodness</L>
<L>I wish attend your fortunes I doe vow it.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Scornd! thou hast temper'd poyson to kill me</L>
<L>Thy selfe shall drinke; since I cannot enjoy thee</L>
<L>My revenge shall.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>

<PB REF="25"/>
Enter Diego.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Die.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where are the Gipsies?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gon;<HI>—Diego</HI> do you love me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Die.</SPEAKER>
<L>Love thee <HI>Juanna!</HI></L>
<L>Is my life mine! it is but mine so long</L>
<L>As it shall do thee service.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>There's a younger Gipsie newly entertain'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Die.</SPEAKER>
<L>A handsome rascall; what of him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>That slave in obsceane Language courted me.</L>
<L>Drew Rialls out, and would have bought my body</L>
<L><HI>Diego</HI> from thee!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Die.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is hee so Itchy? I'le cure him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou shalt not touch the Villaine, I'le spin his fate;</L>
<L>Woman strikes sure, fall the blow ne're so late.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Die.</SPEAKER>
<L>Strike on sinne, thou wilt be a striker.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Fernando, Francisco, Pedro, and Lewys.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>See <HI>Don Lewys,</HI> an Army!</L>
<L>(The strongest Army in <HI>Spaine)</HI> to the full length</L>
<L>Is stretch'd to pluck old Count <HI>Alvarez</HI> home</L>
<L>From his sad banishment.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>With longing Eyes,</L>
<L>(My Lord) I expect the man, your Lordships pardon,</L>
<L>Some businesse cal's me from you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prithee <HI>Don Lewys,</HI></L>
<L>Unlesse th'occasion be too violent,</L>
<L>Stay and be merry with us, all the <HI>Gipsies</HI></L>
<L>Will be here presently.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will attend your Lordship,</L>
<L>Before their sports be done.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be your own Carver,</L>
<L>Not yet shake off these fetters? I see a Sonne</L>
<L>Is heavy when a Father carries him</L>
<L>On his old heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fra.</SPEAKER>
<L>Could I set up my rest,</L>
<L>That hee were lost, or taken prisoner;</L>
<L>I could hold truce with sorrow; but to have him</L>
<L>Vanish I know not how, gon none knowes whither,</L>
<L>'Tis that mads mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pe.</SPEAKER>
<L>You said he sent a Letter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fra.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Letter! a meere Riddle; he's gon to see</L>
<L>

<PB REF="25"/>
His fortune in the Warres, what Warres have wee?</L>
<L>Suppose we had, goes any man toth' Field</L>
<L>Naked, unfurnish'd, both Armes and Money?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, come, he's gon a Wenching; we in our youth</L>
<L>Ran the selfe same Byas.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Diego.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Die.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Gipsies my Lord are come.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are they? let them enter:</L>
<STAGE>Exit Die.</STAGE>
<L>My Lord <HI>De Cortez</HI> send for your Wife and Daughter,</L>
<L>Good company is good Physick, take the paines</L>
<L>To seate your selves in my great Chamber.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Alvarez, Don John, Roderigo, Antonio, Carlo, Eugenia, Pretiosa, Christiana, Sancho, and Soto.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>See they are here; what's your number?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>The figure of nine casts us all up my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nine! let me see—you are ten sure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's our Poet, he stands for a Cipher.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ciphers make numbers; what Playes have you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Five or six my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>It's well so many already.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wee are promist a very merry Tragedy, if all hit right, of <HI>Cobby Nobby.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<P>So, so, a merry Tragedy, there is a way which the <HI>Italians,</HI> and the <HI>Frenchmen</HI> use; that is, on a word given, or some slight Plot,</P>
<L>The Actors will extempore fashion out</L>
<L>Sceanes neate and witty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>We can do that my Lord, please you bestow the Subject</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can you? come hither,</L>
<L>You Master Poet to save you a labour,</L>
<L>Looke you, against your coming I projected</L>
<L>This Comick passage—your Dramma; that's the Sceane.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, I, my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>I lay in our own Country, <HI>Spaine.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis best so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here's a brave part for this old Gipsie—look you</L>
<L>The Father: read the Plot—this young shee Gipsie,</L>
<L>This Lady—now the sonne—play him your selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, I am no Player.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray at this time.</L>
<L>

<PB REF="26"/>
(The Plot being full) to please my noble Friends,</L>
<L>Because your braines must into theirs put Language,</L>
<L>Act thou the Sonnes part,—I'le reward your paines.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Protest my Lord—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, nay, shake off protesting,</L>
<L>When I was young sir, I have plaid my selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your selfe my Lord! you were but a poore Company then.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, full enough honest fellow—will you do it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le venture.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thanke you, let this Father be a <HI>Don</HI></L>
<L>Of a brave spirit, old Gipsie observe mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Play him up high, not like a Pantaloone,</L>
<L>But hotly, nobly, checking this his Sonne,</L>
<L>Whom make a very rake-hell, a debosh'd fellow,—</L>
<L>This poynt I thinke will shew well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>This of the Picture,</L>
<L>It will indeed my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, what part play I?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>What parts dost use to play?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>If your Lordship has ever a Coxcombe, I thinke I could fit you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thanke your Coxcombe-ship.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Put a Coxcombe upon a Lord!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>There are parts to serve you all, goe, goe, make ready,</L>
<L>And call for what you want.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Give me the Plot, our wits are put to triall.</L>
<L>What's the Son's Name, <HI>Lorenzo?</HI> that's your part</L>
<L>Looke onely you to that,—these I'le dispose;</L>
<L>Old <HI>Don Avero,</HI> mine; <HI>Hialdo, Lollio,</HI></L>
<L>Two servants, you for them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>One of the foolish knaves give me, I'le be <HI>Hialdo.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I <HI>Lollio.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is there a Banquet in the Play? wee may call for what wee will.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, here is a Banquet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>I'le goe then and bespeake an ocean of Sweete meates, Marmalad and Custards.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Make hast to know what you must doe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="26"/>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doe I call for enough, and when my Belly is full, fill my Pockets.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<P>To a Banquet there must be Wine, Fortunes a scurvy Whore; if shee makes not my head sound like a Rattle; and my Heels dance the Canaries.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>So, so, dispatch, whil'st me employ our braines</L>
<L>To set things off toth' Life.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le be streight with you,</L>
<L>Why does my Father put this trick on mee?</L>
<L>Spies hee mee through my Vizard? if hee does</L>
<L>He's not the King of <HI>Spaine,</HI> and 'tis no Treason;</L>
<L>If his invention, Jet upon a Stage</L>
<L>Why should not I use action? a debosh'd fellow!</L>
<L>A very rake-hell, this reflects on mee,</L>
<L>And I'le retort it, grown a Poet Father?</L>
<L>No matter in what straine your Play must ruune,</L>
<L>But I shall fit you for a roring Sonne.</L>
<STAGE>Exit. Florish.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Francisco, Pedro, Fernando, Diego, Maria, and Clara.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come Ladies take your places, this their Musick,</L>
<L>'Tis very handsome, oh! I wish this Roome</L>
<L>Were frighted, but with noble friends</L>
<L>As are to you my welcomes, begin there masters.</L>
<STAGE>Florish within.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>Presently my Lord, wee want but a cold Capon for a property.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Call, call for one—now they begin.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Sancho, the Prologue.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>Both short and sweete some say is best,</L>
<L>Wee will not onely be sweete but short,</L>
<L>Take you Pepper in the Nose you mar our sport.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>By no meanes Pepper.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>Of your Love measure us forth but one span,</L>
<L>We do (tho not the best) the best we can.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>A good honest Gipsie.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Alvarez and Soto.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Slave! where's my Son <HI>Lorenzo?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<P>I have sought him my Lord in all foure Elements; in Earth, my Shooes are full of Gravell; in Water, I drop at Nose with sweating; In Aire, wheresoever I heard noyse of Fidlers, or the wide mouthes of Gallon-pots roaring; and in Fire, what


<PB REF="27"/>
Chimney soever I saw smoaking with good cheere, for my Masters Dinner, as I was in hope.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not yet come home? before on this old Tree</L>
<L>Shall grow a branch so blasted, I'le hew it off,</L>
<L>And bury it at my foote, didst thou enquire</L>
<L>At my Brothers?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<L>At your Sisters.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>At my Wives Fathers?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<P>At your Uncles Mothers, no such sheepe has broke through their hedge, no such Calse as your Sonne sucks, or bleates in their ground.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am unblest to have but one Sonne onely,</L>
<L>One staffe to beare my age up—one Taper left,</L>
<L>To light me to my Grave, and that burnes dimly</L>
<L>That leaves me darkling hid in clouds of woe,</L>
<L>He that should prop me is mine overthrow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well done old fellow is't not?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, yes, my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Sancho.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here comes his man <HI>Hialdo.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where's the prodigall your Master sirrah?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>Eating Acorns amongst Swine, draffe amongst Hoggs, and gnawing bones amongst Doggs; has lost all his Money at Dice, his Wits with his Money, and his honesty with both, for hee bum∣fiddles me; makes the Drawers curvet, pitches the Plate over the Bar, scores up the Vintners Name in the Ram-head; flirts his Wife under the Nose, and bids you with a Pox send him more Money.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Art thou one of his Currs to bite me too?</L>
<L>To nayle thee to the Earth were to doe Justice.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Roderigo.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here comes <HI>Bucephalus</HI> my prauncing Master, nayle me now who dares.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<P>I sit like an Owle in the Ivie bush of a Taverne! <HI>Hialdo</HI> I have drawne red Wine from the Vintners owne Hogs∣head.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here's two more, pierce them too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Old <HI>Don,</HI> whom I call Father; am I thy Sonne? if I be, flesh mee with Gold, fat mee with Silver; had I <HI>Spaine</HI> in this hand,


<PB REF="27"/>
and <HI>Portugall</HI> in this, puffe it should flie, where's the Money I sent for?—I'le tickle you for a Rake-hell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not a <HI>Marvedi.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou shalt have none of me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold his Nose to the Grinstone my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall have none!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Charge mee a case of Pistolls.</L>
<L>What I have built I'le ruine, shall I suffer</L>
<L>A Slave to set his Foote upon my heart?</L>
<L>A Sonne! a barbarous Villaine, or if Heaven save thee</L>
<L>Now from my Justice, yet my curse pursues thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Hialdo,</HI> carbonado thou the old Rogue my Father.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whil'st you slice into Collups the rusty Gamon his man there.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<P>No Money! Can Tavernes stand without anon, anon? Fid∣lers live without scraping, Taffaty Girles looke plumpe without pampering? if you will not Lard mee with Money, give mee a Ship, furnish me to Sea.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>To have thee hang'd for Piracy?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>Trim, tram, hang Master hand Man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then send mee to the West-Indies, buy mee some Office there.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>A.</SPEAKER>
<L>To have thy throate cut for thy quarrelling.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Else send me and my ningle <HI>Hialdo</HI> to the Warrs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>A match, wee'l fight Dogge, fight Beare.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Antonio.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>An.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh deare <HI>Hernando!</HI> welcome, clap Wings to your heeles,</L>
<L>And pray my worthy friends bestow upon me</L>
<L>Their present Visitation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Lorenzo,</HI> see the anger of a Father,</L>
<L>Altho it be as low'd and quick as thunder,</L>
<L>Yet'cis done instantly, cast off thy wildnesse,</L>
<L>Be mine, be mine, for I to call thee home</L>
<L>Have with my honor'd friend here, <HI>Don Hernando</HI></L>
<L>Provided thee a Wife.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<P>A Wife! Is shee hansome? is shee rich? Is shee faire? Is shee wity? Is shee honest? Hang honesty. Has shee a sweete Face, Cherry-Cheeke, Strawberry-lip, white-skin, dainty Eye, pretty Foote, delicate Legs? as there's a Girle now.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is a Creature both for Birth and fortunes,</L>
<L>

<PB REF="28"/>
And for most excellent graces of the minde,</L>
<L>Few like her are in <HI>Spaine.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>When shall I see her?—now Father pray take your curse off.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe, the Lady</L>
<L>Lives from <HI>Mardrill,</HI> very neere fourteene Leagues,</L>
<L>But thou shalt see her Picture.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>That, that, most Ladies in these dayes are but very fine Pictures.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Claro, Don John, Engenia, Pretiosa, Christiana, Sancho and Soto.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ladies to you first welcome, my Lords <HI>(Alonzo,</HI></L>
<L>And you worthy Marquesse) thanks for these honours.</L>
<L>Away you: to th'cause now of this meeting, my Sonne <HI>Lorenzo,</HI></L>
<L>Whose wildnesse you all know comes now to th' Lure,</L>
<L>Sits gently; has call'd home his wandering thoughts,</L>
<L>And now will Marry.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pre.</SPEAKER>
<L>A good Wife Fate send him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>One stayd may settle him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Flie to the marke sir, shew me the Wench, or her Face, or any thing I may know 'tis a woman fit for me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee is not here her selfe, but here's her Picture.</L>
<STAGE>A Picture.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord <HI>De Carcamo,</HI> pray observe this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fra.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe attentively<HI>—Don Pedro,</HI> marke it.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Soto.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<P>If you ha done your part, yonders a Wench wud ha a bout with you, <STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Jo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mee!</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Die.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Wench!</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why stand you staring at it? how do you like her?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you in earnest?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes sir, in earnest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am not so hungry after flesh to make the Divell a Cuckold</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>An.</SPEAKER>
<L>Looke not upon the Face, but on the goodness</L>
<L>That dwells within her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Set fire on the Tenement.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee's rich, nobly discended.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did ever Nobility looke so scurvilie?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am sunk in fortuaes, shee may raise us both.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sink, let her to her Granam; marry a VVitch! have you fetch'd a VVife for mee out of <HI>Lapland?</HI> an old Midwife in a velvet Hat, were a goddesse to this: that a red Lip!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="28"/>
<SPEAKER>Pre.</SPEAKER>
<L>There's a red Nose.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>That a yellow haire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why? her teeth may be yellow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where's the full Eye?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee has full blabber Cheekes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Set up thy rest, her marriest thou or none.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<P>None then, were all the Water in the World one Sea, all Kingdomes one Mountaine. I would climbe on all foure, up to the top of that Hill, and head-long hurle my selfe into that abisse of waves e're I would touch the skin of such rough Haberdine, for the breath of her Picture stinkes hither.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>A noyse Within. Enter Don John, Diego, Cardochia, Sancho, and Soto in a hurry.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>What tumult's this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San. Soto.</SPEAKER>
<P>Murder, murder, murder, one of our Gipsies is in danger of hanging, hanging!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ped.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who is hurt?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Die.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis I my Lord, stab'd by this Gipsie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Jo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee struck me first, and I'le not take a blow</L>
<L>From any <HI>Spaniard</HI> breathing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you so brave?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Breake up your play: lock all the doores.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Die.</SPEAKER>
<L>I faint my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fra.</SPEAKER>
<L>Have him to a Surgeon, how fell they out?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh! my good Lord, these Gipsies when they lodg'd</L>
<L>At my house, I had a Jewell from my Pocket</L>
<L>Stolne by this Villaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Joh.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis most false my Lords,</L>
<L>Her own hands gave it mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pre.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee that calls him Villaine,</L>
<L>Or sayes he stole.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hoyday, we heare your scoulding.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>And the hurt Gentleman finding it in his bosome</L>
<L>For that hee stab'd him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hence with all the Gipsies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ped.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ruffians and Theeves, to prison with 'em all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord wee'l leave engagements, in Plate and Money</L>
<L>For all our safe forth-commings; punish not all</L>
<L>For one's offence, wee'l prove our selves no Theeves.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="29"/>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh <HI>Soto!</HI> I make Buttons.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would I could make some, and leave this Trade.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Iron him then, let the rest goe free, but stir not one foote</L>
<L>Out of <HI>Madrill;</HI> bring you in your witnesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<P>Prick him with a Pinne, or pinch him by the Elbow; any thing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord <HI>Don Pedro,</HI> I am your Ward, wee have spent a little Money to get a horrible deale of Wit, and now I am weary of it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pe.</SPEAKER>
<L>My runne-awayes turn'd Juglers! Fortune-Tellers!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<L>No great Fortunes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>To Prison with 'em both: a Genleman play the Asse!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>If all Gentlemen that play the Asse should to Prison, you must widen your Jayles. Come <HI>Soto,</HI> I scorne to beg, set thy foot to mine, and kick at shackles.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>So, so, away with 'em.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<P>Send all our Company after, and wee'l play there, and be as merry as you here. <STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our Comedy turn'd Tragicall! please you Lords walke.</L>
<L>This Actor here and I must change a word,</L>
<L>And I come to you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well my Lord, your pleasure—</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why? couldst thou thinke in any base disguise</L>
<L>To blinde my sight? Fathers have Eagles Eyes.</L>
<L>But pray sir why was this done? why when I thought you</L>
<L>Fast lock'd in <HI>Salamanca,</HI> at your Study,</L>
<L>Leap'd you into a Gipsie?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, with your pardon,</L>
<L>I shall at fit time, to you shew cause for all:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Meane time sir, you have got a Trade to live by,</L>
<L>Best to turne Player, an excellent Ruffian! ha!</L>
<L>But know sir, when I had found you out, I gave you</L>
<L>This project of set purpose, 'tis all my selfe,</L>
<L>What the old Gipsie spake must be my Language,</L>
<L>Nothing are left me but my Offices,</L>
<L>And thin-fac'd honours, and this very Creature</L>
<L>By you so scorn'd, must raise me by your Marrying her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>You would not build your glory on my ruines.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Rascall has bely'd the Lady,</L>
<L>Shee is not halfe so bad, all's one, shee's rich.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="29"/>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh! will you see the joyes of my full youth?</L>
<L>To Dunghill muck, seeke out some wretches Daughter;</L>
<L>Whose soule is lost for gold then? you are more noble</L>
<L>Then t'have your Son, the top branch of your house</L>
<L>Grow in a heape of rubbish; I must marry a thing,</L>
<L>I shall be asham'd to owne, asham'd to bring her</L>
<L>Before a Sun-beame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>I cannot helpe it sir, resolve upon't, and doo't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>And doo't and die.</L>
<L>Is there no face in <HI>Spaine</HI> for you to pick out</L>
<L>But one to fright mee? when you sat the Play here</L>
<L>There was a beauty, to be Lord of which</L>
<L>I would against an Army throw defiance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee! Alas.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>How! how! at every haire of her's</L>
<L>There hangs a very Angel, this! I am ready</L>
<L>To drop down looking at it: Sir I beseech you</L>
<L>Bury mee in this Earth, on which I am humbled</L>
<L>To beg your blessing on mee for a Gipsie,</L>
<L>Rather then—oh! I know not what to terme it.</L>
<L>Pray what is that young pensive piece of beauty?</L>
<L>Your voyce for her, I ey'd her all the scene.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>I saw you did.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Me thought 'twas a sweete Creature.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well tho my present state stands now on Ice,</L>
<L>I'le let it crack and fall, rather then bar thee</L>
<L>Of thy content, this Lady shall goe by then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hang let her there, or any where.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>That young Lannard,</L>
<L>Whom you have such a minde to, if you can whistle her</L>
<L>To come to Fist, make tryall, play the young Falconer.</L>
<L>I will nor mar your marriage, nor yet make</L>
<L>Beauty no wealth, wealth uglinesse, which you wil take.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thanke you sir, put on your Mask good Madam,</L>
<L>The Sun will spoyle your Face else.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="30"/>
<HEAD>ACTUS QUINTUS.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Fernando, Francisco, Pedro, Roderigo, Clara, Maria, as from Church ever the Stage, Fer. stayes Roderigo.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>THou hast now the Wife of thy desires.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, I have;</L>
<L>And in her every blessing that makes Life</L>
<L>Loath to be parted with.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Noble shee is,</L>
<L>And faire, has to enrich her Blood and Beauty</L>
<L>Plenty of Wit, Discourse, Behaviour, Carriage.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>I ow you duty for a double birth,</L>
<L>Being in this happinesse begot againe,</L>
<L>Without which I had been a man of wretchednesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then henceforth, Boy, learne to obey thy fate,</L>
<L>'Tis falne upon thee, know it, and embrace it:</L>
<L>Thy Wife's a wanton.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>A wanton!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Examine through the progresse of thy youth,</L>
<L>What capitall sins, what great one 'tis, for 'tis</L>
<L>A great one th'ast committed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>I a great one!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Else Heaven is not so wrathfull to poure on thee</L>
<L>A misery so full of bitternesse;</L>
<L>I am thy Father, thinke on't, and be just;</L>
<L>Come doe not dally.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Foole 'twere</L>
<L>Impossible that Justice should raine downe</L>
<L>In such a frightfull horror without cause.</L>
<L>Sir, I will know it, rather blush thou didst</L>
<L>An act thou darst not name then that it has</L>
<L>A name to be knowne by.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Turne from mee then,</L>
<L>And as my guilt sighes out this monster Rape,</L>
<L>Oh! doe not lend an Eare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rape! fearefull.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="30"/>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hence, hence springs my due reward.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Th'art none of mine.</L>
<L>Or if thou beest, thou dost bely the stampe</L>
<L>Of thy Nativity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Forgive me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Had shee</L>
<L>Poore wronged Soule (who e're shee was) no Friend,</L>
<L>Nor Father to revenge, had shee no Tongue</L>
<L>To rore her injuries?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas I know her not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace thou wilt blaze a sin beyond all president,</L>
<L>Young man thou shouldst have married her, the Devill</L>
<L>Of lust that riots in thy Eye, should there</L>
<L>Have let full love and pity; not on this stranger</L>
<L>Whom thou hast doted on.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh! had I married her,</L>
<L>I had been then the happiest man alive:</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Clara, Maria, and Pedro: from behinde the Arras.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>As I the happiest Woman being married,</L>
<L>Looke on me sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ped.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall not finde a change</L>
<L>So full of feares as your most noble Father,</L>
<L>In his wise Triall urg'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeed you shall not,</L>
<L>The forfeit of her shame shall be her pawne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why pray d'ee mock my sorrowes? now oh now</L>
<L>My horrors flew about me!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>No thy comforts,</L>
<L>Thy blessings <HI>Roderigo.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>By this Crucifix</L>
<L>You may remember me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha! art thou that Lady wrong'd?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>I was, but now am</L>
<L>Righted in noble satisfaction.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>How can I turne mine Eyes, and not behold</L>
<L>On every side my shame!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more hereafter,</L>
<L>Wee shall have time to talke at large of all,</L>
<L>Love her that's now thine own, doe <HI>Roderigo.</HI></L>
<L>

<PB REF="31"/>
Shee's farre from what I charactred.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>My care shall live about me to deserve your love.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Excellent <HI>Clara</HI>—Fathers both, and Mother,</L>
<L>I will redeeme my fault.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer. Ped. Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our blessings dwell on yee.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Lewys and Francisco.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Married to <HI>Roderigo!</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fra.</SPEAKER>
<L>Judge your selfe,</L>
<L>See where they are.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is this your Husband Lady?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>He is sir, Heavens great hand that on Record,</L>
<L>Fore-points the equall Union of all hearts,</L>
<L>Long since decreed, what this day hath been perfected.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis well then, I am free it seemes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Make smooth</L>
<L>My Lord, those clowds which on your brow deliver</L>
<L>Emblems of storme; I will as far as honour</L>
<L>May priviledge, deserve a noble friendship,</L>
<L>As you from mee deserve a worthy memory.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Husband has prov'd himselfe a friend,</L>
<L>Trusty and try'd, he's welcome I may say</L>
<L>From the University,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>To a new Schoole</L>
<L>Of happy knowledge <HI>Lewys.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, I am not so poore to put this injury up,</L>
<L>The best blood flowes within you is the price.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Lewys</HI> for this time calcalme your anger,</L>
<L>And if I do not give you noble satisfaction,</L>
<L>Call mee to what account you please.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>So, so, I come for Justice t'ee,</L>
<L>And you shall grant it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall and will.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>With speede too.</L>
<L>My poore friend bleeds the whiles.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall your selfe</L>
<L>Before wee part, receive the satisfaction</L>
<L>You come for, who attends</L>
<L>My Lord?</L>
<STAGE>Within Servants.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Prisoner.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>He attends your Lordships pleasure.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>

<PB REF="31"/>
Enter Pretiosa, Eugenia, and Alvarez.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>What would this Girle? foh no tricks.</L>
<L>Get you to your Cabin Hus-wife, wee have no eare for Ballads.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take her away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>A wonderous lively Creature.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pre.</SPEAKER>
<L>Noble Gentlemen,</L>
<L>If a poore Maids, a Gipsie Virgins teares</L>
<L>May soften the hard edge of angry Justice;</L>
<L>Then grant mee gracious hearing (as y'are mercifull.)</L>
<L>I beg my Husbands Life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy Husbands, little one!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pre.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gentle sir, our plighted troaths are Chronicl'd</L>
<L>In that white Booke above, which notes the secrets</L>
<L>Of every thought and heart, he is my Husband,</L>
<L>I am his Wife.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rather his Whore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pre.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now trust mee,</L>
<L>Y'are no good man to say so, I am honest,</L>
<L>Deede la I am, a poore soule that deserves not</L>
<L>Such a bad word, were you a better man</L>
<L>Then you are, you doe mee wrong.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lu:</SPEAKER>
<L>The Toy growes angry.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>And it becomes her sweetly, troath my Lord,</L>
<L>I pitty her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thanke you sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Husband</L>
<L>You'l say is no Thiefe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pre.</SPEAKER>
<L>Upon my Conscience hee is not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dares not strike a man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pre.</SPEAKER>
<L>Unworthily</L>
<L>Hee dares not, but if trod upon, a Worme</L>
<L>Will turne againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>That turning turnes your Worme</L>
<L>Off from the Ladder, Minion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pre.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, I hope</L>
<L>You are not his Judge, you are too young, too chollerick,</L>
<L>Too passionate, the price of Life or Death</L>
<L>Requires a much more grave consideration</L>
<L>Then your yeares warrant, he sit they (like gods)</L>
<L>

<PB REF="32"/>
Upon whose head the reverend badge of Time</L>
<L>Hath seal'd the proofe of Wisdome; to these Oracles</L>
<L>Of riper Judgment, lower in my heart,</L>
<L>Then on my knees, I offer up my suite,</L>
<L>My lawfull suite, which begs they would be gentle</L>
<L>To their owne fames, their own imortall stories,</L>
<L>Oh! doe not thinke my Lords compassion throwne</L>
<L>On a base low estate, on humble People</L>
<L>Lesse meritorious, then if you had favor'd</L>
<L>The faults of great men; and indeed great men</L>
<L>Have often times great faults; he whom I plead for</L>
<L>Is free, the soule of Innocence it selfe</L>
<L>Is not more white, will you pitty him?</L>
<L>I see it is in your Eyes, 'tis a sweete Sun-beame,</L>
<L>Let it shine out; and to adorne your praise</L>
<L>The prayers of the poore shall crowne your dayes,</L>
<L>And theirs are something hard.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beshrew the Girle,</L>
<L>Shee has almost melted mee to teares.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hence trifler—call in my friends,</L>
<L>What hope of ease?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Don John, Diego, and Cardochia.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Die.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good hope, but still I smart,</L>
<L>The worst is in my paine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>The price is high</L>
<L>Shall buy thy vengeance, to receive a wound</L>
<L>By a base Villaines hand, it madds me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Jo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Men subject to th' extremity of Law,</L>
<L>Should carry peace about'em to their Graves,</L>
<L>Else were you nobler then the blood you boast of,</L>
<L>Could any way (my Lord) derive you know,</L>
<L>I would returne sharpe answer to your slanders;</L>
<L>But it suffices I am none of ought</L>
<L>Your rage mistermes mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>None of 'em, no Rascall?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Jo.</SPEAKER>
<L>No Rascall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor no Theefe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Jo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Aske her, that's my Accuser, could your Eyes</L>
<L>

<PB REF="32"/>
Pierce through the secrets of her foule desires;</L>
<L>You might without a parciall Judgement, looke into</L>
<L>A Womans Lust and Malice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>My good Lords,</L>
<L>What I have Articled against this fellow,</L>
<L>I justifie for truth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Jo.</SPEAKER>
<L>On then, no more,</L>
<L>This being true shee sayes; I have deserv'd</L>
<L>To die.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee sit not here to bandy Words,</L>
<L>But minister Law, and that condemns thee</L>
<L>For theft unto the Gallowes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pre.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh my misery!</L>
<L>Are you all Marble-brested? are your bosomes</L>
<L>Hoop'd round with Steele, to cast away a man?</L>
<L>More worthy Life and Honours then a thousand</L>
<L>Of such, as onely pray unto the shaddow</L>
<L>Of abus'd greatnesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Jo.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis in vaine to storme,</L>
<L>My Fate is here determin'd!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pre.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lost Creature,</L>
<L>Art thou grown dull too; is my Love so cheape,</L>
<L>That thou court'st thy destruction, 'cause I love thee?</L>
<L>My Lords, my Lords; speake <HI>Andrew,</HI> prithee now,</L>
<L>Be not so cruell to thy selfe and mee,</L>
<L>One word of thine will doo't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away with him,</L>
<L>To morrow is his day of Execution.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Jo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Even when you will.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pre.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay man thou shalt not goe;</L>
<L>Here are more Women yet, sweete Madam speake:</L>
<L>You Lady, you methinks should have some feeling</L>
<L>Of tendernesse, you may be touch'd as I am,</L>
<L>Troath wert your cause, I'de weepe with you, and joyne</L>
<L>In earnest suite for one you held so deare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, pray speake in his behalfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would, but dare not,</L>
<L>'Tis a fault so cleere and manifest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Back with him to his Dungeon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="33"/>
<SPEAKER>Jo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heaven can tell.</L>
<L>I sorrow not to die, but to leave her,</L>
<L>Who whiles I live is my Lifes comforter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now shall I be reveng'd.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pre.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh mee unhappy!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>See the Girle falls,</L>
<L>Some one looke to her!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Las poore Maide.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eug.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Pretiosa!</HI></L>
<L>Shee does recover, mine honourable Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>In vaine, what is't?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eug.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be pleas'd to give mee private audience;</L>
<L>I will discover something shall advantage</L>
<L>The noblest of this Land.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well I will heare thee,</L>
<L>Bring in the Girle.</L>
<STAGE>Exit. Manet Lewys, Alvarez.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ought with me, what is't?</L>
<L>I care not for thy Company old Ruffin,</L>
<L>Rascall art impudent?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>To beg your service.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hang your selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>By your Fathers Soule sir, heare me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dispatch.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>First, promise mee you will get Repreeve</L>
<L>For the condemned Man, and by my Art,</L>
<L>I'le make you master of what your Heart on Earth</L>
<L>Can wish for, or desire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou ly'st thou canst not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Try mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe that, and then as I am noble,</L>
<L>I will not onely give thy friend his Life,</L>
<L>But royally reward thee, love thee ever.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>I take your word, what would you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>If thou mock'st mee,</L>
<L>'Twere better thou wert damn'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, I am resolute.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Resolve me then, whether the Count <HI>Alvarez,</HI></L>
<L>Who slew my Father, be alive or dead?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is this the mighty matter? the Count lives.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="33"/>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>How!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Count lives!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh fate I now tell mee where?</L>
<L>And be, my better genius.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>I can do't,</L>
<L>In <HI>Spaine</HI> a lives: more, not far from <HI>Madrill,</HI></L>
<L>But in disguise much alter'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wonderfull Scholler,</L>
<L>Miracle of Artists, <HI>Alvarez</HI> living!</L>
<L>And neere <HI>Madrill</HI> too! now for Heavens sake where?</L>
<L>That's all, and I am thine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Walke off my Lord</L>
<L>To the next Field, you shall know all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Apace then, I listen to thee</L>
<L>With a greedy Eare, the Miserable and the Fortunate</L>
<STAGE>Ex. at one dore▪ Enter presently at the other.</STAGE>
<L>Are alike in this, they cannot change their Fate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good, good, you would faine kill him and revenge Your Fathers Death.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bravely, or securely?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not basely for the World.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee are secure.</L>
<STAGE>Two Swords.</STAGE>
<L>Young <HI>Lewys,</HI> two more trusty blades then these,</L>
<L><HI>Spaine</HI> has not in her Army; with this</L>
<L><HI>Alvarez</HI> slew thy Father, and this other,</L>
<L>Was that the King of <HI>France</HI> wore, when great <HI>Charles</HI></L>
<L>In a set Battaile took him Prisoner;</L>
<L>Both I resigne to thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is a new Mistery.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now see this naked bosome, turns the poynts</L>
<L>Of either on this Bulwarke, if thou covet'st</L>
<L>Out of a sprightly youth, and manly thirst</L>
<L>Of vengeance blood, if blood be thy ambition,</L>
<L>Then call to minde the fatall blow that struck</L>
<L><HI>De Castor</HI> thy brave Father to his Grave;</L>
<L>Remember who it was that gave that blow,</L>
<L>His enemy <HI>Alvarez,</HI> heare, and be suddaine,</L>
<L>Behold <HI>Alvarez!</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Death, I am deluded.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="34"/>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art incredulous, as Fate is certaine</L>
<L>I am the man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou that Butcher!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tremble not young man, trust me I have wept</L>
<L>Religiously to wash off from my Conscience</L>
<L>The staine of my offence: twelve yeares and more,</L>
<L>Like to a restlesse Pilgrime I have runne</L>
<L>From foraigne Lands to Lands, to finde out Death.</L>
<L>I am weary of my Life, give mee a Sword,</L>
<L>That thou may'st know with what a perfect zeale</L>
<L>I honour old <HI>De Castors</HI> memory;</L>
<L>I'le fight with thee, I would not have thy hand</L>
<L>Dip'd in a wilfull Murder, I could wish</L>
<L>For one howers space I could pluck back from Time,</L>
<L>But thirty of my yeares, that in my fall</L>
<L>Thou mightst deserve report: now if thou Conquerst</L>
<L>Thou canst not triumph, I am halfe dead already,</L>
<L>Yet I'le not start a foote.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Breathes there a spirit</L>
<L>In such a heape of rage?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh! that I had</L>
<L>A Sonne of equall growth with thee, to tug</L>
<L>For Reputation: by thy Fathers ashes,</L>
<L>I would not kill thee for an other <HI>Spaine,</HI></L>
<L>Yet now I'le do my best, thou art amaz'd,</L>
<L>Come on.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Twelve tedious Winters banishment!</L>
<L>'Twas a long time.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Could they redeeme thy Father?</L>
<L>Would every Age had beene twelve Ages <HI>Lewys,</HI></L>
<L>And I for Pennance every Age a dying,</L>
<L>But 'tis too late to wish.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am o'recome,</L>
<L>Your noblenesse hath conquer'd mee, here ends</L>
<L>All strife betweene our Families, and henceforth</L>
<L>Acknowledge mee for yours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh! thou reviv'st</L>
<L>Fresh horrours to my Fact, for in thy gentlenesse</L>
<L>I see my sinne anew.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="34"/>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our peace is made,</L>
<L>Your Life shall be my care, 'twill be glad newes</L>
<L>To all our noble friends.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Since Heaven will have it so,</L>
<L>I thanke thee glorious Majesty; my Sonne</L>
<L>For I will call thee, e're the next morrow:</L>
<L>Salute the World, thou shalt know stranger mysteries.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have enough to feede on; sir I'le follow yee.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Eugenia, Fernando, and Pretiosa.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Don John</HI> Sonne to the Count of <HI>Carcomo,</HI></L>
<L>Woman take heede thou trifle not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is this</L>
<L>My Lord so strange?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beauty in Youth, and Wit</L>
<L>To set it forth, I see transformes the best</L>
<L>Into what shape Love fancies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pre.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you yet</L>
<L>Give me my Husbands Life?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why little one hee is not Married to thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pre.</SPEAKER>
<L>In his Faith</L>
<L>He is; and faith and troath. I hope binde faster,</L>
<L>Then any other Ceremonies can,</L>
<L>Doe they not pray my Lord?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, where the Parties</L>
<L>Pledg'd, are not too unequall in degree,</L>
<L>As hee and thou art.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pre.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is new Divinity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, behold this Childe well: in her Face,</L>
<L>You may observe by curious insight, something</L>
<L>More then belongs to every common birth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>True, 'tis a pretty Child.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Glasse of misery</L>
<L>Is after many a change of desperate fortune,</L>
<L>At length runne out, you had a Daughter</L>
<L>Call'd <HI>Constanza.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Sister <HI>Guyamara,</HI></L>
<L>Wife to the Count <HI>Alvarez.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="35"/>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace, oh peace!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>And to that Sisters charge you did commit</L>
<L>Your Infant Daughter, in whose birth your Wife</L>
<L>Her Mother dy'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Woman thou art too cruell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pre.</SPEAKER>
<P>What d'ee meane Granam? Lass the noble man Growes angry.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not I, indeed I doe not,</L>
<L>But why d'ee use mee thus?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Child and Sister,</L>
<L>As you suppos'd were drown'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Drown'd, talking Creature!</L>
<L>Suppos'd!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>They live <HI>Fernando</HI> from my hand,</L>
<L>Thy Sisters hand receive thine owne <HI>Constanza,</HI></L>
<L>The sweetest best Child living.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pre.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe you mock me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Torment me on, yet more, more yet and spare not,</L>
<L>My heart is now a breaking: now!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh Brother!</L>
<L>Am I so farre removed off from your Memory,</L>
<L>As that you will not know mee? I expected</L>
<L>An other welcome home, looke on this Casket,</L>
<STAGE>A Casket.</STAGE>
<L>The Legacy your Lady left her Daughter,</L>
<L>When to her Sonne, shee gave her Crucifix.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Right, right, I know yee now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>In all my sorrowes,</L>
<L>My comfort has been here; shee should be,</L>
<L>Be yours, <HI>Constanza</HI> kneele sweete Childe</L>
<L>To thy old Father.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pre.</SPEAKER>
<L>How my Father?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let not</L>
<L>Extremity of joyes ravish Life from mee</L>
<L>Too soone Heaven I beseech thee; thou art my Sister,</L>
<L>My Sister <HI>Guyamara;</HI> how have mine Eyes</L>
<L>Been darkened all this while:—'tis shee!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis Brother,</L>
<L>And this <HI>Constanza,</HI> now no more a stranger,</L>
<L>No <HI>Pretiosa</HI> henceforth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="35"/>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>My soules treasure,</L>
<L>Live to an Age of goodnesse, and so thrive</L>
<L>In all thy wayes, that thou mayst die to live.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pre.</SPEAKER>
<L>But must I call you Father?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou wilt rob mee else</L>
<L>Of that felicity; for whose sake onely</L>
<L>I am ambitious of being young againe;</L>
<L>Rise, rise, mine own <HI>Constanza.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pre.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis a new name,</L>
<L>But 'tis a pretty one, I may be bold</L>
<L>To make a suite t'ee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Any thing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pre.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh Father!</L>
<L>And if you be my Father thinke upon</L>
<L><HI>Don John</HI> my Husband, without him alas</L>
<L>I can be nothing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>As I without thee,</L>
<L>Let me alone <HI>Constanza,</HI> tell mee, tell mee,</L>
<L>Lives yet <HI>Alvarez?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>In your house.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Enough.</L>
<L>Cloy mee not, let me by degrees, disgest</L>
<L>My joyes—within, my Lords <HI>Francisco, Pedro.</HI></L>
<STAGE>Enter Francisco, Pedro, Maria, Roderigo, Clara</STAGE>
<L>Come all at once, I have a World within mee,</L>
<L>I am not mortall sure, I am not mortall,</L>
<L>My honorable Lord, partake my blessings.</L>
<L>Count <HI>Alvarez</HI> lives here in my house;</L>
<L>Your Sonne my Lord, <HI>Francisco, Don John</HI></L>
<L>Is the condemn'd man falsely accus'd of theft,</L>
<L>This my Lord <HI>Pedro,</HI> is my Sister <HI>Guyamare,</HI></L>
<L>Madam, this <HI>Constanza</HI> mine owne Child,</L>
<L>And I am a wondrous merry Man,</L>
<L>Without the Prisoner.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Alvarez, Lewys, Don John, Diego, Sancho, Soto, and Cardocha.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here free and acquited,</L>
<L>

<PB REF="36"/>
By her whose folly drew her to this errour,</L>
<L>And shee for satisfaction is assur'd</L>
<L>To my wrong'd friend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>I crave your pardons,</L>
<L>Hee whose I am, speakes for mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Die.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee both beg it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Excellent, Admirable; my deare Brother.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Never a happy man till now: young <HI>Lewys</HI></L>
<L>And I are reconcil'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lew.</SPEAKER>
<L>For ever faithfully, religiously.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<L>My noble Lord most welcome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>To all my heart payes what it owes, due thanks</L>
<L>Most, most brave youth to thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Jo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I all this while,</L>
<L>Stand but a looker on, and tho my Father</L>
<L>May justly tax the violence of my Passions,</L>
<L>Yet if this Lady, Lady of my life</L>
<L>Must be deny'd, let mee be as I was,</L>
<L>And die betimes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pre.</SPEAKER>
<L>You promis'd mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>I did,</L>
<L>My Lord of <HI>Carcomo,</HI> you see their hearts</L>
<L>Are joyn'd already, so let our consents</L>
<L>To this wish'd Marriage.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fra.</SPEAKER>
<L>I forgive thine errors,</L>
<L>Give mee thy hand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Me thine! but wilt thou love</L>
<L>My Daughter, my <HI>Constanza?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Jo.</SPEAKER>
<L>As my bliss.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pre.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thee as Life, Youth, Beauty, any thing</L>
<L>That makes life comfortable.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Live together one, ever one.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<L>And Heaven Crown your happinesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ped.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now sir, how like you a Prison?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>As Gallants doe a Taverne, being stop'd for a Reckoning, scurvily.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soto.</SPEAKER>
<P>Though you Cag'd us up never so close, wee Sung like Cuckoes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, well, you be your selfe now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="36"/>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>My selfe, am I out of my Wits <HI>Soto?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here now are none but honourable Friends,</L>
<L>Will you to give a farwell to the life</L>
<L>You ha led as Gipsies, these being now found none,</L>
<L>But noble in their Births, alterd in Fortunes,</L>
<L>Give it a merry shaking by the hand;</L>
<L>And cry adue to folly?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wee'l shake our Hands, and our Heeles if you'l give us leave. <STAGE>Dance.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>On Brides, and Bride-Groomes to your Spanish Feasts,</L>
<L>Invite with bent Knees all these Noble Guests.</L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

