<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2011-07-26</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Lauren Proux</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Checklist: x Add TEMPHEAD, change DATE, validate x Add DIV TYPEs, validate x Review structure, use BODY or rarely GROUP x Check PB placement and completeness, ensure sequence of N="" x Proof title page(s) x Check HEAD TRAILER ARGUMENT EPIGRAPH OPENER CLOSER SIGNED SALUTE BYLINE x Check <SUP>,</SUP> oe, abq (Esq;), italic I / J, <SEG REND="decorInit">I</SEG>nitals, &amp;c. x Check # @ -- UNCLEAR LB FIGURE x Check q; startq endq Q&gt; x Correct illegibles from proofsheet x Check illegible page, para, line, span, word, dollar signs Final validate Corrected [ ] illegible groups out of [ ]. Converted [ ] illegible groups to GAP DESC="illegible". DONE</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A93167">
<STC T="W">S3461</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99895772</BIBNO>
<VID>153343</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>THE CARDINAL, A TRAGEDIE, AS It was acted at the private House IN <HI>BLACK FRYERS,</HI> WRITTEN By JAMES SHIRLEY.</P>
<P>Not Printed before.</P>
<P><HI>LONDON,</HI> Printed for <HI>Humphrey Robinson</HI> at the Pigeons, and <HI>Humphrey Moseley</HI> at the Arms in St. <HI>Paul</HI>'s Church-yard. 1652.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>To my worthily honored Friend <HI>G. B.</HI> Esq</HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>SIR,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P><HI>I</HI> Did suffer at the first some contention with∣in me, and looking upon my self, was inclined to stifle my ambitious thoughts in this Dedi∣cation; but when some time, and a happy con∣versation, had preferred me to more acquaintance with you, (which was more argument to me, than the fame I had heard of your reputation, with the most temperate and ingenious men) I found you not only an excellent Judge, but a good Man: at this my modesty took full encouragement, to make this offering, which as I conceive to be the best of my flock, I knew not a better Altar whereon to make it a sacrifice, with this protestation, that it comes (and that is it only, which makes all devoti∣ons
<PB REF="3"/>acceptable) from the heart, and your candid acceptance will bind me with all my services, and remembrance, to merit a reception with you, in the quality and honour of,</P>
<CLOSER><SALUTE>Sir,</SALUTE>
<SIGNED>Your most humble devoted Servant, <HI>JA. SHIRLEY</HI></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="prologue">
<PB REF="3"/>
<HEAD>Prologue.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L>THe Cardinal, cause we express no scene,</L>
<L>We doe believe most of you Gentlemen</L>
<L>Are at this hour in <HI>France,</HI> and busie there,</L>
<L>Though you vouchsafe to lend your bodies here;</L>
<L>But keep your fancy active, till you know</L>
<L>By th' progress of our Play, 'tis nothing so;</L>
<L>A Poets art is to lead on your thought</L>
<L>Through subtle paths and workings of a plot,</L>
<L>And where your expectation does not thrive,</L>
<L>If things fall better, yet you may forgive;</L>
<L>I will say nothing positive, you may</L>
<L>Think what you please, we call it but a Play,</L>
<L>Whether the comick Muse, or Ladies love,</L>
<L>Romance, or direfull Tragedy it prove,</L>
<L>The Bill determines not; and would you be</L>
<L>Perswaded, I would have't a Comedie,</L>
<L>For all the purple in the name, and state</L>
<L>Of him that owns it; but 'tis left to fate;</L>
<L>Yet I will tell you e'r you see it plaid,</L>
<L>What the Author, and he blusht too, when he said</L>
<L>(Comparing with his own for 't had been pride</L>
<L>He thought, to build his wit a Pyramyde.</L>
<L>Vpon anothers wounded Fame,) this Play</L>
<L>Might rivall with his best, and dar'd to say</L>
<L>Troth I am out; he said no more; you then,</L>
<L>When'ts done, may say your pleasures Gentlemen.</L>
</LG>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="encomium">
<PB REF="4"/>
<HEAD>To the surviving Honour and Ornament of the English Scene, <HI>Iames Shirley.</HI></HEAD>
<LG>
<L>AS Fate, which doth all human matters sway,</L>
<L>Makes produest things grow up into decay;</L>
<L>And when they are to envyed greatness grown,</L>
<L>She wantonly falls off, and throws them down:</L>
<L>So, when our English Dramma was at hight,</L>
<L>And shin'd, and rul'd with Majesty and might,</L>
<L>A sudden whirlwind threw it from it seat,</L>
<L>Deflowr'd the Groves, and quench'd the Muses heat.</L>
<L>Yet as in Saints, and Martyr'd bodies, when</L>
<L>They cannot call their blessed Souls agen</L>
<L>To earth; Reliques, and ashes men preserve,</L>
<L>And think they do, but what, blest they deserve:</L>
<L>So I, by my devotion led, aspire</L>
<L>To keep alive your noble Vestal fire,</L>
<L>Honour this piece, which shews, Sir, you have been</L>
<L>The last supporter of the dying Scene;</L>
<L>And though I do not tell you, how you dress</L>
<L>Virtue in gloryes, and bold vice depress;</L>
<L>Nor celebrate your lovely Dutchess fall,</L>
<L>Or the just ruine of your Cardinal;</L>
<L>Yet this I dare assert, when men have nam'd</L>
<L><HI>Iohnson</HI> (the Nations Laureat,) the fam'd</L>
<L><HI>Beaumont,</HI> and <HI>Fletcher,</HI> he, that wo'not see</L>
<L><HI>Shirley,</HI> the fourth, must forfeit his best ey.</L>
</LG>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>HALL.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dramatis personae">
<PB REF="4"/>
<PB REF="5"/>
<HEAD>Persons.</HEAD>
<LIST>
<ITEM><HI>KIng of</HI> Navarre.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Cardinal.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Columbo, <HI>the Cardinals Nephew.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Alvarez.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Hernando, <HI>a Colonel.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Alphonso.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Lords.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Secretary <HI>to the Dutchess.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Colonels</ITEM>
<ITEM>Antonelli, <HI>the Cardinals Servant.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Surgion.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Guard.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Attendants, &amp;c.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Dutchess</HI> Rosaura▪</ITEM>
<ITEM>Valeria, <HI>Ladies.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Celinda, <HI>Ladies.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Placentia, <HI>a Lady that waits upon the Dutchess.</HI></ITEM>
</LIST>
<P><HI>Scene Navarre.</HI></P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="play">
<PB N="1" REF="5"/>
<HEAD>THE CARDINAL.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACT I.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter two Lords (at one door) Secretary (at the other.)</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Lord.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L><SEG REND="decorInit">W</SEG>Ho is that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Lo.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>The Dutchess Secretary.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Lo.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Signior.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Secr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Lordships Servant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Lo.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>How does her Grace since she left her mourning</L>
<L>For the young Duke <HI>Mendoza,</HI> whose timeless death</L>
<L>At Sea, left her a Virgin and a Widdow?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Lo.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Shee's now inclining to a second Bride,</L>
<L>When is the day of mighty mariage</L>
<L>To our great Cardinals Nephew, <HI>Don Columbo?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Secr.</SPEAKER>
<L>When they agree; they wo'not steal to Church,</L>
<L>I guess the ceremonies will be loud, and publick.</L>
<L>Your Lordships will excuse me.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Lo.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>When they agree? alas poor Lady, she</L>
<L>Dotes not upon <HI>Columbo,</HI> when she thinks</L>
<L>Of the young Count <HI>D'Alvarez,</HI> divorc'd from her</L>
<L>By the Kings power.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Lo.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>And Counsell of the Cardinal to advance</L>
<L>His Nephew to the Dutchess bed; 'tis not well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Lo.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Take heed, the Cardinal holds intelligence</L>
<PB REF="6"/>
<L>With every bird i'th' air.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Lo.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Death on his purple pride,</L>
<L>He governs all, and yet, <HI>Columbo</HI> is</L>
<L>A gallant Gentleman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Lo.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>The darling of the War, whom Victory</L>
<L>Hath often courted; a man of daring</L>
<L>And most exalted spirit, pride in him</L>
<L>Dwels like an ornament, where so much honour</L>
<L>Secures his praise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Lo.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>This is no argument</L>
<L>He should usurp, and wear <HI>Alvarez</HI> title</L>
<L>To the fair Dutchess, men of coarser blood</L>
<L>Would not so tamely give this treasure up.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Lo.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Although <HI>Columbos</HI> name is great in war,</L>
<L>Whose glorious art and practice is above</L>
<L>The greatness of <HI>Alvarez,</HI> yet he cannot</L>
<L>Want soul, in whom alone survives the virtue</L>
<L>Of many noble Ancestors, being the last</L>
<L>Of his great family</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Lo.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis not safe, you'l say, to wrastle with the King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Lo.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>More danger if the Cardinal be displeas'd,</L>
<L>Who sits at helm of State; Count <HI>D' Alvarez</HI></L>
<L>Is wiser to obey the stream, than by</L>
<L>Insisting on his privilege to her love,</L>
<L>Put both their fate upon a storm.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Lo.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>If Wisdom, not inborn Fear make him compose,</L>
<L>I like it; how does the Dutchess bear herself?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Lo.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>She moves by the rapture of another wheel</L>
<L>That must be obey'd, like some sad passenger,</L>
<L>That looks upon the coast his wishes fly to,</L>
<L>But is transported by an adverse wind, sometimes</L>
<L>A churlish Pilot.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Lo.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>She has a sweet and noble nature.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Lo.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>That commend; <HI>Alvarez, Hymen</HI> cannot tie</L>
<L>A knot of two more equall hearts and blood.</L>
</SP>
<PB REF="6"/>
<STAGE>Enter Alphonso.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Lo.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Alphonso?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alph.</SPEAKER>
<L>My good Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Lo.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>What great affair</L>
<L>Hath brought you from the confines?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Such as will</L>
<L>Be worth your counsells, when the King hath read</L>
<L>My Letters from the Governour; the <HI>Arragonians,</HI></L>
<L>Violating their confederate oath and league,</L>
<L>Are now in arms; they have not yet marcht towards us,</L>
<L>But 'tis not safe to expect if we may timely</L>
<L>Prevent Invasion</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Lo.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Dare they be so insolent?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Lo.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>This storm I did foresee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Lo.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>What have they, but the sweetness of the King,</L>
<L>To make a crime?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Lo.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>But how appears the Cardinal</L>
<L>At this news?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not pale, although</L>
<L>He knows they have no cause to think him innocent,</L>
<L>As by whose Counsell they were once surpriz'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Lo.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>There is more</L>
<L>Than all our present art can fathome in</L>
<L>This story, and I fear I may conclude,</L>
<L>This flame has breath at home to cherish it;</L>
<L>Ther's treason in some hearts, whose faces are</L>
<L>Smooth to the State.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lords, I take my leave.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Lo.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Your friends good Captain.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Excunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Dutchess, Valeria, Celinda.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweet Madam be less thoughtfull, this obedience</L>
<L>To passion, will destroy the noblest frame</L>
<L>Of beauty that this Kingdom ever boasted.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>This sadness might become your other habit,</L>
<L>And ceremonious black for him that died;</L>
<PB REF="7"/>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he times of sorrow are expir'd, and all</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he joys that wait upon the Court, your birth,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd a new <HI>Hymen</HI> that is coming towards you,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nvite a change.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ladies, I thank you both,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> pray excuse a little melancholy</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hat is behind, my year of mourning hath not</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o cleer'd my account with sorrow, but there may</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ome dark thoughts stay, with sad reflections,</L>
<L>Upon my heart for him I lost; even this</L>
<L>New dress, and smiling garment, meant to shew</L>
<L>A peace concluded twixt my grief and me,</L>
<L>Is but a sad remembrance: but I resolve</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o entertain more pleasing thoughts, and if</L>
<L>You wish me heartily to smile, you must</L>
<L>Not mention grief, not in advice to leave it;</L>
<L>Such Counsells open but afresh the wounds</L>
<L>Ye would close up; and keep alive the cause,</L>
<L>Whose bleeding you would cure; lets talk of something</L>
<L>That may delight; you two are read in all</L>
<L>The Histories of our Court; tell me <HI>Valeria,</HI></L>
<L>Who has thy vote for the most handsome man?</L>
<L>Thus I must counterfeit a peace, when all</L>
<L>Within me is at mutiny.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have examin'd</L>
<L>All that are Candidates for the praise of Ladies.</L>
<L>But find—may I speak boldly to your Grace?</L>
<L>And will you not return it in your mirth,</L>
<L>To make me blush?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, no; speak freely.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>I wo'not rack your patience Madam, but</L>
<L>Were I a Princess, I should think Count <HI>D' Alvarez</HI></L>
<L>Had sweetness to deserve me from the world.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Alvarez!</HI> shee's a spy upon my heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee's young, and active, and compos'd most sweet∣ly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have seen a face more tempting.</L>
</SP>
<PB REF="7"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>It had then</L>
<L>Too much of woman in't, his eys speak movingly</L>
<L>Which may excuse his voice, and lead away</L>
<L>All female pride his captive; His hair Black,</L>
<L>Which naturally falling into curl's—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prethee no more, thou art in love with him.</L>
<L>The man in your esteem <HI>Celinda</HI> now?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Alvarez</HI> is (I must confess) a Gentleman</L>
<L>Of handsome composition, but with</L>
<L>His mind (the greater excellence) I think</L>
<L>Another may delight a Lady more,</L>
<L>If man be well considered, that's <HI>Columbo,</HI></L>
<L>Now, Madam, voted to be yours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Torment!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>She affects him not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>He has person, and a bravery beyond</L>
<L>All men that I observe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>He is a Souldier,</L>
<L>A rough-hewn man, and may shew well at distance;</L>
<L>His talk will fright a Lady; War, and grim-</L>
<L>Fac'd-honor are his Mistrisses; he raves</L>
<L>To hear a Lute; Love meant him not his Priest.</L>
<L>Again your pardon Madam; we may talk,</L>
<L>But you have art to choose and crown affection.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>What is it to be born above these Ladies</L>
<L>And want their freedom? they are not constrain'd,</L>
<L>Nor slav'd by their own greatness, or the Kings;</L>
<L>But let their free hearts look abroad, and choose</L>
<L>By their own eys to love; I must repair</L>
<L>My poor afflicted bosome, and assume</L>
<L>The privilege I was born with; which now prompts me</L>
<L>To tell the King he hath no power nor art</L>
<L>To steer a Lovers Soul.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Secretary.</STAGE>
<L>What says Count <HI>D'Alvares?</HI></L>
</SP>
<PB N="6" REF="8"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam hee'l attend you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wait you as I directed, when he comes</L>
<L>Acquaint me privately.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, I have news,</L>
<L>'Tis now arriv'd the Court, we shall have wars.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>I find an Army here of killing thoughts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>The King has chosen <HI>Don Columbo</HI> General,</L>
<L>Who is immediately to take his leave.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>What flood is let into my heart! how far</L>
<L>Is he to go?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>To <HI>Arragon.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's well</L>
<L>At first, he should not want a pilgrimage</L>
<L>To the unknown World, if my thoughts might convey him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis not impossible he may go thither.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>How?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>To the unknown other World, he goes to fight,</L>
<L>That's in his way, such stories are in nature.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Conceal this news.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>He wo'not be long absent;</L>
<L>The affair will make him swift to kiss your Graces hand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>He cannot flie</L>
<L>With too much wing to take his leave; I must</L>
<L>Be admitted to your conference; ye have</L>
<L>Enlarg'd my spirits, they shall droop no more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are happy, if we may advance one thought</L>
<L>To your Graces pleasure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your ey before was in eclipse, these smiles</L>
<L>Become you Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have not skill to contain my self.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Placentia.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pla.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Cardinals Nephew, Madam, <HI>Don Columbo.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Already? attend him.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ex. Plac.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall we take our leave?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>He shall not know <HI>Valeria</HI> how you prais'd him.</L>
</SP>
<PB N="7" REF="8"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>If He did, Madam, I should have the confidence</L>
<L>To tell him my free thoughts.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Columbo.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, while I'm in study to requite</L>
<L>The Favour you ha' done me, you increase</L>
<L>My debt to such a sum, still by a new honouring</L>
<L>Your servant, I despair of my own freedom.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, he kisseth your white hand, that must</L>
<L>Not surfet in this happiness—and Ladies,</L>
<L>I take your smiles for my encouragement:</L>
<L>I have not long to practise these Court t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cticks.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<L>He has been taught to kiss.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ther's something, Sir,</L>
<L>Upon your brow I did not read before.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<L>Does the Character please you Madam?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>More,</L>
<L>Because it speaks you cheerfull.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis for such</L>
<L>Access of honour, as must make <HI>Columbo</HI></L>
<L>Worth all your love; the King is pleas'd to think</L>
<L>Me fit to lead his Army.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>How, an Army?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<L>We must not use the Priest, till I bring home</L>
<L>Another triumph, that now staies for me</L>
<L>To reap it in the purple field of glory.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>But do you mean to leave me, and expose</L>
<L>Your self to the devouring war? no enemy</L>
<L>Should Divide us; the King is not so cruell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<L>The King is honourable, and this grace</L>
<L>More answers my ambition, than his gift</L>
<L>Of thee, and all thy beauty, which I can</L>
<L>Love, as becomes thy Souldier, and fight</L>
<STAGE>She weeps</STAGE>
<L>To come agen, a conqueror of thee;</L>
<L>Then I must chide this fondnesse.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Secretary.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, the King, and my Lord Cardinal.</L>
</SP>
<PB N="8" REF="9"/>
<STAGE>Enter King, Cardinall, and Lords.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King:</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, I come to call a Servant from you,</L>
<L>And strengthen his excuse; the publick cause</L>
<L>Will plead for your consent; at his return</L>
<L>Your mariage shall receive triumphant ceremonies;</L>
<L>Till then you must dispence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>She appears sad</L>
<L>To part with him, I like it fairly Nephew.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is not the General a gallant man?</L>
<L>What Lady would deny him a small courtesie?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou hast converted me, and I begin</L>
<L>To wish it were no sin.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Leave that to narrow Consciences.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> pleasant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>But <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> would please one better. Do such men</L>
<L>Lie with their Pages?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would'st thou make a shift?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>He is going to a bloody business;</L>
<L>'Tis pity he should dye without some heir;</L>
<L>That Lady were hard-hearted now that would</L>
<L>Not help posterity, for the meer good</L>
<L>O'th' King and Common-wealth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art wild, we may be observ'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your will must guide me, happiness and conquest</L>
<L>Be ever waiting on his sword.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<L>Farewell.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ex. K. Col. Card Lo.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray give leave to examine a few thoughts;</L>
<L>Expect me in the Garden.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladies</SPEAKER>
<L>We attend.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ex. Ladies.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is above all expectation happy;</L>
<L>Forgive me virtue that I have dissembled,</L>
<L>And witness with me, I have not a thought</L>
<L>To tempt or to berray him, but secure</L>
<L>The promise I first made to love and honour.</L>
</SP>
<PB N="9" REF="9"/>
<STAGE>Enter Secretary.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Count <HI>D' Alvarez</HI> Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Admit him.</L>
<L>And let none enterrupt us; how shall I</L>
<L>Behave my looks? the guilt of my neglect,</L>
<L>Which had no seal from hence, will call up blood</L>
<L>To write upon my cheeks the shame and story</L>
<L>In some red Letter.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter D' Alvarez.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D' Alv.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, I present</L>
<L>One that was glad to obey your Grace, and come</L>
<L>To know what your commands are.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where I once</L>
<L>Did promise love, a love that had the Power</L>
<L>And office of a Priest to chain my heart</L>
<L>To yours, it were injustice to command.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D' Alv.</SPEAKER>
<L>But I can look upon you Madam, as</L>
<L>Becomes a servant, with as much humility,</L>
<L>(In tenderness of your honor and great fortune,)</L>
<L>Give up, when you call back your bounty, all that</L>
<L>Was mine, as I had pride to think them favours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hath love taught thee no more assurance in</L>
<L>Our mutuall vows, thou canst suspect it possible,</L>
<L>I should revoke a promise made to heaven</L>
<L>And thee so soon? this must arise from some</L>
<L>Distrust of thy own Faith.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D' Alv.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Graces pardon</L>
<L>To speak with freedom, I am not so old</L>
<L>In cunning to betray, nor young in time</L>
<L>Not to see when, and where I am at loss,</L>
<L>And how to bear my fortune, and my wounds,</L>
<L>Which if I look for health must still bleed inward,</L>
<L>(A hard and desperate condition;)</L>
<L>I am not ignorant your birth and greatness,</L>
<PB N="10" REF="10"/>
<L>Have plac'd you to grow up with the Kings grace,</L>
<L>And jealousie, which to remove, his power</L>
<L>Hath chosen a fit object for your beauty</L>
<L>To shine upon, <HI>Columbo</HI> his great fvavorite;</L>
<L>I am a man, on whom but late the King</L>
<L>Has pleas'd to cast a beam, which was not meant</L>
<L>To make me proud, but wisely to direct,</L>
<L>And light me to my safety. Oh, Dear Madam!</L>
<L>I will not call more witness of my love</L>
<L>(If you will let me still give it that name)</L>
<L>Than this, that I dare make my self a loser,</L>
<L>And to your will give all my blessings up;</L>
<L>Preserve your greatness and forget a triflle,</L>
<L>That shall at best when you have drawn me up,</L>
<L>But hang about you like a cloud, and dim</L>
<L>The glories you are born to.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Misery</L>
<L>Of birth and state! that I could shift into</L>
<L>A meaner blood, or find some art to purge</L>
<L>That part which makes my veins unequall; yet</L>
<L>Those nice distinctions have no place in us,</L>
<L>Ther's but a shadow difference, a title,</L>
<L>Thy stock partakes as much of noble sap</L>
<L>As that which feeds the root of Kings, and he</L>
<L>That writes a Lord, hath all the essence of</L>
<L>Nobility.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D' Alv.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis not a name that makes</L>
<L>Our separation, the Kings displeasure</L>
<L>Hangs a portent to fright us, and the matter</L>
<L>That feeds this exhalation is the Cardinals</L>
<L>Plot to advance his Nephew; then <HI>Columbo,</HI></L>
<L>A man made up for some prodigious Act,</L>
<L>Is fit to be considered; in all three</L>
<L>There is no character you fix upon</L>
<L>But has a form of ruine to us both.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then you do look on these with fear.</L>
</SP>
<PB N="11" REF="10"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D' Alv.</SPEAKER>
<L>With eys</L>
<L>That should think tears a duty to lament</L>
<L>Your least unkind fate; but my youth dares boldly</L>
<L>Meet all the tyranny o'th' stars, whose black</L>
<L>Malevolence but shoot my single tragedy;</L>
<L>You are above the value of many worlds</L>
<L>Peopled with such as I am.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> if <HI>Columbo</HI></L>
<L>Engag'd to war, in his hot thirst of honor,</L>
<L>Find out the Way to death?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D' Alv.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis possible.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or say, no matter by what art or mo tive</L>
<L>He gives his title up, and leave me to</L>
<L>My own Election?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D' Alv.</SPEAKER>
<L>If I then be happy</L>
<L>To have a name within your thought, there can</L>
<L>Be nothing left to crown me with New blessing;</L>
<L>But I dream thus of heaven, and wake to find</L>
<L>My amorous soul a mockery; when the Priest</L>
<L>Shall tie you to another, and the joys</L>
<L>Of mariage leave no thought at leasure to</L>
<L>Look ba<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>k upon <HI>Alvarez,</HI> that must wither</L>
<L>For loss of you, yet then I cannot lose</L>
<L>So much of what I was, once in your favour,</L>
<L>But in a sigh pray still you may live happy.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Heart is in a mist, some good star smile</L>
<L>Upon my resolution, and direct</L>
<L>Two lovers in their chast embrace to meet;</L>
<L><HI>Columbo's</HI> bed contains my winding sheet.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="act">
<PB N="12" REF="11"/>
<HEAD>ACT II.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter General Columbo, Hernando, two Colonels, Alphonso, two Captains, and other Officers, As at a Councell of War.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Columbo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I See no face in all this Councell, that</L>
<L>Hath one pale fear upon't though we arriv'd not</L>
<L>So timely to secure the Town, which gives</L>
<L>Our enemy such triumph.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Colo.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>'Twas betraid</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<L>The wealth of that one City</L>
<L>Will make the enemy glorious.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Colo.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>They dare not plunder it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<L>They give fair quarter yet,</L>
<L>They only seal up mens Estates, and keep</L>
<L>Possession for the Cities use, they take up</L>
<L>Now wares without security, and he</L>
<L>Whose single credit will not pass, puts in</L>
<L>Two leane comrades, upon whose bonds tis not</L>
<L>Religion to deny 'em.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colu.</SPEAKER>
<L>To repair this</L>
<L>With honour Gentlemen?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>My opinion is</L>
<L>To expect a while.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your reason?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Till their own</L>
<L>Surfet betray 'em, for their Souldier</L>
<L>Bred up with coarse and common bread, will shew</L>
<L>Such appetites on the rich cates they find,</L>
<L>They will spare our swords a victory, when their own</L>
<L>Riot and Luxury destroys 'em.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Colo.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>That</L>
<PB REF="11"/>
<L>Will shew our patience too like a fear.</L>
<L>With favour of his excellence I think,</L>
<L>The spoil of Cities takes not off the courage,</L>
<L>But doubles it on Souldiers; besides,</L>
<L>While we have tameness to expect, the noise</L>
<L>Of their success and plenty will encrease</L>
<L>Their Army.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis considerable, we do not</L>
<L>Exceed in Foot or Horse, our Muster not</L>
<L>'Bove sixteen thousand both; and the Infantry</L>
<L>Raw, and not disciplin'd to act.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Their hearts,</L>
<L>But with a brave thought of their Countries honour,</L>
<L>Will teach 'em how to fight, had they not seen</L>
<L>A Sword; but we decline our own too much,</L>
<L>The men are forward in their arms, and take</L>
<L>The use with Avarice of Fame.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>They rise and talk privately.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Colonell.</L>
<L>I do suspect you are a coward.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or else a traytor, take your choice, no more,</L>
<L>I calld you to a Councell Sir, of war,</L>
<L>Yet keep your place.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have worn other names.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Deserve 'em, such</L>
<L>Another were enough to unsoul an Army;</L>
<L>Ignobly talk of patience till they drink</L>
<L>And reel to death? we came to fight and force 'em</L>
<L>To mend their pace; thou hast no honour in thee,</L>
<L>Not enough noble blood to make a blush</L>
<L>For thy tame Eloquence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, I know</L>
<L>My duty to a Generall, yet there are</L>
<L>Some that have known me here; Sir, I desire</L>
<L>To quit my regiment.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colu.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall have licence. Ink and paper—</L>
</SP>
<PB REF="12"/>
<STAGE>Enter with Paper and Standish.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Colo.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>The General's displeas'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Colo.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>How is't <HI>Hernando?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Generall has found out employment for me,</L>
<L>He is writing Letters back.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>To his Mistress.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray do not trouble me, yet prethee speak,</L>
<L>And flatter not thy friend, dost think I dare</L>
<L>Not draw my sword, and use it, when cause</L>
<L>With honour calls to action?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al. Colo.</SPEAKER>
<L>With the most valiant man alive.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>You'l do me some displeasure in your loves,</L>
<L>Pray to your places.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colu.</SPEAKER>
<L>So,</L>
<L>Bear those Letters to the King,</L>
<L>It speaks my resolution before</L>
<L>Another Sun decline to charge the enemy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>A pretty Court way</L>
<L>Of di missing an Officer, I obey; success</L>
<L>Attend your Counsells.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colu.</SPEAKER>
<L>If here be any dare not look on danger,</L>
<L>And meet it like a man with scorn of death,</L>
<L>I beg his absence, and a cowards fear</L>
<L>Consume him to a ghost.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Colo.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>None such here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or if in all your Regiments you find</L>
<L>One man that does not ask to bleed with honour,</L>
<L>Give him a double pay to leave the Army;</L>
<L>Ther's service to be done, will call the spirits</L>
<L>And aid of Men.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Colo.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>You give us all new flame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colu.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am confirm'd, and you must lose no time;</L>
<L>The Souldier that was took last night, to me</L>
<L>Discover'd their whole strength, and that we have</L>
<L>A party in the town; the River that</L>
<PB REF="12"/>
<L>Opens the City to the West unguarded;</L>
<L>We must this night use art and resolutions,</L>
<L>We cannot fall ingloriously.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Capt.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>That voice is every mans.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Souldier, and Secretary with a Letter.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colu.</SPEAKER>
<L>What now?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Letters.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whence?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soul.</SPEAKER>
<L>From the Dutchess.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colu.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are welcome;</L>
<L>Meet at my Tent again this evening; yet stay,</L>
<L>Some Wine—The Dutchess health—</L>
<L>See it go round.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>It wo'not please his Excellence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Colo.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>The Dutchess health.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Cap.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>To me! more wine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Clouds are gathering, and his eys shoot fire;</L>
<L>Observe what thunder follows.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Cap.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>The Generall has but ill news, I suspect</L>
<L>The Dutchess sick, or else the King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Cap.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>May be the Cardinal.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Cap.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>His soul has long been look'd for.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colu.</SPEAKER>
<L>She dares not be so infolent! it is</L>
<L>The Dutchess hand; how am I shrunk in Fame</L>
<L>TO be thus plaid withall? she writes, and counsels,</L>
<L>Under my hand to send her back a free</L>
<L>Resigne of all my interest to her person,</L>
<L>Promise, or love; that ther's no other way</L>
<L>With safety of my honour to revisit her.</L>
<L>The woman is possest with some bold Devil,</L>
<L>And wants an exorcism; or I am grown</L>
<L>A cheap, dull, phlegmatick fool, a Post that's carv'd</L>
<L>I'th' common street, and holding out my forehead</L>
<L>To every scurrill wit to pin disgrace</L>
<L>And libells on't; did you bring this to me Sir?</L>
<PB REF="13"/>
<L>My thanks shall warm your heart.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Draws a Pistoll.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold, hold, my Lord.</L>
<L>I know not what provokes this tempest, but</L>
<L>Her Grace ne't shew'd more freedom from a storm</L>
<L>When I receiv'd this paper; if you have</L>
<L>A will to do an execution,</L>
<L>Your looks without that engin, Sir, may serve.</L>
<L>I did not like the employment.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, had she</L>
<L>No symptome in her eye, or face, of anger</L>
<L>When she gave this in charge?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Serene,</HI> as I</L>
<L>Have seen <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>e morning rise upon the spring,</L>
<L>No trouble in her breath, but such a wind</L>
<L>As came to kiss and fan the smiling flowers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colu.</SPEAKER>
<L>No Poetry.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>By all the truth in prose,</L>
<L>By honesty, and your own honour Sir,</L>
<L>I never saw her look more calm, and gentle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colu.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am too passionate, you must forgive me;</L>
<L>I have found it out the Dutchess loves me dearly,</L>
<L>She exprest a trouble in her when I took</L>
<L>My leave, and chid me with a fullen ey;</L>
<L>'Tis a device to hasten my return;</L>
<L>Love has a thousand arts; I'l answer it,</L>
<L>Beyond her expectation, and put</L>
<L>Her soul to a noble test; your patience Gentlemen;</L>
<L>The Kings health will deserve a sacrifice of Wine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am glad to see this change, and thank my wit</L>
<L>For my redemption.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Col.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, The Souldiers curse on him lo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es not our Master.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Col.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>And they curse loud enough to be heard.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Cap.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Their curse has the nature of Gunpowder.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>They do not pray with half the noise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Col</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Our Generall is not well mixt,</L>
<L>He hes too great a portion of fire.</L>
</SP>
<PB N="17" REF="13"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Col.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>His Mistris cool him, her complexion</L>
<L>Carries some phlegm, when they two meet in bed?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Cap.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>A third may follow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Cap.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis much pity.</L>
<L>The young Duke liv'd not to take the virgin off.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Col.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>'T was the Kings act to match two Rabbet suck∣ers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Col.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>A common trick of State,</L>
<L>The little great man marries, travells then</L>
<L>Till both grow up; and dies when he should do</L>
<L>The feat; these things are still unlucky</L>
<L>On the male side.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colu.</SPEAKER>
<L>This to the Dutchess fair hand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>She will think</L>
<L>Time hath no wing, till I return.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gentlemen,</L>
<L>Now each man to his quarter, and encourage</L>
<L>The Souldier; I shall take a pride to know</L>
<L>Your diligence, when I visit all your</L>
<L>Severall commands.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<L>We shall expect,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Col.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>And move by your directions.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'are all noble.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Cardinal, Dutchess, Placentia.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall perform a visit dayly, Madam,</L>
<L>In th' absence of my Nephew, and be happy</L>
<L>If you accept my care.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have honour'd me,</L>
<L>And if your entertainment have not been</L>
<L>Worthy your Graces person, 'tis because</L>
<L>Nothing can reach it in my power; but where</L>
<L>There is no want of zeal, other defect</L>
<L>Is only a fault to exercise your mercy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are bounteous in all; I take my leave;</L>
<L>My fair Neece, shortly, when <HI>Columbo</HI> has</L>
<L>Purchas'd more honours to prefer his name,</L>
<PB REF="14"/>
<L>And value to your noble thoughts; mean time</L>
<L>Be confident you have a friend, whose Office,</L>
<L>And favour with the King, shall be effectuall</L>
<L>To serve your Grace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your own good deeds reward you,</L>
<L>Till mine rise equall to deserve their benefit.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Cardinal.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Exit Placen.</STAGE>
<L>Leave me a while.</L>
<L>Do not I walk upon the teeth of serpents;</L>
<L>And, as I had a charm against their poyson,</L>
<L>Play with their stings, the Cardinal is subtle?</L>
<L>Whom tis not wisdom to incense, till I</L>
<L>Hear to what destinie <HI>Columbo</HI> leaves me;</L>
<L>May be the greatness of his soul will scorn</L>
<L>To own what comes with murmur, If he can</L>
<L>Interpret me so happily; art come?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Secretary with a Letter.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>His Excellence salutes your Grace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut:</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou hast</L>
<L>A malencholy brow; how did he take my Letter?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>As he would take a blow, with so much sense</L>
<L>Of anger, his whole soul boild in his face,</L>
<L>And such prodigious flame in both his eys</L>
<L>As they'd been th' only seat of fire; and at</L>
<L>Each look a <HI>Salamander</HI> leaping forth,</L>
<L>Not able to endure the Furnace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha! thou dost</L>
<L>Describe him with some horror.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>Soon as he</L>
<L>Had read again, and understood your meaning,</L>
<L>His rage had shot me with a pistoll, had not</L>
<L>I us'd some soft, and penitentiall language,</L>
<L>To charm the Bullet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wait at some more distance;</L>
<L>My soul doth bath it felf in a cold dew;</L>
<PB N="19" REF="14"/>
<L>I magin, I am opening of a Tomb,</L>
<L>Thus I throw off the Marble to discover,</L>
<L>What antick posture death presents in this</L>
<L>Pale monument to fright me—</L>
<STAGE>Reads.</STAGE>
<L>Ha? my heart that call'd my blood and spirits, to</L>
<L>Defend it from the invasion of my fears,</L>
<L>Must keep a guard about it still, lest this</L>
<L>Strange and too mighty joy crush it to nothing.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Antonio.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bid my Steward give thee</L>
<L>Two thousand Ducates; art sure I am awake?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall be able to resolve you, Madam,</L>
<L>When he has paid them oney.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Columbo</HI> now is noble.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit. Dut.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is better than I expected, if my Lady be</L>
<L>Not mad, and live to justifie her bounty.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter King, Alvarez, Hernando, Lords.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>The War is left to him. but we must have</L>
<L>You reconcil'd, if that be all your difference.</L>
<L>His rage flows like a torrent, when he meets</L>
<L>With opposition, leave to wrastle with him,</L>
<L>And his hot blood retreats into a calm,</L>
<L>And then he chides his passion; you shall back</L>
<L>With letters from us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Commands, are not</L>
<L>To be disputed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Alvarez.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Lo.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Lose not</L>
<L>Your self by cool submission, he will find</L>
<L>His error, and the want of such a Souldier.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Lo.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Have you seen the Cardinal?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not yet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Lo.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>He wants no plot—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>The King I must obey;</L>
<PB N="20" REF="15"/>
<L>But let the purple Gownman place his engins</L>
<L>I'th' dark that wounds me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Lo.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Be assur'd</L>
<L>Of what we can to friend you, and the King</L>
<L>Cannot forget your service.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am sorry</L>
<L>For that poor Gentleman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alvar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must consess, Sir,</L>
<L>The Dutchess has been pleas'd to think me worthy</L>
<L>Her favours, and in that degree of honour,</L>
<L>That has oblig'd my life to make the best</L>
<L>Return of service, which is not, with bold</L>
<L>Affiance in her love, to interpose</L>
<L>Against her happiness, and your election;</L>
<L>I love so much her honour, I have quitted</L>
<L>All my desires, yet would not shrink to bleed</L>
<L>Out my warm stock of life, so the last drop</L>
<L>Might benefit her wishes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ki.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall find</L>
<L>A compensation for this act, <HI>Alvarez,</HI></L>
<L>I hath much pleased us.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Dutchess with a Letter, Gentleman-Vsher.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, you are the King,</L>
<L>And in that sacred title it were sin</L>
<L>To doubt a justice, all that does concern</L>
<L>My essence in this world, and a great part</L>
<L>Of the other bliss, lives in you breath.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ki.</SPEAKER>
<L>What intends the Dutchess?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>That will instruct you, Sir, <HI>Columbo</HI> has</L>
<L>Upon some better choice, or discontent,</L>
<L>Set my poor soul at freedom.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ki.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis his character—</L>
<STAGE>Reads,</STAGE>
<L><HI>Madam, I casily discharge all my pretensions</HI></L>
<L><HI>To your love, and person, I leave you to your</HI></L>
<PB N="21" REF="15"/>
<L><HI>Own choice, and in what you have obliged</HI></L>
<L><HI>Your self to me, resume a power to cancell</HI></L>
<L><HI>If you please.</HI></L>
<STAGE>Columbo.</STAGE>
<L>This is strange.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now do an act to make</L>
<L>Your Chronicle belov'd and read for ever.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ki.</SPEAKER>
<L>Express your self.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Since by Divine infusion,</L>
<L>For tis no art could force the Generall to</L>
<L>This Change, second this justice and bestow</L>
<L>The heart you would have given from me, by</L>
<L>Your strict commands to love <HI>Colnmbo,</HI> where</L>
<L>'Twas meant by heaven, and let your breath return</L>
<L>Whom you divorc'd, <HI>Alvarez,</HI> mine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lords.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is but justice, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ki.</SPEAKER>
<L>It was decreed above,</L>
<L>And since <HI>Columbo</HI> has releas'd his interest</L>
<L>Which we had wrought him, not without some force</L>
<L>Upon your will I give you your own wishes,</L>
<L>Receive your own <HI>Alvarez,</HI> when you please</L>
<L>To celebrate your Nuptial, I invite</L>
<L>My self your guest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Eternall blessings Crown you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<L>And every joy your Mariage</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit King, who meets the Cardinal, they confer.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alvar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know not whether I shall wonder most</L>
<L>Or joy to meet this happiness.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now the King hath planted us</L>
<L>Methinks we grow already, and twist our loving souls</L>
<L>Above the wrath of thunder to divide us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alv.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha? The Cardinal</L>
<L>Has met the King, I do not like this conference;</L>
<L>He looks with anger this way, I expect</L>
<L>A tempest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take no notice of his presence,</L>
<L>Leave me to meet, and answer it, if the King</L>
<PB N="22" REF="16"/>
<L>Be firm in's Royall word, I fear no lightning;</L>
<L>Expect me in the Garden.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alv.</SPEAKER>
<L>I obey,</L>
<L>But fear a shipwrack on the coast.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>The King speaks of a Letter that has brought</L>
<L>A riddle in't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis easy to interpret.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>From my Nephew? may I deserve the favour?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>He looks as though his eys would fire the paper.</L>
<L>They are a pair of Burning glasses, and</L>
<L>His envious blood doth give 'em flame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>What lethargy could thus unspirit him?</L>
<L>I am all wonder; do not believe Madam,</L>
<L>But that <HI>Columbo's</HI> love is yet more Sacred,</L>
<L>To honour, and your self, than thus to forfeit</L>
<L>What I have heard him call the glorious wreath</L>
<L>To all his merits, given him by the King,</L>
<L>From whom he took you with more pride than ever</L>
<L>He came from victory; his kisses hang</L>
<L>Yet panting on your lips, and he but now</L>
<L>Exchang'd religious farewell to return,</L>
<L>But with more triumph to be yours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord,</L>
<L>You do believe your Nephews hand was not</L>
<L>Surpriz'd or strain'd to this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Strange arts and windings in the world, most dark,</L>
<L>And subtill progresses; who brought this Letter?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>I enquir'd not his name, I thought it not</L>
<L>Considerable to take such narrow knowledge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Desert, and honour urg'd it here, nor can</L>
<L>I blame you to be angry, yet his person</L>
<L>Oblig'd, you should have given a nobler pause,</L>
<L>Before you made your faith and change so violent</L>
<L>From his known worth, into the arms of one,</L>
<PB N="23" REF="16"/>
<L>How ever fashioned to your amorous wish,</L>
<L>Not equall to his cheapest fame, with all</L>
<L>The gloss of blood and merit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>This comparison,</L>
<L>My good Lord Cardinal, I cannot think,</L>
<L>Flows from an even justice, it betrayes</L>
<L>You partiall where your blood runs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>I fear Madam,</L>
<L>Your own takes two much licence, and will soon,</L>
<L>Fall to the censure of unruly tongues;</L>
<L>Because <HI>Alvarez</HI> has a softer cheek,</L>
<L>Can like a woman trim his want on hair,</L>
<L>Spend half a day with looking in the glass</L>
<L>To find a posture to present himself,</L>
<L>And bring more effeminacy than man,</L>
<L>Or honour to your bed; must he supplant him?</L>
<L>Take heed, the common murmur when it catches</L>
<L>The sent of a lost Fame—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Fame Lord Cardinal?</L>
<L>It stands upon an innocence as clear</L>
<L>As the devotions you pay to heaven,</L>
<L>I shall not urge my Lord your soft indulgence</L>
<L>At my next shrift.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are a fine Court Lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>And you should be a reverend Churchman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>One, that if you have not thrown off modesty.</L>
<L>Would counsell you to leave <HI>Alvarez.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cause you dare do worse</L>
<L>Than Mariage, must not I be admitted what</L>
<L>The Church and Law allowes me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Insolent? then you dare marry him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dare? Let your contracted flame and malice, with</L>
<L><HI>Columbo's</HI> rage higher than that, meet us</L>
<L>When we approach the holy place, clasp'd hand</L>
<L>In hand, wee'l break through all your force and six</L>
<L>Our sacred vows together there.</L>
</SP>
<PB N="24" REF="17"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>I knew</L>
<L>When with as chast a brow you promis'd fair</L>
<L>To another; you are no dissembling Lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would all your actions had no falser lights</L>
<L>About 'em.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>The people would not talk and curse so loud.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'l have you chid into a blush for this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Begin at home great man, ther's cause enough,</L>
<L>You turn the wrong end of the perspective</L>
<L>Upon your crimes, to drive them to a far,</L>
<L>And lesser sight, but let your eys look right</L>
<L>What giants would your pride and surfeit seem?</L>
<L>How gross your avarice, eating up whole families?</L>
<L>How vast are your corruptions and abuse</L>
<L>Of the Kings ear? at which you hang a pendent,</L>
<L>Not to adorn, but ulcerate, while the honest</L>
<L>Nobility, like pictures in the Arras,</L>
<L>Serve only for Court-Ornament; if they speak,</L>
<L>'Tis when you set their tongues, which you wind up,</L>
<L>Like clocks to strike at the just hour you please;</L>
<L>Leave, leave, my Lord, these usurpations,</L>
<L>And be what you were meant a man to cure,</L>
<L>Not let in Agues to Religion;</L>
<L>Look on the Churches wounds.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>You dare presume</L>
<L>In your rude spleen to me, to abuse the Church?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas you give false aym, my Lord, 'tis your</L>
<L>Ambition and Scarlet Sins that tob</L>
<L>Her Altar of the glory, and leave wounds</L>
<L>Upon her brow; which fetches grief, and paleness,</L>
<L>Into her cheeks; Making her troubled bosome</L>
<L>Pant with her groanes, and shroud her holy blushes</L>
<L>Within your reverend purples.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you now take breath?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>In hope, my Lord, you will behold your self</L>
<PB N="25" REF="17"/>
<L>In a true glass, and see those injust acts</L>
<L>That so deform you, and by timely cure,</L>
<L>Prevent a shame before the short haird men</L>
<L>Do croud and call for justice. I take leave.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>This woman has a spirit, that may rise</L>
<L>To tame the Devils, ther's no dealing with</L>
<L>Her angry tongue, 'tis action and revenge</L>
<L>Must calm her fury; were <HI>Columbo</HI> here,</L>
<L>I could resolve, but Letters shall be sent</L>
<L>To th'Army which may wake him into sense</L>
<L>Of his rash folly, or direct his spirit</L>
<L>Some way to snatch his honour from this flame,</L>
<L>All great men know, <HI>The soul of life is same.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACT III.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Valeria, Celinda.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Valeria.</SPEAKER>
<L>I Did not think <HI>Celinda</HI> when I prais'd</L>
<L><HI>Alvarez</HI> to the Dutchess, that things thus</L>
<L>Would come about, what does your Ladiship</L>
<L>Think of <HI>Columbo</HI> now? it staggers all</L>
<L>The Court, he should forsake his Mistress, I</L>
<L>Am lost with wonder yet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Celind.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis very strange</L>
<L>Without a spel; but ther's a fate in love,</L>
<L>I like him ne'r the worse.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter two Lords.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Lo.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Nothing but mariages, and triumph now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>What new access of joy, makes <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="2 words" DISP="〈◊◊〉"/> Lord,</L>
<L>So pleasant?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Lo.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Ther's a Packet <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></L>
<PB N="26" REF="18"/>
<L>Makes the King merry, we are all concernd in't?</L>
<L><HI>Columbo</HI> hath given the enemy a great,</L>
<L>And glorious defeat, and is already</L>
<L>Preparing to march home.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<L>He thriv'd the better for my prayers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Lo.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>You have been his great admirer, Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Lo.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>The King longs to see him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>This news exalts the Cardinal.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Cardinal.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Lo.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>He's here,</L>
<L>He appears with discontent, the Mariage</L>
<L>With Count <HI>D'Alvarez</HI> hath a bitter tast,</L>
<L>And not worn off his palat; but let us leave him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladies.</SPEAKER>
<L>We'l to the Dutchess.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt. manet Car.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>He has not woon so much upon the <HI>Arragon</HI></L>
<L>As he has lost at home, and his neglect</L>
<L>Of what my studies had contriv'd to adde</L>
<L>More luster to our Family by the access</L>
<L>Of the great Dutchess fortune, cools his triumph,</L>
<L>And makes me wild.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Hernando.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>My good Lord Cardinal.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>You made complaint to th' King about your Ge∣neral.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not a complaint my Lord, I did but satisfie</L>
<L>Some questions o'the Kings.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>You see he thrives</L>
<L>Without your personal valour, or advice,</L>
<L>Most grave and learned in the wars.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord,</L>
<L>I Envy not his fortune.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis above</L>
<L>Your Malice, and your noise not worth his anger,</L>
<L>'Tis barking gainst the moon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>More temper would</L>
<PB N="27" REF="18"/>
<L>Become that habit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Military thing would shew some spleen;</L>
<L>I'l blow an Army of such Wasps about</L>
<L>The world; go look your sting you left i'th' Camp, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter King, and Lords.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>The King.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<L>This may be one day counted for.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>All things conspire my Lord to make you fortunate,</L>
<L>Your Nephews glory—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twas your cause and justice</L>
<L>Made him victorious, had he been so valiant</L>
<L>At home, he had had another conquest to</L>
<L>Invite and bid her welcome to new wars.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>You must be reconcil'd to providence, my Lord;</L>
<L>I heard you had a controvercy with</L>
<L>The Dutchess, I will have you friends.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am not Angry.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>For my sake then you shall be pleas'd,</L>
<L>And with me grace the Mariage;</L>
<L>A Churchman must shew Charity, and shine</L>
<L>With first example, she's a woman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall prescribe in all things; Sir, you cannot</L>
<L>Accuse my love, if I still wish my Nephew</L>
<L>Had been so happy to be constant to</L>
<L>Your own, and my election; yet my brain</L>
<L>Cannot reach how this comes about; I know</L>
<L>My Nephew lov'd her with a near affection.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Hernando.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>He'l give you fair account at his return.</L>
<L>Colonel, your Letters may be spar'd, the General</L>
<L>Has finish'd, and is coming home.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am glad on't, sir; my good Lord Cardinal</L>
<L>'Tis not impossible but some man provok'd,</L>
<L>May have a precious mind to cut your throat.</L>
</SP>
<PB N="28" REF="19"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall command me Noble Colonel;</L>
<L>I know you wo'not fail to be at th'wedding.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis not <HI>Columbo</HI> that is maried Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Go teach the postures of the Pike and Musket,</L>
<L>Then dril your <HI>Mi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>midons</HI> into a ditch,</L>
<L>Where sterve, and stink in pickle, you shall find</L>
<L>Me reasonable, you see the King expects me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>So does the Devill; some desperate hand</L>
<L>May help you on your journey.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Secretary and Servants.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here this, I this will fit your part: you shall wear Slashes, because you are a Souldier; here's for the blue mute.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<P>This doublet will never fit me, Pox ont', are these Breeches good enough for a Prince too? <HI>Pedro</HI> playes but a Lord, and he has two laces more in a seam.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<P>You must consider <HI>Pedro</HI> is a foolish Lord, he may wear what lace he please.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2</SPEAKER>
<P>Does my beard fit my cloathes well Gentlemen?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec</SPEAKER>
<P>Pox o'your beard.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3</SPEAKER>
<P>That will fright away the hair.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<P>This fellow plays but a mute, &amp; he is so troublesome, and talks.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3</SPEAKER>
<P>Mr. Secretary might have let <HI>Iaques</HI> play the soldier, He has a black patch already.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2</SPEAKER>
<P>By your favour Mr. Secretary, I was ask'd who writ this play for us.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<P>For u<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>? why art thou any more than a blew mute?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2</SPEAKER>
<P>And by my troth, I said, I thought it was all your own.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<P>Away you Coxcomb.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>4</SPEAKER>
<P>Do'st think he has no more wit then to write a Co∣medy? my Ladies Chaplain made the Play, though he is content for the honour and trouble of the business, to be seen in't.</P>
</SP>
<PB N="29" REF="19"/>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> 5th. <HI>Servant.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>5</SPEAKER>
<P>Did any body see my head Gentlemen 'twas here but now? I shall have never a head to play my part in.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is thy head gone? 'tis well thy part was not in't, Look, look about, has not <HI>Iaques</HI> it?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>4</SPEAKER>
<P>I his head? two'not come on upon my shoulders.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<P>Make hast Gentlemen I'l see whether the King has sup'd; Look every man to his wardrop and his part.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2</SPEAKER>
<P>Is he gone? in my mind a masque had been fitter for a mariage.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>4</SPEAKER>
<P>Why mute? there was no time for't, and the scenes Are troublesome.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2</SPEAKER>
<P>Half a score Deal tack'd together in the clouds, what's that? a Throne to come down and dance; all the properties have been paid forty times over, and are in the Court stock, but the Secretary must have a play to shew his wit.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>4</SPEAKER>
<P>Did not I tell thee twas the Chaplains? hold your tongue Mute.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<P>Under the Rose and would this cloth of Silver dou∣blet might never come off agen, if there be any more plot then you see in the back of my hand.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2</SPEAKER>
<P>You talk of a plot, I'l not give this for the best Poets plot in the world and if it be not well carryed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>4</SPEAKER>
<P>Welll said Mnte.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha, ha; <HI>Pedro</HI> since he put on his doublet, has repea∣ted but three lines, and he has broke five butt ons.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2</SPEAKER>
<P>I know not but by this false beard, and here's hair e∣nough to hang a reasonable honest man, I do not re∣member to say a strong line indeed in the whole Co∣medy; but when the Chambermaid kisses the Cap∣tain.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3</SPEAKER>
<P>Excellent mute.</P>
</SP>
<PB N="30" REF="20"/>
<STAGE>Enter another Servant.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>5</SPEAKER>
<P>They have almost sup'd, and I cannot find my head yet.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>4</SPEAKER>
<P>play in thine own.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>5</SPEAKER>
<P>Thank you for that, so I may have it made a proper∣ty, if I have not a head found me, let Mr. Secretary play my part himself without it.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Secretary.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<P>Are you all ready my Masters? the King is coming through the Gallery, are the women drest?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Rogero</HI> wants a head.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here with a pox to you, take mine, you a player? You a puppy-dog is the Musick ready?</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Gentleman-Vsher.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gent.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gentlemen, it is my Ladies pleasure that you expect till she call for you, there are a company of Ca∣valiers in gallant Equipage newly alighted, have offer'd to present their Revels in honour of this <HI>Hymen;</HI> and 'tis her Graces command, that you be silent till their Enter∣tainment be over.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<P>Gentlemen?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2</SPEAKER>
<P>Affronted?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>5</SPEAKER>
<P>Mr. Secretary, ther's your head again; a man's a man; have I broken my sleep to study fifteen lines for an Ambassador, and after that a Constable, and is it come to this?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<P>Patience Gentlemen, be not so hot, tis but de∣fer'd, and the play may do well enough cold.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>4</SPEAKER>
<P>If it be not presented, the Chaplain will have the greatest loss, he loses his wits.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Hoboies.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<P>This Musick speaks the King upon entrance; retire, retire, and grumble not.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Excunt.</STAGE>
<PB N="31" REF="20"/>
<STAGE>Enter King, Cardinal, Alvarez, Dutchess, Celinda, Va∣leria, Placentia, Lords, Hernando; (they being set) Enter Celumbo, and five more in rich habits Visarded; between every two a torch bearer: They Dance, and after beckon to Alvarez as desirous to speak with him.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alv.</SPEAKER>
<L>With me!</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>They Embrace and whisper</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do you know the Masquers Madam?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not I Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ther's one, but that my Nephew is abroad,</L>
<L>And has more soul than thus to Jyg upon</L>
<L>Their <HI>Hymenrall</HI> night, I should suspect</L>
<L>'Twere he.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>The Mas quers lead in Alvarez.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wher's my Lord <HI>D' Alvarez?</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Recorders.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Call in the Bridegroom.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Columbo, four Masquers, bring in Alvarez dead, in one of their habits, and having laid him down, Excunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>What Mistery is this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>We want the Bridegroom still.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where is <HI>Alvarez</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Columbo points to the body, they an∣vizard it, &amp; find Alvar. bleeding.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh 'tis my Lord hee's murder'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who durst commit this horrid act?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<L>I Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Columbo?</HI> ha!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes; <HI>Columbo</HI> that dares stay</L>
<L>To justifie that act.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most barbarous.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh my dearest Lord!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our guard seize on them all, this sight doth snake</L>
<L>All that is man within me; poor <HI>Alvarez</HI></L>
<L>Is this thy wedding day?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Guard.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you do think there is a heaven or pains,</L>
<L>To punish such black crimes i'th' other world,</L>
<PB N="32" REF="21"/>
<L>Let me have swift, and such exemplar justice</L>
<L>As shall become this great assasinate,</L>
<L>You will take off our faith else, and if here</L>
<L>Such innocence must bleed, and you look on,</L>
<L>Poor men that call you Gods on earth, will doubt</L>
<L>To obey your Laws, nay practise to be Devils,</L>
<L>As fearing if such monstrous sins go on</L>
<L>The Saints will not be safe in Heaven.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall,</L>
<L>You shall have justice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now to come off were brave.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Servant.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Masquers, Sir, are fled, their horse prepar'd</L>
<L>At gate expected to receive 'em, where</L>
<L>They quickly mounted, coming so like friends</L>
<L>None could suspect their hast, which is secur'd</L>
<L>By advantage of the night.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<L>I answer for 'em all, 'tis stake enough</L>
<L>For many lives, but if that poniard</L>
<L>Had voice, it would convince they were but all</L>
<L>Spectators of my act; and now if you</L>
<L>Will give your judgments leave, though at the first</L>
<L>Face of this object your cool bloods were frighted,</L>
<L>I can excuse this deed and call it Justice;</L>
<L>An act, your honours, and your office Sir,</L>
<L>Is bound to build a Law upon, for others</L>
<L>To Imitate; I have but took his life,</L>
<L>And punish'd her with mercy, who had both</L>
<L>Conspir'd to kill the soul of all my fame</L>
<L>Read there,—and read an injury as deep</L>
<L>In my dishpnour, as the Devill knew</L>
<L>A Woman had capacity or malice</L>
<L>To execute read there, how you were cozen'd Sir,</L>
<L>Your power affronted, and my faith, her smiles</L>
<L>A jugling witchcraft to betray and make</L>
<L>My love her horse to stalk withall, and catch</L>
<L>Her curled Minion.</L>
</SP>
<PB N="33" REF="21"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is it possible</L>
<L>The Dutchess could dissemble so, and forfeit</L>
<L>Her modesty with you, and to us all?</L>
<L>Yet I must pity her; my Nephew has</L>
<L>Been too severe, though this affront would call</L>
<L>A dying man from prayers, and turn him Tiger,</L>
<L>There being nothing dearer than our fame,</L>
<L>Which, If a common man, whose blood has no</L>
<L>Ingredient of honour, labour to</L>
<L>Preserve, a Souldier (by his nearest tye</L>
<L>To glory) is above all others, bound</L>
<L>To vindicate; and yet it might have been less bloody.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Charitable Devill!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K. Reads.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>I Pray, my Lord, release under your hand, what you dare challenge in my love or person, as a just for∣feit to my self, this act will speak you honorable to my thoughts, and when you have conquered thus your self, you may proceed to many victories, and after, with safety of your famit visit again</HI></P>
<STAGE>The lost <HI>Rosaura.</HI></STAGE>
<L>To this your Answer was a free resign?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<L>Flatter'd with great opinion of her faith,</L>
<L>And my desert of her (with thought that she,</L>
<L>Who seem'd to weep and chide my easie will</L>
<L>To part with her, could not be guilty of</L>
<L>A treason, or Apostacy so soon,</L>
<L>But rather meant this a device to make</L>
<L>Me expedite the affairs of War) I sent</L>
<L>That paper, which her wickedness not justice,</L>
<L>Applied (what I meant tryall) her divorce;</L>
<L>I lov'd her so, I dare call heaven to witness</L>
<L>I knew not whether I lov'd most; while she,</L>
<L>With him, whose crimson penitence I provok'd,</L>
<L>Conspir'd my everlasting infamy;</L>
<L>Examine but the circumstance.</L>
</SP>
<PB N="34" REF="22"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis clear,</L>
<L>This Match was made at home before she sent</L>
<L>That cunning writ, in hope to take him off,</L>
<L>As knowing his impatient Soul would scorn</L>
<L>To own a blessing came on crutches to him;</L>
<L>It was not well to raise his expectation,</L>
<L>(Had you, Sir, no affront) to ruine him</L>
<L>With so much scandall and contempt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>We have</L>
<L>Too plentifull a circumstance to accuse</L>
<L>You Madam, as the cause of your own sorrows,</L>
<L>But not without an accessary, more</L>
<L>Than young <HI>Alvarez.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Any other instrument?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes I am guilty, with her self, and <HI>Don</HI></L>
<L><HI>Columbo,</HI> though our acts look'd severall waies,</L>
<L>That thought a lover might so soon be ransom'd;</L>
<L>And did exceed the office of a King</L>
<L>To exercise dominion over hearts,</L>
<L>That owe to the prerogative of heaven</L>
<L>Their choice, or Separation; you must therefore,</L>
<L>When you do kneel for Justice, and Revenge,</L>
<L>Madam, consider me a laterall agent</L>
<L>In poor <HI>Alvarez</HI> Tragedy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Lo.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>It was your love to <HI>Don Columbo</HI> Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>So, so; the King is charm'd; do you observe,</L>
<L>How to acquit <HI>Columbo,</HI> he would draw</L>
<L>Himself into the plot; Heaven, is this Justice?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Judgment is divine in this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>And yet,</L>
<L><HI>Columbo</HI> cannot be secure, and we</L>
<L>Just in his pardon, that durst make so great,</L>
<L>And insolent a breach of Law and Duty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Lo.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, Will he turn agen?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>And should we leave</L>
<L>This guilt of blood to Heaven, which cries, and strikes,</L>
<PB N="35" REF="22"/>
<L>With loud appeals the palace of eternity,</L>
<L>Yet here is more to charge <HI>Columbo,</HI> than</L>
<L><HI>Alvarez</HI> blood, and bids me punish it,</L>
<L>Or be no King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis come about my Lords.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>And If I should forgive</L>
<L>His timeless death, I cannot the offence,</L>
<L>That with such boldness struck at me. Has my</L>
<L>Indulgence to your merits which are great</L>
<L>Made me so cheap, your rage could meet, no time</L>
<L>Nor place for your revenge, but where my eys</L>
<L>Must be affrighted, and affronted with</L>
<L>The bloody execution? This contempt</L>
<L>Of Majesty transcends my power to pardon,</L>
<L>And you shall feel my anger Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou shalt have one short prayer more for that.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<L>Have I i'th' progress of my life</L>
<L>No actions to plead me up deserving,</L>
<L>Against this ceremony?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Contain your self.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must be dumb then; where is honour?</L>
<L>And gratitude of Kings, when they forget</L>
<L>Whose hand secur'd their greatness? take my head off,</L>
<L>Examine then which of your silken Lords,</L>
<L>As I have done, will throw himself on dangers;</L>
<L>Like to a floting Iland move in blood;</L>
<L>And where your great desence calls him to stand</L>
<L>A Bullwark, upon his hold brest to take</L>
<L>In death, that you may live: but Souldiers are</L>
<L>Your valiant fools, whom when your own securities</L>
<L>Are bleeding you can cherish, but when once</L>
<L>Your state and nerves are knit, not thinking when</L>
<L>To use their surgery again, you cast</L>
<L>Them off, and let them hang in dusty armories,</L>
<L>Or make it death to ask for pay.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more,</L>
<PB N="36" REF="23"/>
<L>We thought to have put your victory and merits</L>
<L>In ballance with <HI>Alvarez</HI> death, which while</L>
<L>Our mercy was to Iudge, had been your safety;</L>
<L>But the affront to us, made greater by</L>
<L>This boldness to upbraid our royall bounty,</L>
<L>Shall tame or make you nothing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Excellent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Cardinal is not pleas'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Humble your self</L>
<L>To th' King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<L>And beg my life? let cowards do't</L>
<L>That dare not dy, I'l rather have no head</L>
<L>Than owe it to his Charity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>To th' Castle with him.</L>
<L>Madam, I leave you to your grief, and what</L>
<L>The King can recompence to your tears, or honor</L>
<L>Of your dead Lord, expect.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>This shews like Iustice.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACT IV.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter two Lords, Hernando.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Lord.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>THis is the age of wonders.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Lo.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Wonderous mischiefs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Among those guards which some call Tutelar Angels,</L>
<L>Whose office is to govern Provinces,</L>
<L>Is there not one will undertake <HI>Navarre?</HI></L>
<L>Hath heaven forsook us quite?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Columbo</HI> at large?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2</SPEAKER>
<L>And grac'd now more than ever.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<L>He was not pardon'd,</L>
<L>That word was prejudiciall to his fame.</L>
</SP>
<PB N="37" REF="23"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>But as the murder done had been a dream</L>
<L>Vanish'd to memory, he's courted as</L>
<L>Preserver of his Country; with what chains</L>
<L>Of Magick does this Cardinal hold the King?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2</SPEAKER>
<L>What will you say my Lord if they inchant</L>
<L>The Dutchess now; and by some impudent art,</L>
<L>Advance a Mariage to <HI>Columbo</HI> yet?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Say? I'l say no woman can be sav'd, nor is't</L>
<L>Fit, indeed, any should pretend to Heaven</L>
<L>After one such impiety in their sex,</L>
<L>And yet my faith has been so stager'd, since</L>
<L>The King restor'd <HI>Columbo,</HI> I'l be now</L>
<L>Of no Religion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis not possible</L>
<L>She can forgive the murder, I observ'd</L>
<L>Her tears.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why so did I, my Lord,</L>
<L>And if they be not honest, 'tis to be</L>
<L>Half damn'd to look upon a woman weeping.</L>
<L>When do you think the Cardinal said his prayers?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2</SPEAKER>
<L>I know not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heaven forgive my want of charity</L>
<L>But if I were to kill him, he should have</L>
<L>No time to pray, his life could be no sacrifice,</L>
<L>Unless his soul went too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<L>That were too much.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>When you mean to dispatch him, you may give</L>
<L>Time for Confession, they have injur'd me</L>
<L>After another rate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2</SPEAKER>
<L>You are too passionate Cozen.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Columbo, Colonels, Alfonso, Courtiers, (they pass over the Stage.)</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>How the gay men do flutter to congratulate</L>
<L>His Goal delivery? ther's one honest man,</L>
<L>What pity 'tis a gallant fellow should</L>
<PB N="38" REF="24"/>
<L>Depend on knaves for his preferment.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<L>Except this cruelty upon <HI>Alvarez,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Columbo</HI> has no mighty stain upon him;</L>
<L>But for his Uncle—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>If I had a Son</L>
<L>Of twelve years old, that would not fight with him,</L>
<L>And stake his soul against his Cardinals Cap,</L>
<L>I would dis-inherit him; Time has took a lease</L>
<L>But for three lives I hope, a fourth may see</L>
<L>Honesty walk without a crutch.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2</SPEAKER>
<L>This is</L>
<L>But Air and Wildness.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'l see the Dutchess,</L>
<L>You may do well to comfort her,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<L>We must attend the King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>your pleasures.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Her.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter King and Cardinal.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<L>A Man of a brave soul.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2</SPEAKER>
<L>The less his safety;</L>
<L>The King and Cardinal in consult.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Commend us to the Dutchess, and imploy</L>
<L>What language you think fit, and powerfull</L>
<L>To reconcile her to some peace. My Lords.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, I possess all for your sacred uses.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Severally.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Secretary and Celinda.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, you are the welcom'st Lady living.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>To whom, Mr. Secretary?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you have mercy</L>
<L>To pardon so much boldness, I durst say,</L>
<L>To me—I am a Gentleman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>And handsome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>But my Lady has much wanted you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why Mr. Secretary?</L>
</SP>
<PB N="39" REF="24"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are the prettiest,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>So.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>The witiest,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>So.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>The merriest Lady i'th' Court.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I was wish'd to make the Dutchess pleasant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>She never had so deep a cause of sorrow,</L>
<L>Her Chamber's but a Coffin of a larger</L>
<L>Volume, wherein she walks so like a Ghost,</L>
<L>T'would make you pale to see her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tell her Grace I attend here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall most willingly.</L>
<L>A spirited Lady, would I had her in my closet,</L>
<L>She is excellent company among the Lords,</L>
<L>Sure she has an admirable treble—Madam.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>I do suspect this fellow would be nibling</L>
<L>Like some whose narrow fortunes will not rise</L>
<L>To wear things when the inventions rare, and new,</L>
<L>But treading on the heel of pride, they hunt</L>
<L>The fashion when tis crippled, like fell tyrants;</L>
<L>I hope I am not old yet, I had the honour</L>
<L>To be saluted by our Cardinals Nephew</L>
<L>This Morning, ther's a man!</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Secretary.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have prevail'd,</L>
<L>Sweet Madam use what Eloquence you can</L>
<L>Upon her, and if ever I be usefull</L>
<L>To your Ladiships service, your least breath commands me.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Dutchess.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, I come to ask you but one question,</L>
<L>If you were in my State, my state of grief,</L>
<L>I mean an exile from all happiness,</L>
<L>Of this world, and almost of heaven, for my</L>
<L>Affliction is finding out despair,</L>
<PB N="40" REF="25"/>
<L>What would you think of <HI>Don Columbo?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whose Bloody hand wrought all this misery?</L>
<L>Would you not weep as I do? and wish rather</L>
<L>An everlasting spring of tears to drown</L>
<L>Your sight, than let your eys be curst to see</L>
<L>The murderer agen? and glorious?</L>
<L>So careless of his sin, that he is made</L>
<L>Fit for new <HI>Parricide,</HI> even while his soul</L>
<L>Is purpled o'r, and reeks with innocent blood.</L>
<L>But do not, do not answer me, I know</L>
<L>You have so great a spirit, (which I want,</L>
<L>The horrour of his fact surprising all</L>
<L>My faculties) you would not let him live:</L>
<L>But I, poor I, must suffer more, ther's not</L>
<L>One little star in Heaven will look on me,</L>
<L>Unless to choose me out the mark, on whom</L>
<L>It may shoot down some angry influence.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Placentia.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, her's <HI>Don Columbo</HI> says he must</L>
<L>Speak with your Grace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>But he must not, I charge you.</L>
<L>None else wait? Is this well done,</L>
<L>To triumph in his Tyranny? speak Madam,</L>
<L>Speak but your conscience.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Columbo, and Secretary.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, you must not see her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not see her? were she cabled up above</L>
<L>The search of Bullet, or of Fire, were she</L>
<L>Within her Grave, and that the toughest Mine</L>
<L>That ever nature teem'd and groand withall,</L>
<L>I would force some way to see her; do not fear</L>
<L>I come to Court you Madam, y'are not worth</L>
<L>The humblest of my kinder thoughts, I come</L>
<PB N="41" REF="25"/>
<L>To shew the man you have prokvo'd, and lost;</L>
<L>And tell you what remains of my revenge.</L>
<L>Live, but never presume again to marry,</L>
<L>I'l kill the next at th' Altar, and quench all</L>
<L>The smiling tapers with his blood; if after</L>
<L>You dare provoke the Priest, and heaven so much,</L>
<L>To take another, in thy bed I'l cut him from</L>
<L>Thy warm embracc, and throw his heart to Ravens.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>This will appear an unexampled cruelty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your pardon Madam, rage, and my revenge</L>
<L>Not perfect, took away my eys, you are</L>
<L>A noble Lady, this, not worth your ey-beam,</L>
<L>One of so slight a making, and so thin,</L>
<L>An Autumn leaf is of too great a value</L>
<L>To play, which shall be soonest lost i'th' Air;</L>
<L>Be pleas'd to own me by some name, in your</L>
<L>Assurance, I despise to be receiv'd</L>
<L>There, let her witness that I call</L>
<L>You Mistress; honour me to make these Pearls</L>
<L>Your carkanet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, you are too humble in your thoughts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ther's no vexation too great to punish her.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Secretary.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now Nadam?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away you saucy fellow; Madam, I</L>
<L>Must be excus'd, if I do think more honourably</L>
<L>Than you have cause of this great Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why is not</L>
<L>All woman kind concern'd to hate what's impious?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>For my part—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Antonio,</HI> is this a woman?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know not whether she be man or woman,</L>
<L>I should be nimble to find out the Experiment,</L>
<L>She look'd with less state, when <HI>Columbo</HI> came.</L>
</SP>
<PB REF="26"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me entreat your absence, I am cozen'd in her,</L>
<L>I took you for a modest, honest Lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, I scorn any accuser, and</L>
<L>Deducting the great title of a Dutchess,</L>
<L>I shall not need one grain of your dear honour</L>
<L>To make me full weight, if your Grace be jealous</L>
<L>I can remove.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>She is gone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prethee remove</L>
<L>My fears of her return,—she is not worth</L>
<STAGE>Ex. Sec.</STAGE>
<L>Considering, my anger's mounted higher;</L>
<L>He need not put in caution for my next</L>
<L>Marrage, <HI>Alvarez,</HI> I must come to thee,</L>
<L>Thy Virgin, Wife, and Widdow, but not till</L>
<L>I ha' paid those Tragick duties to thy Herse,</L>
<L>Become my piety and love, but how?</L>
<L>Who shall instruct a way?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Placentia.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, <HI>Don</HI></L>
<L><HI>Hernando</HI> much desires to speak with you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will not thy own discretion think I am</L>
<L>Unfit for visit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Please your Grace he brings</L>
<L>Something he says imports your ear, and love</L>
<L>Of the dead Lord <HI>Alvarez.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then admit him.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Hernando.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would speak, Madam, to your self.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your absence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know not how you Grace wil censure so</L>
<L>Much boldness, when you know the affairs I come for.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Servant has prepar'd me to receive it,</L>
<L>If it concern my dead Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can you name</L>
<PB REF="26"/>
<L>So much of your <HI>Alvarez</HI> in a breath</L>
<L>Without one word of your revenge? O Madam,</L>
<L>I come to chide you, and repent my great</L>
<L>Opinion of your virtue, that can walk,</L>
<L>And spend so many hours in naked Solitude,</L>
<L>As if you thought that no arrear were due</L>
<L>To his death, when you had paid his Funerall charges,</L>
<L>Made your eys red, and wept a handkercher;</L>
<L>I come to tell you that I saw him bleed,</L>
<L>I, that can challenge nothing in his name,</L>
<L>And honour, saw his murder'd body warm,</L>
<L>And panting with the labour of his spirits,</L>
<L>Till my amaz'd Soul shrunk and hid it self,</L>
<L>While barbarous <HI>Columbo</HI> grinning stood,</L>
<L>And mock'd the weeping wounds; it is too much</L>
<L>That you should keep your heart alive, so long</L>
<L>After this spectacle, and not revenge it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>You do not know the business of my heart,</L>
<L>That censure me so rashly; yet I thank you,</L>
<L>And if you be <HI>Alvarez</HI> friend, dare tell</L>
<L>Your confidence, that I despise my life,</L>
<L>But know not how to use it in a service,</L>
<L>To speak me his revenger, this will need</L>
<L>No other proof, than that to you, who may</L>
<L>Be sent with cunning to betray me, I</L>
<L>Have made this bold confession, I so much</L>
<L>Desire to sacrifice to that hovering Ghost,</L>
<L><HI>Columbo's</HI> life, that I am not ambitious</L>
<L>To keep my own two minutes after it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you will call me coward, which is equall</L>
<L>To think I am a Traytor, I forgive it,</L>
<L>For this brave resolution, which time</L>
<L>And all the Destinies must aid, I beg</L>
<L>That I may kiss your hand for this, and may</L>
<L>The soul of angry honour guide it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whither?</L>
</SP>
<PB REF="27"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>To <HI>Don Columbo</HI>'s heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is too weak I fear alone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alone? are you in earnest? why? will it not</L>
<L>Be a dishonour to your Justice, Madam,</L>
<L>Another arm should interpose? but that</L>
<L>It were a sawcy act to mingle with you,</L>
<L>I durst, nay I am bound in the revenge</L>
<L>Of him that's dead, (since the whole world has interest,</L>
<L>In every goodmans loss) to offer it;</L>
<L>Dare you command me, Madam?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not command,</L>
<L>But I should more than honour such a truth</L>
<L>In man, that durst against so mighty odds,</L>
<L>Appear <HI>Alvarez</HI> friend and mine; the Cardinal—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is for the second course, <HI>Columbo</HI> must</L>
<L>Be first cut up, his Ghost must lead the dance.</L>
<L>Let him dy first.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>But how?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>How? with a Sword, and if I undertake it,</L>
<L>I wo'not lose so much of my own honour,</L>
<L>To kill him basely.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>How shall I reward</L>
<L>This infinite service? 'tis not Modesty,</L>
<L>While now my husband groanes beneath his tomb,</L>
<L>And calls me to his marble bed, to promise</L>
<L>What this great act might well deserve, my self</L>
<L>If you survive the Victor, but if thus</L>
<L><HI>Alvarez</HI> ashes be appeas'd it must</L>
<L>Deserve an honourable memory;</L>
<L>And though <HI>Columbo</HI> (as he had all power,</L>
<L>And grasp'd the fates) has vow'd to kill the man</L>
<L>That shall succeed <HI>Alvarez</HI>—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tyranny.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet if ever,</L>
<L>I entertain a thought of love hereafter,</L>
<L><HI>Hernando</HI> from the world shall challenge it,</L>
<PB N="45" REF="27"/>
<L>Till when, my Prayers, and fortune, shall wait on you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is too mighty recompence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis all just.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>If I outlive <HI>Columbo</HI> I must not</L>
<L>Expect security at home.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou canst</L>
<L>Not fly, where all my fortunes, and my love,</L>
<L>Shall not atttend to guard thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>If I dye—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy memory</L>
<L>Shall have a shrine, the next within my heart</L>
<L>To my <HI>Alvarez.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Once again your hand,</L>
<L>Your cause is so religious you need</L>
<L>Not strengthen it with your prayers, trust it to me.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Placentia, and Cardinal.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, the Cardinal.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you appear?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>And he had all the horror of the Devil</L>
<L>In's face, I would not balk him.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>He stares upon the Cardinal in his Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>What makes <HI>Hernando</HI> here? I do not like</L>
<L>They should consult, I'l take no note; the King</L>
<L>Fairly salutes your Grace, by whose command</L>
<L>I am to tell you, though his will and actions</L>
<L>Illimited, stoop not to satisfie</L>
<L>The Vulgar inquisition, he is</L>
<L>Yet willing to retain a just opinion,</L>
<L>With those that are plac'd neer him, and although</L>
<L>You look with Natures ey upon your self,</L>
<L>Which needs no perspective to reach, nor art</L>
<L>Of any optick to make greater, what</L>
<L>Your narrow sense applies an injury,</L>
<L>(Our selves still nearest to our selves) but ther's</L>
<PB N="46" REF="28"/>
<L>Another ey that looks abroad and walks</L>
<L>In search of reason, and the weight of things,</L>
<L>With which if you look on him, you will find</L>
<L>His pardon to <HI>Columbo</HI> cannot be</L>
<L>So much against his justice, as your erring</L>
<L>Faith would perswade your anger.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good my Lord,</L>
<L>Your phrase has too much landschape and I cannot</L>
<L>Distinguish at this distance you present</L>
<L>The figure perfect, but indeed my eys</L>
<L>May pray your Lordship find excuse, for tears</L>
<L>Have almost made them blind.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fair, peace restore 'em!</L>
<L>To bring the object nearer, the King says,</L>
<L>He could not be severe to <HI>Don Columbo</HI></L>
<L>Without injustice to his other merits,</L>
<L>Which call more loud for their reward and honour,</L>
<L>Than you for your revenge; the Kingdom made</L>
<L>Happy by those; you only by the last</L>
<L>Uunfortunate, nor was it rationall,</L>
<L>I speak the Kings own Language, he should dy</L>
<L>For taking one mans breath, without whose valour</L>
<L>None now had been alive, without dishonour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>In my poor understanding, 'tis the Crown</L>
<L>Of virtue to proceed in its own tract,</L>
<L>Not deviate from honour, if you acquit</L>
<L>A man of murder, 'cause he has done brave</L>
<L>Things in the War, you will bring down his valour</L>
<L>To a crime, nay to a baud, if it secure</L>
<L>A rape, and but teach those that deserve well</L>
<L>To sin with greater licence; but dispute</L>
<L>Is now too late, my Lord, 'tis done, and you,</L>
<L>By the good King, in tender of my sorrows,</L>
<L>Sent to perswade me, 'tis unreasonable</L>
<L>That Justice should repair me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>You mistake,</L>
<PB N="47" REF="28"/>
<L>For if <HI>Columbo's</HI> death could make <HI>Alvarez</HI></L>
<L>Live, the King had given him up to Law</L>
<L>Your bleeding Sacrifice; but when his life</L>
<L>Was but another treasure thrown away,</L>
<L>To obey a clamorous Statute, it was wisdom</L>
<L>To himself and common safety to take off</L>
<L>This killing edge of Law, and keep <HI>Columbo</HI></L>
<L>To recompence the crime by noble acts,</L>
<L>And sorrow, that in time might draw your pity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is a greater tyranny, than that</L>
<L><HI>Columbo</HI> exercis'd, he kill'd my Lord,</L>
<L>And you not have the charity to let</L>
<L>Me think it worth a punishment,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>To that</L>
<L>In my own name, I answer; I condemn</L>
<L>And urge the blody guilt against my Nephew,</L>
<L>'Twas violent, and cruell, a black deed,</L>
<L>A deed whose memory doth make me shudder,</L>
<L>An act that did betray a tyranous nature,</L>
<L>Which he took up in War, the school of vengeance;</L>
<L>And though the Kings compassion spare him here,</L>
<L>Unless his heart Weep it self out in penitent tears.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>This sounds</L>
<L>As you were now a good man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Does your Grace</L>
<L>Think I have conscience to allow the murder?</L>
<L>Although when it was done, I did obey</L>
<L>The stream of nature, as he was my Kinsman,</L>
<L>To plead he might not pay his forfeit life,</L>
<L>Could I do less for one so near my bloud?</L>
<L>Consider Madam, and be charitable,</L>
<L>Let not this wild injustice, make me lose</L>
<L>The character I bear, and reverend habit.</L>
<L>To make you full acquainted with my innocence,</L>
<L>I challenge here my soul, and heaven to witness</L>
<PB N="48" REF="29"/>
<L>If I had any thought, or knowledge with</L>
<L>My nephews plot, or person, when he came</L>
<L>Under the smooth pretence of friend to violate</L>
<L>Your hospitable laws, and do that act</L>
<L>Whose frequent mention drawes this tear, a whirlwind</L>
<L>Suatch me to endless flames.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must believe,</L>
<L>And ask your Graces pardon, I confess</L>
<L>I ha' not lov'd you since <HI>Alvarez</HI> death,</L>
<L>Though we were recontil'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>I do not blame</L>
<L>Your Jealousie, nor any zeal you had</L>
<L>To prosecute revenge against me, Madam,</L>
<L>As I then stood suspected, nor can yet</L>
<L>Implore your mercy to <HI>Columbo,</HI> all</L>
<L>I have to say is to retain my first</L>
<L>Opinion and credit with your Grace,</L>
<L>Which you may think I urge not out of fear</L>
<L>Or ends upon you, (since, I thank the King,</L>
<L>I stand firm on the base of royall favour)</L>
<L>But for your own sake, and to shew I have</L>
<L>Compassion of your sufferings.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have cleer'd</L>
<L>A doubt my Lord, and by this fair remonstrance,</L>
<L>Given my sorrow so much truce, to think</L>
<L>That we may meet agen, and yet be friends.</L>
<L>But be not angry, if I still remember</L>
<L>By whom <HI>Alvarez</HI> dyed, and weep, and wake</L>
<L>Another Iustice with my prayers,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>All thoughts</L>
<L>That may advance a better peace, dwell with you.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>How would this cozening Statesman bribe my Faith</L>
<L>With flatteries to think him innocent?</L>
<L>No, if his Nephew dy, this Cardinal must not</L>
<L>Be long-liv'd; all the prayers of a wrong'd Widow</L>
<PB N="49" REF="29"/>
<L>Make firm <HI>Hernando</HI>'s Sword, and my own hand</L>
<L>Shall have some glory in the next revenge;</L>
<L>I will pretend my brain with grief distracted,</L>
<L>It may gain easy credit, and beside</L>
<L>The taking off examination</L>
<L>For great <HI>Columbo</HI>'s death, it makes what act</L>
<L>I do in that believ'd want of my reason,</L>
<L>Appear no crime, but my defence; look down</L>
<L>Soul of my Lord, from thy eternall shade,</L>
<L>And unto all thy blest companions boast,</L>
<L>Thy Dutchess busie to revenge thy Ghost.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Columbo, Hernando, Alfonso, Colonel.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Hernando,</HI> now I love thee, and do half</L>
<L>Repent the affront my passion threw upon thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>You wo'not be too prodigall o' your penitence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colu.</SPEAKER>
<L>This makes good thy Nobility of birth,</L>
<L>Thou mayst be worth my anger and my sword,</L>
<L>If thou dost execute as daringly,</L>
<L>As thou provok'st a quarrell, I did think</L>
<L>Thy soul a starveling, or a sleep.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>You'l find it</L>
<L>Active enough to keep your spirit waking,</L>
<L>Which to exasperate, for yet I think</L>
<L>It is not high enough to meet my rage—</L>
<L>D'ee smile?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<L>This noise is worth it, Gentlemen;</L>
<L>I'm sorry this great Soldier has engag'd</L>
<L>Your travel, all his business is to talk.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>A little of your Lordships patience,</L>
<L>You shall have other sport, and swords that will</L>
<L>Be as nimble 'bout your heart, as you can wish,</L>
<L>'Tis pity more than our two single lives,</L>
<L>Should be at stake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Make that no scruple Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>To him then that survives if fate allow</L>
<PB REF="30"/>
<L>That difference, I speak that he may tell</L>
<L>The World, I came not hither on slight anger,</L>
<L>But to revenge my honour stain'd, and trampled on</L>
<L>By this proud man, when General, he commanded</L>
<L>My absence from the field.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colu.</SPEAKER>
<L>I do remember,</L>
<L>And I'l give your Soul now a discharge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>I come to meet it, if your courage be so fortunate.</L>
<L>But there is more than my own injury</L>
<L>You must account for Sir, if my sword prosper,</L>
<L>Whose point and every edge is made more keen</L>
<L>With young <HI>Alvarez</HI> blood, in which I had</L>
<L>A Noble interest; does not that sin benum</L>
<L>Thy Arteries, and turn the guilty flowings,</L>
<L>To trembling gelly in thy veins? canst hear</L>
<L>Me name that murder, and thy spirits not</L>
<L>Struck into air, as thou wert shot by some</L>
<L>Engin from heaven?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are the Dutchess Champion;</L>
<L>Thou hast given me a quarrell now; I grieve</L>
<L>It is determin'd all must fight, and I</L>
<L>Shall lose much honour in his fall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>That Dutchess</L>
<L>(Whom but to mention with thy breath, is sacrilege)</L>
<L>An Orphan of thy making, and condemn'd</L>
<L>By thee to eternall solitude, I come</L>
<L>To vindicate, and while I am killing thee,</L>
<L>By virtue of her prayers sent up for justice,</L>
<L>At the same time, in heaven I am pardon'd for't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<L>I cannot hear the Bravo.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Two words more</L>
<L>And take your chance, before you all I must</L>
<L>Pronounce that noble Lady, without knowledge,</L>
<L>Or thought of what I undertake for her.</L>
<L>Poor soul, Shees now at her Devotions,</L>
<L>Busie with heaven, and wearing out the earth</L>
<PB N="51" REF="30"/>
<L>With her stiff Knees, and bribing her good Angel</L>
<L>With treasures of her eys, to tell her Lord</L>
<L>How much she longs to see him; my attempt</L>
<L>Needs no commission from her, were I</L>
<L>A stranger in <HI>Navarre,</HI> the inborn right</L>
<L>Of every Gentleman to <HI>Alvarez</HI> loss,</L>
<L>Is reason to engage their swords, and lives,</L>
<L>Against the common enemy of virtue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now have you finish'd? I have an instrument</L>
<L>Shall cure this noise, and fly up to thy tongue,</L>
<L>To murder all thy words.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>One little knot</L>
<L>Of phlegm that clogs my stomach, and I ba' done;</L>
<L>You have an Uncle call'd a Cardinal</L>
<L>Would he were lurking now about thy heart,</L>
<L>That the same wounds might reach you both, and send</L>
<L>Your reeling souls together. Now have at you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alph.</SPEAKER>
<L>We must not Sir be idle.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>They fight, Colum∣bo's Second siain.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>What think you now of praying?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Time enough;</L>
<STAGE>He kills Hernando's Second.</STAGE>
<L>Commend me to my friend; the scales are even,</L>
<L>I would be mercifull, and give you time,</L>
<L>Now to consider of the other World,</L>
<L>You'l find your soul benighted presently.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'l find my way i'th' dark.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>They fight, and close, Columbo gets both the swords, and Hernando takes up the seconds Weapon.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colu</SPEAKER>
<L>A stumble's dangerous.</L>
<L>Now ask thy life—Ha?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>I despise to wear it,</L>
<L>A gift from any but the first bestower.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<L>I scorn a base advantage—ha.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am now</L>
<L>Out of your debt.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Columbo throwes away one of the swords. They fight, Hernando wounds Columbo.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<L>Th'ast don't, and I forgive thee.</L>
<L>Give me thy hand, when shall we meet again?</L>
</SP>
<PB REF="31"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Never, I hope.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<L>I feel life ebb apace, yet I'l look upwards,</L>
<L>And shew my face to heaven.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>The matters done,</L>
<L>I must not stay to bury him.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACT V.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter two Lords.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Lord.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L><HI>COlumbo</HI>'s death doth much aflict the King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Lo.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>I thought the Cardinal would have lost his wits</L>
<L>At first, for's nephew, it drownes all the talk</L>
<L>Of the other that were slain.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<L>We are friends.</L>
<L>I do suspect <HI>Hernando</HI> had some interest</L>
<L>And knew how their wounds came.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2</SPEAKER>
<L>His flight confirms it,</L>
<L>For whom the Cardinal has spread his nets.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<L>He is not so weak to trust himself at home</L>
<L>To his Enemies gripe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2</SPEAKER>
<L>All strikes not me so much,</L>
<L>As that the Dutchess, most oppressed Lady,</L>
<L>Should be distracted, and before <HI>Columbo</HI></L>
<L>Was slain.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<L>But that the Cardinal should be made</L>
<L>Her Guardian, is to me above that wonder.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2</SPEAKER>
<L>So it pleas'd the King, and she, with that small stock</L>
<L>Of reason left her, is so kind, and smooth</L>
<L>Upon him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<L>She's turn'd a child agen; a madness,</L>
<L>That would ha' made her brain and blood boil high</L>
<PB N="53" REF="31"/>
<L>In which distemper she might ha' wrought something.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2</SPEAKER>
<L>Had been to purpose.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<L>The Cardinal is cunning, and how e'r</L>
<L>His brow does smile, he does suspect <HI>Hernando</HI></L>
<L>Took fire from her, and waits a time to punish it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2</SPEAKER>
<L>But what a subject of disgrace, and mirth,</L>
<L>Hath poor <HI>Celinda</HI> made herself by pride,</L>
<L>In her belief <HI>Columbo</HI> was her servant.</L>
<L>Her head hath stoop'd much since he died, and she</L>
<L>Almost ridiculous at Court.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Cardinal, Antonelli, Servant.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Cardinal</L>
<L>Is come into the Garden, now—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Walk off,</L>
<L>It troubles me the Dutchess by her loss</L>
<L>Of brain is now beneath my great revenge,</L>
<L>She is not capable to feel my anger,</L>
<L>Which like to unregarded thunder spent</L>
<L>In woods, and lightning aim'd at senseless trees,</L>
<L>Must idly fall, and hurt her not, not to</L>
<L>That sense her guilt deserves a fatall stroke,</L>
<L>Without the knowledg for what crime to fright her,</L>
<L>When she takes leave, and make her tug with death,</L>
<L>Untill her soul sweat, is a Pidgeons torment,</L>
<L>And she is sent a babe to the other World,</L>
<L><HI>Columbo</HI>'s death will not be satisfied,</L>
<L>And I but wound her with a two edg'd feather;</L>
<L>I must do more, I have all opportunity,</L>
<L>(She by the King now made my charge) but she's</L>
<L>So much a turtle I shall lose by killing her,</L>
<L>Perhaps do her a pleasure, and preferment;</L>
<L>That must not be.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Celinda with a Parchment.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is not this she, that would be thought to have been</L>
<PB N="54" REF="32"/>
<L><HI>Columbo</HI>'s Mistress? Madam, his grace is private,</L>
<L>And would not be disturb'd, you may displease him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>What will your worship wager that he shall</L>
<L>Be pleas'd again before we part.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'l say this Diamond Madam, 'gainst a kiss,</L>
<L>And trust your self to keep the stakes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis done.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have long had an appetite to this Lady,</L>
<L>But the Lords keep her up so high— this toy</L>
<L>May bring her on.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>This interruption tasts not of good manners.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>But where necessity my Lord compells,</L>
<L>The boldness may meet pardon, and when you</L>
<L>Have found my purpose, I may less appear</L>
<L>Unmannerly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>To th' business.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>It did please</L>
<L>Your Nephew, Sir, before his death to credit me</L>
<L>With so much honorable favour, I</L>
<L>Am come to tender to his neer'st of blood,</L>
<L>Your self, what does remain a debt to him.</L>
<L>Not to delay your Grace with circumstance,</L>
<L>That deed, if you accept, makes you my heir</L>
<L>Of no contemptible estate— this way</L>
<STAGE>He reads.</STAGE>
<L>Is only left to ty up scurrile tongues,</L>
<L>And saucy men, that since <HI>Columbo</HI>'s death</L>
<L>Venture to Libell on my pride, and folly;</L>
<L>His greatness, and this gift which I enjoy,</L>
<L>Still for my life, beyond which term; a Kingdom's,</L>
<L>Nothing, will curb the giddy spleens of men</L>
<L>That live on impudent rime, and railing at</L>
<L>Each wandering fame they catch.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, this bounty</L>
<L>Will bind my gratitude and care to serve you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am your Graces Servant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Antonelli,</HI></L>
<STAGE>Whisper.</STAGE>
<PB N="55" REF="32"/>
<L>And when this noble Lady visits me</L>
<L>Let her not wait.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>What think you my Officious, Sir; his grace</L>
<L>Is pleas'd, you may conjecture? I may keep</L>
<L>Your Gem, the kiss was never yours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweet Madam—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Talk if you dare, you know I must not wait,</L>
<L>And so farewell for this time.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis in my brain already, and it formes</L>
<L>Apace, good, excellent revenge, and pleasant!</L>
<L>She's now within my talons, 'tis too cheap</L>
<L>A satisfaction for <HI>Columbo</HI>'s death,</L>
<L>Only to kill her by soft charm or force,</L>
<L>I'l rifle first her darling chastity,</L>
<L>'Twil be after time enough to poyson her,</L>
<L>And she to th' world be thought her own destroyer.</L>
<L>As I will frame the circumstance, this night</L>
<L>All may be finished; for the Colonel,</L>
<L>Her agent in my Nephewes death (whom I</L>
<L>Disturb'd at Counsell with her) I may reach him</L>
<L>Hereafter, and be Master of his fate.</L>
<L><HI>We starve our Conscience when we thrive in State.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Secretary, and Placentia.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Placentia,</HI> We two are only left</L>
<L>Of my Ladies Servants, let us be true</L>
<L>To her, and one another, and be sure</L>
<L>When we are at prayers, to curse the Cardinal.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pla.</SPEAKER>
<L>I pity my sweet Lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>I pity her too, but am a little angry;</L>
<L>She might have found another time to lose</L>
<L>Her wits.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pla.</SPEAKER>
<L>That I were a man?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>What would'st thou do <HI>Placentia?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>la.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would revenge my Lady.</L>
</SP>
<PB N="56" REF="33"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis better being a woman, thou mayst do</L>
<L>Things that may prosper better, and the fruit</L>
<L>Be thy own another day.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your wit still loves</L>
<L>To play the wanton.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis a sad time <HI>Placentia,</HI></L>
<L>Some pleasure would do well, the truth is, I</L>
<L>Am weary of my life, and I would have</L>
<L>One fit of mirth before I leave the world.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do not you blush to talk thus wildly?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis good manners</L>
<L>To be a little mad after my Lady;</L>
<L>But I ha' done; who is with her now?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam <HI>Valeria.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not <HI>Celinda?</HI> Ther's a Lady for my humour,</L>
<L>A pretty book of flesh and blood, and well</L>
<L>Bound up, in a fair letter too; would I</L>
<L>Had her with all the Errata.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pla.</SPEAKER>
<L>She has not</L>
<L>An honorable Fame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>Her Fame? that's nothing,</L>
<L>A littie stain, her wealth will fe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ch again</L>
<L>The colour, and bring honour into her cheeks</L>
<L>As fresh; if she were mine, and I had her</L>
<L>Exchequer. I know the way to make her honest,</L>
<L>Honest to th' touch, the test, and the last tryall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pla.</SPEAKER>
<L>How Prethee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, first I would marry her, that's a verb Materiall;</L>
<L>Then I would Print her with an <HI>Index.</HI></L>
<L><HI>Expurgatorius,</HI> a table drawn</L>
<L>Of her Court Heresies, and when she's read</L>
<L><HI>Cum Privilegio,</HI> who dares call her Whore?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pla.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'l leave you, if you talk thus.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>I ha' done,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Placentia,</SPEAKER>
<L>thou may'st be better company</L>
<L>After another progress; and now tell me,</L>
<PB N="57" REF="33"/>
<L>Did'st ever hear of such a patient madness</L>
<L>As my Lady is possest with? she has rav'd</L>
<L>But twice; and she would fright the Cardinall,</L>
<L>Or at a supper if she did but poyson him,</L>
<L>It were a phrensy I could bear withall;</L>
<L>She calls him her dear Governour—</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Hernando disguised having a Letter.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who is this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Her Secretary? Sir,</L>
<L>Here is a Letter if it may have so</L>
<L>Much happiness to kiss her Graces hand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>From whom?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's not in your Commission Sir</L>
<L>To ask, or mine to satisfie, she will want</L>
<L>No understanding when she reads.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas,</L>
<L>Under your favour Sir, you are mistaken,</L>
<L>Her Grace did never more want understanding.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>How?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>have you not heard, her scull is broken Sir</L>
<L>And many pieces taken out, she's mad.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>The sad fame of her distraction</L>
<L>Has two much truth it seems.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pla.</SPEAKER>
<L>If please you Sir</L>
<L>To expect a while, I will present the Letter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray do</L>
<STAGE>Exit Placen.</STAGE>
<L>How long has she been thus Distemper'd Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>Before the Cardinal came to govern here,</L>
<L>Who for that reason by the King was made</L>
<L>Her Guardian, we are now at his devotion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Lamb given up to a Tyger! may diseases</L>
<L>Soon eat him through his heart!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your pardon Sir,</L>
<L>I love that voice, I know it too, a little,</L>
<L>Are not you? be not angry noble Sir,</L>
<PB N="58" REF="34"/>
<L>I can with ease be ignorant agen,</L>
<L>And think you are another man, but if</L>
<L>You be that valiant Gentleman they call —</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whom? What?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>That kill'd, I would not name him if I thought</L>
<L>You were not pleas'd to be that very Gentleman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Am I betraid?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Devil sha'not</L>
<L>Betray you here, kill me, and I will take</L>
<L>My death you are the Noble Colonel;</L>
<L>We are all bound to you for the Generals death,</L>
<L>Valiant <HI>Hernando?</HI> when my Lady knows</L>
<L>You are here, I hope 'twil fetch her wits agen,</L>
<L>But do not talk too loud, we are not all</L>
<L>Honest i'th' house, some are the Cardinals creatures.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou wert faithfull to thy Lady, I am glad</L>
<L>'Tis night, but tell me how the Churchman uses</L>
<L>The Dutchess?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Antonelli.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>He carries Angels in his tongue, and face, but I</L>
<L>Suspect his heart, this is one of his spawns.</L>
<L>Signior <HI>Antonelli.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Honest <HI>Antonio.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>And how, and how—a friend of mine, where is</L>
<L>The Cardinals Grace?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>That will be never answered.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aut.</SPEAKER>
<L>He means to sup here with the Dutchess.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will he?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>We'l have the charming bottles at my chamber,</L>
<L>Bring that Gentleman, we'l be mighty merry.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>I may disturb your jollity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Farewell sweet—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dear <HI>Antonelli—</HI> a round Pox confound you.</L>
<L>This is Court Retorick at the back stairs.</L>
</SP>
<PB N="59" REF="34"/>
<STAGE>Enter Placentia.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do you know this Gentleman?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pla.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lady presently dismist <HI>Valeria,</HI></L>
<L>And bad me bring him to her bed-chamber.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Gentleman has an honest face.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Her words fell from her with some evenness &amp; joy.</L>
<L>Her Grace desires your presence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'l attend her.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would this Soldier had the Cardinal</L>
<L>Upon a promontory, with what a spring</L>
<L>The Churchman would leap down, it were a spectacle</L>
<L>Most rare to see him topple from the precipice,</L>
<L>And souse in the salt water with a noise</L>
<L>To stun the fishes; and if he fell into</L>
<L>A net, what wonder would the simple Sea-guls</L>
<L>Have, to draw up the o'rgrown Lobster,</L>
<L>So ready boild? he shall have my good wishes,</L>
<L>This Colonels coming may be lucky. I</L>
<L>Will be sure none shall interrupt 'em.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Celinda.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is her Grace at opportunity?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>No sweet Madam,</L>
<L>She is a sleep, her Gentlewoman says.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>My business is but visit, I'l expect.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>That must not be, although I like your company.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are grown rich Mr. Secretary.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>I Madam, Alas!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hear you are upon another purchase.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>I upon a purchase?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you want any sum —</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>If I could purchase your sweet favour Madam?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall command me, and my fortune Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>How's this?</L>
</SP>
<PB N="60" REF="35"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have observ'd you Sir a staid,</L>
<L>And prudent Gentleman— and I shall want—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Father for some Infant; he has credit</L>
<STAGE>Aside.</STAGE>
<L>Ith' world; I am not the first cast Lady</L>
<L>Has married a Secretary.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall I wait upon you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whither?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>Any whither.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>I may chance lead you then—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall be honour'd to obey, my blood</L>
<L>Is up, and in this humour I'm for any thing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well Sir, I'l try your Manhood.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis my happiness,</L>
<L>You cannot please me better.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cel.</SPEAKER>
<L>This was struck</L>
<L>I'th' opportunity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am made for ever.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Hernando, and Dutchess.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dear Madam, do not weep.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'are very welcome,</L>
<L>I ha done, I wo'not shed a tear more</L>
<L>Till I meet <HI>Alvarez,</HI> then I'l weep for joy;</L>
<L>He was a fine young Gentleman, and sung sweetly,</L>
<L>And you had heard him but the night before</L>
<L>We were married, you would ha' sworn he had been</L>
<L>A Swan, and sung his own sad Epitaph;</L>
<L>But we'l talk o'the Cardinal.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would his death</L>
<L>Might ransom your fair sense, he should not live</L>
<L>To triumph in the loss, beshrow my manhood;</L>
<L>But I begin to melt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>I pray Sir tell me,</L>
<L>For I can understand, although they say</L>
<L>I have lost my wits; but they are safe enough,</L>
<PB N="61" REF="35"/>
<L>And I shall have 'em when the Cardinal dyes;</L>
<L>Who had a Letter from his Nephew too</L>
<L>Since he was slain.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>From whence?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know not where he is? but in some Bower</L>
<L>Within a Garden he is making Chaplets,</L>
<L>And means to send me one, but I'l not take it,</L>
<L>I have flowers enough I thank him while I live.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>But do you love your Governour?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, but I'l never marry him, I am promis'd</L>
<L>Already.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>To whom Madam?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do not you</L>
<L>Blush when you ask me that, must not you be</L>
<L>My Husband? I know why, but that's a secret;</L>
<L>Indeed if you believe me, I do love</L>
<L>No man alive so well as you, the Cardinal</L>
<L>Shall never know't, hee'l kill us both, and yet</L>
<L>He says he loves me dearly, and has promis'd</L>
<L>To make me well again, but I'm afraid,</L>
<L>One time or other he will give me poyson.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prevent him Madam, and take nothing from him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, do you think 'twil hurt me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>It will kill you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall but dye, and meet my dear lov'd Lord,</L>
<L>Whom when I have kist, I'l come again, and work</L>
<L>A bracelet of my hair for you to carry him,</L>
<L>When you are going to heaven, the poesy shall</L>
<L>Be my own name, in little tears, that I</L>
<L>Will weep next winter, which congeal'd i'th' frost</L>
<L>Will shew like seed-Pearl, you'l deliver it?</L>
<L>I know he'l love, and wear it for my sake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>She is quite lost.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>I pray give me Sir, your pardon,</L>
<L>I know I talk not wisely, but if you had</L>
<L>The burthen of my sorrow, you would miss</L>
<PB N="62" REF="36"/>
<L>Sometimes your better reason; now l'm well,</L>
<L>What will you do when the Cardinal comes?</L>
<L>He must not see you for the world.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>He sha'not,</L>
<L>I'l take my leave before he come.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay stay,</L>
<L>I shall have no friend left me when you go,</L>
<L>He will but sup, he sha'not stay to ly wi' me,</L>
<L>I have the picture of my Lord abed,</L>
<L>Three are to much this weather.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Plecentia.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, the Cardinal.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>He shall sup with the Devil.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>I dare not stay,</L>
<L>The Red-cock will be angry, I'l come agen.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>This sorrow is no fable, now I find</L>
<L>My curiosity is sadly satisfied;</L>
<L>Ha? if the Dutchess in her stragled wits,</L>
<L>Let fall words to betray me to the Cardinal,</L>
<L>The Panther will not leap more fierce to meet</L>
<L>His prey, when a long want of food hath parch'd</L>
<L>His starved maw, than he to print his rage</L>
<L>And tear my heart-strings, every thing is fatall,</L>
<L>And yet she talk'd sometimes with chain of sense,</L>
<L>And said she lov'd me; ha, they come not yet;</L>
<L>I have a sword about me, and I left</L>
<L>My own security to visit death.</L>
<L>Yet I may pause a little, and consider</L>
<L>Which way does lead me to't most honorably;</L>
<L>Does not the Chamber that I walk in tremble?</L>
<L>What will become of her, and me, and all</L>
<L>The world in one small hour? I do not think</L>
<L>Ever to see the day agen, the wings</L>
<L>Of night spread o'r me like a sable Herse-cloath,</L>
<L>The Stars are all close mourners too; but I</L>
<L>Must not alone to the cold silent grave,</L>
<L>I must not; If thou canst <HI>Alvarez</HI> open</L>
<PB N="63" REF="36"/>
<L>That Ebon curtain, and behold the man,</L>
<L>When the worlds justice fails shall right thy ashes,</L>
<L>And feed their thirst with blood, thy Dutchess is</L>
<L>Almost a Ghost already; and doth wear</L>
<L>Her body like a useless upper garment,</L>
<L>The trim and fashion of it lost. Ha?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Placentia.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pla.</SPEAKER>
<L>You need not doubt me, Sir, My Lady prays</L>
<L>You would not think it long, she in my ear,</L>
<L>Commanded me to tell you, that when last</L>
<L>She drank, she had happy wishes to your health.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>And did the Cardinal pledge it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pla.</SPEAKER>
<L>He was not</L>
<L>Invited to't, nor must he know you are here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>What do they talk of prethee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pla.</SPEAKER>
<L>His Grace is very pleasant</L>
<STAGE>A Lute is heard.</STAGE>
<L>And kind to her, but her returns are after</L>
<L>The sad condition of her sense, sometimes unjoynted.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>They have Musick.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pla.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Lute only,</L>
<L>His Grace prepard, they say, the best of <HI>Italy</HI></L>
<L>That waits upon my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>He thinks the Dutchess</L>
<L>Is stung with a Tarantula.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your pardon.</L>
<L>My duty is expected.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gentle Lady.—a voice too?</L>
<LG>
<HEAD>Song within.</HEAD>
<L>S. <HI>Come my</HI> Daphne, <HI>come away,</HI></L>
<L><HI>We do wast the Crystal day;</HI></L>
<L><HI>'Tis</HI> Strephon <HI>calls.</HI> Da <HI>What says my love?</HI></L>
<L>S. <HI>Come follow to the Mirtle Grove,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Where</HI> Venus <HI>shall prepare</HI></L>
<L><HI>New Chaplets for thy hair.</HI></L>
<L>D. <HI>Were I shut up within a Tree,</HI></L>
<L><HI>I'd rend my bark to follow thee.</HI></L>
<L>S. <HI>My Shepherdess, make hast,</HI></L>
<L><HI>The minutes slide too fast:</HI></L>
<PB N="64" REF="37"/>
<L>D. <HI>In those cooler shades will I</HI></L>
<L><HI>Blind, as</HI> Cupid, kiss thine ey.</L>
<L>S. <HI>In thy bosome then I'l stay,</HI></L>
<L><HI>In such warm Snow who would not lose his way.</HI></L>
<STAGE>Chor.</STAGE>
<L><HI>WE'l laugh and leave the world behind,</HI></L>
<L><HI>And Gods themselves that see,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Shall envy thee, and me;</HI></L>
<L><HI>But never find</HI></L>
<L><HI>Such joys, when they embrace a Deity.</HI></L>
</LG>
<L>If at this distance I distinguish, 'tis not</L>
<L>Church musick, and the air's wanton, and no Anthem</L>
<L>Sung to't, but some strange Ode of love, and kisses,</L>
<L>What should this mean?— ha, he is coming hither,</L>
<L>I am betraid, he marches in her hand,</L>
<L>I'l trust a little more, mute as the Arras</L>
<L>My sword and I here.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>He observes</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Cardival, Dutchess, Antonelli, and Attendants.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wait you in the first Chamber, and let none</L>
<L>Presume to interrupt us.</L>
<STAGE>Ex. Serv.</STAGE>
<L>She is pleasant; now for some art to poyson all her inno∣cence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>I do not like the Cardinals humour, he</L>
<L>Little suspects what guest is in my Chamber.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now Madam you are safe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>How means your Lordship?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Safe in my Arms, sweet Dutchess.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do not hurt me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not for the treasures of the world, you are</L>
<L>My pretty charge, had I as many lives</L>
<L>As I have carefull thoughts, to do you service,</L>
<L>I should think all a happy forfeit to</L>
<L>Delight your Grace one minute; 'tis a heaven</L>
<L>To see you smile.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>What kindness call you this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>It cannot want a name while you preserve</L>
<L>So plentifull a sweetness, it is love.</L>
</SP>
<PB N="65" REF="37"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Of me? how shall I know't my Lord?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>By this, and this, swift Messengers to whisper</L>
<L>Our hearts to one another.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Kisses.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray do you come a wooing?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes sweet Madam,</L>
<L>You cannot be so cruell to deny me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>What my Lord?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Another kiss.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can you</L>
<L>Dispense with this my Lord? Alas I fear</L>
<STAGE>Aside.</STAGE>
<L><HI>Hernando</HI> is asleep, or vanish'd from me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have mock'd my blood into a flame, and what</L>
<L>My angry soul had form'd for my revenge,</L>
<L>Is now the object of my amorous sense,</L>
<L>I have took a strong inchantment from her lips,</L>
<L>And fear I shall forgive <HI>Columbo's</HI> death</L>
<L>If She consent to my embrace; come Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whither my Lord?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>But to your bed or couch,</L>
<L>Where if you will be kind, and but allow</L>
<L>Your self a knowledg, love whose shape and raptures</L>
<L>Wise Poets have but glorified in dreams,</L>
<L>Shall make your chamber his eternall Palace;</L>
<L>And with such active and essentiall streams</L>
<L>Of new delights glide o'r your bosome, you</L>
<L>Shall wonder to what unknown world you are</L>
<L>By some blest change translated; why d'e pause?</L>
<L>And look so wild? will you deny your Governour?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>How came you by that Cloven foot?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your fancy</L>
<L>Would turn a traitour to your happiness;</L>
<L>I am your friend, you must be kind.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Unhand me,</L>
<L>Or I'l cry out a rape.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>You wo'not sure?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have been cozend with <HI>Hernando's</HI> shadow,</L>
<L>Here's none but heaven to hear me, help, a rape,</L>
</SP>
<PB N="66" REF="38"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you so good at understanding then,</L>
<L>I must use other argument.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>He forces her.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Go to, Cardinal.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Strikes him. Ex. Dut.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Hernando,</HI> Murder, Treason, help.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>An army sha'not rescue thee, your blood</L>
<L>Is much inflam'd, I have brought a Lancet wi'me,</L>
<L>Shall open your hot veins, and cool your fever;</L>
<L>To vex thy parting Soul, it was the same</L>
<L>Engin that pinc'd <HI>Columbo's</HI> heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Help, Murder.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Antonelli and Servants.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anton.</SPEAKER>
<L>Some ring the bell, 'twil raise the Court,</L>
<L>My Lord is murder'd, 'tis <HI>Hernando.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>The bell rings.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'l make you all some sport,—So, now we are even,</L>
<L>Where is the Dutchess, I would take my leave</L>
<L>Of her, and then bequeath my curse among you.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Her. salls.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter King, Dutchess, Valeria, Lords, Guard.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>How come these bloody objects?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>With a trick my sword found out, I hope he's paid.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Lo</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>I hope so to; a Surgeon for my Lord Cardinal.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Hernando?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Iustice, Oh Iustice Sir, against a ravisher.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir I ha' done you service.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>A bloody service.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis pure Searlet.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Surgeon.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>After such care to perfect my revenge</L>
<L>Thus banded out o'th' world by a womans plot?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have preserv'd the Dutchess from a rape,</L>
<L>Good-night to me and all the world for ever.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Dies.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>So impious.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis most true, <HI>Alvarez</HI> blood</L>
<L>Is now reveng'd, I find my brain return,</L>
<L>And every stragling sense repairing home.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have deserv'd you should turn from me Sir,</L>
<L>My life hath been prodigiously wicked,</L>
<PB N="67" REF="38"/>
<L>My blood is now the Kingdoms balm; oh Sir,</L>
<L>I have abu'd your ear, your trust, your people,</L>
<L>And my own sacred Office, my conscience</L>
<L>Feels now the sting, oh shew your charity,</L>
<L>And with your pardon like a cool soft gale</L>
<L>Fan my poor sweating soul; that wanders through</L>
<L>Unhabitable climes, and parched deserts;</L>
<L>But I am lost, if the great World forgive me,</L>
<L>Unless I find your mercy for a crime</L>
<L>You know not Madam, yet against your life.</L>
<L>I must confess, more than my black intents</L>
<L>Upon your honour, y'are already poyson'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>By whom?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>By me,</L>
<L>In the revenge I ow'd <HI>Columbo</HI>'s loss,</L>
<L>With your last meat was mixt a poyson that</L>
<L>By subtle, and by sure degrees must let in death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Look to the Dutchess, our Physicians?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay, I will deserve her mercy, though I cannot</L>
<L>Call back the deed, in proof of my repentance,</L>
<L>If the last breath of a now dying man</L>
<L>May gain your charity, and belief, receive</L>
<L>This Ivory box, in it an antidote</L>
<L>'Bove that they boast the great magistrall medicine,</L>
<L>That pouder mixt with wine by a most rare</L>
<L>And quick access to the heart will fortifie it</L>
<L>Against the rage of the most nimble poyson,</L>
<L>I am not worthy to present her with it,</L>
<L>Oh take it and preserve her innocent life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Lo.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Strange, he should have a good thing in such readyness.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>This that which in my jealousie and state</L>
<L>Trusting to false predictions of my birth,</L>
<L>That I sh dy by poyson, I preserv'd</L>
<L>For my own safety, wonder not, I made,</L>
<L>That my companion was to be my resuge.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Servant with a bowle of Wine.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Lo.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Her's some touch of grace.</L>
</SP>
<PB N="68" REF="39"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>in greater proof of my pure thoughts I take</L>
<L>This first, and with my dying breath confirm</L>
<L>My penitence, it may benefit her life,</L>
<L>But not my wounds; oh hasten to preserve her,</L>
<L>And though I merit not her pardon, let not</L>
<L>Her fair soul be divorc'd</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is some charity, may it prosper Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Valeria.</SPEAKER>
<L>How does your grace?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>And must I owe my life to him whose death</L>
<L>Was my ambition? take this free acknowledgment,</L>
<L>I had intent this night with my own hand</L>
<L>To be <HI>Alvarez</HI> lusticer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>You were mad,</L>
<L>And thought past apprehension of revenge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>That shape I did usurp, great Sir, to give</L>
<L>My Art more freedom and defence, but when</L>
<L><HI>Hernando</HI> came to visit me, I thought</L>
<L>I might defer my execution,</L>
<L>Which his owe rage suppli'd without my guilt,</L>
<L>And when his lust grew high, met with his blood.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Lo.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>The Cardial smiles.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now my revenge has met</L>
<L>With you my nimble Dutchess, I have took</L>
<L>A shape to give my act more freedom too,</L>
<L>And now I am sure she's poyson'd, with that doze</L>
<L>I gave her last.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Th'art not so horrid?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha! some Cordiall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas no preservative</L>
<L>Hath wings to overtake it, were her heart</L>
<L>Lock'd in a quarry, it would search, and kill</L>
<L>Before the aids can reach it; I am sure</L>
<L>You sha not now laugh at me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>How came you by that poyson?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>I prepar'd it,</L>
<L>Resolving when I had enjoy'd her, which</L>
<PB N="69" REF="39"/>
<L>The Colonel prevented, by some art</L>
<L>To make her take it, and by death conclude</L>
<L>My last revenge; you have the fatal Story.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is so great a wickedness, it will</L>
<L>Exceed belief.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>I knew I could not live.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Surgeon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your wounds, Sir, were not desperate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not mortall? ha? were they not mortall?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Surg.</SPEAKER>
<L>If I have skill in Surgery.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then I have caught my self in my own Engin.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Lo.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>It was your fate you said to dy by poyson.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>That was my own prediction to abuse</L>
<L>Your faith, no humane art can now resist it,</L>
<L>I feel it knocking at the seat of life,</L>
<L>It must come in, I have wrackt all my own</L>
<L>To try your charities, new it would be rare,</L>
<L>If you but waft me with a little prayer,</L>
<L>My wings that flag may catch the wind, but 'tis</L>
<L>In vain, the mist is risen, and ther's none</L>
<L>To stear my wandring bark.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Dyes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Lo.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>He's dead?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>With him</L>
<L>Dy all deceived trust.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Lo.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>This was a strange impiety.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>When men</L>
<L>Of Gifts and sacred Function once decline</L>
<L>From virtue, their ill deeds transcend example.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>The minute's come that I must take my leave too.</L>
<L>Your hand great Sir, and though you be a King,</L>
<L>We may exchange forgiveness, heaven forgive,</L>
<L>And all the world. I come, I come <HI>Alvarez</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Dyes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dispose their bodies for becoming funeral;</L>
<L>How much are Kings abus'd by those they take</L>
<L>To royall grace? whom when they cherish most</L>
<L>By nice indulgence, they doo often arm</L>
<L>Against themselves; from whence this maxim springs,</L>
<L><HI>None have more need of Perspectives than Kings.</HI></L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="epilogue">
<PB REF="40"/>
<HEAD>Epilogue.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Within.</STAGE>
<P>Mr. <HI>Polla'd,</HI> wher's Mr. <HI>Pollard</HI> for the Epi∣logue?</P>
<STAGE>He is thrust upon the Stage, and falls.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epilogue.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>I Am coming to you Gentlemen, the Poet</HI></L>
<L><HI>Has help'd me thus far on my way, but I'l</HI></L>
<L><HI>Be even with him; the Play is a Tragedy,</HI></L>
<L><HI>The first that ever he compos'd for us,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Wherein he thinks he has done pretily,</HI></L>
<STAGE>Enter Servant.</STAGE>
<L><HI>And I am sensible; I prethee look</HI></L>
<L><HI>Is nothing out of joynt? has he broke nothing?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Serv.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Nor Sir, I hope.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Yes, he has broke his Epilogue all to peeces,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Canst thou put it together agen?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Not I Sir.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Epi.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Nor I, prethee be gone, hum? Mr. Poet,</HI></L>
<L><HI>I have a teeming mind to be reveng'd.</HI></L>
<L><HI>You may assist, and not be seen in't now.</HI></L>
<L><HI>If you please Gentlemen, for I do know</HI></L>
<L><HI>He listens to the issue of his cause,</HI></L>
<L><HI>But blister not your hands in his applause,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Your private smile, your nod, or hum, to tell</HI></L>
<L><HI>My fellows, that you like the business well;</HI></L>
<L><HI>And when without a clap you go away,</HI></L>
<L><HI>I'l drink a small-bear health to his second day;</HI></L>
<L><HI>And break his heart, or make him swear, and rage,</HI></L>
<L><HI>He'l write no more for the unhappy Stage;</HI></L>
<L><HI>But that's too much, so we should lose; faith shew it,</HI></L>
<L><HI>And if you like his play, 'ts as well, he knew it.</HI></L>
</SP>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
<BACK>
<DIV1 TYPE="publisher's note">
<PB REF="40"/>
<HEAD>A Catalogue of the Au∣thors Poems already Printed</HEAD>
<LIST>
<HEAD>Tragedies.</HEAD>
<ITEM><HI>THe Traytour</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Philip Chabot Admirall of France</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Loves Cruelty</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>The Maids Revenge</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Dukes Mistri;</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>The Cardinal.</HI></ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<HEAD>Comedies and Tragi-comedies.</HEAD>
<ITEM><HI>The School of Complement</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>The Lady of Pleasure</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Hide-parke</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>The Constant Maid.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg">Falsely as∣cribed to <HI>Jo. Fletcher.</HI></NOTE> <HI>The Coronation</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>The Changes, or Love in a Maze</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>The Gratefull Servant</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>The Patron of Ireland</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>The Humorous Court</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>The wedding</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>The Ball, or French Dancing Master</HI></ITEM>
<PB REF="41" MS="y"/>
<ITEM><HI>The Gamester</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>The Example</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>The Bird in a cage</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>The Royall Master</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>The Opportunity</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>The Witty Faire one</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>The Imposture</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>The Brothers</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>The Sisters.</HI></ITEM>
</LIST>
<P><HI>A Masque of the four Honorable Innes of Court, pre∣sented before the King and Queens Majesty at</HI> Whitehall <HI>in the Banqueting house.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Poems.</HI></P>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BACK>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

